The Principles of Human Knowledge

George Berkeley

Copyright ©2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth.
First launched: July 2004 Last amended: November 2007
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Introduction   1
Sections 1–50   11
Sections 51–99   25
Sections 100–156   39

Principles George Berkeley Introduction

Introduction

1 intro. Philosophy is just the study of wisdom and truth, so one might reasonably expect that those who have spent most time and care on it would enjoy a greater calm and serenity of mind, know things more clearly and certainly, and be less disturbed with doubts and difficulties than other men. But what we find is ·quite different, namely that· the illiterate majority of people, who walk the high road of plain common sense and are governed by the dictates of nature, are mostly comfortable and undisturbed. To them nothing that is familiar appears hard to explain or to understand. They don’t complain of any lack of certainty in their senses, and are in no danger of becoming sceptics. But as soon as we depart from sense and instinct to follow the light of a higher principle—i.e. to reason, meditate, and reflect on the nature of things—a thousand doubts spring up in our minds concerning things that we previously seemed to understand fully. We encounter many prejudices and errors of the senses; and when we try to correct these by reason, we are gradually drawn into crude paradoxes, difficulties, and inconsistencies that multiply and grow on us as our thoughts progress; until finally, having wandered through many intricate mazes, we find ourselves back where we started or—which is worse—we sit down in a forlorn scepticism.

2 intro. The cause of this is thought to be the obscurity of things or the natural weakness and imperfection of our understandings. It is said that our faculties are few in number and are designed by nature ·merely· to promote survival and comfort, not to penetrate into the inward essence and constitution of things. Besides, (·they say·), it isn’t surprising that the finite mind of man runs into absurdities and contradictions—ones from which it can’t possibly escape—when it tackles things that involve infinity, because it is of the nature of the infinite not to be comprehended by anything that is finite.

3 intro. But when we lay the blame ·for our paradoxes and difficulties· on our faculties rather than on our wrong use of them, perhaps we are letting ourselves down too lightly. It is hard to believe that right deductions from true principles should ever lead to conclusions that can’t be maintained or made consistent. We should believe that God has been more generous with men than to give them a strong desire for knowledge that he has placed out of their reach. That wouldn’t square with the kindly ways in which Providence, having given creatures various desires, usually supplies them the means—if used properly—to satisfy them. I’m inclined to think that most if not all of the difficulties that have in the past puzzled and deceived philosophers and blocked the way to knowledge are entirely of our own making. We have first raised a dust, and then we complain that we can’t see.

4 intro. My purpose therefore is to try to discover what the underlying sources are of all that doubtfulness and uncertainty, those absurdities and contradictions, into which the various sects of philosophy have fallen—and indeed fallen so badly that the wisest men have thought our ignorance to be incurable, thinking that it comes from the natural dullness and limitedness of our faculties. Surely it is well worth the trouble to make a strict enquiry into the first principles of human knowledge, to sift and examine them on all sides; especially since there may be some grounds to suspect that the obstacles and difficulties that block and confuse the mind in its search for truth don’t spring from any

1

Principles George Berkeley Introduction

darkness and intricacy in the objects, or any natural defect in the understanding, but come rather from false principles that have been insisted on and might have been avoided.

5 intro. When I consider how many great and extraordinary men have already tried to do this, my own attempt seems difficult and discouraging. But I have some hope ·of success·, because the largest views aren’t always the clearest, and he who is shortsighted will have to bring the object nearer to him, and may by looking closely at the fine details notice things that have escaped far better eyes.

6 intro. You will understand the rest of this work more easily if I begin by discussing the nature of language and how it can be misused. I need especially to attend to a doctrine that seems to have played a large part in making people’s theories complex and confusing, and to have caused endless errors and difficulties in most branches of knowledge. I am referring to the theory that the mind has a power of forming abstract ideas or notions of things. Anyone who knows anything about the writings and disputes of philosophers must realize that a great part of them is spent on abstract ideas, which are thought to be especially the object of the sciences of logic and metaphysics, and of all learning of the supposedly most abstracted and elevated kind. In all of these studies, almost every discussion assumes that there are abstract ideas in the mind, and that it is quite familiar with them.

7 intro. Everyone agrees that the qualities of things never really exist in isolation from one another; rather, they are mixed and blended together, several in the same object. But, we are told ·by the supporters of ‘abstract ideas’·, the mind can consider each quality on its own, abstracted from the others with which it is united in the object, and in that way the mind forms abstract ideas. For example, your eyesight presents you with an object that is extended, coloured, and moving; and your mind resolves this mixed or compound idea into its simple, constituent parts, and views each in isolation from the rest; which is how it forms the abstract ideas of extension, of colour, and of motion. It isn’t possible for colour or motion to exist without extension: but ·according to these ‘abstract idea’ theorists· the mind can by abstraction form the idea of colour without extension, and of motion without either colour or extension.

8 intro. [This section continues to expound the theory of abstract ideas, in preparation for an attack on it.] Again, the mind observes that the extended things that we perceive by sense, although they vary in size, shape and so on, also all have something in common; and it singles out and isolates the common element, thereby forming a highly abstract idea of extension. This is neither line, surface, nor solid, and it has no particular shape or size; it is an idea entirely separated out from all these ·features that distinguish extended things from one another·. Similarly the mind can leave out all the differences amongst the colours that are seen, retaining only what is common to them all; and in this way it makes an idea of colour, which is not red, blue, white or any other specific colour. Again, by considering motion on its own—separated out not only from the body that moves but also from how it moves, in what direction and how fast—the mind forms an abstract idea of motion, which is equally applicable to all particular movements that we can perceive through our senses—·the movement of a beckoning finger and the movement of Venus around the sun·.

9 intro. [The exposition of the theory of abstract ideas continues, becoming increasingly sarcastic in tone.] The kind of mental separation through which the mind forms abstract ideas of qualities taken singly also enables it to achieve abstract ideas of more complex items each of which includes a number of

2

Principles George Berkeley Introduction

qualities that exist together ·in a single object·. For example, having observed that Peter, James, and John have certain features of shape etc. in common, the mind forms a complex idea that leaves out whatever differentiates these men from one another or from other men, and retains only what is common to all; and in this way it makes an abstract idea that applies equally to all men, excluding any details that might tie it down to any one man in particular. This (they say) is how we come to have the abstract idea of man (or of humanity or human nature, if you like). This idea includes colour, because every man has some colour; but then it can be neither white, nor black, nor any particular colour, because there is no one colour that all men have. The idea also includes height ·because every man has some height or other·, but it is neither tall nor short nor middling, but something abstracted from all these ·because there is no one height that all men have·. Similarly for all the rest. Furthermore, many sorts of creatures correspond in some ways but not all to the complex idea of man; and the mind, leaving out the features that are special to men and retaining only the ones that are shared by all the living creatures, forms the idea of animal. This abstracts not only from all particular men, but also all birds, beasts, fishes, and insects. The constituent parts of the abstract idea of animal are body, life, sense, and spontaneous motion [= ‘the ability to move without being pushed or pulled’]. By ‘body’ is meant body without any particular shape or size, because no one shape or size is common to all animals. The idea doesn’t include any specific kind of covering—hair or feathers or scales, etc.—but nor does it specify bare skin; for various animals differ in respect of whether they have hair, feathers, scales, or bare skin, so that all those differences must be left out of the abstract idea of animal. For the same reason, the spontaneous motion must not be walking, flying or creeping; but it is a motion all the same. What kind of motion it can be isn’t easy to conceive.

10 intro. Whether others have this amazing ability to form abstract ideas, they will know better than I. Speaking for myself: I find that I do indeed have a capacity for imagining—representing to myself the ideas of particular things that I have perceived—and of splitting those ideas up and re-assembling them in various ways. I can imagine a man with two heads, or the upper parts of a man joined to the body of a horse. I can consider the hand, the eye, the nose, each by itself abstracted or separated from the rest of the body. But then whatever hand or eye I imagine, it must have some particular shape and colour. Similarly, any idea that I form of a man must be of a specific kind of man: he must be white or black or brown, straight or crooked, tall or short or middling. Try as I may, I can’t get into my mind the abstract idea of man that is described in the preceding section. And I find it equally impossible to form an abstract idea of motion that leaves out the thing that moves and is neither swift nor slow, curved nor straight. The same holds for absolutely all abstract ideas. I freely admit that I can perform ‘abstraction’ in a certain sense, namely: when several parts or qualities are united in an object, I can have the thought of one of them separated from the others if it could really exist apart from them. But I deny that I can perform ‘abstraction’ in the standard meaning of that word, which covers two kinds of mental performance: (1) conceiving abstractly and in isolation a quality that couldn’t exist in isolation ·as we are said to do with colour and motion·; and (2) forming a general notion by abstracting from particulars in the way I have described, ·as we are said to do with man and animal·. There is reason to think that most people are like me in this respect. The majority of people, who are

3

Principles George Berkeley Introduction

simple and illiterate, never claim to have abstract notions. Such notions are described ·by those who believe in them· as difficult to form; it takes hard work, we are told, to make an abstract idea. So we can reasonably conclude that if there are any abstract ideas they are all in the minds of learned people.

11 intro. Let us see what can be said in defence of this theory of abstract ideas. What attracts philosophers to a view that seems so remote from common sense? A rightly admired philosopher who died not long ago certainly helped to make the doctrine popular when he suggested that the biggest intellectual difference between man and beast is that men can form abstract ideas while beasts cannot. [Berkeley’s Principles was published in 1710; John Locke, to whom Berkeley is referring here, had died in 1704. In their time ‘brute’ and ‘beast’ were standard terms for non-human animals.] He wrote

What perfectly distinguishes men from brutes is that men have general ideas, this being something that the brutes aren’t equipped to do. Clearly, we don’t see in them the faintest trace of the use of general signs to stand for universal ideas; so we can reasonably suppose that they lack the ability to abstract, i.e. to make general ideas, since they have no use of words or any other general signs. (Locke, Essay Concerning Human Understanding II.xi.10)

A little later he wrote:

So we are entitled to conclude that this is what marks off the species of brutes from men. It creates a clear gap between them, which eventually broadens out to a great width. If the brutes have any ideas at all rather than being mere machines (as some people think they are), we can’t deny that they have a certain degree of reason. That some of them sometimes reason seems to me as obvious as that they sense things; but when they reason, it is only with particular ideas, just as they receive them from their senses. Even the highest of the brutes are confined within those narrow limits, I believe, and have no capacity to widen their intellectual range through any kind of abstraction. (II.xi.11)

I readily agree with this author that brutes have no capacity for abstraction. But if that’s our criterion for whether something is a brute, I am afraid that many who are accepted as men should be counted among the brutes! We have no evidence that brutes have abstract general ideas, the author said, because we don’t observe them using words or other general signs. He was assuming that one can’t use words unless one has general ideas; which implies that men who use language can abstract or make their ideas general. That the author was thinking along these lines can be seen in how he answered his own question: ‘Since all things that exist are only particulars, how do we come by general terms?’ His answer was, ‘Words become general by being made the signs of general ideas’ (III.iii.6). But ·I maintain, on the contrary, that· it seems that a word becomes general by being made the sign not of one abstract general idea but of many particular ideas, any one of which it may suggest to the mind. Consider for example the propositions A thing’s change of motion is proportional to the force that is exerted on it, and Whatever is extended can be divided. These axioms are to be understood as holding for motion and extension in general; but that doesn’t imply that they suggest to my thoughts

•an idea of motion without a body moved, and with no determinate direction or velocity,

or that I must conceive

•an abstract general idea of extension, which is not line or surface or solid, not large or small, not black or white or red or of any other determinate colour.

4

Principles George Berkeley Introduction

All that is needed is that the first axiom is true for every motion that I consider, whether it be swift or slow, perpendicular or horizontal or oblique, and in whatever object; and that the second axiom holds for every specific extension, whether line or surface or solid, and whether of this or that size or shape.

12 intro. We shall be better placed to understand what makes a word a general term if we first understand how ideas become general. (I emphasize that I don’t deny that there are general ideas—only that there are abstract general ideas. In the passages I have quoted, every mention of general ideas carries the assumption that they are formed by abstraction in the manner described in 7 and 9 above.) If we want to speak meaningfully and not say things that we can’t make sense of, I think we shall agree to the following. An idea, which considered in itself is particular, becomes general in its meaning by being made to represent or stand for all other particular ideas of the same sort as itself. Suppose for example that a geometrician, proving the validity of a procedure for cutting a line in two equal parts, draws a black line one inch long. As used in this geometrical proof, this particular line is general in its significance because it is used to represent all particular lines, so that what is proved regarding it is proved to hold for all lines. And just as that particular line becomes general by being used as a sign, so the word ‘line’—which in itself is particular—is used as a sign with a general meaning. The line is general because it is the sign not of an abstract or general line but of all particular straight lines that could exist, and the word is general for the same reason—namely that it stands equally well for each and every particular line.

13 intro. To give you a still clearer view of what abstract ideas are supposed to be like, and of how we are supposed to need them, I shall quote one more passage from the Essay Concerning Human Understanding:

For children and others whose minds have not yet been put to work much, abstract ideas aren’t as easy to form as particular ones are. If adults find them easy, that is only because they have had so much practice. For when we reflect carefully and in detail on them, we’ll find that general ideas are mental fictions or contrivances that are quite difficult to construct; we don’t come by them as easily as we might think. The general idea of a triangle, for example, though it isn’t one of the most abstract, comprehensive, and difficult ideas, can’t be formed without hard work and skill. For that idea must be neither oblique nor rectangle, neither equilateral, equicrural, nor scalenon, but all and none of these at once. In effect, it is something imperfect that cannot exist, an idea in which parts of several different and inconsistent ideas are put together. It is true that because of our imperfect human condition, the mind needs such ideas for two of its main purposes—communication, and the growth of knowledge—so it moves as fast as it can to get them. Still, there is reason to suspect that such ideas indicate how imperfect we are. Anyway, what I have said is enough to show that the ideas that come earliest and most easily to the mind aren’t abstract and general ones, and that our earliest knowledge doesn’t involve them. (IV.vii.9)

If anyone ·thinks he· can form in his mind an idea of a triangle such as the one described in that passage, I shan’t waste my time trying to argue him out of it. I merely ask you, the reader, to find out for sure whether you have such an idea. This can’t be very difficult. What is easier than for you

5

Principles George Berkeley Introduction

to look a little into your own thoughts and discover whether you do or can have an idea that fits the description we have been given of the general idea of a triangle—‘neither oblique nor rectangle, neither equilateral, equicrural, nor scalenon, but all and none of these at once’?

14 intro. Much is said ·by Locke· about how difficult abstract ideas are—about the care and skill that is needed in forming them. And everyone agrees that it takes hard mental work to free our thoughts from particular objects and raise them to the level of theorizing that involves abstract ideas. It would seem to follow that the forming of abstract ideas is too difficult to be necessary for communication, which is so easy and familiar for all sorts of people. But, we are told ·by Locke, replying to this point·, that if adults find abstract ideas easy to form, that’s only because they have become good at it through long practice. Well, I would like to know when it is that people are busy overcoming that difficulty and equipping themselves with what they need for communication! It can’t be when they are grown up, for by then ·they can communicate, so that· it seems the difficulty is behind them; so it has to be something they do in their childhood. But surely the labour of forming abstract notions—with so many to be formed, and each of them so difficult—is too hard a task for that tender age. Who could believe that a couple of children cannot chatter about sugar-plums and toys until they have first tacked together numberless inconsistencies and so formed abstract general ideas in their minds, attaching them to every common name they make use of?

15 intro. Abstract ideas are no more needed, in my opinion, for the growth of knowledge than they are for communication. I entirely agree with the widespread belief that all knowledge and demonstration concerns universal notions; but I can’t see that those are formed by abstraction. The only kind of universality that I can grasp doesn’t belong to anything’s intrinsic nature; a thing’s universality consists how it relates to the particulars that it signifies or represents. That is how things, names, or notions that are intrinsically particular are made to be universal ·through their relation to the many particulars that they represent·. When I prove a proposition about triangles, for instance, I am of course employing the universal idea of a triangle; but that doesn’t involve me in thinking of a triangle that is neither equilateral nor scalenon nor equicrural! All it means is that the particular triangle I have in mind, no matter what kind of triangle it may be, is ‘universal’ in the sense that it equally stands for and represents all triangles whatsoever. All this seems to be straightforward and free of difficulties.

16 intro. You may want to make this objection:

How can we know any proposition to be true of all particular triangles unless we first see it demonstrated of the abstract idea of a triangle that fits all the particular ones? Just because a property can be demonstrated to belong to some one particular triangle, it doesn’t follow that it equally belongs to any other triangle that differs in some way from the first one. For example, having demonstrated of an isosceles right-angled triangle that its three angles are equal to two right ones, I can’t conclude from this that the same holds for all other triangles that don’t have a right angle and two equal sides. If we are to be certain that this proposition is universally true, it seems, we must either •prove it of every particular triangle (which is impossible) or •prove it once and for all of the abstract idea of a triangle, in which all the particulars are involved and by which they are all equally represented.

To this I answer that although the idea I have in view

6

Principles George Berkeley Introduction

while I make the demonstration may be (for instance) that of an isosceles right-angled triangle whose sides are of a determinate length, I can still be certain that it applies also to all other triangles, no matter what their sort or size. I can be sure of this because neither the right angle nor the equality of sides nor length of the sides has any role in the demonstration. It is true that the diagram I have in view ·in the proof· includes all these details, but they aren’t mentioned in the proof of the proposition. It isn’t said that the three angles are equal to two right ones because one of them is a right angle, or because the sides that form it are of the same length. This shows that the demonstration could have held good even if the right angle had been oblique and the sides unequal. That is why I conclude that the proposition holds for all triangles, having •demonstrated it ·in a certain way· to hold for a particular right-angled isosceles triangle—not because I •demonstrated it to hold for the abstract idea of a triangle! I don’t deny that a man can abstract, in that he can consider a figure merely as triangular without attending to the particular qualities of the angles or relations of the sides. But that doesn’t show that he can form an abstract general inconsistent idea of a triangle. Similarly, because all that is perceived is not considered, we may think about Peter considered as a man, or considered as an animal, without framing the abstract idea of man or of animal.

17 intro. It would be an endless and a useless task to trace the scholastic philosophers [that is, mediaeval followers of Aristotle], those great masters of abstraction, through all the tangling labyrinths of error and dispute that their doctrine of abstract natures and notions seems to have led them into. What bickerings and controversies have arisen about those matters, and [Berkeley adds sarcastically] what great good they have brought to mankind, are well enough known these days, and I needn’t go on about them. It would have been better if the bad effects of that doctrine ·of abstract natures and notions· had been confined to the people who most openly adhered to it. ·But the bad effects have spread further·. When men consider

•that the advancement of knowledge has been pursued with great care, hard work, and high abilities, and yet most branches of knowledge remain full of darkness and uncertainty, and of disputes that seem likely never to end; and •that even propositions thought to be supported by the most clear and compelling demonstrations contain paradoxes that are utterly at variance with the understandings of men; and •that only a small portion of them brings any real benefit to mankind other than as an innocent diversion and amusement;

the consideration of all this is apt to make people depressed, and to give them a complete contempt for all study. Perhaps this will cease when we have a view of the false principles that people have accepted, of which I think the one that has had the widest influence over the thoughts of enquiring and theory-building men is the doctrine of abstract general ideas.

18 intro. This prevailing view about abstract ideas seems to me to have its roots in language. There is some evidence for this in what is openly said by the ablest supporters of abstract ideas, who acknowledge that they are made for the purpose of naming; from which it clearly follows that if there had been no such thing as speech or universal signs, abstraction would never have been thought of. (See Essay III.vi.39 and elsewhere.) So let us examine how words have helped to give rise to the mistaken view that there are abstract ideas. ·They have contributed to it through two mistakes about language, which I shall now discuss·. (1) People assume that every name does or should have just

7

Principles George Berkeley Introduction

one precise and settled signification. This encourages them to believe in abstract, determinate ideas, each serving as the true and only immediate signification of some general name, and to think further that a general name comes to signify this or that particular thing through the mediation of these abstract ideas—·for example, •the general name ‘pebble’ stands for •my abstract idea of pebble, which in a certain way fits •the pebble I hold in my hand; and that’s how the general name comes to apply to the particular pebble·. [Here, as in Locke’s writings, a ‘general name’ is just a general word, such as ‘pebble’, ‘daffodil’ and ‘triangle’. ‘Signification’ could often be replaced by ‘meaning’, but not always.] Whereas really no general name has a single precise and definite signification; each general name can equally well signify a great number of particular ideas. All of this clearly follows from what I have already said; reflect on it a little and you’ll agree. Here is a possible objection:

When a name has a definition, that ties it down to one determinate signification. For example, ‘triangle’ is defined as ‘plane surface bounded by three straight lines’; and that definition confines the word ‘triangle’ to standing for one certain idea and no other.

To this I reply that that definition of ‘triangle’ doesn’t say whether the surface is large or small, black or white, nor whether the sides are long or short, equal or unequal, nor what angles they form. Each of these can vary greatly; so there is no one settled idea to which the signification of the word ‘triangle’ is confined. It is one thing to make a name always obey the same definition, and another to make it always stand for the same idea: one is necessary, the other useless and impracticable.

19 intro. (2) Words helped in another way to produce the doctrine of abstract ideas, namely through the widespread opinion that language is for the communicating of our ideas and for nothing else, and that every significant name stands for an idea. People who think this, and who can see the obvious fact that some names that are regarded as significant don’t have particular specific ideas corresponding to them, conclude that such names must stand for abstract notions. Now, nobody will deny that many names that are in use amongst thoughtful people don’t always put determinate particular ideas into the minds of listeners. And even when a name does stand for ideas, it doesn’t have to arouse them in the listener’s mind every time it is used, even in the strictest reasonings. That is because in reading and conversation names are mostly used as letters are in algebra: each letter stands for a particular number, but you can conduct a proof accurately without at each step having each letter bring to mind the particular number it is meant to stand for.

20 intro. Besides, the communicating of ideas through words isn’t the chief and only end of language, as people commonly think. Speech has other purposes as well: raising emotions, influencing behaviour, changing mental attitudes. The communication of ideas is often subservient to these other purposes, and sometimes it doesn’t take place at all because the purposes can be achieved without it. I urge you to reflect on your own experience. When you are hearing or reading a discourse, doesn’t it often happen that emotions of fear, love, hatred, admiration, disdain, and so on arise immediately in your mind when you see or hear certain words, without any ideas intervening between the words and the emotion? It may well be that those •words did originally evoke •ideas that produced those sorts of •emotions; but I think you will find that, once the language has become familiar, hearing the sounds or seeing the •words is often followed by those •emotions immediately, entirely leaving out the •ideas that used to be a link in the chain. For example, can’t we be influenced by the promise of ‘a good

8

Principles George Berkeley Introduction

thing’ without having an idea of what it is? Again, isn’t a threat of ‘danger’ enough to make us afraid, even if we don’t think of any particular evil that is likely to befall us or even form an idea of danger in the abstract? If you reflect a little on your own situation in the light of what I have said, I think you’ll find it obvious that general names are often used, in a perfectly proper way, without the speaker’s intending them as marks of ideas in his own mind that he wants to arouse in the mind of the hearer. Even proper names, it seems, aren’t always spoken with the intention of bringing into hearers’ minds the ideas of those individuals who are named. For example, when a schoolman [= ‘follower of Aristotle’] tells me ‘Aristotle has said it’, I understand him merely to be trying to incline me to accept his opinion with the deference and submission that custom has linked with the name ‘Aristotle’, ·and my idea of Aristotle doesn’t come into it·. Countless examples of this kind could be given, but why should I go on about things that I’m sure are abundantly illustrated in your own experience?

21 intro. I think I have •shown the impossibility of abstract ideas. I have •considered what has been said on their behalf by their ablest supporters, and have •tried to show they are of no use for the purposes for which they are thought to be necessary. And, lastly, I have •traced them to their source, which appears to be language. It can’t be denied that words are extremely useful: they make it possible for all the knowledge that has been gained by the enquiries of men at many times and in all nations to be pulled together and surveyed by a single person. But at the same time it must be admitted that most branches of knowledge have been made enormously much darker and more difficult by the misuse of words and turns of phrase. Therefore, since words are so apt to influence our thoughts, when I want to consider any ideas I shall try to take them bare and naked, keeping out of my thoughts—as much as I can—the names that those ideas have been given through long and constant use. From this I expect to get the following ·three· advantages:-

22 intro. •First, I shall be sure to keep clear of all purely verbal controversies—those weeds whose springing up, in almost all branches of knowledge, has been a principal hindrance to the growth of true and sound knowledge. •Secondly, this seems to be a sure way to extricate myself from that fine and delicate net of abstract ideas, which has so miserably perplexed and entangled the minds of men (with this special feature: the more sharp-witted and exploratory any man’s mind is, the more completely he is likely to be trapped and held by the net!). •Thirdly, so long as I confine my thoughts to my own ideas with the words peeled off, I don’t see how I can easily be mistaken. The objects that I consider are all ones that I clearly and adequately know: I can’t fall into error by thinking I have an idea that I really don’t have, or by imagining that two of my own ideas are alike (or that they are unalike) when really they are not. To observe how my ideas agree or disagree, and to see which ideas are included in any compound idea and which are not, all I need is to pay attention to what happens in my own understanding.

23 intro. But I can’t get all these advantages unless I free myself entirely from the deception of words. I hardly dare promise myself that, because the union between words and ideas began early and has been strengthened by many years of habit ·in thought and speech·, making it very difficult to dissolve. This difficulty seems to have been very much increased by the doctrine of abstraction. For so long as men thought their words have abstract ideas tied to them, it isn’t surprising that they used words in place of ideas: they found that they couldn’t set aside the word and retain

9

Principles George Berkeley Introduction

the abstract idea in the mind, because abstract ideas are perfectly inconceivable. That is the principal cause for the fact that men who have emphatically recommended to others that in their meditations they should lay aside all use of words and instead contemplate their bare ideas have failed to do this themselves. Recently many people have become aware of the absurd opinions and meaningless disputes that grow out of the misuse of words. And they had given good advice about how to remedy these troubles—namely that we should attend not to the words that signify ideas but rather to the ideas themselves. But however good this advice that they have given others may be, they obviously couldn’t properly follow it themselves so long as they thought that •the only immediate use of words was to signify ideas, and •that the immediate signification of every general name was a determinate, abstract idea.

24 intro. But when you know that these are mistakes, you can more easily prevent your thoughts from being influenced by words. Someone who knows that he has only particular ideas won’t waste his time trying to conceive the abstract idea that goes with any name. And someone who knows that names don’t always stand for ideas will spare himself the labour of looking for ideas where there are none to be had. So it is desirable that everyone should try as hard as he can to obtain a clear view of the ideas he wants to consider, separating from them all the clothing and clutter of words that so greatly blind our judgment and scatter our attention. In vain do we extend our view into the heavens, and presumably into the entrails of the earth; in vain do we consult the writings of learned men, and trace the dark footsteps of antiquity; we need only draw aside the curtain of words, to behold the fairest tree of knowledge, whose fruit, ·namely, our ‘bare naked ideas’·, is excellent and lies within reach of our hand.

25 intro. Unless we take care to clear the first principles of knowledge from being burdened and deluded by words, we can reason from them for ever without achieving anything; we can draw consequences from consequences and be never the wiser. The further we go, the more deeply and irrecoverably we shall be lost and entangled in difficulties and mistakes. To anyone who plans to read the following pages, therefore, I say: Make my words the occasion of your own thinking, and try to have the same sequence of thoughts in reading that I had in writing. This will make it easy for you to discover the truth or falsity of what I say. You will run no risk of being deceived by my words, and I don’t see how you can be led into an error by considering your own naked, undisguised ideas.

10

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

Sections 1–50

1. Anyone who surveys the objects of human knowledge will easily see that they are all ideas that are either •actually imprinted on the senses or •perceived by attending to one’s own emotions and mental activities or •formed out of ideas of the first two types, with the help of memory and imagination, by compounding or dividing or simply reproducing ideas of those other two kinds. By sight I have the ideas of light and colours with their different degrees and variations. By touch I perceive hard and soft, heat and cold, motion and resistance, and so on; and each of these also admits of differences of quantity or degree. Smelling supplies me with odours; the palate with tastes; and hearing conveys sounds to the mind in all their variety of tone and composition. And when a number of these are observed to accompany each other, they come to be marked by one name and thus to be thought of as one thing. Thus, for example, a certain colour, taste, smell, shape and consistency having been observed to go together, they are taken to be one distinct thing, called an ‘apple’. Other collections of ideas constitute a stone, a tree, a book, and similar perceptible things; and these can arouse the emotions of love, hate, joy, grief, and so on, depending on whether they please or displease us.

2. As well as all that endless variety of ideas, or objects of knowledge, there is also something that knows or perceives them, and acts on them in various ways such as willing, imagining, and remembering. This perceiving, active entity is what I call ‘mind’, ‘spirit’, ‘soul’, or ‘myself’. These words don’t refer to any one of my ideas, but rather to something entirely distinct from them, something in which they exist, or by which they are perceived. Those two are equivalent, because the existence of an idea consists in its being perceived.

3. Everyone will agree that our thoughts, emotions, and ideas of the imagination exist only in the mind. It seems to me equally obvious that the various sensations or ideas that are imprinted on our senses cannot exist except in a mind that perceives them—no matter how they are blended or combined together (that is, no matter what objects they constitute). You can know this intuitively [= ‘you can see this as immediately self-evident’] by attending to what is meant by the term ‘exist’ when it is applied to perceptible things. The table that I am writing on exists, that is, I see and feel it; and if I were out of my study I would still say that it existed, meaning that •if I were in my study I would perceive it, or that •some other spirit actually does perceive it. Similarly,

‘there was an odour’—i.e. it was smelled;

‘there was a sound’—it was heard;

‘there was a colour or shape’—it was seen or felt.

This is all that I can understand by such expressions as these. There are those who speak of things that ·unlike spirits· do not think and ·unlike ideas· exist whether or not they are perceived; but that seems to be perfectly unintelligible. For unthinking things, to exist is to be perceived; so they couldn’t possibly exist out of the minds or thinking things that perceive them.

4. It is indeed widely believed that all perceptible objects—houses, mountains, rivers, and so on—really exist independently of being perceived by the understanding. But however widely and confidently this belief may be held, anyone who has the courage to challenge it will—if I’m not mistaken—see that it involves an obvious contradiction. For what are houses, mountains, rivers etc. but things we perceive by sense? And what do we perceive besides our own ideas or

11

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

sensations? And isn’t it plainly contradictory that these, either singly or in combination, should exist unperceived?

5. If we thoroughly examine this belief ·in things existing independently of the mind· it will, perhaps, be found to depend basically on the doctrine of abstract ideas. For can there be a more delicate and precise strain of abstraction than to distinguish •the existence of perceptible things from •their being perceived, so as to conceive them existing unperceived? Light and colours, heat and cold, extension and shapes, in a word the things we see and feel—what are they but so many sensations, notions, ideas, or sense impressions? And can any of these be separated, even in thought, from perception? Speaking for myself, I would find it no easier to do that than to divide a thing from itself! I don’t deny that I can abstract (if indeed this is properly called abstraction) by conceiving separately objects that can exist separately, even if I have never experienced them apart from one another. I can for example imagine a human torso without the limbs, or conceive the smell of a rose without thinking of the rose itself. But my power of conceiving or imagining goes no further than that: it doesn’t extend beyond the limits of what can actually exist or be perceived. Therefore, because I can’t possibly see or feel a thing without having an actual sensation of it, I also can’t possibly conceive of a perceptible thing distinct from the sensation or perception of it.

6. Some truths are so close to the mind, and so obvious, that as soon as you open your eyes you will see them. Here is an important truth of that kind:

All the choir of heaven and furniture of the earth, in a word all those bodies that compose the mighty structure of the world, have no existence outside a mind; for them to exist is for them to be perceived or known; consequently so long as they aren’t actually perceived by (i.e. don’t exist in the mind of) myself or any other created spirit, they must either have no existence at all or else exist in the mind of some eternal spirit; because it makes no sense—and involves all the absurdity of abstraction—to attribute to any such thing an existence independent of a spirit.

To be convinced of this, you need only to reflect and try to separate in your own thoughts the existence of a perceptible thing from its being perceived—·you’ll find that you can’t·.

7. From what I have said it follows that the only substances are spirits—things that perceive. Another argument for the same conclusion is the following ·down to the end of the section·. The perceptible qualities are colour, shape, motion, smell, taste and so on, and these are ideas perceived by sense. Now it is plainly self-contradictory to suppose that an idea might exist in an unperceiving thing, for to have an idea is just the same as to perceive: so whatever has colour, shape and so on must perceive these qualities; from which it clearly follows that there can be no unthinking substance or substratum of those ideas.

8. ‘But’, you say, ‘though the ideas don’t exist outside the mind, still there may be things like them of which they are copies or resemblances, and these things may exist outside the mind in an unthinking substance.’ I answer that the only thing an idea can resemble is another idea; a colour or shape can’t be like anything but another colour or shape. Attend a little to your own thoughts and you will find that you can’t conceive of any likeness except between your ideas. Also: tell me about those supposed originals or external things of which our ideas are the pictures or representations—are they perceivable or not? If they are, then they are ideas, and I have won the argument; but if you say they are not, I appeal to anyone whether it makes sense to assert that a colour

12

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

is like something that is invisible; that hard or soft is like something intangible; and similarly for the other qualities.

9. Some philosophers distinguish ‘primary qualities’ from ‘secondary’ qualities: they use the •former term to stand for extension, shape, motion, rest, solidity and number; by the •latter term they denote all other perceptible qualities, such as colours, sounds, tastes, and so on. Our ideas of secondary qualities don’t resemble anything existing outside the mind or unperceived, they admit; but they insist that our ideas of primary qualities are patterns or images of things that exist outside the mind in an unthinking substance that they call ‘matter’. By ‘matter’, therefore, we are to understand an inert, senseless substance in which extension, shape and motion actually exist. But I have already shown that extension, shape, and motion are quite clearly nothing but ideas existing in the mind, and that an idea can’t be like anything but another idea, and that consequently neither they nor things from which they are copied can exist in an unperceiving substance. So the very notion of so-called ‘matter’, or corporeal substance, clearly involves a contradiction.

10. Those who assert that shape, motion and the other primary qualities exist outside the mind in unthinking substances say in the same breath that colours, sounds, heat, cold, and other secondary qualities do not. These, they tell us, are sensations that exist in the mind alone, and depend on the different size, texture, and motion of the minute particles of matter. They offer this as an undoubted truth that they can prove conclusively. Now if it is certain that (1) primary qualities are inseparably united with secondary ones, and can’t be abstracted from them even in thought, it clearly follows that (2) primary qualities exist only in the mind, just as the secondary ones do. ·I now defend (1)·. Look in on yourself, and see whether you can perform a mental abstraction that enables you to conceive of a body’s being extended and moving without having any other perceptible qualities. Speaking for myself, I see quite clearly that I can’t form an idea of an extended, moving body unless I also give it some colour or other perceptible quality which is admitted ·by the philosophers I have been discussing· to exist only in the mind. In short, extension, shape and motion, abstracted from all other qualities, are inconceivable. It follows that these primary qualities must be where the secondary ones are—namely in the mind and nowhere else.

11. ·Here’s a further point about extension and motion·. Large and small, and fast and slow, are generally agreed to exist only in the mind. That is because they are entirely relative: whether something is large or small, and whether it moves quickly or slowly, depends on the condition or location of the sense-organs of the perceiver. [See the end of 14 for a little light on the quick/slow part of this point.] So if there is extension outside the mind, it must be neither large nor small, and extra-mental motion must be neither fast nor slow. I conclude that there is no such extension or motion. (If you reply ‘They do exist; they are extension in general and motion in general’, that will be further evidence of how greatly the doctrine about extended, movable substances existing outside the mind depends on that strange theory of abstract ideas.).... So unthinking substances can’t be extended; and that implies that they can’t be solid either, because it makes no sense to suppose that something is solid but not extended.

12. Even if we grant that the other primary qualities exist outside the mind, it must be conceded that number is entirely created by the mind. This will be obvious to anyone who notices that the same thing can be assigned different numbers depending on how the mind views it. Thus, the

13

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

same distance is •one or •three or •thirty-six, depending on whether the mind considers it in terms of •yards, •feet or •inches. Number is so obviously relative and dependent on men’s understanding that I find it surprising that anyone should ever have credited it with an absolute existence outside the mind. We say one book, one page, one line; all these are equally units—·that is, each is one something·—yet the book contains many pages and the page contains many lines. In each case, obviously, what we are saying there is one of is a particular combination of ideas arbitrarily put together by the mind, ·for example, the arbitrary combination of ideas that we choose to call ‘a book’·.

13. Some philosophers, I realize, hold that unity is a simple or uncompounded idea that accompanies every other idea into the mind. I don’t find that I have any such idea corresponding to the word ‘unity’. I could hardly overlook it if it were there in my mind: it ought to be the most familiar to me of all my ideas, since it is said to accompany all my other ideas and to be perceived by all the ways of sensation and reflection. In short, it is an abstract idea!

14. Here is a further point. Some modern philosophers argue that certain perceptible qualities have no existence in matter or outside the mind; their arguments can be used to prove the same thing of all perceptible qualities whatsoever. They point out for instance that a body that appears cold to one hand seems warm to the other, from which they infer that •heat and cold are only states of the mind and don’t resemble anything in the corporeal substances that cause them. If that argument is good, then why can’t we re-apply it to prove that •shape and extension don’t resemble any fixed and determinate qualities existing in matter, because they appear differently to the same eye in different positions, or eyes in different states in the same position? Again, they argue that •sweetness isn’t really in the thing that is described as ‘sweet’, because sweetness can be changed into bitterness without there being any alteration in the thing itself—because the person’s palate has been affected by a fever or some other harm. Is it not equally reasonable to argue that •motion isn’t outside the mind because a thing will appear to move more or less quickly—without any change in the thing itself—depending on whether the succession of ideas in the observer’s mind is slow or fast?

15. In short, the arguments that are thought to prove that colours and tastes exist only in the mind have as much force to prove the same thing of extension, shape and motion. Really, though, these arguments don’t prove that there is no extension or colour in an outward object, but only that our senses don’t tell us what an object’s true extension or colour is. My own previous arguments ·do better: they· clearly show it to be impossible that any colour or extension or other perceptible quality should exist in an unthinking thing outside the mind, or indeed that there should be any such thing as an object outside the mind.

16. But let us examine the usual opinion a little further. It is said that extension is a quality of matter, and that matter is the substratum that supports it. Please explain to me what is meant by matter’s ‘supporting’ extension. You reply: ‘I have no idea of matter; so I can’t explain it.’ I answer: Even if you have no positive meaning for ‘matter’—·that is, have no idea of what matter is like in itself·—you must at least have a relative idea of it, so that you know how matter relates to qualities, and what it means to say that it ‘supports’ them. If you don’t even know that, you have no meaning at all in what you are saying. Explain ‘support’, then! Obviously it cannot be meant here in its usual or literal sense, as when we say that pillars support a building: in what sense, then,

14

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

are we to understand it?

17. When we attend to what the most carefully precise philosophers say they mean by ‘material substance’, we find them admitting that the only meaning they can give to those sounds is the idea of being in general, together with the relative notion of its supporting qualities. The general idea of being seems to me the most abstract and incomprehensible of all. As for its ‘supporting qualities’: since this cannot be understood in the ordinary sense of those words (as I have just pointed out), it must be taken in some other sense; but we aren’t told what that other sense is. I am sure, therefore, that there is no clear meaning in either of the two parts or strands that are supposed to make up the meaning of the words ‘material substance’. Anyway, why should we trouble ourselves any further in discussing this material substratum or support of shape and motion and other perceptible qualities? ·Whatever we make of its details—the notions of being in general, and of support·—it is clearly being said that shape and motion and the rest exist outside the mind. Isn’t this a direct contradiction, and altogether inconceivable?

18. Suppose it were possible for solid, figured, movable substances to exist outside the mind, corresponding to the ideas we have of bodies—how could we possibly know that there are any such things? We must know it either by sense or by reason. Our senses give us knowledge only of our sensations—ideas—things that are immediately perceived by sense—call them what you will! They don’t inform us that outside the mind (that is, unperceived) there exist things that resemble the item s that are perceived. The materialists themselves admit this. So if we are to have any knowledge of external things, it must be by reason, inferring their existence from what is immediately perceived by sense. But what reasons can lead us •from the ideas that we perceive •to a belief in the existence of bodies outside the mind? The supporters of matter themselves don’t claim that there is any necessary connection between material things and our ideas. We could have all the ideas that we now have without there being any bodies existing outside us that resemble them; everyone admits this, and what happens in dreams, hallucinations and so on puts it beyond dispute. Evidently, then, we aren’t compelled to suppose that there are external bodies as causes of our ideas. Those ideas are sometimes, so they could be always, produced without help from bodies yet falling into the patterns that they do in fact exhibit.

19. ‘Even though external bodies aren’t absolutely needed to explain our sensations,’ you might think, ‘the course of our experience is easier to explain on the supposition of external bodies than it is without that supposition. So it is at least probable there are bodies that cause our minds to have ideas of them.’ But this is not tenable either. The materialists admit that they cannot understand how body can act upon spirit, or how it is possible for a body to imprint any idea in a mind; and that is tantamount to admitting that they don’t know how our ideas are produced. So the production of ideas or sensations in our minds can’t be a reason for supposing the existence of matter or corporeal substances, because it admittedly remains a mystery with or without that supposition. So even if it were possible for bodies to exist outside the mind, the belief that they actually do so must be a very shaky one; since it involves supposing, without any reason at all, that God has created countless things that are entirely useless and serve no purpose.

20. In short, if there were external bodies, we couldn’t possibly come to know this; and if there weren’t, we might have the very same reasons to think there were that we

15

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

have now. No-one can deny the following to be possible: A thinking being might, without the help of external bodies, be affected with the same series of sensations or ideas that you have, imprinted in the same order and with similar vividness in his mind. If that happened, wouldn’t that thinking being have all the reason to believe ‘There are corporeal substances that are represented by my ideas and cause them in my mind’ that you can possibly have for believing the same thing? Of course he would; and that consideration is enough, all on its own, to make any reasonable person suspect the strength of whatever arguments he may think he has for the existence of bodies outside the mind.

21. If, even after what has been said, more arguments were needed against the existence of matter, I could cite many errors and difficulties (not to mention impieties) that have sprung from that doctrine. It has led to countless controversies and disputes in philosophy, and many even more important ones in religion. But I shan’t go into the details of them here, because I think arguments about ·materialism’s· bad consequences are unnecessary for confirming what has, I think, been well enough proved a priori regarding its intrinsic defects, and the lack of good reasons to support it. [The word ‘materialism’ doesn’t occur in the Principles. It is used in this version, in editorial notes and interventions, with the meaning that Berkeley gives it in other works, naming the doctrine that •there is such a thing as mind-independent matter, not the stronger doctrine that •there is nothing but matter.]

22. I am afraid I have given you cause to think me needlessly long-winded in handling this subject. For what is the point of hammering away at something that can be proved in a line or two, convincing anyone who is capable of the least reflection? Look into your own thoughts, and try to conceive it possible for a sound or shape or motion or colour to exist outside the mind, or unperceived. Can you do it? This simple thought-experiment may make you see that what you have been defending is a downright contradiction. I am willing to stake my whole position on this: if you can so much as conceive it possible for one extended movable substance—or in general for any one idea or anything like an idea—to exist otherwise than in a mind perceiving it, I shall cheerfully give up my opposition to matter; and as for all that great apparatus of external bodies that you argue for, I shall admit its existence, even though you cannot either give me any reason why you believe it exists, or assign any use to it when it is supposed to exist. I repeat: the bare possibility of your being right will count as an argument that you are right.

23. ‘But’, you say, ‘surely there is nothing easier than to imagine trees in a park, for instance, or books on a shelf, with nobody there to perceive them.’ I reply that this is indeed easy to imagine; but let us look into what happens when you imagine it. You form in your mind certain ideas that you call ‘books’ and ‘trees’, and at the same time you omit to form the idea of anyone who might perceive them. But while you are doing this, you perceive or think of them! So your thought-experiment misses the point; it shows only that you have the power of imagining or forming ideas in your mind; but it doesn’t show that you can conceive it possible for the objects of your thought to exist outside the mind. To show that, you would have to conceive them existing unconceived or unthought-of, which is an obvious contradiction. However hard we try to conceive the existence of external bodies, all we achieve is to contemplate our own ideas. The mind is misled into thinking that it can and does conceive bodies existing outside the mind or unthought-of because it pays no attention to itself, and so doesn’t notice that it contains or thinks of the things that it conceives. Think about it a little and you will see that what I am saying is plainly true;

16

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

there is really no need for any of the other disproofs of the existence of material substance.

24. It takes very little enquiry into our own thoughts to know for sure whether we can understand what is meant by ‘the absolute existence of perceptible objects outside the mind’. To me it is clear that those words mark out either a direct contradiction or else nothing at all. To convince you of this, I know no easier or fairer way than to urge you to attend calmly to your own thoughts: if that attention reveals to you the emptiness or inconsistency of those words, that is surely all you need to be convinced. So that is what I insist on: the phrase ‘the absolute existence of unthinking things’ has either no meaning or a self-contradictory one. This is what I repeat and teach, and urge you to think about carefully.

25. All our ideas—sensations, things we perceive, call them what you will—are visibly inactive; there is no power or agency in them. One idea or object of thought, therefore, cannot produce or affect another. To be convinced of this we need only to attend to our ideas. They are wholly contained within the mind, so whatever is in them must be perceived. Now, if you attend to your ideas, whether of sense or reflection, you will not perceive any power or activity in them; so there is no power or activity in them. Think about it a little and you’ll realize that passiveness and inertness are of the essence of an idea, so that an idea can’t do anything or be the cause (strictly speaking) of anything; nor can it resemble anything that is active, as is evident from 8. From this it clearly follows that extension, shape and motion can’t be the cause of our sensations. So it must be false to say that our sensations result from powers that things have because of the arrangement, number, motion, and size of the corpuscles in them.

26. We perceive a continual stream of ideas: new ones appear, others are changed or totally disappear. These ideas must have a cause—something they depend on, something that produces and changes them. It is clear from 25 that this cause cannot be any quality or idea or combination of ideas, ·because that section shows that ideas are inactive, i.e. have no causal powers; and thus qualities have no powers either, because qualities are ideas·. So the cause must be a substance, ·because reality consists of nothing but substances and their qualities·. It cannot be a corporeal or material substance, because I have shown that there is no such thing. We must therefore conclude that the cause of ideas is an incorporeal active substance—a spirit.

27. A spirit is an active being. It is simple, in the sense that it doesn’t have parts. When thought of as something that •perceives ideas, it is called ‘the understanding’, and when thought of as •producing ideas or doing things with them, it is called ‘the will’. ·But understanding and will are different powers that a spirit has; they aren’t parts of it·. It follows that no-one can form an idea of a soul or spirit. We have seen in 25 that all ideas are passive and inert, and therefore no idea can represent an active thing, ·which is what a spirit is·, because no idea can resemble an active thing. If you think about it a little, you’ll see clearly that it is absolutely impossible to have an idea that is like an active cause of the change of ideas. The nature of spirit (i.e. that which acts) is such that it cannot itself be perceived; all we can do is to perceive the effects it produces. ·To perceive a spirit would be to have an idea of it, that is, an idea that resembles it; and I have shown that no idea can resemble a spirit because ideas are passive and spirits active·. If you think I may be wrong about this, you should look in on yourself and try to form the idea of a power or of an active being, ·that is, a thing that has power·. To do this, you need to have ideas of two principal powers called ‘will’ and ‘understanding’, these

17

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

ideas being distinct from each other and from a third idea of substance or being in general, which is called ‘soul’ or ‘spirit’; and you must also have a relative notion of spirit’s supporting or being the subject of those two powers. Some people say that they have all that; but it seems to me that the words ‘will’ and ‘spirit’ don’t stand for distinct ideas, or indeed for any idea at all, but for something very different from ideas. Because this ‘something’ is an agent, it cannot resemble or be represented by any idea whatsoever. Though it must be admitted that we have some notion of soul, spirit, and operations of the mind such as willing, loving and hating, in that we understand the meanings of those words.

28. I find I can arouse ideas in my mind at will, and vary and shift the mental scene whenever I want to. I need only to will, and straight away this or that idea arises in my mind; and by willing again I can obliterate it and bring on another. It is because the mind makes and unmakes ideas in this way that it can properly be called active. It certainly is active; we know this from experience. But anyone who talks of ‘unthinking agents’ or of ‘arousing ideas without the use of volition’ is merely letting himself be led astray by words.

29. Whatever power I may have over my own thoughts, however, I find that the ideas I get through my senses don’t depend on my will in the same way. When in broad daylight I open my eyes, it isn’t in my power to choose whether or not I shall see anything, or to choose what particular objects I shall see; and the same holds for hearing and the other senses. My will is not responsible for the ideas that come to me through any of my senses. So there must be some other will—some other spirit—that produces them.

30. The ideas of sense are stronger, livelier, and clearer than those of the imagination; and they are also steady, orderly and coherent. Ideas that people bring into their own minds at will are often random and jumbled, but the ideas of sense aren’t like that: they come in a regular series, and are inter-related in admirable ways that show us the wisdom and benevolence of the series’ author. The phrase ‘the laws of nature’ names the set rules or established methods whereby the mind we depend on—·that is, God·—arouses in us the ideas of sense. We learn what they are by experience, which teaches us that such and such ideas are ordinarily accompanied or followed by such and such others.

31. This gives us a sort of foresight that enables us to regulate our actions for the benefit of life. Without this we would always be at a loss: we couldn’t know how to do anything to bring ourselves pleasure or spare ourselves pain. That food nourishes, sleep refreshes, and fire warms us; that to sow in the spring is the way to get a harvest in the fall, and in general that such and such means are the way to achieve such and such ends—we know all this not by discovering any necessary connection between our ideas but only by observing the settled laws of nature. Without them we would be utterly uncertain and confused, and a grown man would have no more idea than a new-born infant does of how to manage himself in the affairs of life.

32. This consistent, uniform working obviously displays the goodness and wisdom of ·God·, the governing spirit whose will constitutes the laws of nature. And yet, far from leading our thoughts towards him, it sends them ·away from him· in a wandering search for second causes—·that is, for causes that come between God and the effects we want to explain·. For when we perceive that certain ideas of sense are constantly followed by other ideas, and we know that this isn’t our doing, we immediately attribute power and agency to the ideas themselves, and make one the cause of another—than which nothing can be more absurd and

18

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

unintelligible. Thus, for example, having observed that when we perceive by sight a certain round luminous figure, we at the same time perceive by touch the idea or sensation called heat, we infer that the sun causes heat. Similarly, when we perceive that a collision of bodies is accompanied by sound, we are inclined to think the latter an effect of the former.

33. The (1) ideas imprinted on the senses by the author of nature are called ‘real things’; and those (2) that are caused by the imagination, being less regular, vivid, and constant, are more properly called ‘ideas’ or ‘images’ of things that they copy and represent. But our (1) sensations, however vivid and distinct they may be, are nevertheless ideas; that is, they exist in the mind, or are perceived by it, as truly as (2) the ideas that mind itself makes. The (1) ideas of sense are agreed to have more reality in them—i.e. to be more strong, orderly, and coherent—than ideas made by the mind; but this doesn’t show that they exist outside the mind. They are also less dependent on the spirit or thinking substance that perceives them, for they are caused by the will of another and more powerful spirit, ·namely God·; but still they are ideas, and certainly no idea—whether faint or strong—can exist otherwise than in a mind perceiving it.

34. Before we move on, I have to spend some time in answering objections that are likely to be made against the principles I have laid down. ·I shall answer twelve of them, ending in 72; and further objections will occupy 73–84. My answer to the first of the twelve will run to the end of 40·. If fast-thinking readers find me too long-winded about this, I hope they will pardon me. ·My excuse is that· people aren’t all equally quick in getting a grasp on topics such as this, and I want to be understood by everyone. First, then, this will be objected:

By your principles everything real and substantial in nature is banished out of the world, and replaced by a chimerical [= ‘unreal or imaginary’] system of ideas. All things that exist do so only in the mind ·according to you·, that is, they are purely notional. Then what becomes of the sun, moon, and stars? What must we think of houses, rivers, mountains, trees, stones—even of our own bodies, for that matter? Are all these mere illusions, creatures of the imagination?

To all this—and any other objections of the same sort—I answer that the principles I have laid down don’t deprive us of any one thing in nature. Whatever we see, feel, hear, or in any way conceive or understand remains as secure as ever, and is as real as ever. There is a real world, and the distinction between realities and chimeras retains its full force. This is evident from 29–30 and 33, where I have shown what is meant by ‘real things’ in opposition to chimeras or ideas made by us; but by that account real things and chimeras both exist in the mind, and in that sense are alike in being ideas.

35. I don’t argue against the existence of any one thing that we can take in, either by sense or reflection. I don’t in the least question that the things I see with my eyes and touch with my hands do exist, really exist. The only thing whose existence I deny is what philosophers call ‘matter’ or ‘corporeal substance’. And in denying this I do no harm to the rest of mankind—·that is, to people other than philosophers·—because they will never miss it. The atheist indeed will lose the rhetorical help he gets from an empty name, ·‘matter’·, which he uses to support his impiety; and the philosophers may find that they have lost a great opportunity for word-spinning and disputation.

19

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

36. If you think that this detracts from the existence or reality of things, you are very far from understanding what I have said in the plainest way I could think of. Here it is again, in brief outline. There are spiritual substances, minds, or human souls, which cause •ideas in themselves through acts of the will, doing this as they please; but these ideas are faint, weak, and unsteady as compared with other •ideas that minds perceive by sense. The latter ideas, being impressed on minds according to certain rules or laws of nature tell us that they are the effects of a mind that is stronger and wiser than human spirits. The latter are said to have more reality in them than the former: by which is meant that they are more forceful, orderly, and distinct, and that they aren’t fictions of the mind that perceives them. In this sense, the sun that I see by day is the real sun, and what I imagine by night is the idea of the former. In the sense I am here giving to ‘reality’, it is evident that every plant, star, rock, and in general each part of the system of the world, is as much a real thing by my principles as by any others. Whether you mean by ‘reality’ anything different from what I do, I beg you to look into your own thoughts and see.

37. You will want to object: ‘At least it is true that you take away all corporeal substances.’ I answer that if the word ‘substance’ is taken in the ordinary everyday sense—standing for a combination of perceptible qualities such as extension, solidity, weight, etc.—I cannot be accused of taking substance away. But if ‘substance’ is taken in a philosophic sense—standing for the support of qualities outside the mind—then indeed I agree that I take it away, if one may be said to ‘take away’ something that never had any existence, not even in the imagination.

38. ‘But’, you say, ‘it sounds weird to say that •we eat and drink ideas, and are clothed with them.’ So it does, because the word ‘idea’ isn’t used in ordinary talk to signify the combinations of perceptible qualities that are called things; and any expression that differs from the familiar use of language is bound to seem weird and ridiculous. But this doesn’t concern the truth of the proposition, which in other words merely says that •we are fed and clothed with things that we perceive immediately by our senses. The hardness or softness, the colour, taste, warmth, shape and such like qualities, which combine to constitute the various sorts of food and clothing, have been shown to exist only in the mind that perceives them; and this is all I mean by calling them ‘ideas’; which word, if it was as ordinarily used as ‘thing’, would sound no weirder or more ridiculous than ‘thing’ does ·in the statement that we eat and drink things and are clothed with them·. My concern isn’t with the propriety of words but with the truth of my doctrine. So if you will agree with me that what we eat, drink, and clothe ourselves with are immediate objects of sense that cannot exist unperceived or outside the mind, I will readily agree with you that it is more proper—more in line with ordinary speech—to call them ‘things’ rather than ‘ideas’.

39. Why do I employ the word ‘idea’, rather than following ordinary speech and calling them ‘things’? For two reasons: first, because the term ‘thing’, unlike ‘idea’, is generally supposed to stand for something existing outside the mind; and secondly, because ‘thing’ has a broader meaning than ‘idea’, because it applies to spirits, or thinking things, as well as to ideas. Since the objects of sense •exist only in the mind, and also •are unthinking and inactive ·which spirits are not·, I choose to mark them by the word ‘idea’, which implies those properties.

40. You may want to say: ‘Say what you like, I will still believe my senses, and will never allow any arguments,

20

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

however plausible they may be, to prevail over the certainty of my senses.’ Be it so, assert the obvious rightness of the senses as strongly as you please—I shall do the same! What I see, hear, and feel exists—i.e. is perceived by me—and I don’t doubt this any more than I doubt my own existence. But I don’t see how the testimony of the senses can be brought as proof of the existence of anything that is not perceived by sense. I don’t want anyone to become a sceptic, and to disbelieve his senses; on the contrary, I give the senses all the emphasis and assurance imaginable; and there are no principles more opposed to scepticism than those I have laid down, as will be clearly shown later on.

41. Secondly [of the twelve objections mentioned in 34], it will be objected that there is a great difference between (for instance) real fire and the idea of fire, between actually being burnt and dreaming or imagining oneself to be burnt. The answer to this—and to all the similar objections that may be brought against my position—is evident from what I have already said. At this point I shall add only this: if real fire is very different from the idea of fire, so also is the real pain that comes from it very different from the idea of that pain; but nobody will maintain that real pain could possibly exist in an unperceiving thing, or outside the mind, any more than the idea of it can.

42. Thirdly, it will be objected that we see things actually outside us, at a distance from us; and these things don’t exist in the mind, for it would be absurd to suppose that things that are seen at the distance of several miles are as near to us as our own thoughts. In answer to this I ask you to considered the fact that in dreams we often perceive things as existing at a great distance off, and yet those things are acknowledged to exist only in the mind.

43. In order to clear up this matter more thoroughly, let us think about how we perceive distance, and things placed at a distance, by sight. For if we really do see external space, and bodies actually existing in it at various distances from us, that does seem to tell against my thesis that bodies exist nowhere outside the mind. It was thinking about this difficulty that led me to write my Essay towards a New Theory of Vision, which was published recently. In that work I show that distance or externality is not immediately of itself perceived by sight, nor is it something we grasp or believe in on the basis of lines and angles, or anything that has a necessary connection with it. Rather, it is only suggested to our thoughts by certain visible ideas and sensations that go with vision—ideas which in their own nature are in no way similar to or related to either •distance or •things at a distance. By a connection taught us by experience they come to signify and suggest distances and distant things to us, in the same way that the words of a language suggest the ideas they are made to stand for. ·There is nothing intrinsic to the word ‘red’ that makes it the right name for that colour; we merely learn what it names through our experience of general usage. Similarly, there is nothing intrinsic to my present visual idea that makes it an idea of a tree in the middle distance; but ideas like it have been connected with middle-distance things in my experience·. Thus, a man who was born blind, and afterwards made to see, wouldn’t at first sight think the things he saw to be outside his mind or at any distance from him ·because he wouldn’t have had any experience enabling him to make that connection·. See section 41 of the New Theory.

44. The ideas of sight and of touch constitute two species, entirely distinct and different from one another. The former are marks and forward-looking signs of the latter. (Even in my New Theory I showed—·though this wasn’t its central purpose·—that the items that are perceived only by sight

21

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

don’t exist outside the mind and don’t resemble external things. Throughout that work I supposed that tangible objects—·ones that we feel·—do exist outside the mind. I didn’t need that common error in order to establish the position I was developing in the book; but I let it stand because it was beside my purpose to examine and refute it in a treatment of vision.) Thus, the strict truth of the matter is this: when we see things at a distance from us, the ideas of sight through which we do this don’t •suggest or mark out to us things actually existing at a distance, but only •warn us about what ideas of touch will be imprinted in our minds if we act in such and such ways for such and such a length of time. On the basis of what I have already said in the present work, and of 147 and other parts of the New Theory, it is evident that visible ideas are the language in which the governing spirit on whom we depend—·God·—tells us what tangible ideas he is about to imprint on us if we bring about this or that movement of our own bodies. For a fuller treatment of this point, I refer you to the New Theory itself.

45. Fourthly, this will be objected:

It follows from your principles that things are at every moment annihilated and created anew. The objects of sense ·according to you· exist only when they are perceived; so the trees are in the garden and the chairs in the parlour only as long as there is somebody there to perceive them. When I shut my eyes all the furniture in the room is reduced to nothing, and merely from my opening them it is again created.

In answer to all this, I ask you to look back at 3, 4, etc. and then ask yourself whether you mean by ‘the actual existence’ of an idea anything but its being perceived. For my part, after the most carefully precise enquiry I could make, I cannot discover that I mean anything else by those words. I ask you again—·as I did in 25 intro·—to examine your own thoughts, and not to allow yourself to be imposed on by words. If you can conceive it to be possible for either your ideas or things of which they are copies to exist without being perceived, then I throw in my hand; but if you can’t, you will admit that it is unreasonable for you to stand up in defence of you know not what, and claim to convict me of absurdity because I don’t assent to propositions that at bottom have no meaning in them.

46. It would be as well to think about how far the commonly accepted principles of philosophy are themselves guilty of those alleged absurdities. It is thought to be highly absurd that when I close my eyes all the visible objects around me should be reduced to nothing; but isn’t this what philosophers commonly admit when they all agree that light and colours—which are the only immediate objects of sight and only of sight—are mere sensations, and exist only while they are perceived? Again, some may find it quite incredible that things should be coming into existence at every moment; yet this very notion is commonly taught in the schools [= the Aristotelian philosophy departments]. For the schoolmen, though they acknowledge the existence of matter, and say that the whole world is made out of it, nevertheless hold that matter cannot go on existing without God’s conserving it, which they understand to be his continually creating it.

47. Furthermore, a little thought will show us that even if we do admit the existence of matter or corporeal substance, it will still follow from principles that are now generally accepted, that no particular bodies of any kind exist while they aren’t perceived. For it is evident from 11 and the following sections that the matter philosophers stand up for is an incomprehensible something, having none of those particular qualities through which the bodies falling under

22

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

our senses are distinguished one from another. To make this more plain, bear in mind that the infinite divisibility of matter is now accepted by all, or at least by the most approved and considerable philosophers, who have demonstrated it conclusively from principles that are generally accepted. ·Now consider the following line of thought, starting from the premise of the infinite divisibility of matter·.

Each particle of matter contains an infinite number of parts that aren’t perceived by sense ·because they are too small·. Why, then, does any particular body seem to be of a finite magnitude, or exhibit only a finite number of parts to our senses? Not because it has only finitely many parts, for it contains an infinite number of parts. Rather, it is because our senses aren’t acute enough to detect any more. Therefore, in proportion as any of our senses becomes more acute, it will perceive more parts in the object; that is, the object will appear larger, and its shape will be different because parts near its outer edges—ones that before were unperceivable—will appear to give it a boundary whose lines and angles are very different from those perceived by the sense before it became sharper. If the sense in question became infinitely acute, the body would go through various changes of size and shape, and would eventually seem infinite. All this would happen with no alteration in the body, only a sharpening of the sense. Each body, therefore, considered in itself, is infinitely extended and consequently has no shape.

From this it follows that even if we grant that the existence of matter is utterly certain, it is equally certain—as the materialists are forced by their own principles to admit—that the particular bodies perceived through the senses don’t exist outside the mind, nor does anything like them. According to them, each particle of matter is infinite and shapeless, and it is the mind that makes all that variety of bodies that compose the visible world, none of which exists any longer than it is perceived.

48. When you think about it, the objection brought in 45 turns out not to provide reasonable support for any accusation against my views. I do indeed hold that the things we perceive are nothing but ideas that can’t exist unperceived, but it doesn’t follow that they have no existence except when they are perceived by us; for there may be some other spirit that perceives them when we don’t. Whenever I say that bodies have no existence outside ‘the mind’, I refer not to this or that particular mind but to all minds whatsoever. So it doesn’t follow from my principles that bodies are annihilated and created every moment, or that they don’t exist at all during the intervals between our perception of them.

49. Fifthly, it may be objected that if extension and shape exist only in the mind, it follows that the mind is extended and shaped, because extension is a quality or attribute that is predicated of the subject in which it exists. I answer that those qualities are ‘in the mind’ only in that they are perceived by it—that is, not as qualities or attributes ·of it· but only as ideas ·that it has·. It no more follows that the soul or mind is extended because extension exists only in it than it follows that the mind is red or blue because (as everyone agrees) those colours exist only in it. As to what philosophers say of subject and mode [= ‘quality’], that seems very groundless and unintelligible. For instance, in the proposition A die is hard, extended, and square they hold that the word ‘die’ refers to a subject or substance that is distinct from the hardness, extension, and squareness that are predicated of it—a subject in which those qualities exist. I cannot make sense of this. To me a die seems to be nothing

23

Principles George Berkeley 1–50

over and above the things that are called its ‘qualities’. And to say that a die is hard, extended, and square isn’t to attribute those qualities to a subject distinct from and supporting them, but only to explain the meaning of the word ‘die’.

50. Sixthly, you will object like this:

Many things have been explained in terms of matter and motion. if you take away these you will destroy the whole corpuscular philosophy [that is, the approach to physics in which the key concepts are those of matter, motion, and physical structure], and undermine those mechanical principles that have been applied with so much success to explain the phenomena. In short, whatever advances have been made in the study of nature by ancient scientists or by modern ones have all built on the supposition that corporeal substance or matter

really exists. To this I answer that every single phenomenon that is explained on that supposition could just as well be explained without it, as I could easily show by going through them all one by one. ·Instead of that, however, I shall do something that takes less time, namely show that the supposition of matter cannot explain any phenomenon·. To explain the phenomena is simply to show why upon such and such occasions we are affected with such and such ideas. But how matter should operate on a mind, or produce any idea in it, is something that no philosopher or scientist will claim to explain. So, obviously, there can be no use for ·the concept of· matter in natural science. Besides, those who try explain things do it not by corporeal substance but by shape, motion and other qualities; these are merely ideas and therefore can’t cause anything, as I have already shown. See 25.

24

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

Sections 51–99

51. Seventhly, from what I have said you will want to protest:

It seems absurd to take away natural causes, and attribute everything to the immediate operation of spirits! According to your principles, we must no longer say that fire heats or water cools, but that a spirit heats, and so forth. If someone actually talked like that, wouldn’t he be laughed at, and rightly so?

Yes, he would. In matters like this we ought to think with the learned and speak with the vulgar [= ‘with the common people’]. ·There is nothing disreputable about this; learned people already do ‘speak with the vulgar’ in many respects·. People who are perfectly convinced of the truth of the Copernican system in astronomy still say that ‘the sun rises’, ‘the sun sets’, ‘the sun is high in the sky’; and it would surely seem ridiculous to speak in any other way. Think about this a little and you will see that the acceptance of my doctrines wouldn’t even slightly disturb or alter the common use of language.

52. In the ordinary affairs of life, we can go on using any turns of phrase—even ones that are false when taken in a really strict sense—so long as they arouse in us appropriate thoughts or feelings or dispositions to act in ways that are good for us. Indeed, this is unavoidable, because the standards for proper speech are set by what is customary, so that language has to be shaped by commonly held opinions, which are not always the truest. So even in the strictest philosophic reasonings we cannot alter the outlines of the English language so completely that we never provide faultfinders with an opportunity to accuse us of difficulties and inconsistencies in what we say. But a fair and honest reader will gather what is meant by a discourse from its over-all tendency and from how its parts hang together, making allowances for those inaccurate turns of phrase that common use has made inevitable.

53. As for the thesis that there are no corporeal causes—·that is, no bodies that have causal powers·—this used to be maintained by some of the schoolmen, and also more recently by some modern philosophers ·such as Malebranche·. Those moderns did believe that matter exists, but they insisted that God alone is the immediate cause of everything. They saw that none of the objects of sense has any power or activity included in it, from which they inferred that the same holds for the bodies that they thought to exist outside the mind. Yet they went on believing in such bodies! That is, they believed in a vast multitude of created things that were admittedly incapable of producing any effects in nature, so that there was no point in God’s creating them since he could have done everything just as well without them. Even if this were possible, it would still be a very puzzling and extravagant supposition.

54. In the eighth place, some may think that the existence of matter, or of external things, is shown by the fact that all mankind believe in it. Must we suppose the whole world to be mistaken?—·the objection runs·—and if so, how can we explain such a wide-spread and predominant error? I answer, •first, that when we look into it carefully we may find that the existence of matter or of things outside the mind is not really believed in by as many people as the objector imagines. Strictly speaking, it is impossible to believe something that involves a contradiction, or has no meaning in it; and I invite you to consider impartially whether ‘matter’ and ‘things

25

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

outside the mind’ aren’t of that sort. In one sense indeed, men may be said to ‘believe that matter exists’: that is, they act as if the immediate cause of their sensations, which affects them every moment and is so nearly present to them, were some unsensing and unthinking being. But that they should clearly have any meaning for those words, and make out of them a settled theoretical opinion, is what I cannot conceive. This isn’t the only case where men deceive themselves by imagining they believe propositions that they have often heard but basically have no meaning in them.

55. But in any case (and this is my •second reply), even if some proposition is firmly believed by nearly everyone, that is a weak argument for its truth to anyone who considers what a vast number of prejudices and false opinions are everywhere accepted with the utmost tenacity by unreflecting people—i.e. by the great majority of people. There was a time when ·everyone·, even learned men, regarded as monstrous absurdities the view that there are there are lands on the opposite side of the globe, and the view that the earth moves. ·The learned now know better, but· when we consider what a small proportion of mankind they are, we can expect that even now those notions (·of the earth’s moving and of there being lands on the far side of it·) are not widely accepted in the world.

56. But I am challenged to explain this prejudice ·that there is matter outside the mind·, and to account for its popularity. I now do so. Men became aware that they perceived various ideas of which they themselves were not the authors, because these ideas weren’t caused from within, and didn’t depend on the operation of their wills. This led them to think that those ideas—those objects of perception—had an existence independent of the mind and outside it; and it never entered their heads that a contradiction was involved in those words. But philosophers plainly saw that the immediate objects of perception don’t exist outside the mind, and this led them to correct, up to a point, the mistake of the common man. In doing this, though, they ran into another mistake that seems equally absurd, namely: that certain objects really exist outside the mind, having an existence distinct from being perceived, and our ideas are only images or resemblances of these objects, imprinted by the objects on the mind. And this view of the philosophers has the same source as the common man’s mistake: they realized that they weren’t the authors of their own sensations, which they clearly knew were imprinted from outside and must therefore have some cause distinct from the minds on which they were imprinted.

57. Why did they suppose that the ideas of sense are caused in us by things they resemble, rather than attributing them to ·the causal action of· spirit, which is the only kind of thing that can act? ·For three reasons.·. First, the philosophers weren’t aware of the inconsistency of supposing that

•things like our ideas exist outside minds, and that

•things like our ideas have power or activity.

Second, the supreme spirit that causes those ideas in our minds isn’t presented to us by any particular finite collection of perceptible ideas, in the way that human agents are marked out by their size, skin-colour, limbs, and motions. Third, the supreme spirit’s operations are regular and uniform. Whenever the course of nature is interrupted by a miracle, men are ready to admit that a superior being is at work; but when we see the course of events continue in the ordinary way, we aren’t prompted to reflect on this. Although the order and interlinking of events is evidence for the greatest wisdom, power, and goodness in their creator, it is so constant and familiar to us that we don’t think of the events as the immediate effects of a free spirit—especially since inconstancy and changeability in acting, though really

26

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

an imperfection, is looked on as a sign of freedom. [That completes Berkeley’s ’eighth’ objection. There is no ninth.]

58. Tenthly, this will be objected:

The views you advance are inconsistent with various sound truths in science and mathematics. For example, the motion of the earth is now universally accepted by astronomers as a truth grounded in the clearest and most convincing reasons; but on your principles there can be no such motion. For motion is only an idea; so it doesn’t exist except as perceived; but the motion of the earth is not perceived by sense.

I answer that the doctrine that the earth moves, if rightly understood, will be found to agree with my principles. The question ‘Does the earth move?’ amounts in reality to just this:

Do we have reason to conclude from what astronomers have observed that if we were placed in such and such circumstances, at such or such a position and distance both from the earth and sun, we would see the earth moving among the choir of the planets and appearing in all respects like one of them?

·The answer is Yes·. This is a conclusion we can reasonably draw from the phenomena through the established rules of nature, which we have no reason to mistrust.

59. From the experience we have had of the order and succession of ideas in our minds, we can often make something better than uncertain conjectures—indeed, sure and well-grounded predictions—concerning the ideas we •shall have if we •do engage in this or that complex sequence of actions; and these predictions enable us to judge correctly what •would have appeared to us if things •had been ·in such and such specific ways· very different from those we are in at present. That is what the knowledge of nature consists in—an account that preserves the usefulness and certainty of such knowledge without conflicting with what I have said. It will be easy to re-apply this ·line of thought· to any other objections of the same sort concerning the size of the stars or any other discoveries in astronomy or nature.

60. In the eleventh place, you will want to ask [the question runs to the end of the section]: ‘What purpose is served by the intricate organization of plants, and the wonderful mechanism in the parts of animals? All those internal parts so elegantly contrived and put together, because they are ideas, have no power, no capacity to operate in any way; nor are they necessarily connected with the effects that are attributed to them. So couldn’t plants grow and send out leaves and blossoms, and animals move as they now do, just as well •without all those inner parts as •with them? If every effect is produced by the immediate action of a spirit, everything that is fine and skillfully put together in the works of man or of nature seems to be made in vain. According to this doctrine, a skilled watchmaker who makes the spring and wheels and other parts of a watch, putting them together in the way that he knows will produce the movements that he wants the hands to make, should think that he is wasting his time and that it is an intelligence—·namely, God’s·—that steers the hands of the watch so that they tell the time. If so, why shouldn’t that intelligence do it without his having to take the trouble to make the parts and put them together? Why doesn’t an empty watch-case serve as well as one containing a mechanism? Also, why is it that whenever a watch doesn’t go right there is some corresponding fault to be found in its mechanism, and when the fault is repaired the watch works properly again? The same questions arise regarding the clockwork of nature, much of which is so wonderfully fine and subtle that it could hardly be detected by the best microscope.’

27

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

61. ·Here are three preliminaries to my main answer to this·. First, even if my principles do fail to solve some difficulties concerning how providence manages the world, and what uses it assigns to the various parts of nature, this objection couldn’t carry much weight against the truth and certainty of those things that can be conclusively proved a priori. Secondly, the commonly accepted principles suffer from similar difficulties; for we can challenge their adherents to explain why God should take those round-about methods of getting results by instruments and machines, when everyone knows that he could have achieved them by the mere command of his will, without all that apparatus. Indeed (thirdly), if we think about it hard we shall find that this objection tells with greater force against those who believe in those machines outside the mind; for it has been made evident that solidity, bulk, shape, motion and the like have no activity or efficacy in them, and so cannot produce any one effect in nature. See 25. So anyone who supposes them to exist (allowing the supposition to be possible) when they aren’t perceived does this obviously to no purpose; for the only use that is assigned to them, as they exist unperceived, is to produce those perceivable effects that can’t in truth be ascribed to anything but spirit.

62. But to come nearer to the difficulty, it must be observed that though the making of all those parts and organs isn’t absolutely necessary for producing any effect, it is necessary for producing things in a constant, regular way according to the laws of nature. There are certain general laws that run through the whole chain of natural effects; we learn these by the observation and study of nature, and apply them in making artificial things for the use and ornament of life, as well as in explaining the various phenomena. Such an explanation consists only in showing how a particular phenomenon conforms to the general laws of nature, or (the same thing) in revealing the uniformity that there is in the production of natural effects. You can see this if you attend to particular explanations that scientists have offered for phenomena. I showed in 31 that the supreme agent’s regular constant methods of working have a great and obvious usefulness to us. And it is no less obvious that a particular size, shape, motion, and structure, though not absolutely necessary for any effect, are necessary for the effect to be produced according to the standing mechanical laws of nature. Thus, for instance, it can’t be denied that God (the intelligence that sustains and rules the ordinary course of things) could produce a miracle if he wanted to, causing all the movements on the dial of a watch without anyone’s supplying it with a working mechanism; but if he is to act in conformity with the rules of mechanism, established and maintained by him for wise ends, it is necessary that those actions of the watchmaker in which he makes and then adjusts the machinery precede the movements of the hands on the dial; and also that any disorder in those movement be accompanied by the perception of some corresponding disorder in the machinery, the correction of which cures the disorder.

63. It may indeed sometimes be necessary that the author of nature display his overruling power in producing some appearance that doesn’t fit his ordinary pattern of events. Such exceptions from the general rules of nature are just what’s needed to surprise and awe men into an acknowledgment of the divine being; but then they aren’t to be used often, for if they were they would fail to have that effect. Besides, God seems to prefer •convincing our reason about what he is like through the works of nature, which reveal so much harmony and ingenuity in their structure and are such plain indications of wisdom and good-will in their author, to •astonishing us by anomalous and surprising events into

28

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

believing that he exists.

64. The objection brought in 60 really amounts only to the following. Ideas aren’t produced anyhow and at random; there is a certain order and connection amongst them, like the order of causes and effects; and they come in various combinations that are put together in a very regular manner as though by design. These combinations seem like instruments in the hand of nature. Hidden behind the scenes, so to speak, they secretly operate in producing the appearances that are seen on the world’s stage, though they themselves are detected only by the scientist who looks for them. But since one idea can’t cause another, what is the purpose of this order and connection? Since those ‘instruments in the hand of nature’ are mere powerless perceptions in the mind, and so can’t help in the production of natural effects, I am being asked why they exist at all. That is to ask why it is that when we closely inspect God’s works he causes us to observe such a great variety of ideas, inter-related in ways that are so regular and look so much like the result of a designer’s skill. It isn’t credible that he would to no purpose put himself to the expense (so to speak) of all that skillful design and regularity.

65. ·My answer to all this has two parts·. First, the connection of ideas doesn’t imply the relation of cause and effect, but only of a mark or sign with the thing signified. The fire I see is not the •cause of the pain I suffer when I come too close, but a •sign that warns me of that pain. Similarly, the noise that I hear is not an •effect of a collision of nearby bodies, but a •sign of it. Secondly, the reason why ideas are formed into machines, i.e. regular combinations that manifest a designer’s skill, is the same as the reason why letters are combined into words. If a few basic ideas are to signify a great number of effects and actions, there must be different ways of combining them; if these combinations are to be usable by everyone, they must be contrived wisely ·so that they can carry vast amounts of information yet still be understood by us·; and if they are to be always available and helpful, they must be governed by rules ·that don’t change from time to time·. In this way we are given a great deal of information about what to expect from such and such actions, and how to go about arousing such and such ideas. And really that is all that is clearly meant when people say that by finding out the shape, texture, and structure of the inner parts of bodies, whether natural or artificial, we can discover what the thing is really like and how it can be used.

66. Hence it is evident that things that are •the wholly inexplicable source of great absurdities when they are regarded as causes that help to produce effects can be •very naturally explained, and have a proper and obvious use assigned them when they are considered only as marks or signs for our information. What the scientist ought to be doing is to detect and decipher those signs (this language, so to speak) instituted by the author of nature, not claiming to explain things in terms of corporeal causes—a claim that seems to have too much estranged the minds of men from ·God·, that active principle, that supreme and wise spirit, ‘in whom we live, move, and have our being’.

67. In the twelfth place, this may be objected:

It is clear from what you have said that there can be no such thing as an inert, senseless, extended, solid, shaped, movable substance existing outside the mind, which is how philosophers describe matter. But suppose someone leaves out of his idea of matter the positive ideas of extension, shape, solidity, and motion, and says that all he means by that word is an inert senseless substance that exists outside the

29

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

mind (or unperceived) and is the occasion of our ideas, meaning ·by ‘occasion’· that God is pleased to cause ideas in us when matter is present. There seems to be no reason why matter in this sense of the word should not exist.

In answer to this I say first that it seems no less absurd to suppose a substance without qualities than it is to suppose qualities without a substance. Anyway, secondly, if this unknown substance exists where does it do so? We agree that it doesn’t exist in the mind; and it is equally certain that it doesn’t exist in some place, for all (place or) extension exists only in the mind, as I have already proved. So it exists nowhere at all!

68. Let us examine a little the description of matter that is given to us here. [This next sentence reflects the fact that ‘substance’ comes from Latin meaning ‘stand under’.] It neither acts, nor perceives, nor is perceived, for that is all it means to say that it is an inert, senseless, unknown substance—which is a definition entirely made up of negatives (except for the relative notion of its standing under or supporting, but notice that it supports ·no qualities, and therefore supports· nothing at all), so that it comes as close as you like to being the description of a nonentity. ‘But’, you say, ‘it is the unknown occasion at the presence of which ideas are caused in us by the will of God.’ I would like to know how anything can be present to us if it isn’t perceivable by sense or reflection, isn’t capable of producing any idea in our minds, isn’t at all extended, has no form, and exists in no place! The words ‘to be present’, as used here, have to be taken in some abstract and strange meaning that I cannot grasp.

69. Again, let us examine what is meant by ‘occasion’. So far as I can gather from the common use of language, that word signifies either •the agent that produces some effect, or •something that is observed to accompany or go before ·a kind of event· in the ordinary course of things. But when it is applied to matter as described in 67, the word ‘occasion’ cannot be taken in either of those senses. For matter is said to be passive and inert, and so it cannot be an agent or cause. It is also unperceivable, because devoid of all perceptible qualities, and so it cannot be the occasion of our perceptions in the latter sense—as when burning my finger is said to be the occasion of the pain that goes with it. So what can be meant by calling matter an ‘occasion’? this term is used either with no meaning or with some meaning very distant from its commonly accepted one.

70. Perhaps you will say this:

Although matter is not perceived by us, it is perceived by God, and to him it is the occasion of causing ideas in our minds. We do observe that our sensations are imprinted on our minds in an orderly and constant manner, which makes it reasonable for us to suppose there are certain constant and regular occasions of their being produced. That is, there are certain permanent and distinct portions of matter corresponding to our ideas; they don’t cause the ideas in our minds or any other way immediately affect us, because they are altogether passive and unperceivable by us; but God can and does perceive them, and lets them serve as occasions to remind him when and what ideas to imprint on our minds, so that things may go on in a constant, uniform manner.

71. In answer to this, I remark that on this account of matter we are no longer discussing the existence of a thing distinct from spirit and idea, from perceiving and being perceived. ·For matter is now being said to be perceived by God, and so· our concern now is with the question of whether there are

30

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

certain ideas (of I know not what sort) in the mind of God that are marks or notes that direct him how to produce sensations in our minds in a constant and regular method—in much the way that the notes of music ·in a score· direct a musician to produce a tune, though the listeners don’t perceive the ·written· notes and may be entirely ignorant of them. But this notion of matter seems too extravagant to deserve a refutation. And anyway it doesn’t count against what I have been defending, namely the thesis that there is no senseless unperceived substance.

72. The constant, uniform way that our sensations run will, if we follow the light of reason, lead us to infer the goodness and wisdom of the spirit who causes them in our minds. But I cannot see anything else that we can reasonably infer. To me, I say, it is obvious that the existence of an infinitely wise, good, and powerful spirit is quite enough to explain all the appearances of nature. As for inert, senseless matter: nothing that I perceive has the slightest connection with it, or leads to the thoughts of it. I challenge anyone to •use it to explain any natural phenomenon, however small, or •show any sort of reason, even one yielding only a very low probability, that he has for believing in its existence, or even •provide a tolerable sense or meaning for that supposition. ·The last point isn’t met by saying that matter is at least an occasion·. For, as to its being an occasion, I think I have shown plainly that with regard to us it is no occasion; so if it is an occasion to anyone it must be to God—his occasion for causing ideas in us—and we have just seen what this amounts to.

73. It is worthwhile to reflect a little on the motives that induced men to suppose the existence of material substance. As we watch those motives or reasons gradually weaken and die, we can correspondingly weaken the assent that was based on them. •First, it was thought that colour, shape, motion, and the other perceptible qualities really do exist outside the mind; and this led them to think they needed to suppose some unthinking substratum or substance in which the qualities exist, since they couldn’t be conceived to exist by themselves. •Secondly, some time later men became convinced that colours, sounds, and the rest of the perceptible secondary qualities have no existence outside the mind; so they stripped those qualities off this substratum or material substance, leaving only the primary ones, shape, motion, and such like, which they still conceived to exist outside the mind and consequently to need a material support. But I have shown that none even of the primary qualities can possibly exist otherwise than in a spirit or mind that perceives them, so we are left with no remaining reason to suppose the existence of matter. Indeed it is utterly impossible that any such thing should exist, so long as ‘matter’ is taken to stand for an unthinking substratum of qualities, in which they exist outside the mind.

74. The materialists themselves conceded that matter was thought of only as a support for qualities. With that reason having collapsed, one might expect that the mind would naturally and without reluctance give up the belief that was based on it alone. Yet the prejudice is riveted so deeply in our thoughts that we can hardly tell how to part with it, and this inclines us, since the thing itself is indefensible, at least to retain the name, which we use to convey I know not what abstracted and indefinite notions of being or occasion, though without any show of reason, at least so far as I can see. Looking at it from our side: what do we perceive among all the ideas, sensations and notions that are imprinted on our minds by sense or reflection from which we can infer the existence of an inert, thoughtless, unperceived occasion? Looking at it from the side of ·God·, the all-sufficient spirit:

31

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

why should we believe or even suspect that he is directed by an inert occasion to cause ideas in our minds?

75. We have here a very extraordinary and lamentable example of the force of prejudice. Against all the evidence of reason, people remain devoted to a stupid, thoughtless something that they insert in such a way as to screen themselves off, so to speak, from the providence of God, and move him further away from the affairs of the world. But even if •they do all they can to secure the belief in matter, even if •when reason forsakes them they try to support their opinion by the bare possibility of the thing, and even if •they defend that poor possibility by an uninhibited use of imagination with no guidance from reason—still the most they get out of this is that there are certain unknown ideas in the mind of God; for this is what is meant (if indeed anything is meant) by ‘occasion with regard to God’. And this, at the bottom line, is no longer contending for the thing but only for the name.

76. I shan’t argue about whether there are such ideas in the mind of God, and whether they may be called ‘matter’. But if you stick to the notion of an unthinking substance, or support of extension, motion, and other perceptible qualities, then to me it is most evidently impossible there should be any such thing, because it is a plain contradiction that those qualities should exist in or be supported by an unperceiving substance.

77. You may say this:

Still, granting that there is no thoughtless support of extension and of the other •qualities we perceive, perhaps there’s an inert unperceiving substance or substratum of some •other qualities that are as incomprehensible to us as colours are to a man born blind, because we don’t have a sense adapted to them. If we had a new sense, perhaps we would no more doubt of their existence than a blind man doubts the existence of light and colours when he regains his sight.

I answer first that if what you mean by ‘matter’ is only the unknown support of unknown qualities, it doesn’t matter whether there is such a thing, since it no way concerns us; and I don’t see what good it will do us to dispute about we know not what, and we know not why.

78. But secondly, if we had a new sense it could only provide us with new ideas or sensations; and then we would have the same reason against their existing in an unperceiving substance that I have already offered with relation to shape, motion, colour, and the like. Qualities, as I have shown, are nothing but sensations or ideas, which exist only in a mind perceiving them; and this is true not only of the ideas we are acquainted with at present but likewise of all possible ideas whatsoever.

79. You will insist:

What if I have no reason to believe in the existence of matter? What if I can’t find any use for it, or explain anything by it, or even conceive what is meant by that word? It is still not a contradiction to say ‘Matter exists, and it is in general a substance, or occasion of ideas’; though admittedly there may be great difficulties in unfolding the meaning of those words, or standing by any particular account of what they mean.

I answer that when words are used without a meaning you may put them together as you please without danger of running into a contradiction. You may say, for example, that ‘Twice two is equal to seven’, so long as you declare that you don’t intend those words in their usual meanings, but for marks of you know not what. And by the same

32

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

reason you may say ‘There is an inert thoughtless substance without qualities, which is the occasion of our ideas’. We shall understand just as much by one proposition as by the other.

80. In the last place, you will say:

What if we give up the cause of material substance, and say only that matter is an unknown something, neither substance nor quality, neither spirit nor idea, inert, thoughtless, indivisible, immovable, unextended, existing in no place? Whatever arguments may be brought against substance or occasion, or any other positive notion of matter, are of no effect so long as this negative definition of ‘matter’ is kept to.

I answer that you may, if you see fit, use ‘matter’ in the same sense that other men use ‘nothing’, thus making those terms equivalent. For, after all, this is what appears to me to be the result of that definition: when I attentively consider its parts, either all together or one at a time, I don’t find there is any kind of effect or impression made on my mind different from what is caused by the term ‘nothing’.

81. You may reply that this definition includes something that sufficiently distinguishes it from ‘nothing’, namely the positive, abstract idea of quiddity [= ‘being-the-kind-of-thing-it-is’], entity, or existence. I admit that those who claim to be able to form abstract general ideas do talk as if they had such an idea; they call it the most abstract and general notion of all, while I call it the most incomprehensible. I see no reason to deny that there is a great variety of spirits, of different orders and capacities, whose abilities are far greater and more numerous than those the author of my being has bestowed on me. And for me to claim, on the basis of my own few, niggardly, narrow inlets of perception, what ideas the inexhaustible power of the supreme spirit may imprint on them would certainly be the utmost folly and presumption. For all I know, there may be innumerable sorts of ideas or sensations that differ from one another, and from any that I have perceived, as much as colours differ from sounds. But however ready I am to acknowledge how little I grasp of the endless variety of spirits and ideas that might possibly exist, when someone claims to have a notion of entity or existence—abstracted from spirit and idea, from perceiving and being perceived—I suspect him of a downright inconsistency and of trifling with words. And now we should consider the objections that may be made on religious grounds.

82. Some people think this:

Although the arguments for the real existence of bodies that are drawn from reason don’t amount to demonstrations, yet the holy scriptures are so clear about this that they will sufficiently convince every good Christian that bodies do really exist and are something more than mere ideas. The scriptures relate innumerable facts that obviously involve the reality of timber, stone, mountains, rivers, cities, and human bodies.

I answer that any writing at all, religious or secular, which uses ‘timber’, ‘stone’ and such words in their common meanings, or so as to have some meaning, runs no risk of having its truth called into question by my doctrine. That all those things really exist, that there are bodies—and even corporeal substances when this phrase is taken in its ordinary-language sense—has been shown to be agreeable to my principles: and the difference between things and ideas, realities and chimeras, has been clearly explained. I don’t think that either what philosophers call matter, or the existence of objects outside the mind, is mentioned anywhere in scripture.

33

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

83. Whether or not there are external things, everyone agrees that the proper use of words is in signalling our •conceptions, or •things only as they are known and perceived by us; and from this it plainly follows that in the doctrines I have laid down there is nothing inconsistent with the correct meaningful use of language, and that discourse of any kind whatsoever, as long as it is intelligible, remains undisturbed. But all this seems so obvious from what I have already said that there is no need for me to go on about it.

84. But this will be urged:

Miracles, at least, become much less striking and important on your principles. What must we think of Moses’ rod? Rather than its really being turned into a serpent, was there only a change of ideas in the minds of the spectators? Are we to suppose that all our saviour did at the marriage-feast in Cana was to influence the sight, smell, and taste of the guests in such a way as to create in them the appearance or mere idea of wine? The same may be said of all other miracles. On your principles they must all be regarded as merely cheats, or illusions of the imagination.

To this I reply that the rod was changed into a real serpent, and the water into real wine. That this doesn’t in the least contradict what I have elsewhere said will be evident from 34–5. But this business of real and imaginary has been already so plainly and fully explained, and so often referred to, and the difficulties about it are so easily answered by what I have already said, that it would be an insult to your understanding to explain it all over again here. I shall only observe that if at table all who were present could see, smell, taste and drink wine, and feel the effects of it, that leaves me with no doubt as to its reality. So that in the final analysis the worry about real miracles isn’t raised by my principles but is raised by the received principles [= by materialism], so that it counts for rather than against my position.

85. I have finished with the objections announced in 34, which I tried to present as clearly and with as much force and weight as I could. My next task is to consider the consequences of my principles. Some of these come to the surface immediately, for example that several difficult and obscure questions on which much speculation has been wasted, are ·on my principles· entirely banished from philosophy. Can corporeal substance think? Is matter infinitely divisible? How does matter act on spirit? These and similar questions have endlessly led philosophers astray in all ages; but because they depend on the existence of matter they don’t arise on my principles. Many other advantages, concerning religion as well as the sciences, can easily be deduced from what I have laid down. But this will appear more plainly in what follows ·from here to the end of the work·.

86. From the principles I have laid down, it follows that human knowledge can naturally be classified under two headings—knowledge of ideas, and of spirits. I shall take these separately. First, as to ideas or unthinking things, our knowledge of these has been very much obscured and confused, and we have been led into very dangerous errors, by supposing a two-fold existence of the objects of sense, •one intelligible, or in the mind, •the other real and outside the mind. The latter has been thought to give unthinking things a natural existence of their own, distinct from being perceived by spirits. This, which I think I have shown to be a most groundless and absurd notion, is the very root of scepticism: as long as men thought that real things existed outside the mind, and that their knowledge was real only to the extent that it conformed to real things, it followed that they couldn’t be certain that they had any real knowledge

34

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

at all. For how can it be known that the things that are perceived conform to those that aren’t perceived, i.e. that exist outside the mind?

87. Colour, shape, motion, extension, and the like, considered only as so many sensations in the mind, are perfectly known, because there is nothing in them that isn’t perceived. But if they are looked on as signs or images that are meant to copy things existing outside the mind, then we are all involved in scepticism ·through a line of thought that goes like this·:

We see only the appearances of things, not their real qualities. We can’t possibly know what a thing’s size, shape or motion is, really and absolutely, in itself; all we can know is how its size etc. relate to our senses. Our ideas can vary while things remain the same, and which of our ideas—whether indeed any of them—represent the true quality really existing in the thing is something we have no way to discover. For all we know, everything that we see, hear, and feel may be only phantom and empty chimera, and not at all agree with the real things existing in the real world.

All this scepticism follows from supposing a difference between things and ideas, and that the former exist outside the mind, or unperceived. It would be easy to expand on this topic and show how the arguments advanced by sceptics in all ages depend on the supposition of external objects.

88. So long as we credit unthinking things with having a real existence distinct from their being perceived, we can’t possibly know for sure •what the nature is of any real unthinking being, or even •that it exists. And so we see philosophers distrust their senses, and doubt the existence of heaven and earth, of everything they see or feel, even of their own bodies. And after all their labour and struggle of thought, they are forced to admit that we cannot get any self-evident or conclusively proved knowledge of the existence of perceptible things. But all this doubtfulness, which so bewilders and confuses the mind and makes philosophy ridiculous in the eyes of the world, vanishes if we give our words meanings, and don’t distract ourselves with the terms ‘absolute’, ‘external’, ‘exist’, and such like, signifying we know not what. I can as well doubt my own existence as the existence of things that I actually perceive by sense. For it is an obvious contradiction to suppose that any perceptible object should •be immediately perceived by sight or touch and at the same time •have no existence in nature, because the very existence of an unthinking being consists in being perceived.

89. If we are to erect a firm system of sound and real knowledge that can withstand the assaults of scepticism, nothing is more important, it seems, than to provide it with a beginning in a distinct account of what is meant by

‘thing’, ‘reality’, ‘existence’:

for it will be pointless to dispute concerning

things’ real existence,

or claim to have any knowledge of it, when we haven’t fixed the meaning of those words. ‘Thing’ or ‘being’ is the most general name of all; it applies to two entirely distinct and unalike kinds of item, which have nothing in common but the name; they are spirits and ideas. The former are active, indivisible substances: the latter are inert, fleeting, dependent beings, which don’t exist by themselves, but are supported by—or exist in—minds or spiritual substances. We comprehend our own existence by inward feeling or reflection, and that of other spirits by reason. We may be said to have some knowledge or notion of our own minds, of spirits and active beings, although we don’t in a strict sense have ideas of them. Similarly we know and have a notion of •relations

35

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

between things or ideas, which relations are distinct from the •ideas or things related, because the •ideas may be perceived by us without our perceiving the relations. To me it seems that we can know about and talk about ideas, spirits, and relations, and that it would be improper to extend the term ‘idea’ to signify everything we know or have any notion of.

90. Ideas imprinted on the senses are real things, or do really exist. I don’t deny that; but I deny that they can exist outside the minds that perceive them, and that they resemble anything existing outside the mind—since the very being of a sensation or idea consists in being perceived, and the only thing an idea can resemble is an idea. The things perceived by sense can be called ‘external’ with regard to their origin, because they aren’t generated from within by the mind itself, but imprinted ·from outside· by a spirit other than the one that perceives them. Perceptible objects can also be said to be ‘outside the mind’ in another sense, namely, when they exist in some other mind. Thus when I shut my eyes, the things I saw may still exist, but it must be in another mind.

91. It would be a mistake to think that what I am saying here detracts in the least from the reality of things. It is acknowledged on the generally accepted principles [= materialism] that all perceptible qualities—extension, motion, and the rest—need a support because they can’t exist by themselves. But the objects perceived by sense are admitted to be nothing but combinations of those qualities, and so they can’t exist by themselves. Up to this point we all agree. So that when I deny that the things perceived by sense exist independently of a substance or support in which they may exist, I take nothing away from the received opinion of their reality, and am not guilty of any new doctrine in that respect. The only difference ·between myself and other philosophers· is that according to me the unthinking beings perceived by sense have no existence distinct from being perceived, and cannot therefore exist in any substance other than those unextended, indivisible substances, spirits, which act and think and perceive them; whereas the common run of philosophers hold that the perceptible qualities exist in an inert, extended, unperceiving substance that they call ‘matter’, to which they attribute a natural existence outside all thinking beings—i.e. distinct from being perceived by any mind whatsoever, even the eternal mind of the creator. The only ideas they suppose to be in God’s mind are ideas of the corporeal substances he has created, if indeed they allow that those substances were created.

92. ·Following on from that last remark·: Just as the doctrine of matter or corporeal substance has—as I have shown—been the main pillar and support of scepticism, so likewise all the impious schemes of atheism and irreligion have been erected on that same foundation. Indeed, it has been thought so difficult to conceive matter produced out of nothing that the most celebrated among the ancient philosophers, even of those who maintained the existence of a God, have thought matter to be uncreated and coeternal with God. I needn’t tell the story of how great a friend material substance has been to atheists in all ages. All their monstrous systems depend on it so obviously and so necessarily that once this corner-stone is removed the whole structure ·of atheism· collapses; so that it is no longer worthwhile to attend separately to the absurdities of each wretched sect of atheists.

93. It is very natural that impious and profane people should readily accept systems that favour their inclinations, by mocking immaterial substance and supposing the soul to be divisible and subject to decay as the body is; systems that exclude all freedom, intelligence, and design from the

36

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

formation of things, and instead make a self-existent, stupid, unthinking substance the root and origin of all things. It is also natural that they should listen to those who deny a Providence, or a superior mind surveying the affairs of the world, attributing the whole series of events either to blind chance or fatal necessity, arising from collisions of bodies. [Here ‘fatal necessity’ means ‘necessity such that whatever does happen was always bound to happen and could in theory have been predicted’.] And when on the other hand men with better principles see the enemies of religion putting so much stress on unthinking matter, all of them working so hard and ingeniously to reduce everything to it, I think they should rejoice to see them deprived of their grand support, and driven from their only fortress. Without that fortress ·of materialism·, Epicureans, Hobbists and the like haven’t so much as the shadow of something to say, and ·winning the argument against them· becomes the most cheap and easy triumph in the world.

94. The existence of matter, or unperceived bodies, has been the main support not only of atheists and fatalists but also of idolatry in all its various forms. If men would only consider that the sun, moon, and stars, and every other object of the senses are nothing but sensations in their minds, having no existence except in being perceived, no doubt they would never fall down and worship their own ideas! Rather, they would do homage to ·God·, that eternal invisible mind that produces and sustains all things.

95. The same absurd principle ·of materialism·, by mingling itself with the principles of our faith, has given considerable difficulties to Christians. Think how many scruples and objections have been raised by Socinians and others concerning the resurrection! Don’t the most plausible of them depend on the supposition that sameness of a body comes not from its form (i.e. what is perceived by sense) but from the material substance that remains the same in different forms? All the dispute is about the identity of this material substance; take it away, and mean by ‘body’ what every plain ordinary person means by it—namely that which is immediately seen and felt, which is only a combination of perceptible qualities or ideas—and then the ·seemingly· most unanswerable objections of the Socinians etc. come to nothing.

96. When matter is expelled out of nature, it drags with it so many sceptical and impious notions, such an incredible number of disputes and puzzling questions that have been thorns in the sides of theologians as well as philosophers, and made so much fruitless work for mankind, that if the arguments that I have produced against it are not found to be perfectly conclusive (which I think they obviously are), I am sure all the friends of knowledge, peace, and religion have reason to wish they were.

97. Knowledge relating to ideas has suffered errors and difficulties not only from the belief in the external existence of the objects of perception but also from the doctrine of abstract ideas (as expounded in my Introduction). The plainest things in the world, those we are most intimately acquainted with and perfectly know, appear strangely difficult and incomprehensible when they are considered in an abstract way. Everybody knows what time, place, and motion are in particular cases; but when they are passed through the hands of a metaphysician they become too abstract and rarefied to be grasped by men of ordinary sense. Tell your servant to meet you at such a time, in such a place, and he will never spend time thinking about the meanings of those words; he has no difficulty at all in understanding that particular time and place, or the movements he has to make to get there. But if time is separated from all the particular

37

Principles George Berkeley 51–99

actions and ideas that diversify the day, and is taken merely to be the continuation of existence or duration in the abstract, then even a philosopher may be at a loss to understand it.

98. Whenever I try to form a simple idea of time, abstracted from the succession of ideas in my mind—time that flows uniformly and is gone through by all beings—I am lost and entangled in inextricable difficulties. I have no notion of it at all. But I hear others say that it is infinitely divisible, and speak of it in a manner that leads me to entertain strange thoughts about my existence. That is because ·I have no awareness of having passed through an infinity of periods of time, so that· the doctrine that time is infinitely divisible absolutely requires me to think either •that I exist through innumerable ages without a thought, or else •that I am annihilated every moment of my life; and these seem equally absurd. Time is therefore nothing when it is abstracted from the succession of ideas in our minds; and from this it follows that the duration of any finite spirit must be estimated by the number of ideas or actions succeeding each other in that spirit or mind. This plainly implies that the soul always thinks; and indeed anyone who tries in his thoughts to separate or abstract the existence of a spirit from its thinking will, I believe, find it no easy task!

99. Similarly, when we try to abstract extension and motion from all other qualities and consider them by themselves, we immediately lose sight of them, and are led to wild conclusions. These all depend on a twofold abstraction: first, it is supposed that •extension, for example, can be abstracted from all other perceptible qualities; and secondly, that •the existence of extension can be abstracted from its being perceived. But if you think hard and take care to understand what you say, I think you will agree •that all perceptible qualities are sensations, and all are real; •that where extension is, colour is too—namely in your mind—and •that if they are copies from patterns it must be patterns existing in some other mind; and •that the objects of sense are nothing but those sensations combined, blended, or (if I may put it this way) concreted together—none of which can be supposed to exist unperceived. [Berkeley is making a mild pun here: ‘concreted together’ = ‘fused together’, and ‘concrete’ = ‘opposite of “abstract”’.]

38

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

Sections 100–156

100. Everyone may think he knows what it is for a man to be happy, or an object to be good. But few people can claim to make an abstract idea of happiness separated from all particular pleasures, or of goodness separated from everything that is good. Similarly a man may be just and virtuous without having precise ideas of justice and virtue. The opinion that words like those stand for general notions, abstracted from all particular persons and actions, seems to have made morality difficult, and the study of it less useful to mankind. And in effect the doctrine of abstraction has contributed greatly towards spoiling the most useful parts of knowledge.

101. Natural science and mathematics are the two great provinces of speculative [= not practical, not moral] science that have to do with ideas received from the senses; and I shall make some remarks about each of these, starting with the former. ·This discussion will run up to the end of 117, after which I shall turn to mathematics·. It is with natural science that the sceptics ·seem to· triumph: the great stock of arguments they produce, to belittle our faculties and make mankind appear ignorant and low, are drawn principally from the premise that we are incurably blind as to the true and real nature of things. They exaggerate this, and love to enlarge on it. We are miserably made fools of, they say, by our senses, and fobbed off with the outside, the mere appearance, of things. The real essence—the internal qualities and constitution of every little object—is hidden from our view; every drop of water, every grain of sand, contains something that it is beyond the power of human understanding to fathom or comprehend. But it is evident from what I have shown that this complaint is wholly groundless, and that false principles are making us mistrust our senses to such an extent that we think we know nothing of things that in fact we comprehend perfectly.

102. One great inducement to our pronouncing ourselves ignorant of the nature of things is the opinion—which is popular these days—that every thing contains within itself the cause of its own properties: or ·in other words· that there is in each object an inner essence that is the source from which its perceptible qualities flow and on which they depend. Some have claimed to account for appearances by ·an essence consisting of· secret and mysterious qualities, but recently they are mostly explained in terms of mechanical causes, that is, the shape, motion, weight, etc. of imperceptible particles. But really the only agent or cause is spirit, because obviously motion and all the other ideas are perfectly inert. See 25. Hence, to try to explain the production of colours or sounds by shape, motion, size etc. has to be wasted labour. That’s why attempts of that kind can always be seen to be unsatisfactory. (The same can be said in general, of any ‘explanation’ that assigns one idea or quality as the cause of another.) I needn’t say how many hypotheses and speculations we are spared by my doctrine, and how much simpler it makes the study of nature.

103. The great mechanical principle that is now in vogue is attraction, which seems to some people to provide a good enough explanation of a stone’s falling to the earth, or the sea’s swelling towards the moon. But how are we enlightened by being told this is done by attraction? Is it that this word signifies the kind of tendency ·that is involved·, telling us that the event comes from bodies’ pulling one another, rather than from their being pushed towards each other? But that

39

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

tells us nothing about how this ‘pulling’ is done. For all we know to the contrary, it could as well be called pushing as pulling. Again, we see the parts of steel hold firmly together, and this also is accounted for by attraction; but here as in the other examples I can’t see that this does more than merely to describe the effect. As for how the effect is produced, or what the cause is that produces it, the ‘explanation’ in terms of attraction doesn’t even try to tell us that.

104. It is true that if we consider a number of phenomena together, and compare them, we may observe some likeness and conformity amongst them. For example, in •the falling of a stone to the ground, in •the rising of the sea towards the moon, and in •cohesion and crystallization, there is a similarity because each involves bodies’ combining or approaching one another. So any phenomenon of that sort may not seem strange or surprising to a man who has accurately observed and compared the effects of nature. When we find an event strange or surprising, it is always something that is uncommon, a thing by itself, out of the ordinary course of our observation. We don’t find it strange that bodies tend towards the centre of the earth, because that is what we perceive every moment of our lives. But bodies’ having a similar gravitation towards the centre of the moon may seem odd and unaccountable to most men, because we see it only in the tides. But ·things are different with· a scientist, whose thoughts take in a larger extent of nature. He observes that certain events in the heavens bear some likeness to ones on the earth, indicating that innumerable bodies tend to move towards each other, and he gives this tendency the general name ‘attraction’, and thinks he has explained anything that can be shown to be an instance of it. Thus he explains the tides by the attraction of our earth-and-water globe towards the moon; he doesn’t find that odd or anomalous, but sees it only as one example of a general rule or law of nature.

105. So if we consider how natural scientists differ from other men in respect of their knowledge of phenomena, we shall find that the difference consists, not in •a more exact knowledge of the causes that produce phenomena (for that can only be the will of a spirit), but rather in •a greater breadth of comprehension. Through this—·that is, through the amount of data they take account of·—scientists can discover analogies, harmonies, and agreements among the works of nature, and can explain particular effects. Such ‘explaining’ consists in bringing events under general rules (see 62) that are based on the analogy and uniformness observed in the production of natural effects. We like such rules, and try to find them, because they extend our view beyond what is ·temporally· present and ·spatially· near to us, and enable us to make very probable conjectures about things that may have happened at very great distances of time and place, as well as to predict things to come. This sort of striving towards omniscience is something that the mind likes greatly.

106. But we should proceed cautiously in matters like this, for we are apt to lay too great a stress on analogies, and—at the expense of truth—to indulge the mind in its eagerness to extend its knowledge into general theorems. For example, gravitation, or mutual attraction, appears in many instances; and this leads some people to rush into calling it universal, maintaining that attracting and being attracted by every other body is an essential quality inherent in all bodies whatsoever. Whereas it appears that the fixed stars have no such tendency to move towards each other; and gravitation is so far from being essential to bodies that in some instances a quite contrary principle seems to show itself; as in the upward growth of plants, and the elasticity of the air. There is nothing necessary or essential about any of this; it depends entirely on the will of the governing spirit,

40

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

who causes certain bodies to stick together or tend towards each other, according to various laws, while he keeps others at a fixed distance; and to some he gives a quite contrary tendency to fly apart, just as he sees convenient.

107. After what I have said, I think we may lay down the following conclusions. First, it is clear that philosophers give themselves needless trouble when they look for any natural cause other than a mind or spirit. Secondly, considering that the whole creation is the work of a wise and good agent, scientists should think it fitting to employ their thoughts (contrary to what some hold) about the purposes of things; and I must confess that I see no reason why pointing out the various ends to which natural things are adapted, and for which they were originally with great wisdom contrived, should not be thought to be one good way of accounting for them, and altogether worthy of a scientist. Thirdly, what I have said provides no reason why men shouldn’t study how things go in the world, making observations and experiments. That these are useful to us, enabling us to draw general conclusions, results not from •any unchangeable properties of, or relations between, things themselves, but only from •God’s goodness and kindness to men in his management of the world. See 30–31. Fourthly, by diligently observing the phenomena within our view, we can discover the general laws of nature, and from them deduce further phenomena. I don’t say demonstrate [= ‘prove in a rigorously valid manner’]; for all deductions of this kind depend on supposing that the author of nature always operates uniformly, constantly keeping to those rules that we regard as principles—though we can’t know for sure that they are.

108. Those men who make general rules from phenomena, and afterwards derive phenomena from those rules, seem to be considering signs rather than causes. A man may understand natural signs well without being able to say by what rule a one event is a sign of another. And just as it is possible to write improperly through too strictly observing general rules of grammar, so also in arguing from general rules of nature we may extend the analogy too far and thus run into mistakes.

109. In reading ordinary books a wise man will choose to fix his thoughts on the meaning of what he reads, and on its application to his life, rather than bringing to mind grammatical remarks on the language. Similarly in reading the book of nature, it seems beneath the dignity of the mind to make a show of exactness in bringing each particular phenomenon under general rules, or showing how it follows from them. We should aim at nobler views, ones that •will relax and elevate the mind with a prospect of the beauty, order, extent, and variety of natural things; then •enable us by proper inferences from them to enlarge our notions of the grandeur, wisdom, and kindness of the creator; and lastly •bring us to do our best to make the various parts of the creation subservient to the ends they were designed for—namely, God’s glory and the life and comfort of ourselves and our fellow-creatures.

110. The best key to natural science is widely agreed to be a certain celebrated treatise of mechanics—·Newton’s Principia·. At the start of that justly admired treatise, time, space, and motion are each distinguished into

absolute and relative,

·or, giving the same distinction in different words·,

true and apparent,

or ·in yet other words·

mathematical and vulgar [= ‘that of the plain uneducated ordinary person’].

According to the author’s extensive account of it, this dis-

41

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

tinction does presuppose that time, space and motion exist outside the mind, and that they are ordinarily •conceived as relating to perceptible things; but •really in their own nature they have no relation to them at all.

111. As for time, as it is taken ·by Newton· in an absolute or abstracted sense, for the duration or continuance of the existence of things, I have nothing to add to what I said about this in 97–8. For the rest, this celebrated author holds that there is an •absolute space which, not being perceivable by the senses, is the same everywhere and is immovable: and he takes •relative space to be the measure of absolute space, which being movable and defined by its situation in relation to perceptible bodies, is commonly taken to be immovable ·or absolute· space. He defines place as the part of space that is occupied by some body. And according as the space is absolute or relative, so also is the place. Absolute motion is said to be the moving of a body from one absolute place to another, as relative motion is from one relative place to another. And because the parts of absolute space don’t fall under our senses, instead of them we are obliged to use their perceptible measures, ·namely parts of relative space·; and so we define both place and motion in relation to bodies that we regard as immovable. But, it is said ·by Newton·, in scientific matters we must abstract from our senses, since it may be that none of those bodies that seem to be at rest are truly so: and a thing that is moved relatively may be really—·that is, absolutely·—at rest. Similarly, a single body may at one time be both in relative rest and in motion, or even be moving with contrary relative motions, according as its place is variously defined. All this indeterminacy is to be found in the apparent ·or relative· motions, but not at all in the true or absolute ones, and so science should attend only to the latter. True motions, we are told ·by Newton·, are distinguished from apparent or relative ones by the following ·five· properties. •In true or absolute motion, anything that keeps the same position in relation to a whole undergoes any motions that the whole undergoes. •When a place is moved, anything that is in the place is also moved: so that a body moving in a place that is in motion undergoes the motion of its place. •A body never starts to move or changes how it is moving unless a force acts on it. •A body’s true motion is always changed when force acts on it. •In circular motion that is merely relative, there is no centrifugal force; but in true or absolute circular motion there is centrifugal force, which is proportional to the quantity of motion.

112. Despite all this, it doesn’t appear to me that there can be any motion except relative motion. To conceive motion, ·it seems to me·, one must conceive at least two bodies that alter in their distance from, or position in relation to, each other. Hence if there was one only body in existence, it couldn’t possibly be moved. This seems obvious, because the idea that I have of motion necessarily includes relation.

113. But although in every motion one must conceive two or more bodies, it can happen that only one of them is moved, namely the one that is acted on by the force causing the change of distance. Someone might define relative motion in such a way that a body counts as moving if it changes its distance from some other body, even if the force or action causing that change is not applied to it. But ·that would be a bad definition, and here is why·. Relative motion is something we perceived by our senses, something we have to do with in the ordinary affairs of life; so it seems that every man of common sense knows what it is, as well as the best scientist. Now, I ask anyone whether, in this sense of ‘motion’, the stones under his feet move as he walks along the street, because they change their distances from his feet? It seems to me that though motion includes a relation

42

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

of one thing to another, it is not necessary that each of the related things be said to move. As a man may think of something that doesn’t think, so a body may be moved to or from another body that doesn’t move.

114. As the place of a thing happens to be variously defined, so its motion varies. A man in a ship may be said to be motionless in relation to the sides of the vessel, and yet to move in relation to the land. Or he may move eastward in respect of the ship and westward in respect of the land. In the common affairs of life, men never go beyond the earth to define the place of any body, so that what is motionless in respect of the earth is thought of as absolutely motionless. But scientists, who have a greater extent of thought and more accurate notions of the system of things, have learned that even the earth itself moves. In order therefore to fix their notions, they seem to conceive the material universe as finite, and its unmoving outer walls or shell to be the place in terms of which they estimate ‘true motions’. If we consult our own conceptions, I think we shall find that the only idea we can form of absolute motion is basically the idea of relative motion defined in that manner, ·i.e. in terms of relations to the outermost shell of the universe·. For, as I have already remarked, absolute motion without external relation is incomprehensible; and all the above-mentioned properties, causes, and effects ascribed to absolute motion will, I think, be found to fit with this ·outer-shell· kind of relative motion. As to what is said ·by Newton· about centrifugal force, namely that it doesn’t at all belong to circular relative motion: I don’t see how this follows from the experiment that is brought to prove it. [Berkeley here gives the reference to Newton’s Principia.] For the water in the vessel, at the time at which it is said to have the greatest relative circular motion, really has no motion at all; as is plain from the foregoing section. ·In the following section I defend this further·.

115. A body doesn’t count as moving unless (1) its distance from, or relation to, some other body alters, and (2) the force or action bringing about that alteration is applied to it ·rather than to the other body·. If either of these is lacking, I don’t think that it conforms with how people in general think and speak to say that the body ‘is in motion’. I grant indeed that when a body’s distance from some other alters, we may think it is moving although no force is acting on it; but if we think this it is because we think of the body in question as having the relevant force applied to it. This shows only that we are capable of wrongly thinking a thing to be in motion when it is not.

116. From what has been said, it follows that the scientific consideration of motion doesn’t imply the existence of an absolute space, distinct from the space that •is perceived by the senses, •is related to bodies, and •cannot exist outside the mind, as is clear from the principles that prove the same thing of all other objects of sense. If we look into it closely we shall perhaps find that we can’t even form an idea of pure space without bodies. This, I must confess, seems impossible, as being a most abstract idea. When I cause a motion in some part of my body, if it is free or without resistance I say there is space; but if I find resistance, then I say there is body; and in proportion as the resistance to motion is lesser or greater, I say the space is more or less pure. So that when I speak of pure or empty space, don’t think that the word ‘space’ stands for an idea that can be conceived without body and motion. (We are apt to think every noun stands for a distinct idea that can be separated from all others; and this has led to infinite mistakes.) Thus, when I say that if all the world were annihilated except for my own body, there would still remain ‘pure space’, all I mean is that I conceive it possible ·in that eventuality· for the limbs of my body to be moved on all sides without the least resistance.

43

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

If my body were also annihilated, there could be no motion, and consequently no space. Some people may think that eyesight provides them with the idea of pure space; but it is plain from what I have shown elsewhere that the ideas of space and distance aren’t obtained through sight. See the New Theory of Vision.

117. What I am saying here seems to put an end to all those disputes and difficulties that have sprung up amongst the learned concerning the nature of pure space. Its biggest benefit is to free us from that dangerous dilemma, in which some who have thought about this topic see themselves as trapped, namely: having to think either that •real space is God, or else that •there is something besides God that is ·also· eternal, uncreated, infinite, indivisible, unchanging—each of which may fairly be thought pernicious and absurd. It is certain that a good many divines, as well as highly reputed philosophers, have thought that space must be divine, because they could not conceive its being limited or its being annihilated. And recently some ·such as Spinoza· have undertaken to show that the attributes of God (which cannot be shared) are possessed by space. However unworthy of the divine nature this doctrine may seem, I don’t see how we can avoid it if we adhere to the commonly accepted opinions.

118. Up to here I have written about natural science. Now let us enquire into that other great branch of speculative knowledge, namely mathematics. ·See the start of 101·. Celebrated though it is for its clearness and certainty of demonstration, which is matched hardly anywhere else, mathematics cannot be supposed altogether free from mistakes if in its principles there lurks some secret error that mathematicians share with the rest of mankind. Mathematicians deduce their theorems from premises that are highly certain; but their first principles are confined to the concept of quantity; and they don’t ascend into any enquiry concerning those higher maxims that influence all the particular sciences ·including ones that aren’t quantitative·. Any errors involved in those ·higher· maxims will infect every branch of knowledge, including mathematics. I don’t deny that the principles laid down by mathematicians are true, or that their methods of deduction from those principles are clear and beyond dispute. But I hold •that there are certain erroneous maxims that spread wider than mathematics, and for that reason are not explicitly mentioned there, though they are tacitly assumed throughout the whole progress of that science; and •that the bad effects of those secret, unexamined errors are diffused through all the branches of mathematics. To be plain, I suspect that mathematicians as well as other men are caught in the errors arising from the doctrines of abstract general ideas and of the existence of objects outside the mind.

119. Arithmetic has been thought to have for its object abstract ideas of number. A considerable part of speculative knowledge is supposed to consist in understanding the properties and mutual relations of numbers. The belief in the pure and intellectual nature of numbers in the abstract has won for them the esteem of those thinkers who put on a show of having an uncommon subtlety and elevation of thought. It has put a price on the most trifling numerical theorems that are of no practical use and serve only to pass the time; and it has infected the minds of some people so much that they have dreamed of mighty mysteries involved in numbers, and tried to explain natural things by means of them. But if we look into our own thoughts, and consider the doctrines I have laid down, we may come to have a low opinion of those high flights and abstractions, and to look on all researches into numbers as mere earnest trivialities insofar as they aren’t practically useful in improving our lives.

44

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

120. Unity in the abstract I have considered in 13. From that discussion and from what I said in the Introduction, it plainly follows there is no such idea. But number being defined as a collection of units, we can conclude that if there is no such thing as unity or unit in the abstract, there are no ideas of number in the abstract denoted by names and numerals. Therefore, if theories in arithmetic are abstracted •from the names and numerals, and •also from all use and practical application as well as •from particular things that are numbered, they have no subject matter at all. This shows us how entirely the science of numbers is subordinate to practical application, and how empty and trifling it becomes when considered as a matter of mere theory.

121. There may be some people who, deluded by the empty show of discovering abstracted truths, waste their time on useless arithmetical theorems and problems. So it will be worthwhile to consider that pretence more fully, and expose its emptiness. We can do this clearly by looking first at arithmetic in its infancy, observing what originally set men going on the study of that science, and what scope they gave it. It is natural to think that at first men, for ease of memory and help in calculations, made use of counters, or in writing made use of single strokes, points, or the like, each of which was made to stand for a unit—that is, some one thing of whatever kind they were dealing with at that time. Afterwards they discovered the more compact ways of making one symbol stand in place of several strokes or points. ·For example, the Romans used V instead of five points, X instead of ten points, and so on.· And lastly, the notation of the Arabians or Indians—·the system using 1, 2, 3, etc.·—came into use, in which, by the repetition of a few characters or figures, and varying the meaning of each figure according to its place in the whole expression, all numbers can be conveniently expressed. This seems to have been done in imitation of language, so that the notation in numerals runs exactly parallel to the naming of numbers in words: the nine simple numerals correspond to the first nine names of numbers, and the position of a simple numeral in a longer one corresponds to the place of the corresponding word in a longer word-using name for a number. ·Thus, for example, ‘7’ corresponds to ‘seven’; and the significance of ‘7’ in ‘734’—namely, as standing for seven hundreds—corresponds to the significance of ‘seven’ in ‘seven hundred and thirty-four’·. And agreeably to those rules about how a numeral’s value is determined by its place in the sequence, methods were contrived for working out what row of numerals is needed to name a given number, and what number is named by a given row of numerals. Having found the numerals one seeks, keeping to the same rule or parallelism throughout, one can easily read them into words; and so the number becomes perfectly known. For we say that the number of such-and-suches is known when we know the names or numerals (in their proper order) that belong to the such-and-suches according to the standard system, For when we know these signs, we can through the operations of arithmetic know the signs of any part of the particular sums signified by them; and by thus computing in signs (because of the connection established between them and the distinct numbers of things each of which is taken for a unit), we can correctly add up, divide, and proportion the things themselves that we intend to number.

122. In arithmetic therefore we have to do not with the things but with the signs, though these concern us not for their own sake but because they direct us how to act in relation to things, and how to manage them correctly. Just as I have remarked concerning language in general (19 intro), so here too abstract ideas are thought to be signified by numerals or number-words at times when they don’t

45

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

suggest ideas of particular things to our minds. I shan’t go further into this subject now, except to remark that what I have said shows clearly that the things that are taken to be abstract truths and theorems concerning numbers are really about nothing but •particular countable things—or about •names and numerals, which were first attended to only because they are signs that can aptly represent whatever •particular things men needed to calculate about. To study these ·names or numerals· for their own sake, therefore, would be just as wise and pointful as to neglect the true use or original intention and purpose of language, and to spend one’s time on irrelevant criticisms of words, or on purely verbal reasonings and controversies.

123. From numbers we move on to discuss extension, which (considered as relative) is the object of geometry. The infinite divisibility of finite extension, though it isn’t explicitly asserted either as an axiom or as a theorem in the elements of geometry, is assumed throughout it, and is thought to have so inseparable and essential a connection with the principles and proofs in geometry that mathematicians never call it into question. This notion is the source of all those deceitful geometrical paradoxes that so directly contradict the plain common sense of mankind, and are found hard to swallow by anyone whose mind is not yet perverted by learning. It is also the principal source of all the fine-grained and exaggerated subtlety that makes the study of mathematics so difficult and tedious. So if I can make it appear that nothing whose extent is finite contains innumerable parts, or is infinitely divisible, that will immediately •free the science of geometry from a great number of difficulties and contradictions that have always been thought a reproach to human reason, and also •make the learning of geometry a much less lengthy and difficult business than it has been until now. ·My discussion of infinite divisibility will run to the end of 132·.

124. Every particular finite extension [= ‘finitely extended thing’] that could possibly be the object of our thought is an idea existing only in the mind, and consequently each part of it must be perceived. If I cannot perceive innumerable parts in any finite extension that I consider, it is certain that they aren’t contained in it: and it is evident that indeed I cannot distinguish innumerable parts in any particular line, surface, or solid that I either perceive by sense or picture to myself in my mind; and so I conclude that no such thing contains innumerable parts. Nothing can be more obvious to me than that the extended things I have in view are nothing but my own ideas, and it is equally obvious that I can’t break any one of my ideas down into an infinite number of other ideas—which is to say that none of them is infinitely divisible. If ‘finite extension’ means something distinct from a finite idea, I declare that I don’t know what it means, and so cannot affirm or deny anything regarding it. But if the terms ‘extension’, ‘parts’, and the like are given any meaning that we can conceive, that is, are taken to stand for ideas, then to say ‘a finite quantity or extension consists of infinitely many parts’ is so obvious a contradiction that everyone sees at a glance that it is so. And it could never gain the assent of any reasonable creature who is not brought to it by gentle and slow degrees, like bringing a converted pagan to believe that in the communion service the bread and wine are turned into the body and blood of Jesus Christ. Ancient and rooted prejudices do often turn into principles; and once a proposition has acquired the force and credit of a principle, it is given the privilege of being excused from all examination, as is anything deducible from it. There is no absurdity so gross that the mind of man can’t be prepared in this way to swallow it!

125. Someone whose understanding is prejudiced by the doctrine of abstract general ideas may be persuaded that

46

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

extension in the abstract is infinitely divisible, whether or not the ideas of sense are. And someone who thinks the objects of sense exist outside the mind may be brought by that to think that a line an inch long may contain innumerable parts really existing, though they are too small to be discerned. These errors—·abstract ideas, and existence outside the mind·—are ingrained in geometricians’ minds as thoroughly as in other men’s, and have a similar influence on their reasonings; and it wouldn’t be hard to show how they serve as the basis for the arguments that are employed in geometry to support the infinite divisibility of extension. At present I shall only make some general remarks about why the mathematicians cling to this doctrine so fondly.

126. I have pointed out that the theorems and demonstrations of geometry are about universal ideas (15 intro). And I explained in what sense this ought to be understood, namely that the particular lines and figures included in the diagram are supposed to stand for innumerable others of different sizes. In other words, when the geometer thinks about them he abstracts from their size; this doesn’t imply that he forms an abstract idea, only that he doesn’t care what the particular size is, regarding that as irrelevant to the demonstration. Thus, an inch-long line in the diagram must be spoken of as though it contained ten thousand parts, since it is regarded not in its particular nature but as something universal, and it is universal only in its signification, through which it represents innumerable lines longer than it is, in which ten thousand parts or more may be distinguished, even though it is itself a mere inch in length. In this manner the properties of the lines signified are (by a very usual figure of speech) transferred to the sign, and from that are mistakenly thought to belong to the sign—·the inch-long line·—considered in its own nature.

127. Because there is no number of parts so great that there couldn’t be a line containing more, the inch-line is said to contain parts more than any assignable number; which is not true of the inch itself but is true for the things it signifies. But men lose sight of that distinction, and slide into a belief that the small particular line drawn on paper has in itself innumerable parts. There is no such thing as the ten-thousandth part of •an inch; but there is a ten-thousandth part of •a mile or of •the diameter of the earth, which may be signified by that inch. When therefore I delineate a triangle on paper, and take one inch-long side (for example) to be the radius ·of a circle·, I consider this as divided into ten thousand or a hundred thousand parts, or more. For though the ten-thousandth part of that line, considered in itself, is nothing at all, and consequently may be neglected without any error or inconvenience, yet these drawn lines are only marks standing for greater lengths of which a ten-thousandth part may be very considerable; and that is why, to prevent significant errors in practice, the radius must be taken to have ten thousand parts or more.

128. What I have said makes plain why, if a theorem is to become universal in its use, we have to speak of the lines drawn on the page as though they did have parts that really they don’t have. When we speak in this way, if we think hard about what we are doing we’ll discover that we cannot conceive an inch itself as consisting of (or being divisible into) a thousand parts, but only some other line that is far longer than an inch and is represented by it. And ·we’ll discover· that when we say that a line is infinitely divisible, we must mean a line that is infinitely long. The procedure I have described here seems to be the chief reason why the infinite divisibility of finite extension has been thought necessary for geometry.

47

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

129. The various absurdities and contradictions that flowed from this false principle might have been expected to count as so many arguments against it. But ·this didn’t happen, because· it is maintained—I know not by what logic—that propositions relating to infinity are not to be challenged on grounds of what follows from them. As though contradictory propositions could be reconciled with one another within an infinite mind! Or as though something absurd and inconsistent could have a necessary connection with truth, or flow from it! But whoever considers the weakness of this pretence will think that it was contrived on purpose to humour the laziness of the mind, which would rather slump into an indolent scepticism than take the trouble to carry through a severe examination of the principles it has always embraced as true.

130. Recently the theories about infinites have run so high and led to such strange notions that large worries and disputes have grown up among contemporary geometers. Some notable mathematicians, not content with holding that finite lines can be divided into an infinite number of parts, also maintain that each of those infinitesimals is itself subdivisible into an infinity of other parts, or infinitesimals of a second order, and so on ad infinitum. I repeat: these people assert that there are infinitesimals of infinitesimals of infinitesimals, without ever coming to an end! According to them, therefore, an inch does not merely contain an infinite number of parts, but an infinity of an infinity of an infinity... ad infinitum of parts. Others hold that all orders of infinitesimals below the first are nothing at all, because they reasonably think it absurd to imagine that there is any positive quantity or part of extension which though multiplied infinitely can never equal the smallest given extension. And yet on the other hand it seems no less absurd to think that the square-root, cube-root etc. of a genuine positive number should itself be nothing at all; which they who hold infinitesimals of the first order, denying all of the subsequent orders, are obliged to maintain.

131. Doesn’t this, then, give us reason to conclude that both parties are in the wrong, and that there are really no such things as infinitely small parts, or an infinite number of parts contained in any finite quantity? You may say that this will destroy the very foundations of geometry, and imply that those great men who have raised that science to such an astonishing height have all along been building a castle in the air. To this I reply that whatever is useful in geometry and promotes the benefit of human life still remains firm and unshaken on my principles. That science, considered as practical, will be helped rather than harmed by what I have said; though to show this clearly fully might require a separate book. For the rest, even if my doctrines imply that some of the more intricate and subtle parts of theoretical mathematics may be peeled off without prejudice to the truth, I don’t see what damage this will bring to mankind. On the contrary, it is highly desirable that men of great abilities and tenacious minds should turn their thoughts away from those distractions and employ them in studying things that lie nearer to the concerns of life, or have a more direct influence on how we live.

132. It may be said that various undoubtedly true theorems have been discovered by methods in which •infinitesimals were used, which couldn’t have happened if •their existence included a contradiction in it. I answer that when you look into this thoroughly you won’t find any case where you need to conceive infinitesimal parts of finite lines, or even quantities smaller than the smallest you can perceive. You’ll find that this is never done, because it is impossible. ·This completes my discussion of infinite divisibility·.

48

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

133. What I have said makes it clear that very numerous and important errors have arisen from the false principles that I have criticized in the earlier parts of this work. And the opposites of those erroneous tenets seem to be very fruitful principles that have innumerable consequences that are highly advantageous to true philosophy as well as to religion. I have shown in detail that matter, or the absolute existence of corporeal objects, has always been the chief source of the strength and confidence of the most openly declared and pernicious enemies of all knowledge, human and divine. And, surely, if •by distinguishing the real existence of unthinking things from their being perceived, and allowing them a substance of their own out of the minds of spirits, no one thing is explained in nature, but on the contrary many inexplicable difficulties arise; if •the supposition of matter is shaky at best, because there is not so much as one single reason to support it; if •its consequences cannot survive the light of examination and free enquiry, but screen themselves under the dark and general claim that infinites can’t be understood; if furthermore •the removal of this matter doesn’t bring the slightest bad consequence, if it is not even missed in the world, but everything is conceived just as well—indeed better—without it; if, lastly, •both sceptics and atheists are forever silenced by the doctrine that there are only spirits and ideas, and this philosophy is perfectly agreeable both to reason and religion; we might expect that it—·my philosophy·—would be admitted and firmly embraced, even if it were offered only as an hypothesis, and the existence of matter were allowed as possible, which I have clearly shown that it isn’t.

134. It is true that my principles reject as useless various disputes and speculations that are widely thought to be important parts of learning. But however great a prejudice against my notions this may give to those who have already been deeply engaged ·in such speculations· and made large advances in studies of that nature, I hope that others won’t hold it against my principles and tenets that they shorten the labour of study, and make human sciences more clear, wide-ranging, and manageable than they were before!

135. Having completed what I planned to say about the knowledge of ideas, my next topic is spirits. We have more knowledge of these than we are commonly thought to have. We don’t know the nature of spirits, people think, because we have no ideas of spirits. But I have shown in 27 that it is plainly impossible for there to be an idea of a spirit; so surely it oughtn’t to be regarded as a defect in our understanding that it doesn’t have any such idea. To the arguments of 27 I shall add one more. I have shown that a spirit is the only substance or support in which ideas can exist; and it is obviously absurd to suppose that this support of ideas should itself be an idea, or be like an idea.

136. It may be said—and some have said—that we lack a sense that would enable us to know substances, and that if we had such a sense we would know our own soul as we do a triangle. ·Our inability to perceive substances, on this view, is like the blind person’s inability to see things·. To this I answer that if we did have a new sense, all it could present us with would be some new sensations or ideas of sense, ·just as happens when someone is cured of blindness·. But nobody, I think, will say that what he means by ‘soul’ and ‘substance’ is only some particular sort of idea or sensation! So when you think it through you can see that regarding our faculties as defective because they give us no idea of spirit or active thinking substance is as unreasonable as criticizing them because they don’t enable us to comprehend a round square.

49

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

137. The opinion that spirits are to be known in the way that ideas and sensations are known has given rise to many absurd doctrines and much scepticism about the nature of the soul. It has probably led some people to doubt whether they had a soul, as distinct from their body, since they couldn’t find that they had an idea of it. In fact, the mere meanings of the words are enough to refute the proposition that an idea (meaning: something inactive, whose existence consists in being perceived) could be the image or likeness of a spirit (meaning: an active thing that exists independently of being perceived).

138. ‘Although an idea cannot resemble a spirit in its thinking, acting or existing independently,’ you may say, ‘it may resemble it in other ways. An idea or image of a thing needn’t be like it in every respect.’ I answer that if the idea doesn’t resemble the thing in the ways I have mentioned, it can’t possibly represent it in any other respect. If you leave out the power of willing, thinking and perceiving ideas, nothing remains in respect of which an idea could resemble a spirit. All we mean by the word ‘spirit’ is ‘that which thinks, wills, and perceives’; this is the whole meaning of that term. So if none of those powers can be represented in an idea, there can be no idea at all of a spirit.

139. You may object that if no idea is signified by the terms ‘soul’, ‘spirit’ and ‘substance’, they must be meaningless. I answer that those words do mean or signify a real thing, which is neither an idea nor like an idea, but is a thing that perceives ideas, and wills, and reasons about them. I am myself a thing of that kind: what I refer to by the word ‘I’ is the same as what is meant by ‘soul’ or ‘spiritual substance’. You may object:

Why quarrel over a word? The immediate significations of other general words are by common consent called ‘ideas’, so there’s no reason not to give that same label to what is signified by the general term ‘spirit’ or ‘soul’.

To that I reply that the unthinking objects of the mind all have in common that they are entirely passive and exist only in being perceived; whereas a soul or spirit is an active being whose existence consists not in being perceived but in perceiving ideas and in thinking. ·These are two utterly, profoundly different categories of thing·. So we need to maintain the distinction between ‘spirit’ and ‘idea’, so as to avoid ambiguity and running together things that are utterly opposite and unlike one another. See 27.

140. In a broad sense, indeed, we can be said to have an idea or rather a notion of spirit—that is, we understand the meaning of the word ‘spirit’, otherwise we couldn’t use it in affirming or denying things of spirits. Furthermore, we suppose that our own ideas resemble ideas in the minds of others; for example, my ideas of blueness or heat resemble the ideas of blueness and heat that other people have. In that sense our own soul is the image or idea of the souls of others because it resembles them. And so we conceive ideas in the minds of other spirits by means of our own ideas, and we know other spirits by means of our own soul.

141. Those who assert that the soul is naturally immortal mustn’t be thought to mean that nothing, not even the infinite power of the creator who first brought it into existence, could possibly annihilate the soul. Their view is merely that the soul is not at risk of being broken or pulled apart in accordance with the ordinary laws of nature or motion. Some people think the soul of man to be only a thin living flame, or a gaseous system of ‘animal spirits’; and on that view it is as easily destructible as the body, because nothing is more easily dissipated than flame or gas, which couldn’t

50

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

possibly survive the ruin of the body that houses it. This view ·that the soul is naturally perishable· has been eagerly embraced and cherished by the worst people, who see it as the strongest antidote to virtue and religion. But I have shown clearly that bodies, no matter what their structure or materials, ·including flames and ‘animal spirits’·, are merely passive ideas in the mind. The mind itself is more unlike them than light is unlike darkness. I have shown that the soul is indivisible, incorporeal, unextended, and it is therefore incapable of being destroyed by natural processes. ·It can’t fall apart because it has no parts·. What we call ‘the course of nature’ is a series of motions, changes, decays and disintegrations that we see natural bodies undergoing constantly; none of this can possibly affect an active, simple, uncompounded substance: such a being therefore is indissoluble by the force of nature, which is to say that the human soul is naturally immortal.

142. What I have said presumably makes it clear that our souls cannot be known in the way that senseless, inactive objects are known; that is, we can’t know them by having ideas of them. We can say of both spirits and ideas that they ‘exist’, ‘are known’ and so on, but these words don’t mean that spirits have anything in common with ideas. They aren’t alike in any respect; and we have no more chance of •increasing our powers so that we can know a spirit as we do a triangle than we have of •becoming able to see a sound! I emphasize this because I think it may help us to clear up several important questions and prevent some dangerous errors about the nature of the soul. Although it isn’t strictly right to say that we have an idea of an active being or of an action, we can be said to have a notion of them. I have some knowledge or notion of my mind and of how it acts with regard to ideas, in that I know or understand what is meant by those words. When I know something, I have some notion of it. The terms ‘idea’ and ‘notion’ could be treated as interchangeable with one another, if that is what people want; but we speak more clearly and properly when we distinguish very different things by giving them different names. Incidentally, because relations include an act of the mind it is less strictly accurate to say that we have ideas of relations and relational properties than to say that we have notions of them. But these days the word ‘idea’ is used more broadly, to cover spirits and relations and acts; ·and there’s no point in fussing about this, because· it is after all a verbal matter.

143. I should add that the doctrine of abstract ideas has had a large share in making intricate and obscure those sciences that focus on spiritual things. Men have imagined they could form abstract notions of the powers and acts of the mind, and could consider them apart from the mind or spirit itself, and also apart from their respective objects and effects. In this way a great many dark and indeterminate words, presumed to stand for abstract notions, have been introduced into metaphysics and morality, and from these have grown countless distractions and disputes amongst the learned.

144. But nothing seems to have contributed more to pulling men into controversies and mistakes about •the nature and operations of the mind than their custom of speaking of •them in terms borrowed from perceptible ideas. The will is termed the motion of the soul; which encourages people to liken the mind of man to a ball in motion, pushed and determined by the objects of sense as necessarily as the ball is by the stroke of a racket. This creates endless worries and dangerous errors in morality. All this could be cleared up, and the truth be made to appear plain, uniform, and consistent, if philosophers would only look into themselves

51

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

and think hard about what they mean by what they say.

145. From what I have said, it is clear that the only way we can know that there are other spirits is through what they do—that is, the ideas they arouse in us. Some of the changes and recombinations that I perceive among my ideas inform me there are certain particular agents like myself, which accompany those ideas and concur in [= ‘agree to’, ‘go along with’] their production in my mind. Whereas I know about my own ideas immediately, my knowledge of other spirits is not immediate; it depends on the intervention of ideas that I take to be effects or signs of agents (spirits) other than myself.

146. ·Those ‘other agents’, however, are not all human·. Though we are sometimes convinced that human agents are involved in producing some events. everyone can see that the things we call ‘the works of nature’—that is, the great majority of the ideas or sensations that we perceive—are not produced by human wills and don’t depend on them in any way. So there must be some other spirit that causes them, since it is contradictory that they should exist by themselves. (See 29.) ·What is the nature of that ‘other spirit’? Here is how we can find out·. We can attend carefully to •how regular, orderly and inter-connected natural things are; to •the surprising magnificence, beauty and perfection of the larger parts of the creation, and the delicately intricate way in which its smaller parts are arranged; to •how harmoniously all the parts fit together; and, above all—this being something that we don’t view with the astonishment it deserves—to •the laws of pain and pleasure, and the instincts (that is, the natural inclinations, appetites, and emotions) of animals. If while considering all this we also attend to the nature of the attributes one, eternal, infinitely wise, good and perfect, we shall see clearly that they are attributes of that spirit I have mentioned—the one who makes everything happen and gives everything its reality.

147. Clearly, then, we know God as certainly and immediately as we know any mind or spirit other than ourselves. Indeed, God’s existence is far more evidently perceived than the existence of other men, because nature has infinitely more and bigger effects than those that are attributed to human agents. ·Indeed, the things that are done by humans are at the same time effects of nature—that is, they are also done by God·. Every sign of a man’s existence—that is, every effect produced by a man—points even more strongly to the existence of that spirit who is the author of nature. ·Here is why·. When you have an effect on me, all that you actually will to do is to move your own limbs ·or larynx·; that the movements you make with your body should lead to any change in the ideas in my mind depends wholly on the will of the creator. It is he alone who keeps other spirits ‘in step’ with one another in such a way that they can perceive one another’s existence. Yet this pure, clear light that illuminates us all, making us visible to one another, is in itself invisible.

148. The unthinking herd all seem to hold that they cannot see God. ‘If only we could see him in the way we see a man,’ they say, ‘we would believe that he exists and, as believers, obey his commands.’ But, unfortunately ·for them·, we need only open our eyes to have a fuller and clearer view of the sovereign lord of all things than we have of any one of our fellow-creatures! I am not supposing that we have a direct and immediate view of God (as some think we do), or that when we see bodies we do so not directly but rather by seeing something that represents them in the essence of God (·as Malebranche thinks we do·)—a doctrine that I confess to finding incomprehensible. Let me explain what I do mean. A human spirit or person isn’t perceived by sense, because

52

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

it isn’t an idea; so when we see the colour, size, shape, and motions of a man, all we perceive are certain sensations or ideas caused in our own minds; and these, being exhibited to us in various distinct collections, serve to indicate to us the existence of finite created spirits like ourselves. Clearly, then, we don’t see a man, if by ‘man’ is meant something that lives, moves, perceives, and thinks as we do. What we perceive is a certain collection of ideas that leads us to think there is a distinct source of thought and motion like ourselves, accompanying it and represented by it. That is also how we see God. The only difference is that whereas some one finite and narrow assemblage of ideas points to a particular human mind, we perceive clear indications of the divinity wherever we look, at any time and in any place. That is because everything we see, hear, feel, or in any way perceive by sense is a sign or effect of the power of God; as is our perception of the motions that are produced by men.

149. Clearly, then, nothing can be more evident to anyone who is capable of the least reflection than the existence of God, or a spirit •who is intimately present to our minds, producing in them all the variety of ideas or sensations that we continually undergo, •on whom we have an absolute and entire dependence, in short, •in whom we live and move and have our being. Very few people have reasoned their way to this great truth, which lies so near and obvious to the mind. That is a sad example of the stupidity and inattention of men who, though they are surrounded with such clear manifestations of God, are so little affected by them that it is as though they were blinded with excess of light.

150. ‘But’, you will say, ‘doesn’t nature have a share in the production of natural things? Must they all be ascribed to the immediate operation of God and nothing else?’ I answer that if by ‘nature’ you mean only the visible series of effects or sensations imprinted on our minds according to certain fixed and general laws, then clearly nature (in this sense) cannot produce anything at all. But if by ‘nature’ you mean some being distinct from God, from the laws of nature, and from the things perceived by sense, I have to say that the word is to me an empty sound with no intelligible meaning. Nature in this meaning of the word is a vain chimera, introduced by heathens who didn’t grasp the omnipresence and infinite perfection of God. It is harder to explain its being accepted among Christians who profess belief in the holy scriptures; for the latter constantly ascribe to the immediate hand of God the effects that heathen philosophers customarily attribute to nature. [Berkeley here gives three biblical quotations.] But although this is the constant language of scripture, yet Christians are weirdly reluctant to believe that God concerns himself so nearly in our affairs. They would prefer to suppose him to be at a great distance from us, and substitute ·matter, i.e.· a blind unthinking deputy in his place, though St. Paul says that God is ‘not far from every one of us’.

151. No doubt these objections will be raised:

The slow and gradual methods that are kept to in the production of natural things don’t seem to be caused by the immediate hand of an almighty agent. Furthermore, monsters, untimely births, fruits blasted in the blossom, rains falling in desert places, miseries incident to human life, are all evidence that the whole frame of nature isn’t immediately actuated and superintended by a spirit of infinite wisdom and goodness.

But much of the answer to this is plain from 62: those methods of nature are absolutely necessary if things are to go according to the most simple and general rules, and in a steady and consistent manner; and that is evidence for both the wisdom and goodness of God. This mighty machine of nature is so skillfully contrived that while its motions

53

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

and various phenomena strike on our senses, the hand that drives the whole thing is itself not perceivable by men of flesh and blood. ‘Verily,’ says the prophet ‘thou art a God that hidest thyself’ (Isaiah xlv.15). But though God conceals himself from the eyes of sensual and lazy people who won’t take the slightest trouble to think, to an unbiassed and attentive mind nothing can be more plainly legible than the close presence of an all-wise spirit who designs, regulates, and sustains the whole system of being. It is clear from what I have pointed out elsewhere that operating according to general and stated laws is necessary for our guidance in the affairs of life, and for letting us into the secret of nature; so much so that without such laws all breadth of thought, all human wisdom and design, would be useless—indeed there couldn’t be any such faculties or powers in the mind. See 31. That single consideration is far more than enough to counterbalance whatever particular inconveniences may arise from the order of nature.

152. Bear in mind also that the very blemishes and defects of nature are of some use, because they make an agreeable sort of variety, and augment the beauty of the rest of the creation, as shadows in a picture serve to set off the brighter and more sunlit parts. You would also do well to think critically about the tendency to charge the author of nature with imprudence because of the waste of seeds and embryos and the accidental destruction of plants and animals before they come to full maturity. Doesn’t this come from a prejudice that was acquired through familiarity with powerless mortals who have to scrimp and save? We may indeed think it wise for a man to manage thriftily things that he can’t acquire without work and trouble. But we mustn’t imagine that the inexplicably fine system of an animal or vegetable costs the great creator any more work or trouble in its production than a pebble does; for nothing is more evident than the fact that an omnipotent spirit can casually produce anything by a mere fiat or act of his will. This makes it clear that the splendid profusion of natural things shouldn’t be interpreted as weakness or wastefulness in the agent who produces them, but rather be looked on as evidence of how richly powerful he is.

153. As for the mixture of pain or uneasiness that the world contains, as a result of the general laws of nature and the actions of finite imperfect spirits: this, in the state we are in at present, is indispensably necessary to our well-being. But our field of vision is too narrow: we take, for instance, the idea of some one particular pain into our thoughts, and count it as evil; whereas if we take a broader view so as to take in •the various ends, connections, and dependencies of things, •on what occasions and in what proportions we are affected with pain and pleasure, •the nature of human freedom, and •the design with which we are put into the world—then we shall be forced to admit that particular things that appear to be evil when considered by themselves have the nature of good when considered as linked with the whole system of beings.

154. From what I have said it will be obvious to any thinking person that the only reason anyone has sided with atheism or with the Manichean heresy ·according to which reality is the product of opposing forces of good and evil· is that there has been too little attention and too little breadth of view. Thoughtless little souls may indeed mock the works of providence, whose beauty and order they can’t or won’t take in. But those who are capable of breadth and balance in their thought, and are also thoughtful in temperament, can never sufficiently admire the divine traces of wisdom and goodness that shine throughout the economy of nature. Still, what truth is there that shines so strongly on the mind that

54

Principles George Berkeley 100–156

we cannot escape seeing it by turning our thought away from it, wilfully shutting our eyes? So is it any wonder that the general run of men, who are always intent on business or pleasure, and aren’t accustomed to focussing or opening the eye of their mind, should have less conviction and certainty of the existence of God than might be expected in reasonable creatures?

155. We should wonder that there are men so stupid as to neglect such an evident and momentous truth, rather than wondering that they don’t believe it, given that they neglect it. And yet it is to be feared that too many intelligent, leisured people who live in Christian countries have sunk into a sort of atheism, simply through a slack and dreadful negligence. For it is downright impossible that a soul pierced and enlightened with a thorough sense of the omnipresence, holiness, and justice of that almighty spirit, should persist in remorselessly violating his laws. We ought therefore earnestly to meditate and dwell on those important points, so as to become convinced beyond all doubt that the eyes of the Lord are in every place beholding the evil and the good; that he is with us and keeps us in all places to which we go, and gives us bread to eat, and clothes to wear; that he is present and conscious to our innermost thoughts; and that we have a most absolute and immediate dependence on him. A clear view of these great truths cannot but fill our heart with awed caution and holy fear, which is the strongest incentive to virtue and the best guard against vice.

156. For, after all, the first place in our studies should be given to the consideration of God and of our duty. The main purpose of my labours has been to promote such a consideration; so I shall regard them as altogether useless and ineffectual if what I have said doesn’t inspire my readers with a pious sense of the presence of God, and—having shown the falseness or emptiness of those barren speculations that make the chief employment of learned men—make them more disposed to reverence and to embrace the salutary truths of the gospel, the knowledge and practice of which is the highest perfection of human nature.

55

Three Dialogues between Hylas and Philonous

in opposition to Sceptics and Atheists

George Berkeley

Copyright copyright2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought.
First launched: July 2004 Last amended: November 2007
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

The First Dialogue 1
The Second Dialogue 27
The Third Dialogue 40

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

The First Dialogue

Philonous: Good morning, Hylas: I didn’t expect to find you out and about so early.

Hylas: It is indeed somewhat unusual: but my thoughts were so taken up with a subject I was talking about last night that I couldn’t sleep, so I decided to get up and walk in the garden.

Phil: That’s good! It gives you a chance to see what innocent and agreeable pleasures you lose every morning. Can there be a pleasanter time of the day, or a more delightful season of the year? That purple sky, those wild but sweet notes of birds, the fragrant bloom on the trees and flowers, the gentle influence of the rising sun, these and a thousand nameless beauties of nature inspire the soul with secret raptures. But I’m afraid I am interrupting your thoughts; for you seemed very intent on something.

Hyl: Yes, I was, and I’d be grateful if you would allow me to carry on with it. But I don’t in the least want to deprive myself of your company, for my thoughts always flow more easily in conversation with a friend than when I am alone. Please, may I share with you the thoughts I have been having?

Phil: With all my heart! It is what I would have requested myself, if you hadn’t asked first.

Hyl: I was considering the odd fate of those men who have in all ages, through a desire to mark themselves off from the common people or through heaven knows what trick of their thought, claimed either to believe nothing at all or to believe the most extravagant things in the world. This wouldn’t matter so much if their paradoxes and scepticism didn’t bring consequences that are bad for mankind in general. But there’s a risk that they will do that, and that when men who are thought to have spent their whole time in the pursuit of knowledge claim to be entirely ignorant of everything, or advocate views that are in conflict with plain and commonly accepted principles, this will tempt other people—who have less leisure for this sort of thing—to become suspicious of the most important truths, ones they had previously thought to be sacred and unquestionable.

Phil: I entirely agree with you about the bad effects of the paraded doubts of some philosophers and the fantastical views of others. I have felt this so strongly in recent times that I have dropped some of the high-flown theories I had learned in their universities, replacing them with ordinary common opinions. Since this revolt of mine against metaphysical notions and in favour of the plain dictates of nature and common sense, I swear that I find I can think ever so much better, so that I can now easily understand many things which previously were mysteries and riddles.

Hyl: I am glad to find there was nothing in the accounts I heard of you.

Phil: What, if you please, were they?

Hyl: In last night’s conversation you were represented as someone who maintains the most extravagant opinion that ever entered into the mind of man, namely that there is no such thing as material substance in the world.

Phil: I seriously believe that there is no such thing as what philosophers call ‘material substance’; but if I were made to see anything absurd or sceptical in this, then I would have the same reason to renounce this belief as I think I have now to reject the contrary opinion.

1

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Hyl: What! can anything be more fantastical, more in conflict with common sense, or a more obvious piece of scepticism, than to believe there is no such thing as matter?

Phil: Steady on, Hylas! What if it were to turn out that you who hold that there is matter are—by virtue of that opinion—a greater sceptic, and maintain more paradoxes and conflicts with common sense, than I who believe no such thing?

Hyl: You have as good a chance of convincing me that the part is greater than the whole as of convincing me that I must give up my belief in matter if I am to avoid absurdity and scepticism.

Phil: Well then, are you content to accept as true any opinion that turns out to be the most agreeable to common sense, and most remote from scepticism?

Hyl: With all my heart. Since you want to start arguments about the plainest things in the world, I am content for once to hear what you have to say.

Phil: Tell me, please, Hylas: what do you mean by a ‘sceptic’?

Hyl: I mean what everyone means, ‘someone who doubts everything’.

Phil: So if someone has no doubts concerning some particular point, then with regard to that point he cannot be thought a sceptic.

Hyl: I agree with you.

Phil: Does doubting consist in accepting the affirmative or the negative side of a question?

Hyl: Neither. Anyone who understands English must know that doubting signifies a suspense between the two sides.

Phil: So if someone denies any point, he can no more be said to doubt concerning it than he who affirms it with the same degree of assurance.

Hyl: True.

Phil: And so his denial no more makes him a sceptic than the other is.

Hyl: I acknowledge it.

Phil: Then how does it happen, Hylas, that you call me a sceptic because I deny what you affirm, namely the existence of matter? For all you know, I may be as firmly convinced in my denial as you are in your affirmation.

Hyl: Hold on a moment, Philonous. My definition of ‘sceptic’ was wrong; but you can’t hold a man to every false step he makes in conversation. I did say that a sceptic is someone who doubts everything; but I should have added, ‘... or who denies the reality and truth of things’.

Phil: What things? Do you mean the principles and theorems of sciences? But these, you know, are universal intellectual notions, and have nothing to do with matter, so that the denial of matter doesn’t imply the denial of them.

Hyl: I agree about that. But what about other things? What do you think about distrusting the senses, denying the real existence of sensible things, or claiming to know nothing of them? Isn’t that enough to qualify a man as a sceptic? [Throughout the Dialogues, ‘sensible’ means ‘capable of being sensed’—that is, visible or audible or tangible etc.]

Phil: Well, then, let us see which of us it is that denies the reality of sensible things, or claims to have the greatest ignorance of them; since, if I understand you rightly, he is to be counted the greater sceptic.

2

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Hyl: That is what I desire.

Phil: What do you mean by ‘sensible things’?

Hyl: Things that are perceived by the senses. Can you imagine that I mean anything else?

Phil: I’m sorry, but it may greatly shorten our enquiry if I have a clear grasp of your notions. Bear with me, then, while I ask you this further question. Are things ‘perceived by the senses’ only the ones that are perceived immediately? Or do they include things that are perceived mediately, that is, through the intervention of something else?

Hyl: I don’t properly understand you.

Phil: In reading a book, what I immediately perceive are the letters ·on the page·, but mediately or by means of these the notions of God, virtue, truth, etc. are suggested to my mind. Now, there’s no doubt that •the letters are truly sensible things, or things perceived by sense; but I want to know whether you take •the things suggested by them to be ‘perceived by sense’ too.

Hyl: No, certainly, it would be absurd to think that God or virtue are sensible things, though they may be signified and suggested to the mind by sensible marks with which they have an arbitrary connection.

Phil: It seems then, that by ‘sensible things’ you mean only those that can be perceived immediately by sense.

Hyl: Right.

Phil: Doesn’t it follow from this that when I see one part of the sky red and another blue, and I infer from this that there must be some cause for that difference of colours, that cause cannot be said to be a ‘sensible thing’ or perceived by eyesight?

Hyl: It does.

Phil: Similarly, when I hear a variety of sounds I cannot be said to hear their causes.

Hyl: You cannot.

Phil: And when by touch I feel a thing to be hot and heavy, I can’t say with any truth or correctness that I feel the cause of its heat or weight.

Hyl: To head off any more questions of this kind, I tell you once and for all that by ‘sensible things’ I mean only things that are perceived by sense, and that the senses perceive only what they perceive immediately; because they don’t make inferences. So the deducing of causes or occasions from effects and appearances (which are the only things we perceive by sense) is entirely the business of reason. [In this context, ‘occasion’ can be taken as equivalent to ‘cause’. The two terms are separated in the Second Dialogue at page 35.]

Phil: We agree, then, that sensible things include only things that are immediately perceived by sense. Now tell me whether we immediately perceive

by sight anything besides light, colours, and shapes;

by hearing anything but sounds;

by the palate anything besides tastes;

by the sense of smell anything besides odours;

by touch anything more than tangible qualities.

Hyl: We do not.

Phil: So it seems that if you take away all sensible qualities there is nothing left that is sensible.

Hyl: I agree.

Phil: Sensible things, then, are nothing but so many sensible qualities, or combinations of sensible qualities.

3

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Hyl: Nothing else.

Phil: So heat is a sensible thing.

Hyl: Certainly.

Phil: Does the reality of sensible things consist in being perceived? or is it something different from their being perceived—something that doesn’t involve the mind?

Hyl: To exist is one thing, and to be perceived is another.

Phil: I am talking only about sensible things. My question is: By the ‘real existence’ of one of them do you mean an existence exterior to the mind and distinct from their being perceived?

Hyl: I mean a real absolute existence—distinct from, and having no relation to, their being perceived.

Phil: So if heat is granted to have a real existence, it must exist outside the mind.

Hyl: It must.

Phil: Tell me, Hylas, is this real existence equally possible for all degrees of heat that we feel; or is there a reason why we should attribute it to some degrees of heat and not to others? If there is, please tell me what it is.

Hyl: Whatever degree of heat we perceive by sense we can be sure exists also in the object that occasions it.

Phil: What, the greatest as well as the least?

Hyl: Yes, because the same reason holds for both: they are both perceived by sense; indeed, the greater degree of heat is more ·intensely· sensibly perceived; so if there is any difference it is that we are more certain of the real existence of a greater heat than we can be of the reality of a lesser.

Phil: But isn’t the most fierce and intense degree of heat a very great pain?

Hyl: No-one can deny that.

Phil: And can any unperceiving thing have pain or pleasure?

Hyl: Certainly not.

Phil: Is your material substance a senseless thing or does it have sense and perception?

Hyl: It is senseless, without doubt.

Phil: So it can’t be the subject of pain.

Hyl: Indeed it can’t.

Phil: Nor, consequently, can it be the subject of the greatest heat perceived by sense, since you agree that this is a considerable pain.

Hyl: I accept that.

Phil: Then what are we to say about your external object? Is it a material substance, or is it not?

Hyl: It is a material substance with the sensible qualities inhering in it.

Phil: But then how can a great heat exist in it, since you agree it cannot exist in a material substance? Please clear up this point.

Hyl: Hold on, Philonous! I’m afraid I went wrong in granting that intense heat is a pain. I should have said not that the pain is the heat but that it is the consequence or effect of the heat.

Phil: When you put your hand near the fire, do you feel one simple uniform sensation or two distinct sensations?

Hyl: Just one simple sensation.

4

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: Isn’t the heat immediately perceived?

Hyl: It is.

Phil: And the pain?

Hyl: True.

Phil: Well, then, seeing that they are both immediately perceived at the same time, and that the fire affects you with only one simple or uncompounded idea [= one idea without parts], it follows that this one simple idea is both the immediately perceived intense heat and the pain; and consequently, that the immediately perceived intense heat is identical with a particular sort of pain.

Hyl: It seems so.

Phil: Consult your thoughts again, Hylas: can you conceive an intense sensation to occur without pain or pleasure?

Hyl: I cannot.

Phil: Or can you form an idea of sensible pain or pleasure in general, abstracted from every particular idea of heat, cold, tastes, smells, etc.?

Hyl: I don’t find that I can.

Phil: Then doesn’t it follow that sensible pain is nothing but intense degrees of those sensations or ideas?

Hyl: That is undeniable. In fact, I’m starting to suspect that a very great heat can’t exist except in a mind perceiving it.

Phil: What! are you then in that sceptical state of suspense, between affirming and denying?

Hyl: I think I can be definite about it. A very violent and painful heat can’t exist outside the mind.

Phil: So according to you it has no real existence.

Hyl: I admit it.

Phil: Is it certain, then, that no body in nature is really hot?

Hyl: I haven’t said that there is no real heat in bodies. I only say that there’s no such thing as an intense real heat ·in bodies·.

Phil: But didn’t you say earlier that all degrees of heat are equally real, or that if there is any difference the greater heat is more certainly real than the lesser?

Hyl: Yes, I did; but that was because I had overlooked the reason there is for distinguishing between them, which I now plainly see. It is this: because •intense heat is nothing but a particular kind of painful sensation, and •pain can’t exist except in a perceiving being, it follows that •no intense heat can really exist in an unperceiving corporeal [= ‘bodily’] substance. But that’s no reason for denying that less intense heat can exist in such a substance.

Phil: But how are we to draw the line separating degrees of heat that exist only in the mind from ones that exist outside it?

Hyl: That isn’t hard. The slightest pain can’t exist unperceived, as you know; so any degree of heat that is a pain exists only in the mind. We don’t have to think the same for degrees of heat that are not pains.

Phil: I think you agreed a while back that no unperceiving being is capable of pleasure, any more than it is of pain.

Hyl: I did.

Phil: Well, isn’t warmth—a milder degree of heat than what causes discomfort or worse—a pleasure?

Hyl: What of it?

Phil: It follows that warmth can’t exist outside the mind in any unperceiving substance, or body.

5

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Hyl: So it seems.

Phil: So ·we have reached the position that· degrees of heat that aren’t painful and also ones that are can exist only in a thinking substance! Can’t we conclude from this that external bodies are absolutely incapable of any degree of heat whatsoever?

Hyl: On second thoughts, I am less sure that warmth is a pleasure than I am that intense heat is a pain.

Phil: I don’t claim that warmth is as •great a pleasure as heat is a pain. But if you admit it to be even a •small pleasure, that is enough to yield my conclusion.

Hyl: I could rather call it ‘absence of pain’. It seems to be merely the lack of pain and of pleasure. I hope you won’t deny that this quality or state is one that an unthinking substance can have!

Phil: If you are determined to maintain that warmth is not a pleasure, I don’t know how to convince you otherwise except by appealing to your own experience. But what do you think about cold?

Hyl: The same as I do about heat. An intense degree of cold is a pain; for to feel a very great cold is to experience a great discomfort, so it can’t exist outside the mind. But a lesser degree of cold can exist outside the mind, as well as a lesser degree of heat.

Phil: So when we feel a moderate degree of heat (or cold) from a body that is applied to our skin, we must conclude that that body has a moderate degree of heat (or cold) in it?

Hyl: We must.

Phil: Can any doctrine be true if it necessarily leads to absurdity?

Hyl: Certainly not.

Phil: Isn’t it an absurdity to think that a single thing should be at the same time both cold and warm?

Hyl: It is.

Phil: Well, now, suppose that one of your hands is hot and the other cold, and that they are both at once plunged into a bowl of water that has a temperature between the two. Won’t the water seem cold to one hand and warm to the other?

Hyl: It will.

Phil: Then doesn’t it follow by your principles that the water really is both cold and warm at the same time—thus believing something that you agree to be an absurdity?

Hyl: I admit that that seems right.

Phil: So the principles themselves are false, since you have admitted that no true principle leads to an absurdity.

Hyl: But, after all, can anything be more absurd than to say that there is no heat in the fire?

Phil: To make the point still clearer, answer me this: in two cases that are exactly alike, oughtn’t we to make the same judgment?

Hyl: We ought.

Phil: When a pin pricks your finger, doesn’t it tear and divide the fibres of your flesh?

Hyl: It does.

Phil: And when hot coal burns your finger, does it do any more?

Hyl: It does not.

6

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: You hold that the pin itself doesn’t contain either the sensation that it causes, or anything like it. So, given what you have just agreed to—·namely that like cases should be judged alike·—you ought to hold that the fire doesn’t contain either •the sensation that it causes or •anything like it.

Hyl: Well, since it must be so, I am content to give up this point, and admit that heat and cold are only sensations existing in our minds. Still, there are plenty of other qualities through which to secure the reality of external things.

Phil: But what will you say, Hylas, if it turns out that the same argument applies with regard to all other sensible qualities, and that none of them can be supposed to exist outside the mind, any more than heat and cold can?

Hyl: Proving that would be quite a feat, but I see no chance of your doing so.

Phil: Let us examine the other sensible qualities in order. What about tastes? Do you think they exist outside the mind, or not?

Hyl: Can anyone in his right mind doubt that sugar is sweet, or that wormwood is bitter?

Phil: Tell me, Hylas: is a sweet taste a particular kind of pleasure or pleasant sensation, or is it not?

Hyl: It is.

Phil: And isn’t bitterness some kind of discomfort or pain?

Hyl: I grant that.

Phil: If therefore sugar and wormwood are unthinking corporeal substances existing outside the mind, how can sweetness and bitterness—that is, pleasure and pain—be in them?

Hyl: Hold on, Philonous! Now I see what has deluded me all this time. You asked whether heat and cold, sweetness and bitterness, are particular sorts of pleasure and pain; to which I answered simply that they are. I should have answered by making a distinction: those qualities as perceived by us are pleasures or pains, but as existing in the external objects they are not. So we cannot conclude without qualification that there is no heat in the fire or sweetness in the sugar, but only that heat or sweetness as perceived by us are not in the fire or the sugar. What do you say to this?

Phil: I say it is irrelevant. We were talking only about ‘sensible things’, which you defined as things we immediately perceive by our senses. Whatever other qualities you are talking about have no place in our conversation, and I don’t know anything about them. You may indeed claim to have discovered certain qualities that you don’t perceive, and assert that they exist in fire and sugar; but I can’t for the life of me see how that serves your side in the argument we were having. Tell me then once more, do you agree that heat and cold, sweetness and bitterness (meaning the qualities that are perceived by the senses), don’t exist outside the mind?

Hyl: I see it is no use holding out, so I give up the cause with respect to those four qualities. Though I must say it sounds odd to say that sugar isn’t sweet.

Phil: It might sound better to you if you bear this in mind: someone whose palate is diseased may experience as bitter stuff that at other times seems sweet to him. And it’s perfectly obvious that different people perceive different tastes in the same food, since what one man delights in another loathes. How could this be, if the taste were really inherent in the food?

Hyl: I admit that I don’t know how.

7

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: Now think about odours. Don’t they exactly fit what I have just been saying about tastes? Aren’t they just so many pleasing or displeasing sensations?

Hyl: They are.

Phil: Then can you conceive it to be possible that they should exist in an unperceiving thing?

Hyl: I cannot.

Phil: Or can you imagine that filth and excrement affect animals that choose to feed on them with the same smells that we perceive in them?

Hyl: By no means.

Phil: Then can’t we conclude that smells, like the other qualities we have been discussing, cannot exist anywhere but in a perceiving substance or mind?

Hyl: I think so.

Phil: What about sounds? Are they qualities really inherent in external bodies, or not?

Hyl: They don’t inhere in the sounding bodies. We know this, because when a bell is struck in a vacuum, it sends out no sound. So the subject of sound must be the air.

Phil: Explain that, Hylas.

Hyl: When the air is set into motion, we perceive a louder or softer sound in proportion to the air’s motion; but when the air is still, we hear no sound at all.

Phil: Granting that we never hear a sound except when some motion is produced in the air, I still don’t see how you can infer from this that the sound itself is in the air.

Hyl: This motion in the external air is what produces in the mind the sensation of sound. By striking on the ear-drum it causes a vibration which is passed along the auditory nerves to the brain, whereon the mind experiences the sensation called sound.

Phil: What! is sound a sensation?

Hyl: As I said: as perceived by us it is a particular sensation in the mind.

Phil: And can any sensation exist outside the mind?

Hyl: No, certainly.

Phil: But if sound is a sensation, how can it exist in the air, if by ‘the air’ you mean a senseless substance existing outside the mind?

Hyl: Philonous, you must distinguish sound as it is perceived by us from sound as it is in itself; or—in other words—distinguish the sound we immediately perceive from the sound that exists outside us. The former is indeed a particular kind of sensation, but the latter is merely a vibration in the air.

Phil: I thought I had already flattened that distinction by the answer I gave when you were applying it in a similar case before. But I’ll let that pass. Are you sure, then, that sound is really nothing but motion?

Hyl: I am.

Phil: Whatever is true of real sound, therefore, can truthfully be said of motion.

Hyl: It may.

Phil: So it makes sense to speak of motion as something that is loud, sweet, piercing, or low-pitched!

Hyl: I see you are determined not to understand me. Isn’t it obvious that those qualities belong only to sensible sound,

8

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

or ‘sound’ in the ordinary everyday meaning of the word, but not to ‘sound’ in the real and scientific sense, which (as I have just explained) is nothing but a certain motion of the air?

Phil: It seems, then, there are two sorts of sound—the common everyday sort that we hear, and the scientific and real sort ·that we don’t hear·.

Hyl: Just so.

Phil: And the latter kind of sound consists in motion.

Hyl: As I told you.

Phil: Tell me, Hylas, which of the senses do you think the idea of motion belongs to? The sense of hearing?

Hyl: Certainly not. To the senses of sight and touch.

Phil: It should follow then, according to you, that real sounds may possibly be seen or felt, but can never be heard.

Hyl: Look, Philonous, make fun of my views if you want to, but that won’t alter the truth of things. I admit that the inferences you draw from them sound a little odd; but ordinary language is formed by ordinary people for their own use, so it’s not surprising if statements that express exact scientific notions seem clumsy and strange.

Phil: Is it come to that? I assure you, I think I have scored a pretty big win when you so casually depart from ordinary phrases and opinions; because what we were mainly arguing about was whose notions are furthest from the common road and most in conflict with what people in general think. Your claim that real sounds are never heard, and that we get our idea of sound through some other sense—can you think that this is merely an odd-sounding scientific truth? Isn’t something in it contrary to nature and the truth of things?

Hyl: Frankly, I don’t like it either. Given the concessions I have already made, I had better admit that sounds also have no real existence outside the mind.

Phil: And I hope you won’t stick at admitting the same of colours.

Hyl: Pardon me; the case of colours is very different. Can anything be more obvious than the fact that we see colours on the objects?

Phil: The objects you speak of are, I suppose, corporeal substances existing outside the mind.

Hyl: They are.

Phil: And they have true and real colours inhering in them?

Hyl: Each visible object has the colour that we see in it.

Phil: Hah! is there anything visible other than what we perceive by sight?

Hyl: There is not.

Phil: And do we perceive anything by our senses that we don’t perceive immediately?

Hyl: How often do I have to say it? I tell you, we do not.

Phil: Bear with me, Hylas, and tell me yet again whether anything is immediately perceived by the senses other than sensible qualities. I know you asserted that nothing is; but I want to know now whether you still think so.

Hyl: I do.

Phil: Now, is your corporeal substance either a sensible quality or made up of sensible qualities?

Hyl: What a question to ask! Who ever thought it was?

9

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: Here is why I ask. When you say that each visible object has the colour that we see in it, you imply that either (1) visible objects are sensible qualities, or else (2) something other than sensible qualities can be perceived by sight. But we earlier agreed that (2) is false, and you still think it is; ·so we are left with the thesis (1) that visible objects are sensible qualities·. Now, in this conversation you have been taking it that visible objects are corporeal substances; and so we reach the conclusion that your corporeal substances are nothing but sensible qualities.

Hyl: You may draw as many absurd consequences as you please, and try to entangle the plainest things; but you will never persuade me out of my senses. I clearly understand my own meaning.

Phil: I wish you would make me understand it too! But since you don’t want me to look into your notion of corporeal substance, I shall drop that point. But please tell me whether the colours that we see are •the very ones that exist in external bodies or •some other colours.

Hyl: They are the very same ones.

Phil: Oh! Then are the beautiful red and purple that we see on those clouds over there really in them? Or do you ·rather· think that the clouds in themselves are nothing but a dark mist or vapour?

Hyl: I must admit, Philonous, that those colours aren’t really in the clouds as they seem to be at this distance. They are only apparent colours.

Phil: Apparent call you them? How are we to distinguish these apparent colours from real ones?

Hyl: Very easily. When a colour appears only at a distance, and vanishes when one comes closer, it is merely apparent.

Phil: And I suppose that real colours are ones that are revealed by looking carefully from close up?

Hyl: Right.

Phil: Does the closest and most careful way of looking use a microscope, or only the naked eye?

Hyl: A microscope, of course.

Phil: But a microscope often reveals colours in an object different from those perceived by unassisted sight. And if we had microscopes that could magnify to as much as we liked, it is certain that no object whatsoever when seen through them would appear with the same colour that it presents to the naked eye.

Hyl: Well, what do you conclude from that? You can’t argue that there are really and naturally no colours on objects, just because we can contrive artificial ways to alter them or make them vanish.

Phil: It can obviously be inferred from your own concessions, I think, that all the colours we see with our naked eyes are only apparent—like those on the clouds—since they vanish when one looks more closely and accurately, as one can with a microscope. And to anticipate your next objection I ask you whether the real and natural state of an object is revealed better by a very sharp and piercing sight, or by one that is less sharp.

Hyl: By the former, without doubt.

Phil: Isn’t it plain from ·the science of· optics that microscopes make the sight more penetrating, and represent objects as they would appear to the eye if it were naturally endowed with extreme sharpness?

Hyl: It is.

10

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: So the microscopic representation of a thing should be regarded as the one that best displays the thing’s real nature, or what the thing is in itself. so the colours perceived through a microscope are more genuine and real than those perceived in any other way.

Hyl: I admit that there’s something in what you say.

Phil: Besides, it’s not only possible but clearly true that there actually are animals whose eyes are naturally formed to perceive things that are too small for us to see. What do you think about those inconceivably small animals that we perceive through microscopes? Must we suppose they are all totally blind? If they can see, don’t we have to suppose that their sight has the same use in preserving their bodies from injuries as eyesight does in all other animals? If it does have that use, isn’t it obvious that they must see particles that are smaller than their own bodies, which will present them with a vastly different view of each object from the view that strikes our senses? Even our own eyes don’t always represent objects to us in the same way. Everyone knows that to someone suffering from jaundice all things seem yellow. So isn’t it highly probable that animals whose eyes we see to be differently structured from ours, and whose bodily fluids are unlike ours, don’t see the same colours as we do in every object From all of this, shouldn’t it seem to follow that all colours are equally •apparent, and that none of the ones that we see are •really in any outer object?

Hyl: It should.

Phil: To put it past all doubt, consider the following. If colours were real properties or qualities inhering in external bodies, they couldn’t be altered except by some alteration in the very bodies themselves: but isn’t it evident that the colours of an object can be changed or made to disappear entirely through the use of a microscope, or some change in the fluids in the eye, or a change in the viewing distance, without any sort of real alteration in the thing itself? Indeed, even when all the other factors remain unaltered some objects present different colours to the eye depending on the angle from which they are looked at. The same thing happens when we view an object in different brightnesses of light. And everyone knows that the same bodies appear differently coloured by candle-light from what they do in daylight. Add to these facts our experience of a prism, which separates the different rays of light and thereby alters the colour of an object, causing the whitest object to appear deep blue or red to the naked eye. Now tell me whether you still think that each body has its true, real colour inhering in it. If you think it has, I want to know what •particular distance and orientation of the object, what •special condition of the eye, what •intensity or kind of light is needed for discovering that true colour and distinguishing it from the apparent ones.

Hyl: I admit to being quite convinced that they are all equally apparent, that no such thing as colour really inheres in external bodies, and that colour is wholly in the light. What confirms me in this opinion is the fact that colours are more or less vivid depending on the brightness of the light, and that when there is no light no colours are seen. Furthermore, if there were colours in external objects, how could we possibly perceive them? No external body affects the mind unless it acts first on our sense-organs; and the only action of bodies is motion, and this can’t be communicated except in collisions. So a distant object can’t act on the eye, and so can’t enable itself or its properties to be perceived by the mind. From this it plainly follows that what immediately causes the perception of colours is some substance that is

11

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

in contact with the eye—such as light.

Phil: What? Is light a substance?

Hyl: I tell you, Philonous, external light is simply a thin fluid substance whose tiny particles, when agitated with a brisk motion and in various ways reflected to the eyes from the different surfaces of outer objects, cause different motions in the optic nerves; these motions are passed along to the brain, where they cause various states and events; and these are accompanied by the sensations of red, blue, yellow, etc.

Phil: It seems, then, that all the light does is to shake the optic nerves.

Hyl: That is all.

Phil: And as a result of each particular motion of the nerves the mind is affected with a sensation, which is some particular colour.

Hyl: Right.

Phil: And these sensations have no existence outside the mind.

Hyl: They have not.

Phil: Then how can you say that colours are in the light, since you take light to be a corporeal substance external to the mind?

Hyl: Light and colours as immediately perceived by us cannot exist outside the mind. I admit that. But in themselves they are only the motions and arrangements of certain insensible particles of matter.

Phil: Colours then, in the ordinary sense—that is, understood to be the immediate objects of sight—cannot be had by any substance that doesn’t perceive.

Hyl: That is what I say.

Phil: Well, then, you give up your position as regards those sensible qualities which are what all mankind takes to be colours. Think what you like about the scientists’ invisible colours; it is not my business to argue about them. But I suggest that you consider whether it is wise for you, in a discussion like this one, to affirm that the red and blue we see are not real colours, and that certain unknown motions and shapes which no man ever did or could see are real colours. Aren’t these shocking notions, and aren’t they open to as many ridiculous inferences as those you had to give up in the case of sounds?

Hyl: I have to admit, Philonous, that I can’t keep this up any longer. Colours, sounds, tastes—in a word, all that are termed ‘secondary qualities’—have no existence outside the mind. But in granting this I don’t take anything away from the reality of matter or external objects, because various philosophers maintain what I just did about secondary qualities and yet are the far from denying matter. [In this context, ‘philosophers’ means ‘philosophers and scientists’.] To make this clearer: philosophers divide sensible qualities into primary and secondary. •Primary qualities are extendedness, shape, solidity, gravity, motion, and rest. They hold that these really exist in bodies. •Secondary qualities are all the sensible qualities that aren’t primary; and the philosophers assert that these are merely sensations or ideas existing nowhere but in the mind. No doubt you are already aware of all this. For my part, I have long known that such an opinion was current among philosophers, but I was never thoroughly convinced of its truth till now.

Phil: So you still believe that extension and shapes are inherent in external unthinking substances? [Here ‘extension’ could mean ‘extendedness’ or it could mean ‘size’.]

12

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Hyl: I do.

Phil: But what if the arguments that are brought against secondary qualities hold against these also?

Hyl: Why, then I shall have to think that shape and extension also exist only in the mind.

Phil: Is it your opinion that the very shape and extension that you perceive by sense exist in the outer object or material substance?

Hyl: It is.

Phil: Have all other animals as good reason as you do to think that the shape and extension that they see and feel is in the outer object?

Hyl: Surely they do, if they can think at all.

Phil: Tell me, Hylas, do you think that the senses were given to all animals for their preservation and well-being in life? or were they given only to men for that end?

Hyl: I don’t doubt that they have the same use in all other animals.

Phil: If so, mustn’t their senses enable them to perceive their own limbs, and to perceive bodies that are capable of harming them?

Hyl: Certainly.

Phil: A tiny insect, therefore, must be supposed to see its own foot, and other things of that size or even smaller, seeing them all as bodies of considerable size, even though you can see them—if at all—only as so many visible points.

Hyl: I can’t deny that.

Phil: And to creatures even smaller than that insect they will seem even bigger.

Hyl: They will.

Phil: So that something you can hardly pick out ·because it is so small· will appear like a huge mountain to an extremely tiny animal.

Hyl: I agree about all this.

Phil: Can a single thing have different sizes at the same time?

Hyl: It would be absurd to think so.

Phil: But from what you have said it follows that the true size of the insect’s foot is •the size you see it having and •the size the insect sees it as having, and •all the sizes it is seen as having by animals that are even smaller. That is to say, your own principles have led you into an absurdity.

Hyl: I seem to be in some difficulty about this.

Phil: Another point: didn’t you agree that no real inherent property of any object can be changed unless the thing itself alters?

Hyl: I did.

Phil: But as we move towards or away from an object, its visible size varies, being at one distance ten or a hundred times greater than at another. Doesn’t it follow from this too that size isn’t really inherent in the object?

Hyl: I admit that I don’t know what to think.

Phil: You will soon be able to make up your mind, if you will venture to think as freely about this quality as you have about the others. Didn’t you admit that it was legitimate to infer that neither heat nor cold was in the water from the premise that the water seemed warm to one hand and cold to the other?

Hyl: I did.

13

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: Isn’t it the very same reasoning to infer that there is no size or shape in an object from the premise that to one eye it seems little, smooth, and round, while to the other eye it appears big, uneven, and angular?

Hyl: The very same. But does the latter ever happen?

Phil: You can at any time find out that it does, by looking with one eye bare and with the other through a microscope.

Hyl: I don’t know how to maintain it, yet I am reluctant to give up extension [= ‘size’], because I see so many odd consequences following from the concession that extension isn’t in the outer object.

Phil: Odd, you say? After the things you have already agreed to, I hope you won’t be put off from anything just because it is odd! But in any case wouldn’t it seem very odd if the general reasoning that covers all the other sensible qualities didn’t apply also to extension? If you agree that no idea or anything like an idea can exist in an unperceiving substance, then surely it follows that no shape or mode of extension [= ‘or specific way of being extended’] that we can have any idea of—in perceiving or imagining—can be really inherent in matter. Whether the sensible quality is shape or sound or colour or what you will, it seems impossible that any of these should subsist in something that doesn’t perceive it. (Not to mention the peculiar difficulty there must be in conceiving a material substance, prior to and distinct from extension, to be the substratum of extension. ·I’ll say more about that shortly·.)

Hyl: I give up on this point, for just now. But I reserve the right to retract my opinion if I later discover that I was led to it by a false step.

Phil: That is a right you can’t be denied. Shapes and extendedness being disposed of, we proceed next to motion. Can a real motion in any external body be at the same time both very swift and very slow?

Hyl: It cannot.

Phil: Isn’t the speed at which a body moves inversely proportional to the time it takes to go any given distance? Thus a body that travels a mile in an hour moves three times as fast as it would if it travelled only a mile in three hours.

Hyl: I agree with you.

Phil: And isn’t time measured by the succession of ideas in our minds?

Hyl: It is.

Phil: And isn’t it possible that ideas should succeed one another twice as fast in your mind as they do in mine, or in the mind of some kind of non-human spirit?

Hyl: I agree about that.

Phil: Consequently the same body may seem to another spirit to make its journey in half the time that it seems to you to take. (Half is just an example; any other fraction would make the point just as well.) That is to say, according to your view that both of the perceived motions are in the object, a single body can really move both very swiftly and very slowly at the same time. How is this consistent either with common sense or with what you recently agreed to?

Hyl: I have nothing to say to it.

Phil: Now for solidity: If you don’t use ‘solidity’ to name any sensible quality, then it is irrelevant to our enquiry. If you do use it to name a sensible quality, the quality must be either hardness or resistance. But each of these is plainly relative to our senses: it is obvious that what seems hard to one animal may appear soft to another that has greater

14

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

force and firmness of limbs; and it is equally obvious that the resistance I feel ·when I press against a body· is not in the body.

Hyl: I agree that the sensation of resistance, which is all you immediately perceive, is not in the body; but the cause of that sensation is.

Phil: But the causes of our sensations aren’t immediately perceived, and therefore aren’t sensible. I thought we had settled this point.

Hyl: I admit that we did. Excuse me if I seem a little embarrassed; I am having trouble quitting my earlier views.

Phil: It may be a help for you to consider this point: once extendedness is admitted to have no existence outside the mind, the same must be granted for motion, solidity, and gravity, since obviously they all presuppose extendedness. So it is superfluous to enquire into each of them separately; in denying extendedness, you have denied them all to have any real existence.

Hyl: If this is right, Philonous, I wonder why the philosophers who deny the secondary qualities any real existence should yet attribute it to the primary qualities. If there’s no difference between them, how can this be accounted for?

Phil: It isn’t my business to account for every opinion of the philosophers! But there are many possible explanations, one of them being that ·those philosophers were influenced by the fact that· pleasure and pain are associated with the secondary qualities rather than with the primary ones. Heat and cold, tastes and smells, have something more vividly pleasing or disagreeable than what we get from the ideas of extendedness, shape, and motion. And since it is too visibly absurd to hold that pain or pleasure can be in an unperceiving substance, men have more easily been weaned from believing in the external existence of the secondary qualities than of the primary ones. You will see that there is something in this if you recall the distinction you made between moderate heat and intense heat, allowing one a real existence ·outside the mind· while denying it to the other. But after all, there is no rational basis for that distinction; for surely a sensation that is neither pleasing nor painful is just as much a sensation as one that is pleasing or painful; so neither kind should be supposed to exist in an unthinking subject.

Hyl: It has just come into my head, Philonous, that I have somewhere heard of a distinction between absolute and sensible extendedness. Granted that large and small consist merely in the relation other extended things have to the parts of our own bodies, and so aren’t really in the substances themselves; still, we don’t have to say the same about absolute extendedness, which is something abstracted from large and small, from this or that particular size and shape. Similarly with motion: fast and slow are altogether relative to the succession of ideas in our own minds. But just because those special cases of motion do not exist outside the mind, it doesn’t follow that the same is true of the absolute motion that is abstracted from them.

Phil: What distinguishes one instance of motion, or of extendedness, from another? Isn’t it something •sensible—for instance some speed, or some size and shape?

Hyl: I think so.

Phil: So these qualities—·namely, absolute motion and absolute extendedness·—which are stripped of all •sensible properties, have no features making them more specific in any way.

Hyl: That is right.

15

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: That is to say, they are extendedness in general, and motion in general.

Hyl: If you say so.

Phil: But everyone accepts the maxim that every thing that exists is particular. How then can motion in general, or extendedness in general, exist in any corporeal substance?

Hyl: I will need time to think about that.

Phil: I think the point can be speedily decided. Without doubt you can tell whether you are able to form this or that idea in your mind. Now I’m willing to let our present dispute be settled in the following way. If you can form in your thoughts a distinct abstract idea of motion or extendedness, having none of those sensible qualities—swift and slow, large and small, round and square, and the like—which we agree exist only in the mind, then I’ll capitulate. But if you can’t, it will be unreasonable for you to insist any longer on something of which you have no notion.

Hyl: To be frank, I cannot.

Phil: Can you even separate the ideas of extendedness and motion from the ideas of all the so-called secondary qualities?

Hyl: What! isn’t it easy to consider extendedness and motion by themselves, abstracted from all other sensible qualities? Isn’t that how the mathematicians handle them?

Phil: I acknowledge, Hylas, that it is not difficult to form general propositions and reasonings about extendedness and motion, without mentioning any other qualities, and in that sense to treat them abstractedly. I can pronounce the word ‘motion’ by itself, but how does it follow from this that I can form in my mind the idea of motion without an idea of body? Theorems about extension and shapes can be proved without any mention of large or small or any other sensible quality, but how does it follow from this that the mind can form and grasp an abstract idea of extension, without any particular size or shape or ·other· sensible quality? Mathematicians study quantity, disregarding any other sensible qualities that go with it on the grounds that they are irrelevant to the proofs. But when they lay aside the words and contemplate the bare ideas, I think you’ll find that they aren’t the pure abstracted ideas of extendedness.

Hyl: But what do you say about pure intellect? Can’t abstracted ideas be formed by that faculty?

Phil: Since I can’t form abstract ideas at all, it is clearly impossible for me to form them with help from ‘pure intellect’, whatever faculty you mean that phrase to refer to. Setting aside questions about the nature of pure intellect and its spiritual objects such as virtue, reason, God, etc., I can say this much that seems clearly true: sensible things can only be perceived by the senses or represented by the imagination; so shape and size don’t belong to pure intellect because they are initially perceived through the senses. If you want to be surer about this, try and see if you can frame the idea of any shape, abstracted from all particularities of size and from other sensible qualities.

Hyl: Let me think a little—I don’t find that I can.

Phil: Well, can you think it possible that something might really exist in nature when it implies a contradiction in its conception?

Hyl: By no means.

Phil: Therefore, since even the mind can’t possibly separate the ideas of •extendedness and motion from •all other sensible qualities, doesn’t it follow that where •the former exist •the latter must also exist?

Hyl: It would seem so.

16

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: Consequently the very same arguments that you agreed to be decisive against the •secondary qualities need no extra help to count just as strongly against the •primary qualities also. Besides, if you trust your senses don’t they convince you that all sensible qualities co-exist, that is, that they all appear to the senses as being in the same place? Do your senses ever represent a motion or shape as being divested of all other visible and tangible qualities?

Hyl: You needn’t say any more about this. I freely admit—unless there has been some hidden error or oversight in our discussion up to here—that all sensible qualities should alike be denied existence outside the mind. But I fear that I may have been too free in my former concessions, or overlooked some fallacy in your line of argument. In short, I didn’t take time to think.

Phil: As to that, Hylas, take all the time you want to go back over our discussion. You are at liberty to repair any slips you have made, or to support your initial opinion by presenting arguments that you have so far overlooked.

Hyl: I think it was a big oversight on my part that I failed to distinguish sufficiently the object from the sensation. The sensation cannot exist outside the mind, but it doesn’t follow that the object cannot either.

Phil: What object do you mean? The object of the senses?

Hyl: Exactly.

Phil: So it is immediately perceived?

Hyl: Right.

Phil: Explain to me the difference between what is immediately perceived and a sensation.

Hyl: I take the sensation to be an act of the perceiving mind; beside which, there is something perceived, which I call the object ·of the act·. For example, there is red and yellow on that tulip, but the act of perceiving those colours is in me only, and not in the tulip.

Phil: What tulip are you talking about? Is it the one that you see?

Hyl: The same.

Phil: And what do you see beside colour, shape, and extendedness?

Hyl: Nothing.

Phil: So you would say that the red and yellow are coexistent with the extension, wouldn’t you?

Hyl: ·Yes, and· I go further: I say that they have a real existence outside the mind in some unthinking substance.

Phil: That the colours are really in the tulip which I see, is obvious. Nor can it be denied that this tulip may exist independently of your mind or mine; but that any immediate object of the senses—that is, any idea or combination of ideas—should exist in an unthinking substance, or exterior to all minds, is in itself an obvious contradiction. Nor can I imagine how it follows from what you said just now, namely that the red and yellow are in the tulip you saw, since you don’t claim to see that unthinking substance.

Hyl: You are skillful at changing the subject, Philonous.

Phil: I see that you don’t want me to push on in that direction. So let’s return to your distinction between sensation and object. If I understand you correctly, you hold that in every perception there are two things of which one is an action of the mind and the other is not.

Hyl: True.

17

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: And this action can’t exist in or belong to any unthinking thing; but whatever else is involved in a perception may do so.

Hyl: That is my position.

Phil: So that if there were a perception without any act of the mind, that perception could exist in an unthinking substance.

Hyl: I grant that. But it is impossible that there should be such a perception.

Phil: When is the mind said to be active?

Hyl: When it produces, puts an end to, or changes anything.

Phil: Can the mind produce, discontinue, or change anything in any way except by an •act of the will?

Hyl: It cannot.

Phil: So the mind is to count as being active in its perceptions to the extent that •volition is included in them.

Hyl: It is.

Phil: When I •pluck this flower I am active, because I do it by a hand-movement which arose from my volition; so likewise in •holding it up to my nose. But is either of these smelling?

Hyl: No.

Phil: I also act when I draw air through my nose, because my breathing in that manner rather than otherwise is an effect of my volition. But this isn’t smelling either; for if it were, I would smell every time I breathed in that manner.

Hyl: True.

Phil: Smelling, then, is a result of all this ·plucking, holding up, and breathing in·.

Hyl: It is.

Phil: But I don’t find that my will is involved any further—·that is, in anything other than the plucking, holding up, and breathing in·. Whatever else happens—including my perceiving a smell—is independent of my will, and I am wholly passive with respect to it. Is it different in your case, Hylas?

Hyl: No, it’s just the same.

Phil: Now consider seeing: isn’t it in your power to open your eyes or keep them shut, to turn them this way or that?

Hyl: Without doubt.

Phil: But does it similarly depend on your will that when you look at this flower you perceive white rather than some other colour? When you direct your open eyes towards that part of the sky, can you avoid seeing the sun? Or is light or darkness the effect of your volition?

Hyl: No, certainly.

Phil: In these respects, then, you are altogether passive.

Hyl: I am.

Phil: Tell me now, does seeing consist •in perceiving light and colours or rather in •opening and turning the eyes?

Hyl: The former, certainly.

Phil: Well, then, since in the actual perception of light and colours you are altogether passive, what has become of that action that you said was an ingredient in every sensation? And doesn’t it follow from your own concessions that the perception of light and colours—which doesn’t involve any action—can exist in an unperceiving substance? And isn’t this a plain contradiction?

Hyl: I don’t know what to think.

18

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: Furthermore, since you distinguish active and passive elements in every perception, you must do it in the perception of pain. But how could pain—however inactive it is—possibly exist in an unperceiving substance? Think about it, and then tell me frankly: aren’t light and colours, tastes, sounds, etc. all equally passions or sensations in the mind? You may call them ‘external objects’, and give them in words whatever kind of existence you like; but examine your own thoughts and then tell me whether I am not right?

Hyl: I admit, Philonous, that when I look carefully at •what goes on in my mind, all I can find is that I am a thinking being that has a variety of sensations; and I can’t conceive how a sensation could exist in an unperceiving substance. But when on the other hand I look in a different way at •sensible things, considering them as so many properties and qualities, I find that I have to suppose a material substratum, without which they can’t be conceived to exist.

Phil: Material substratum you call it? Tell me, please, which of your senses acquainted you with it?

Hyl: It is not itself sensible; only its properties and qualities are perceived by the senses.

Phil: I presume, then, that you obtained the idea of it through reflection and reason.

Hyl: I don’t claim to have any proper •positive idea of it. [Here ‘positive’ means ‘non-relational’: Hylas means that he doesn’t have an idea that represents what material substance is like in itself.] But I conclude that it exists, because qualities can’t be conceived to exist without a support.

Phil: So it seems that you have only a •relative notion of material substance: you conceive it only by conceiving how it relates to sensible qualities.

Hyl: Right.

Phil: Tell me, please, what that relation is.

Hyl: Isn’t it sufficiently expressed in the term ‘substratum’ or ‘substance’? [One is Latin, and means ‘underneath layer’; the other comes from Latin meaning ‘standing under’.]

Phil: If so, the word ‘substratum’ should mean that it is spread under the sensible qualities.

Hyl: True.

Phil: And consequently ·spread· under extendedness.

Hyl: I agree.

Phil: So in its own nature it is entirely distinct from extendedness.

Hyl: I tell you, extendedness is only a quality, and matter is something that supports qualities. And isn’t it obvious that the supported thing is different from the supporting one?

Phil: So something distinct from extendedness, and not including it, is supposed to be the substratum of extendedness.

Hyl: Just so.

Phil: Tell me, Hylas, can a thing be spread without being extended? Isn’t the idea of extendedness necessarily included in ·that of· spreading?

Hyl: It is.

Phil: So anything that you suppose to be spread under something else must have in itself an extendedness distinct from the extendedness of the thing under which it is spread.

Hyl: It must.

19

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: Consequently every bodily substance, being the substratum of extendedness, must have in itself another extendedness which qualifies it to be a substratum, ·and that extendedness must also have something spread under it, a sub-substratum, so to speak·, and so on to infinity. Isn’t this absurd in itself, as well as conflicting with what you have just said, namely that the substratum was something distinct from extendedness and not including it?

Hyl: Yes, but Philonous you misunderstand me. I don’t mean that matter is ‘spread’ in a crude literal sense under extension. The word ‘substratum’ is used only to express in general the same thing as ‘substance’.

Phil: Well, then, let us examine the relation implied in the term ‘substance’. Is it not the relation of standing under qualities?

Hyl: The very same.

Phil: But doesn’t a thing have to be extended if it is to stand under or support another?

Hyl: Yes.

Phil: So isn’t this supposition infected with the same absurdity as the previous one?

Hyl: You still take things in a strict literal sense; that isn’t fair, Philonous.

Phil: I don’t want to force any meaning onto your words; you are free to explain them as you please. But please make me understand something by them! You tell me that matter supports or stands under accidents. How? As your legs support your body?

Hyl: No; that is the literal sense.

Phil: Please let me know any sense, literal or not literal, that you understand it in.—How long must I wait for an answer, Hylas?

Hyl: I don’t know what to say. I once thought I understood well enough what was meant by matter’s ‘supporting’ qualities. But now the more I think about it the less I understand it. In short, I find that I don’t know anything about it.

Phil: So it seems that you have no idea at all, either positive or relative, of matter. You don’t know what it is in itself, or what relation it has to qualities.

Hyl: I admit it.

Phil: And yet you said that you couldn’t conceive the real existence of qualities without conceiving at the same time a material support for them.

Hyl: I did.

Phil: That amounted to saying that when you conceive the real existence of qualities you also conceive something that you can’t conceive!

Hyl: It was wrong, I admit. But still I fear there is some fallacy or other. Let me try this: It has just occurred to me that we were both led into error by your treating each quality by itself. I grant that no quality can exist on its own outside the mind; colour can’t exist without extension, nor can shape exist without some other sensible quality. But as a number of qualities united or blended together constitute an entire sensible thing, there is no obstacle to supposing that such things—·that is, such collections of qualities·—can exist outside the mind.

Phil: Are you joking, Hylas, or do you have a very bad memory? We did indeed go through all the qualities by

20

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

name, one after another; but my arguments—or rather your concessions—nowhere tended to prove that the

secondary qualities don’t exist ·outside the mind· in isolation;

the point was rather that

secondary qualities don’t exist ·outside the mind· at all.

·It’s true that existing-in-isolation did come up in our discussion·: in discussing shape and motion, we concluded they couldn’t exist outside the mind because it was impossible even in thought to separate them from all secondary qualities, so as to conceive them existing by themselves. But this wasn’t the only argument I used on that occasion. However, if you like we can set aside our whole conversation up to here, counting it as nothing. I am willing to let our whole debate be settled as follows: If you can conceive it to be possible for any mixture or combination of qualities, or any sensible object whatever, to exist outside the mind, then I will grant it actually to be so.

Hyl: By that test, the point will soon be decided. What is easier than to conceive a tree or house existing by itself, independently of and unperceived by any mind whatsoever? I conceive them existing in that way right now.

Phil: Tell me, Hylas, can you see a thing which is at the same time unseen?

Hyl: No, that would be a contradiction.

Phil: Is it not as great a contradiction to talk of conceiving a thing which is unconceived?

Hyl: It is.

Phil: The tree or house therefore which you think of is conceived by you.

Hyl: How could it be otherwise?

Phil: And what is conceived is surely in the mind.

Hyl: Without question, what is conceived is in the mind.

Phil: Then what led you to say that you conceived a house or tree existing independently and out of all minds whatsoever?

Hyl: That was an oversight, I admit; but give me a moment to think about what led me into it. It was—·I now realize, after reflection·—an amusing mistake. As I was thinking of a tree in a solitary place with nobody there to see it, I thought that was conceiving a tree as existing unperceived or unthought of, overlooking the fact I myself conceived it all the while. But now I plainly see that all I can do is to form ideas in my own mind. I can conceive in my own thoughts the idea of a tree, or a house, or a mountain, but that is all. And this is far from proving that I can conceive them existing out of the minds of all spirits.

Phil: You agree, then, that you can’t conceive how any corporeal sensible thing should exist otherwise than in a mind.

Hyl: I do.

Phil: And yet you will earnestly contend for the truth of something that you can’t even conceive.

Hyl: I admit that I don’t know what to think, but I still have doubts. Isn’t it certain that I see things at a distance? Don’t we perceive the stars and moon, for example, to be a long way away? Isn’t this, I say, obvious to the senses?

Phil: Don’t you in dreams also perceive objects like those?

Hyl: I do.

Phil: And don’t they then appear in the same way to be distant?

21

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Hyl: They do.

Phil: But do you conclude that the apparitions in a dream are outside the mind?

Hyl: By no means.

Phil: Then you ought not to conclude that sensible objects ·seen when you are awake· are outside the mind, from their appearance or the manner in which you perceive them.

Hyl: I admit that. But doesn’t my ·visual· sense deceive me in those cases, ·by telling me that sensible objects are at a distance when really they are not·?

Phil: By no means. Neither eyesight nor reason inform you that the idea or thing that you immediately perceive actually exists outside the mind. By eyesight you know only that you are affected with certain sensations of light and colours, etc. And you won’t say that these are outside the mind.

Hyl: True; but all the same, don’t you think that eyesight makes some suggestion of outerness or distance?

Phil: When you approach a distant object, do the visible size and shape keep changing, or do they appear the same at all distances?

Hyl: They are in a continual change.

Phil: So sight doesn’t ‘suggest’ or in any way inform you that the visible object you immediately perceive exists at a distance, or that it will be perceived when you move further forward; because there is a continued series of visible objects succeeding each other during the whole time of your approach.

Hyl: I agree about that: but still I know, on seeing an object, what object I shall see after I have gone a certain distance—never mind whether it is exactly the same object or not. So something about distance is still being suggested.

Phil: My dear Hylas, just think about that a little, and then tell me whether there is anything more to it that this: From the ideas that you actually perceive by sight you have by experience learned to infer (in accordance with the general rules of nature) what other ideas you will experience after such and such a succession of time and motion.

Hyl: Upon the whole, I think that’s what it comes down to.

Phil: Isn’t it obvious that if a man born blind were suddenly enabled to see, he would start with no experience of what may be suggested by sight?

Hyl: It is.

Phil: So he would not, according to you, have any notion of distance linked to the things he saw. He would take the latter to be a new set of sensations existing only in his mind.

Hyl: That is undeniable.

Phil: But to make it still more plain: isn’t distance a line running out from the eye?

Hyl: It is.

Phil: Can a line so situated be perceived by sight?

Hyl: It cannot.

Phil: So doesn’t it follow that distance isn’t strictly and immediately perceived by sight?

Hyl: It seems so.

Phil: Again, do you think that colours are at a distance?

Hyl: I have to acknowledge that they are only in the mind.

22

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: But don’t colours appear to the eye as coexisting at the same place as extension and shape

Hyl: They do.

Phil: Then how can you conclude from ·the deliverances of· sight that shapes •do exist outside the mind, when you agree that colours •don’t? The sensible appearances of both are the very same.

Hyl: I don’t know what to answer.

Phil: Even if distance were truly and immediately perceived by the mind, it still wouldn’t follow that it existed out of the mind. For whatever is immediately perceived is an idea; and can any idea exist out of the mind?

Hyl: It would be absurd to suppose so. But tell me, Philonous, can we perceive or know nothing except our ideas?

Phil: Set aside ·what we may know through· the rational deducing of causes from effects; that is irrelevant to our enquiry. As for the senses: you are the best judge of whether you •perceive anything that you don’t •immediately perceive. And I ask you, are the things you immediately perceive anything but your own sensations or ideas? In the course of this conversation you have more than once declared yourself on those two points; this latest question of yours seems to indicate that you have changed your mind.

Hyl: To tell you the truth, Philonous, I think there are two kinds of objects: one kind perceived immediately, and called ‘ideas’; the other kind are real things or external objects perceived by the mediation of ideas, which resemble and represent them. Now I grant that ideas don’t exist outside the mind; but the second sort of objects do. I am sorry I didn’t think of this distinction sooner; it would probably have cut short your discourse.

Phil: Are those external objects perceived by •sense, or by •some other faculty?

Hyl: They are perceived by sense.

Phil: What? Is there anything perceived by sense that isn’t immediately perceived?

Hyl: Yes, Philonous, there is—in a way. For example, when I look at a picture or statue of Julius Caesar, I may be said to perceive him in a fashion (though not immediately) by my senses.

Phil: You seem to hold, then, that our ideas, which are all that we immediately perceive, are pictures of external things; and that the latter are also perceived by sense because they have a conformity or resemblance to our ideas.

Hyl: That is my meaning.

Phil: And in the same way that Julius Caesar, in himself invisible, is nevertheless perceived by sight, so also real things, in themselves imperceptible, are perceived by sense.

Hyl: In the very same way.

Phil: Tell me, Hylas, when you look at the picture of Julius Caesar, do you see with your eyes anything more than some colours and shapes, with a certain symmetry and composition of the whole?

Hyl: Nothing else.

Phil: And wouldn’t a man who had never known anything about Julius Caesar see as much?

Hyl: He would.

23

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Phil: So he has his sight, and the use of it, as perfectly as you have yours.

Hyl: I agree with you.

Phil: Then why are your thoughts directed to the Roman emperor while his are not? This can’t come from the sensations or ideas of sense that you perceive at that moment, for you have agreed that you have in that respect no advantage over the man who has never heard of Julius Caesar. So it seems that the direction of your thoughts comes from reason and memory—doesn’t it?

Hyl: It does.

Phil: So that example of yours doesn’t show that anything is perceived by sense that isn’t immediately perceived. I don’t deny that we can be said in a certain sense to perceive sensible things mediately by sense: that is when the immediate perception of ideas by one sense suggests to the mind others, perhaps belonging to another sense, of a kind that have often been perceived to go with ideas of the former kind. For instance, when I hear a coach drive along the streets, all that I immediately perceive is the sound; but from my past experience that such a sound is connected with a coach, I am said to ‘hear the coach’. Still, it is obvious that in truth and strictness nothing can be heard but sound; and the coach in that example is not strictly perceived by sense but only suggested from experience. Similarly, when we are said to see a red-hot bar of iron; the solidity and heat of the iron are not the objects of sight, but are suggested to the imagination by the colour and shape that are strictly perceived by that sense. In short,

the only things that are actually and strictly perceived by any sense are the ones that would have been perceived even if we had only just acquired that sense ·and were using it for the first time·.

As for other things, clearly they are only suggested to the mind by past experience. But to return to your comparison of ·imperceptible ‘real things’ with· Caesar’s picture: obviously, if you keep to this you’ll have to hold that the real things that our ideas copy are perceived not by sense but by some internal faculty of the soul such as •reason or •memory. I would be interested to know what arguments •reason gives you for the existence of your ‘real things’ or material objects; or whether you •remember seeing them formerly ·not as copied by your ideas but· as they are in themselves; or if you have heard or read of anyone else who did!

Hyl: I can see that you want to make fun of me, Philonous; but that will never convince me.

Phil: All I want is to learn from you how to come by knowledge of material things. Whatever we perceive is perceived either immediately by sense, or mediately by reason and reflection. But you have excluded sense; so please show me what reason you have to believe in their existence, or what means you can possibly adopt to prove, to my understanding or your own, that they exist.

Hyl: To be perfectly frank, Philonous, now that I think about it I can’t find any good reason for my position. But it seems pretty clear that it’s at least possible that such things really exist; and as long as there is no absurdity in supposing them, I shall continue in my belief until you bring good reasons to the contrary.

Phil: What? Has it come to this, that you believe in the existence of material objects, and that this belief is based on the mere possibility of its being true? Then you challenge me to bring reasons against it; though some people would think that the burden of proof lies with him who holds the affirmative position. Anyway, this very thesis that

24

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

you are now determined to maintain without any reason is in effect one that you have—more than once during this conversation—seen good reason to give up. But let us set all that aside. If I understand you rightly, you say our ideas don’t exist outside the mind, but that they are copies, likenesses, or representations of certain originals that do.

Hyl: You have me right.

Phil: Our ideas, then, are like external things.

Hyl: They are.

Phil: Do those external things have a stable and permanent nature independently of our senses; or do they keep changing as we move our bodies and do things with our faculties or organs of sense?

Hyl: Real things, obviously, have a fixed and real nature which remains the same through any changes in our senses or in how our bodies are placed or how they move. Such changes may indeed affect the ideas in our minds, but it would be absurd to think they had the same effect on things existing outside the mind.

Phil: How, then, can things that are perpetually fleeting and variable as our ideas are be copies or likenesses of any thing that is fixed and constant? Since all sensible qualities—size, shape, colour, etc.—that is, our ideas, are continually changing with every alteration in the distance, medium, or instruments of sensation, how can any fixed material object be properly represented or depicted by several distinct things ·or ideas·, each of which is so unlike the others? Or if you say that the object resembles just one of our ideas, how can we distinguish that true copy from all the false ones?

Hyl: I have to admit, Philonous, that I am at a loss. I don’t know what to say to this.

Phil: There is more. Are material objects in themselves perceptible or imperceptible?

Hyl: Properly and immediately nothing can be perceived but ideas. All material things, therefore, are in themselves insensible, and can be perceived only through ideas of them.

Phil: Ideas are sensible, then, and their originals—the things they are copies of—are insensible?

Hyl: Right.

Phil: But how can something that is sensible be like something that is insensible? Can a real thing, in itself invisible, be like a colour? Can a real thing that isn’t audible be like a sound? In a word, can anything be like a sensation or idea but another sensation or idea?

Hyl: I must admit that I think not.

Phil: Can there possibly be any doubt about this? Don’t you perfectly know your own ideas?

Hyl: Yes, I know them perfectly; for something that I don’t perceive or know can’t be any part of my idea.

Phil: Well, then, examine your ideas, and then tell me if there’s anything in them that could exist outside the mind, or if you can conceive anything like them existing outside the mind.

Hyl: Upon looking into it I find that I can’t conceive or understand how anything but an idea can be like an idea. And it is most evident that no idea can exist outside the mind.

Phil: So you’re forced by your own principles to deny the reality of sensible things, because you made it consist in an absolute existence outside the mind. That is to say, you are a downright sceptic. So I have met my target, which was to show that your principles lead to scepticism.

25

Three Dialogues George Berkeley First Dialogue

Hyl: For the present I am, if not entirely convinced, at least silenced.

Phil: I wonder what more you would require in order to be perfectly convinced. Haven’t you been free to explain yourself in any way you liked? Were any little conversational slips held against you? Weren’t you allowed to retract or reinforce anything you had previously said, as best served your purpose? Hasn’t everything you could say been heard and examined with all the fairness imaginable? In a word, haven’t you on every point been convinced out of your own mouth? And if you can now discover any flaw in any of your former concessions, or think of any remaining tactic, any new distinction, shading, or comment whatsoever, why don’t you produce it?

Hyl: A little patience, Philonous. I am at present so bewildered to see myself entangled, and as it were imprisoned in the labyrinths you have led me into, that I can’t be expected to find my way out on the spur of the moment. You must give me time to look around me, and recollect myself.

Phil: Listen—isn’t that the college-bell? Let us go in, and meet here again tomorrow morning. In the mean time you can think about this morning’s conversation, and see if you can find any fallacy in it, or invent any new means to extricate yourself.

Hyl: Agreed.

26

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

The Second Dialogue

Hylas: I beg your pardon, Philonous, for not meeting you sooner. All this morning my head was so filled with our recent conversation that I didn’t notice the time of the day, or indeed anything else!

Philonous: I am glad you were so focussed on it. I hope that if there were any mistakes in your concessions, or fallacies in my reasonings from them, you will now show them to me.

Hyl: I assure you, ever since I saw you I have done nothing but search for mistakes and fallacies, and with that in mind I have examined in detail the whole course of yesterday’s conversation. But it has all been useless; for the views I was led into in the conversation seemed even clearer and more obvious when I reviewed them today; and the more I think about them the more irresistibly they force my assent to them.

Phil: Don’t you think that this is a sign that they are genuine, and that they proceed from nature and are in accordance with right reason? Truth and beauty have this in common: they both show to advantage when looked at closely and carefully. The false glitter of error and heavy make-up can’t endure being looked at for too long or from too close up!

Hyl: I admit there is a great deal in what you say. And I am as convinced as anyone could be of the truth of those strange consequences ·that you argued for yesterday·, so long as I keep in mind the reasonings that lead to them. But when those arguments are out of my thoughts, ·my mind goes the other way·; there seems to be something so satisfactory, natural and intelligible in the modern way of explaining things that I confess that I don’t know how to reject it.

Phil: I don’t know what way you mean.

Hyl: I mean the ·modern· way of accounting for our sensations or ideas.

Phil: How does it do that?

Hyl: It is supposed that •the mind resides in some part of the brain, from which the nerves originate, spreading out from there to all parts of the body; that •outer objects act in different ways on the sense-organs, starting up certain vibrations in the nerves; that •the nerves pass these vibrations along to the brain (where the mind is located); and that •the mind is variously affected with ideas according to the various impressions or traces the vibrations make in the brain.

Phil: And call you this an explanation of how we are affected with ideas?

Hyl: Why not, Philonous? Have you any objection to it?

Phil: I need to know first whether I have rightly understood your ·‘modern’· hypothesis. According to it, certain traces in the brain are the causes or occasions of our ideas. [The special meaning of ‘occasion’ that is at work here will be explained on page 35; it doesn’t matter in the mean time.] Tell me, please, do you mean by ‘the brain’ a sensible thing?

Hyl: What else do you think I could possibly mean?

Phil: Sensible things are all immediately perceivable; and things that are immediately perceivable are ideas; and these exist only in the mind. This much, if I am not mistaken, you have long since agreed to.

Hyl: I don’t deny it.

27

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

Phil: So the brain that you speak of, being a sensible thing, exists only in the mind! I would like to know whether you think it reasonable to suppose that one idea or thing existing in the mind occasions all the other ideas. And if you do think this, how do you account for the origin of that primary idea or ‘brain’ itself?

Hyl: I don’t explain the origin of our ideas by the brain which is perceivable to •sense, because it is ·as you say· only a combination of sensible ideas. I am talking about another brain, which I •imagine.

Phil: But aren’t imagined things just as much in the mind as perceived things are?

Hyl: I must admit that they are.

Phil: So the difference ·between perceiving and imagining· isn’t important. You have been accounting for ideas by certain motions or impressions in the brain, that is, by some alterations in an idea—and it doesn’t matter whether it is •sensible or •imaginable.

Hyl: I begin to suspect my hypothesis.

Phil: Apart from spirits, our own ideas are the only things we know or conceive. So when you say that all ideas are occasioned by impressions in the brain, do you conceive this brain or not? If you do, then you talk of ideas imprinted on an idea, causing that same idea, which is absurd. If you don’t conceive it, you talk unintelligibly instead of forming a reasonable hypothesis.

Hyl: I can now see clearly that it was a mere dream. There is nothing in it.

Phil: It’s no great loss; for, after all, this way of ‘explaining’ things (as you called it) could never have satisfied any reasonable man. What connection is there between a •vibration in the nerves and •sensations of sound or colour in the mind? How could one possibly cause the other?

Hyl: But I could never have seen it as being so empty as it now seems to be!

Phil: Well, then, are you finally satisfied that no sensible things have a real existence, and that you are in truth a complete sceptic?

Hyl: It is too plain to be denied.

Phil: Look! aren’t the fields covered with a delightful green? Isn’t there something in the woods and groves, in the rivers and clear springs, that soothes, delights, transports the soul? At the view of the wide and deep ocean, or some huge mountain whose top is lost in the clouds, or of an old gloomy forest, aren’t our minds filled with a pleasing horror? Even in rocks and deserts, isn’t there an agreeable wildness? It is such a sincere pleasure to see earth’s natural beauties! Doesn’t she preserve and renew our enjoyment of them by intermittently drawing the veil of over her face, and doesn’t she change her dress with the seasons? How aptly the elements are disposed! What variety and usefulness even in the lowest things that nature produces! What delicacy, what beauty, what complexity of organization in the bodies of animals and plants! How finely all things are suited to their particular ends and also to their roles as appropriate parts of the whole! And while they mutually aid and support, don’t they also display each other in a better light? Raise now your thoughts from this globe of earth to all those glorious glittering objects that adorn the high arch of heaven. The motion and situation of the planets—aren’t they admirably orderly? Have those globes ever been known to stray in their repeated journeys through pathless space? Doesn’t each of them sweep out the same area between itself and the sun

28

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

in any two equal periods of time? So fixed and unchanging are the laws by which the unseen Author of nature runs the universe. How vivid and radiant is the shine of the fixed stars! How magnificent and rich the careless profusion with which they seem to be scattered throughout the whole vault of the sky! Yet the telescope brings into view a new host of stars that escape the naked eye. Here they seem to be nearby and small, but a closer view ·through a telescope shows them to be· immense orbs of light at various distances, sunk deep in the abyss of space. Now you must call imagination to your aid ·so as to get some imaginative picture of things you can’t actually see·. Our feeble limited senses can’t pick out innumerable worlds (·planets·) revolving round the central fires (·suns·), in each of which the energy of an all-perfect mind is displayed in endless forms; ·so those are things you must simply imagine·. But neither •sense nor •imagination is big enough to take in the boundless extent ·of the universe· with all its glittering furniture. With all the hard work that we give to •those two faculties, exerting and straining each of them to its utmost reach, there’s always a vast surplus left ungrasped. Yet all the vast bodies that make up this mighty universe, however distant they may be, are by some secret mechanism—some divine power and artifice—linked in a mutual dependence and interconnection with each other, and with this earth (which almost slipped out of my thoughts, getting lost in the crowd of worlds!). Isn’t the whole system immense, beautiful, more glorious than we can say or think? Then how should we treat those philosophers who want to deprive these noble and delightful scenes of all reality? How should we think of principles implying that all the visible beauty of the creation is a false imaginary glare? To put it bluntly, can you expect this scepticism of yours not to be thought extravagantly absurd by all reasonable people?

Hyl: Other men may think as they please, but you have nothing to reproach me with. My comfort is that you are as much a sceptic as I am.

Phil: There, Hylas, I beg leave to differ from you.

Hyl: What? Having along agreed to the premises, are you now denying the conclusion and leaving me to maintain by myself these paradoxes that you led me into? This surely isn’t fair.

Phil: I deny that I agreed with you in those views that led to scepticism. You indeed said that the •reality of sensible things consisted in an absolute existence out of the minds of spirits, or distinct from their being perceived. And under the guidance of this notion of reality you are obliged to deny that sensible things have any real existence; that is, according to your own definition [on page 3] you declare yourself to be a sceptic. But I didn’t say and didn’t think that the •reality of sensible things should be defined in that manner. To me it is evident, for the reasons you agree to, that sensible things can’t exist except in a mind or spirit. From this I conclude not that they have no real existence but that—seeing they don’t depend on my thought, and have an existence distinct from being perceived by me—there must be some other mind in which they exist. As sure as the sensible world really exists, therefore, so sure is there an infinite, omnipresent Spirit who contains and supports it.

Hyl: What? This is no more than I and all Christians hold—and indeed all non-Christians who believe there is a God and that he knows and understands everything.

Phil: Yes, but here’s the difference. Men commonly believe that •all things are known or perceived by God because they believe in •the existence of a God, whereas ·for me the order of reasons is reversed·; I immediately and necessarily

29

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

conclude •the existence of a God because •all sensible things must be perceived by him.

Hyl: As long as we all believe the same thing, what does it matter how we come by that belief?

Phil: But we don’t believe the same thing. Philosophers hold that God perceives all corporeal things, but they attribute to such things an absolute existence independently of their being perceived by any mind whatever; and I don’t. Besides, isn’t there a difference between saying

There is a God, therefore he perceives all things

and saying

Sensible things do really exist; if they really exist they must be perceived by an infinite mind; therefore there is an infinite mind, or God?

This provides you with a direct and immediate proof, from a most evident premise, of the existence of a God. Theologians and philosophers had proved beyond all controversy, from the beauty and usefulness of the various parts of the creation, that it was the workmanship of God. But some of us have the advantage that we can prove the existence of an infinite mind from •the bare existence of the sensible world, without getting help from astronomy and natural philosophy and without bringing in facts about •how wonderfully the parts of the world relate to one another. What gives us this advantage is just the simple thought that the sensible world is what we perceive by our various senses, that nothing is perceived by the senses except ideas, and that no idea and no thing of which an idea is a copy can exist otherwise than in a mind. ·With that at your disposal· you can now oppose and baffle the most strenuous advocate for atheism, without any laborious search into the sciences, without any sophisticated reasoning, and without tediously long arguments. This single reflection on impossibility that the visible world or any part of it—even the most low-grade and shapeless part of it—should exist outside a mind is enough to overthrow the whole system of atheism. It destroys those miserable refuges ·of the atheist·, the eternal succession of unthinking causes and effects, or the chance coming together of atoms—those wild fantasies of Vanini, Hobbes, and Spinoza. Let any one of those supporters of impiety look into his own thoughts, and see if he can conceive how so much as a rock, a desert, a chaos, or a confused jumble of atoms—how anything at all, either sensible or imaginable—can exist independently of a mind; and he need go no further to be convinced of his folly. Can anything be fairer than to let the disagreement be settled by the outcome of such a test, leaving it to the atheist himself to see if he can conceive, even •in thought, the state of affairs that he holds to be true •in fact?

Hyl: It is undeniable that there is something highly serviceable to religion in the position you are taking. But don’t you think it looks very like the view of some eminent recent philosophers—·notably Malebranche·—that we ‘see all things in God’?

Phil: I would gladly know about that; please explain it to me.

Hyl: They think that because the soul (·or mind·) is immaterial, it can’t be united with material things so as to perceive them in themselves, but that it perceives them through its union with the substance of God. Because that is a spiritual substance, it is purely intelligible, that is, capable of being the immediate object of a ·human· mind’s thought. Furthermore, God’s essence contains perfections corresponding to each created thing, and this correspondence enables those perfections to represent created things to the ·human· mind.

Phil: I don’t understand how our ideas, which are entirely passive and inert, can be (or be like) any part of the essence

30

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

of God, who is indivisible, never passive, always active. This hypothesis is open to many other obvious objections, but I shall only add that in making a created world exist otherwise than in the mind of a spirit, the hypothesis ·of Malebranche· is liable to all the absurdities of the more usual views. Added to which it has a special absurdity all its own, namely that it makes the material world serve no purpose. If it is valid to argue against other hypotheses in the sciences that they suppose nature or the Divine Wisdom to make something for no purpose, or to employ tedious round-about methods to get a result which could have been achieved much more easily and swiftly, what are we to think of this hypothesis which supposes that the whole world was made for no purpose?

Hyl: But don’t you also hold that we see all things in God? If I’m not mistaken, your thesis comes near to that.

Phil: Few men think, but all insist on having opinions, which is why men’s opinions are superficial and confused. It isn’t surprising that doctrines which in themselves are ever so different should nevertheless be confused with one another by people who don’t think hard about them. So I shan’t be surprised if some men imagine that I run into the wild fantasies of Malebranche, though in truth I am very remote from them. He builds on the most abstract general ideas, which I entirely disclaim. He asserts an absolute external world, which I deny. He maintains that we are deceived by our senses, and don’t know the real natures or the true forms and shapes of extended things; of all which I hold the direct contrary! So that over-all there are no principles more fundamentally opposite than his and mine. I have to say that I entirely agree with what the Holy Scripture says, that ‘in God we live and move and have our being’. But I am far from believing that we ‘see things in his essence’ in the manner you have presented. Here is my view, in a nutshell:

It is evident that the things I perceive are my own ideas, and that no idea can exist except in a mind. It is equally obvious that these ideas, or things perceived by me—or things of which they are copies—exist independently of my mind, because I know that I am not their author, it being out of my power to choose what particular ideas I shall experience when I open my eyes or ears. So they must exist in some other mind, who wills that they be exhibited to me.

The things I immediately perceive, I repeat, are ideas or sensations, call them what you will. But how can any idea or sensation exist in or be produced by anything other than a mind or spirit? That really is inconceivable; and to assert something that is inconceivable is to talk nonsense, isn’t it?

Hyl: Without doubt.

Phil: On the other side, it is very conceivable that ideas or sensations should exist in, and be produced by, a spirit; because this is just what I experience daily in myself, when I perceive countless ideas, and by an act of my will can form a great variety of them, raising them up in my imagination. (Though I have to say that these creatures of my imagination are not as distinct, strong, vivid, and permanent as are the ones I perceive through my senses, which latter are called ‘real things’.) From all this I conclude that there is a mind that affects me every moment with all the sensible impressions I perceive. And from the variety, order, and manner of these impressions I conclude that the author of them is wise, powerful, and good, beyond anything I can comprehend. Please get this straight: I do not say—·as Malebranche does·—that I see things by perceiving something that represents them in the intelligible essence of God. I don’t ·even· understand that. What I say is this: the things I perceive are known by the understanding, and produced

31

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

by the will, of an infinite Spirit. Isn’t all this very plain and evident? Is there anything more in it than what a little observation of our own minds and what happens in them not only enables us to conceive but also obliges us to assent to?

Hyl: I think I understand you very clearly; and I admit that the proof you give of a Deity is as convincing as it is surprising. But granting that God is the supreme and universal cause of all things, mightn’t there be a third kind of thing besides spirits and ideas? May we not admit a subordinate and limited cause of our ideas? In a word, may there not for all that be matter?

Phil: How often must I teach you the same thing? You agree that the things immediately perceived by sense exist nowhere outside the mind; but everything that is perceived by sense is perceived immediately; therefore there is nothing sensible ·or perceivable· that exists outside the mind. So the matter that you still insist on is presumably ·meant to be· something intelligible—something that can be discovered by reason and not by the senses.

Hyl: You are in the right.

Phil: Pray let me know what reasoning your belief in matter is based on; and what this ‘matter’ is, in your present sense of the word.

Hyl: I find myself affected with various ideas which I know I haven’t caused. And they couldn’t cause themselves or cause one another, nor could they exist on their own, because they are wholly inactive, transient, dependent beings. So they have some cause other than me and other than themselves; all I claim to know about this is that it is the cause of my ideas. And this thing, whatever it is, I call ‘matter’.

Phil: Tell me, Hylas, is everyone free to change the current proper meaning of a common word in any language? For example, suppose a traveller told you that in a certain country men can ‘pass unhurt through the fire’; and when he explained himself you found that he meant by ‘fire’ what others call ‘water’; or suppose he said that there are trees that walk on two legs, meaning men by the term ‘trees’. Would you think this reasonable?

Hyl: No; I should think it very absurd. Common custom is the standard of correctness in language. And deliberately to speak improperly is to pervert the use of speech, and can’t achieve anything except to prolong and multiply disputes when there is no real difference of opinion.

Phil: And doesn’t ‘matter’, in the common current meaning of the word, signify an extended, solid, movable, unthinking, inactive substance?

Hyl: It does.

Phil: And hasn’t it been made evident that no such substance can possibly exist? And even if it did exist, how can something inactive be a cause? and how can something unthinking be a cause of thought? You are free to give the word ‘matter’ a meaning that is contrary to its ordinary one, and to tell me that you understand by ‘matter’ an unextended, thinking, active being, which is the cause of our ideas. But this is just playing with words, committing the very fault that you have just now rightly condemned. I don’t find fault with your reasoning, in that you infer a cause from the phenomena; but I deny that the cause that reason allows you to infer can properly be called ‘matter’.

Hyl: There is indeed something in what you say. But I am afraid you don’t properly grasp what I mean. I wouldn’t want you to take me to be denying that God, or an infinite spirit,

32

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

is the supreme cause of all things. All I am arguing is that subordinate to the supreme agent ·or cause· there is a cause of a limited and lower kind, which concurs in [= ‘goes along with’] the production of our ideas, not by the action proper to spirits (namely acts of will) but by the action proper to matter (namely motion).

Phil: You keep relapsing into your old exploded notion of a movable (and consequently extended) substance existing outside the mind. What! have you already forgotten what you were convinced of? Do you want me to repeat everything I have said about this? Really, this isn’t arguing fairly, still to assume the existence of something that you have so often admitted not to exist. But letting that go, I ask Aren’t all your ideas perfectly passive and inert, including no kind of action in them?

Hyl: They are.

Phil: And are sensible qualities anything else but ideas?

Hyl: How often have I agreed that they are not?

Phil: But isn’t motion a sensible quality?

Hyl: It is.

Phil: Consequently it is no action.

Hyl: I agree with you. And indeed it is obvious that when I move my finger it remains passive; but my will that produced the motion is active.

Phil: Now I want to know in the first place •whether, given that motion is not action, you can conceive any action other than volition; in the second place •whether to say something and conceive nothing is not to talk nonsense; and lastly, •whether having considered the premises, you don’t see that it is highly absurd and unreasonable to suppose that our ideas have any efficient or active cause other than spirit.

Hyl: I give up the point entirely. But although matter may not be a cause, what blocks it from being an instrument subservient to the supreme agent in the production of our ideas?

Phil: An instrument, you say. Please tell me about the shape, springs, wheels, and motions of that instrument?

Hyl: I don’t claim to be able to do that, because both this substance and its qualities are entirely unknown to me.

Phil: What? So you think it is made up of unknown parts, and has unknown motions and an unknown shape.

Hyl: I don’t think it has any shape or motion at all, because you have convinced me that no sensible qualities can exist in an unperceiving substance.

Phil: But what notion can we possibly have of an instrument that has no sensible qualities, not even extension?

Hyl: I don’t claim to have any notion of it.

Phil: And what reason do you have to think that this unknown and inconceivable something does exist? Is it that you think God cannot act as well without it, or that you find by experience that some such thing is at work when you form ideas in your own mind?

Hyl: You are always nagging me for reasons for what I believe. What reasons do you have for not believing it?

Phil: For me, seeing no reason for believing something is a sufficient reason for not believing it. But, setting aside reasons for believing, you will not so much as let me know what it is you want me to believe, since you say you have no sort of notion of it. I beg you to consider whether it is like a philosopher, or even like a man of common sense, to claim to believe you know not what and you know not why.

33

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

Hyl: Hold on, Philonous! When I tell you that matter is an ‘instrument’, I don’t mean absolutely nothing. Admittedly I don’t know what the particular kind of instrument it is; but still I have some notion of instrument in general, which I apply to it.

Phil: But what if it should turn out that even the most general notion of instrument, understood as meaning something distinct from cause, contains something that makes the use of an instrument inconsistent with the divine attributes?

Hyl: Show me that and I shall give up the point.

Phil: ·I shall now do so·. What do you mean by the general nature or notion of instrument?

Hyl: The general notion is made up of what is common to all particular instruments.

Phil: Don’t all instruments have this in common: they are used only in doing things that can’t be performed by the mere act of our wills? Thus, for instance, I never use an instrument to move my finger, because it is done by a volition. But I would use an instrument if I wanted to remove part of a rock or tear up a tree by the roots. Do you agree with this? Or can you show any example where an instrument is used in producing an effect which immediately depends on the will of the agent?

Hyl: I admit that I can’t.

Phil: Well, then, how can you suppose that an all-perfect Spirit, on whose will all things absolutely and immediately depend, would need an instrument in his operations, or that he would use one if he didn’t need it? Thus, it seems to me, you have to admit that it would be incompatible with the infinite perfection of God for him to use a lifeless inactive instrument ·such as matter is supposed to be·. That is, your own statements oblige you to give up the point.

Hyl: No answer to that comes readily to mind.

Phil: ·There is an answer that should come to your mind·. You should be ready to admit to the truth when it has been fairly proved to you. ·I shall state the proof again·. We •beings whose powers are finite are forced to make use of instruments. And the use of an instrument shows that the agent is limited by rules that were prescribed by someone else ·and not by him·, and that he cannot get what he wants except in such-and-such a way and in such-and-such conditions. This seems clearly to imply that the •supreme unlimited agent uses no tool or instrument at all. An omnipotent Spirit has only to will that something happen and it happens, straight off, without the use of any means. When •means are employed by inferior agents ·like you and me·, it isn’t because of any real causal power that is in •them, any necessary fitness to produce the desired effect. Rather, it is to comply with the laws of nature, or those conditions prescribed to us by ·God·, the first cause, who is himself above all limitation or prescription whatsoever.

Hyl: I will no longer maintain that matter is an instrument. But don’t take me to be giving up on its existence, because, despite everything you have said, it may still be an occasion.

Phil: How many shapes is your matter to take? How often must it be proved not to exist before you are content to let it go? By all the laws of debate I am entitled to blame you for so frequently changing the meaning of the principal term ·(‘matter’)·, but I shan’t press that point. ·Instead·, I ask you this: having already denied matter to be a cause, what do you mean when you affirm that it is an occasion? And when you have shown what you mean by ‘occasion’, then please

34

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

show me what reason leads you to believe there is such an occasion of our ideas.

Hyl: As to the first point: by ‘occasion’ I mean an inactive, unthinking being, at the presence of which God causes ideas in our minds.

Phil: And what may be the nature of that inactive, unthinking being?

Hyl: I know nothing of its nature.

Phil: Proceed then to the second point, and give me some reason why we should believe in the existence of this inactive, unthinking, unknown thing.

Hyl: When we see ideas produced in our minds in an orderly and constant manner, it is natural to think they have some fixed and regular occasions at the presence of which they are excited.

Phil: You acknowledge then that God alone is the cause of our ideas, and that he causes them in the presence of those occasions.

Hyl: That is what I think.

Phil: No doubt God perceives the things that you say are present to him.

Hyl: Certainly; otherwise they couldn’t provide him with occasions of acting.

Phil: Without insisting now on your making sense of this hypothesis, or on your answering all the puzzling questions and difficulties that beset it, I merely ask:

•Isn’t the order and regularity found in the series of our ideas—that is, the course of nature—sufficiently explained by the wisdom and power of God?

•Doesn’t it take away from God’s wisdom and power to suppose that any unthinking substance influences or directs him concerning what to do and when to do it?

•Even if I granted you all that you contend for ·regarding matter as God’s occasion for acting·, would you get the result you want?

·The point of the last question is that· it’s hard to see how the external or absolute existence of an unthinking substance, distinct from its being perceived, can be inferred from there being certain things perceived by the mind of God which are to him the occasion of producing ideas in us.

Hyl: I am utterly at a loss about what to think. This notion of occasion now seems to be just as groundless as the rest.

Phil: Don’t you at last see that in all these different senses of ‘matter’ you have only been supposing you know not what, for no reason, and to no purpose?

Hyl: I freely admit to having become less fond of my notions, since you have examined them in such precise detail. But still, I think I have some confused •perception that there is such a thing as •matter.

Phil: •Either you perceive the existence of matter immediately, or you perceive it mediately. If immediately, please tell me by which of the senses you perceive it. If mediately, let me know what reasoning you employ to infer it from things that you do perceive immediately. So much for the perception. •Then for the matter itself: I ask whether it is object, substratum, cause, instrument, or occasion? You have already argued for each of these, shifting your notions and making matter appear first in one guise and then in another. And each thing you have offered has been disapproved and rejected by yourself. If you have anything new to advance, I would gladly hear it.

35

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

Hyl: I think I have already offered all I had to say on those topics. I am at a loss what more to urge.

Phil: And yet you’re reluctant to part with your old prejudice. But to make it easier for you to drop it, I ask you to consider—as well as all my other points—the question of •how you could possibly be affected by matter if it did exist. And the question of •whether it would make any difference to the ideas you experience—and thus make any difference to your reasons to believe in its existence—if matter didn’t exist?

Hyl: I agree that •it is possible we might perceive all things just as we do now without there being any matter in the world; and ·in answer to your first question·, •I can’t conceive how matter—if there is such a thing—could produce any idea in our minds. And I also admit that you have entirely satisfied me that it is impossible for there to be such a thing as matter in any of the previous senses of the term. But still I can’t help supposing that there is matter in some sense or other. I don’t claim to settle what sense that is.

Phil: I don’t demand that you define exactly the nature of that unknown being. Just tell me whether it is a substance; and if it is, whether you can suppose a substance without qualities; and if on the other hand you suppose it to have qualities, please tell me what those qualities are, ·or· at least what it means to say that matter ‘supports’ them.

Hyl: We have already argued on those points. I have no more to say about them. But to head off any further questions, let me tell you that I now understand by ‘matter’ neither substance nor accident, thinking nor extended being, neither cause, instrument, nor occasion, but something entirely unknown, different from all those.

Phil: It seems then that you include in your present notion of matter nothing but the general abstract of idea of entity ·or thing·.

Hyl: Nothing else, except that I add to this general idea ·of thing· the negation of all those particular things, qualities, or ideas that I perceive, imagine, or in any way apprehend.

Phil: Where, please, do you suppose that this unknown matter exists?

Hyl: Oh Philonous! now you think you have entangled me; for if I say it exists in some place, you will infer that it exists in the mind, since we agree that place or extension exists only in the mind; but I am not ashamed to admit my ignorance. I don’t know where it exists; but I am sure it doesn’t exist in a place. There is a negative answer for you; and such answers are all you can expect to get for all your remaining questions about matter.

Phil: Since you won’t tell me where it exists, please inform me about how you suppose it to exist, or what you mean by saying that it ‘exists’.

Hyl: It neither thinks nor acts, neither perceives nor is perceived.

Phil: But what positive content is there in your abstracted notion of its existence?

Hyl: When I look into it carefully I don’t find that I have any positive notion or meaning at all. I tell you again: I am not ashamed to admit my ignorance. I don’t know what is meant by its ‘existence’, or how it exists.

Phil: Keep up this frankness, good Hylas, and tell me sincerely whether you can form a distinct idea of entity in general, abstracting from and excluding all thinking and corporeal beings, all particular things whatsoever.

36

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

Hyl: Hold on, let me think a little—I confess, Philonous, I don’t find that I can. At first glance I thought I had some dilute and airy notion of pure entity in abstract; but when I focussed on it, it vanished. The more I think about it, the more am I confirmed in my wise decision to give only negative answers ·to your questions· and not to claim the slightest positive knowledge or conception of matter, its where, its how, its entity, or anything about it.

Phil: So when you speak of the ‘existence of matter’, you have no notion in your mind.

Hyl: None at all.

Phil: Here is where I think we have got to; please tell me if I am wrong. You attributed existence outside the mind first to

•the immediate objects ·of our perceptions· (this came from your belief in material substance); then to

•their archetypes—·the things of which they are copies·; then to

•their causes; then to

•instruments; then to

•occasions; and lastly to

•something in general, which on examination turns out to be nothing.

So matter comes to nothing. What do you think, Hylas? Isn’t this a fair summary of your whole proceeding?

Hyl: Be that as it may, yet I still insist that our not being able to conceive a thing is no argument against its existence.

Phil: I freely grant that the existence of a thing that is not immediately perceived may reasonably be inferred from a cause, effect, operation, sign, or other circumstance; and that it would be absurd for any man to argue against the existence of that thing, from his having no direct and positive notion of it. But where •there is nothing of all this; where

•neither reason nor revelation induces us to believe in the existence of a thing,

•we don’t have even a relative notion of it,

•what is offered is so abstract that it rises above the distinction between perceiving and being perceived (between spirit and idea), and lastly

•not even the most inadequate or faint idea ·of it· is claimed to exist—

where all this is the case, I shan’t indeed draw any conclusion against the reality of any notion or against the existence of anything; but I shall infer that you mean nothing at all, that you are using words to no purpose, without any design or meaning whatsoever. And I leave it to you to consider how ·such· mere jargon should be treated.

Hyl: To be frank, Philonous, your arguments seem in themselves unanswerable, but their effect on me has not been enough to produce that total conviction, that wholehearted agreement, that comes with demonstration [= ‘rigorous knock-down proof’]. I find myself still relapsing into an obscure surmise of something-or-other that I call ‘matter’.

Phil: But don’t you realize, Hylas, that two things must co-operate to take away all doubts and produce a complete mental assent? However clear the light is in which a visible object is set, it won’t be distinctly seen if there is any imperfection in the vision or if the eye is not directed towards it. And however solid and clearly presented a demonstration is, yet if there is also prejudice or wrong bias in the understanding, can it be expected all at once to see the truth clearly and adhere to it firmly? No! For that to happen, time and effort are needed; the attention must be awakened and held by frequent repetition of the same thing—often in the same light, often in different lights. I have said it already, and find I must still repeat it to get you to accept it: when

37

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

you claim to accept you don’t know what, for you don’t know what reason, and for you don’t know what purpose, you are taking extraordinary liberties. Can this be parallelled in any art or science, any sect or profession of men? Or is there anything so shamelessly groundless and unreasonable to be met with even in the lowest of common conversation? But you persist in saying ‘Matter may exist’, without knowing what you mean by ‘matter’ or what you mean by saying that it ‘exists’. What makes this especially surprising is the fact that it’s something you have just decided to say; you aren’t led to it by any reasons at all; for I challenge you to show me something in nature that needs matter to explain or account for it.

Hyl: The reality of things can’t be maintained without supposing the existence of matter. Don’t you think this is a good reason why I should be earnest in its defence?

Phil: The reality of things! What things, sensible or intelligible?

Hyl: Sensible things.

Phil: My glove, for example?

Hyl: That or any other thing perceived by the senses.

Phil: Let us fix on one particular thing. Isn’t it a sufficient evidence to me of the existence of this glove that I see it and feel it and wear it? And if it isn’t, how could I be assured of the reality of this thing, which I actually see in this place, by supposing that some unknown thing which I never did or can see exists in an unknown manner, in an unknown place, or in no place at all? How can the supposed reality of something intangible be a proof that anything tangible really exists? Or of something invisible that any visible thing really exists? Put generally: how can the supposed reality of something imperceptible be a proof of the existence of a perceptible thing? Explain this and I shall think that nothing is too hard for you!

Hyl: Over-all I am content to admit that the existence of matter is highly improbable; but I don’t see that it is directly and absolutely impossible.

Phil: Even if matter is granted to be possible, that doesn’t give it a claim to existence, any more than a golden mountain or a centaur, ·which are also possible·.

Hyl: I admit that; but still you don’t deny that it is possible; and something that is possible may, for all you know, actually exist.

Phil: I do deny it to be possible; and I think I have proved that it isn’t, from premises that you have conceded. In the ordinary sense of the word ‘matter’, is anything more implied than an extended, solid, shaped, movable substance, existing outside the mind? And haven’t you admitted over and over that you’ve seen evident reason for denying the possibility of such a substance?

Hyl: True, but that is only one sense of the term ‘matter’.

Phil: But isn’t it the only proper, genuine, commonly accepted sense? And if matter in such a sense is proved impossible, may it not be thought with good grounds to be absolutely impossible? Otherwise how could anything be proved impossible? Indeed, how could there be any proof at all, of anything, to a man who feels free to unsettle and change the common meanings of words?

Hyl: I thought philosophers might be allowed to speak more accurately than common people do, and were not always confined to the common meaning of a term.

Phil: But the meaning I have stated is the common accepted sense among philosophers. Anyway, setting that point aside,

38

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Second Dialogue

haven’t I let you take ‘matter’ in whatever sense you pleased? And haven’t you used this privilege to the utmost extent, sometimes entirely changing the meaning, at others leaving out or putting into the definition of ‘matter’ whatever at that moment best served your purposes, contrary to all the known rules of reason and logic? And hasn’t this shifting, unfair method of yours spun out our dispute to an unnecessary length, matter having been scrutinised in each particular one of those senses and, by your own admission, refuted in each of them? And can any more be required to •prove the absolute impossibility of a thing than •to prove it to be impossible in every particular sense that you or anyone else understands it in?

Hyl: I am not so thoroughly satisfied that you have proved the impossibility of matter in the last most obscure, abstracted and indefinite sense.

Phil: When is a thing shown to be impossible?

Hyl: When an inconsistency is demonstrated between the ideas contained in its definition.

Phil: But where there are no ideas, no contradiction between ideas can be demonstrated.

Hyl: I agree with you.

Phil: Now, consider the sense of the word ‘matter’ that you have just called obscure and indefinite: by your own admission it is obvious that this includes no idea at all, no sense—except an unknown sense, which is the same thing as none. So you can’t expect me to prove an inconsistency between ideas where there are no ideas, or to prove the impossibility of ‘matter’ taken in an unknown sense, that is, in no sense at all. I aimed only to show that you meant nothing; and I got you to admit that. So that in all your various senses you have been shown to mean nothing at all, or if something then an absurdity. If this isn’t sufficient to prove the impossibility of a thing, I wish you would tell me what is.

Hyl: I admit that you have proved that matter is impossible; nor do I see what else can be said in defence of it. But when I give up matter I come to suspect all my other notions. For surely none could be more seemingly evident than this once was; yet it now seems as false and absurd as it previously seemed true. But I think we have discussed the point enough for the present. I would like to spend the rest of today running over in my thoughts the various parts of this morning’s conversation, and I’ll be glad to meet you again here tomorrow at about the same time.

Phil: I’ll be here.

39

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

The Third Dialogue

Philonous: Tell me, Hylas, what has come of yesterday’s meditation? Has it confirmed you in the views you held when we parted? Or has it given you cause to change your opinion?

Hylas: Truly my opinion is that all our opinions are equally useless and uncertain. What we approve today we condemn tomorrow. We make a fuss about knowledge, and spend our lives in the pursuit of it, yet all the time, alas! we know nothing; and I don’t think we can ever know anything in this life. Our faculties are too narrow and too few. Nature certainly never intended us for speculation [= ‘for the pursuit of true theories’].

Phil: What? You say we can know nothing, Hylas?

Hyl: There isn’t one single thing in the world whose real nature we can know.

Phil: Are you going to tell me that I don’t really know what fire or water is?

Hyl: You may indeed know that fire appears hot, and water fluid; but that is merely knowing what sensations are produced in your own mind when fire or water is applied to your sense-organs. You are utterly in the dark as to their internal constitution, their true and real nature.

Phil: Don’t I know that this is a real stone that I’m standing on, and that what I see before my eyes is a real tree?

Hyl: Know? No, it is impossible that you or any man alive should know it. All you know is that you have such and such an idea or appearance in your own mind. But what does that have to do with the real tree or stone? I tell you, the colour, shape, and hardness that you perceive aren’t the real natures of those things, or in the least like them. The same may be said of all other real things or corporeal substances that make up the world. None of them has in itself anything like the sensible qualities that we perceive. So we shouldn’t claim to affirm or know anything about them as they are in their own nature.

Phil: But surely, Hylas, I can distinguish gold, for example, from iron. How could I do that if I didn’t know what either truly was?

Hyl: Believe me, Philonous, you can only distinguish between your own ideas. That yellowness, that weight, and other sensible qualities—do you think that they are really in the gold? They are only relations to the senses, and have no absolute existence in nature. And in claiming to distinguish the species of real things on the basis of the appearances in your mind, you may be acting as foolishly as someone who inferred that two men were of a different species because their clothes were of different colours.

Phil: It seems, then, that we are fobbed off with the appearances of things, and false appearances at that. The food I eat and the clothes I wear have nothing in them that is like what I see and feel.

Hyl: Just so.

Phil: But isn’t it strange that everyone should be thus deceived. and be so foolish as to believe their senses? And yet men (I don’t know how) eat and drink and sleep and get on with their lives as comfortably and conveniently as if they really knew the things they have to deal with.

40

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

Hyl: They do so; but you know ordinary practical affairs don’t require precise theoretical knowledge. So the common people can retain their mistakes and yet manage to bustle through the affairs of life. But philosophers know better things.

Phil: You mean, they know that they know nothing.

Hyl: That is the very peak and perfection of human knowledge.

Phil: But are you serious about all this, Hylas? Are you really convinced that you know nothing real in the world? If you were going to write, wouldn’t you call for pen, ink, and paper, like anyone else? And wouldn’t you know what it was you were calling for?

Hyl: How often must I tell you that I don’t know the real nature of any single thing in the universe? It is true that I sometimes use pen, ink, and paper, but I declare positively that I don’t know what any of them is in its own true nature. And the same is true with regard to every other corporeal thing. Furthermore, we are ignorant not only of the true and real nature of things but even of their existence. It can’t be denied that we perceive certain appearances or ideas; but it can’t be concluded from this that bodies really exist. Indeed, now that I think about it, my former concessions oblige me to declare that it is impossible that any real corporeal thing should exist in nature.

Phil: You amaze me! Was ever anything more wild and extravagant than the notions you now maintain? Isn’t it evident that you are led into all these extravagances by the belief in material substance? That’s what makes you dream of those unknown natures in every thing. It is what leads you to distinguish the reality of things from their sensible appearances. It is to this that you are indebted for being ignorant of what everyone else knows perfectly well. Nor is this all: you are ignorant not only of the true nature of every thing, but of whether any thing really exists, or whether there are any true natures at all; because you attribute to your ‘material beings’ an absolute or external existence and suppose that their reality consists in that. As you are eventually forced to admit that such an existence means either a direct contradiction or nothing at all, it follows that you are obliged to pull down your own hypothesis of material substance, and positively to deny the real existence of any part of the universe. And so you are plunged into the deepest and most deplorable scepticism that anyone ever suffered from. Tell me, Hylas, isn’t that what has happened?

Hyl: Yes, it is. Material substance was no more than an hypothesis, and a false and groundless one too. I will no longer waste my breath defending it. But whatever •hypothesis you advance, whatever system you introduce in place of it, I am sure it will appear every bit as false, if you allow me to question you about it. Allow me to treat you as you have me, and I’ll lead you through as many perplexities and contradictions to the very same state of scepticism that I myself am in at present.

Phil: I assure you, Hylas, I don’t claim to formulate any •hypothesis at all. I have the common man’s frame of mind; I am simple enough to believe my senses and to leave things as I find them. Here’s what I think, in plain words. The real things are the very things I see and feel and perceive by my senses. I know these; and because I find that they satisfy all the needs and purposes of life, I have no reason to worry about any other unknown beings. A piece of sensible [= ‘perceptible’] bread, for instance, would appease my hunger better than ten thousand times as much of that insensible, unintelligible, ‘real’ bread you speak of. It is also my opinion

41

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

that colours and other sensible qualities are in the objects. I can’t for the life of me help thinking that snow is white, and fire hot. You indeed, who by ‘snow’ and ‘fire’ mean certain external, unperceived, unperceiving substances, are right to deny whiteness or heat to be qualities inherent in them. But I, who understand by ‘snow’ and ‘fire’ the things I see and feel, am obliged to think as other folk do. And as I am no sceptic about •the nature of things, I am not a sceptic either about •their existence. That a thing should be really perceived by my senses, and at the same time not really exist, is to me a plain contradiction; since I cannot abstract, even in thought, the •existence of a sensible thing from •its being perceived. Wood, stones, fire, water, flesh, iron, and other such things that I name and talk about are things that I know. And I wouldn’t have known them if I hadn’t perceived them by my senses; and

•things perceived by the senses are immediately perceived; and

•things that are immediately perceived are ideas; and

•ideas can’t exist outside the mind.

So it follows that

the •existence of things I perceive by my senses consists in •being perceived.

When they are actually perceived, therefore, there can be no doubt about their existence. Away, then, with all that scepticism, all those ridiculous philosophical doubts! What a joke is it for a philosopher to question the existence of sensible things until it is proved to him from the truthfulness of God, or to claim that our knowledge about this falls short of the knowledge we have of things that are obviously self-evident or rigorously proved. I might as well doubt my own existence as the existence of the things that I actually see and feel.

Hyl: Not so fast, Philonous! You say that you can’t conceive how sensible things should exist outside the mind—don’t you?

Phil: I do.

Hyl: Supposing you were annihilated, can’t you conceive it to be possible that things perceivable by sense might still exist?

Phil: I can; but then it must be in another mind. When I say that sensible things can’t exist out of the mind, I don’t mean my mind in particular, but all minds. Now, they clearly have an existence exterior to my mind, since I find by experience that they are independent of it. There is therefore some other mind in which they exist during the intervals between the times when I perceive them; as likewise they did before my birth, and would do after my supposed annihilation. And as the same is true with regard to all other finite created minds, it necessarily follows that there is an omnipresent, eternal Mind which knows and comprehends all things, and lets us experience them in a certain manner according to rules that he himself has ordained and that we call the ‘laws of nature’. [Although ‘comprehends’ can mean ‘understands’, here it probably means ‘includes’—all things are known by, and are in, the mind of God.]

Hyl: Tell me, Philonous: are all our ideas perfectly inert beings? Or have they any agency included in them?

Phil: They are altogether passive and inert.

Hyl: And isn’t God an agent, a being purely active?

Phil: I agree.

Hyl: So an idea cannot be like God, or represent his nature.

Phil: It cannot.

42

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

Hyl: •If you have no idea of the mind of God, how can you conceive it to be possible that things exist in his mind? ·That is, if you have no idea of his mind, how can you have any thought about his mind?· On the other hand, •if you can have a thought about the mind of God without having an idea of him, then why can’t I conceive the existence of matter without having an idea of it?

Phil: I acknowledge that strictly speaking I have no idea either of God or any other spirit; for these, being active, can’t be represented by things that are perfectly inert, as our ideas are. Still, even though I have no idea of myself because I am a spirit or thinking substance, I know that I exist. I know this, indeed, as certainly as I know that my ideas exist. I also know what I mean by the terms ‘I’ and ‘myself’; and I know this immediately or intuitively, though I don’t perceive it as I perceive a triangle, a colour or a sound. The mind (spirit, soul) is the indivisible and unextended thing that thinks, acts and perceives. It is indivisible because it is unextended; and it is unextended because the only extended, shaped, movable things are ideas; and something that perceives ideas, and that thinks and wills, clearly can’t itself be an idea. Ideas are inactive things that are perceived: and spirits are things of a totally different sort. So I deny that my soul is an idea, or like an idea. However, my soul can be said to furnish me with an ‘idea’ of God in a broad sense of the word ‘idea’—that is, an image or likeness of God, though indeed an extremely inadequate one. I get my notion of God by reflecting on my own soul, heightening its powers and removing its imperfections. ·My basic thought of God, therefore, is the thought of ‘a thing that is like me except... ’ and so on·. So although I have no •inert idea of God in my mind, I do have in myself a kind of •active image of him ·because I myself am an image = likeness of him·. And though I don’t perceive him by sense, still I have a notion of him, which is to say that I know him by reflection and reasoning. I immediately know my own mind and my own ideas; and these give me, in an indirect way, a grasp of the possibility that other spirits and ideas exist. Further, from the fact that I exist and the fact that I find that my ideas ·of sense· aren’t caused by me, I reason my way to the unavoidable conclusion that a God exists and that all created things exist in his mind. So much for your first question. By this time you can probably answer your second question for yourself. ·I have shown that there are four different ways in which things can come before the mind, and none of them is a way in which matter could come before your mind·. (i) You don’t perceive matter by mentally representing it, as you do an inactive being or idea; (ii) nor do you know it, as you know yourself, by an act of mentally attending to yourself. (iii) You don’t understand it indirectly, through a resemblance between it and either your ideas or yourself; and (iv) you don’t bring it into your mind by reasoning from what you know immediately. All of this makes the case of matter widely different from that of God, ·because your knowledge of him involves (iii) and (iv)·.

Hyl: You say that your own soul supplies you with a kind of idea or image of God; but you admit that strictly speaking you have no idea of your soul. You even assert that spirits are utterly different in kind from ideas, which means that no idea can be like a spirit, which implies that there can be no idea of a spirit. So you have no idea of spiritual substance, yet you insist that spiritual substance exists. On the other hand, from your having no idea or notion of material substance you infer that material substance doesn’t exist. Is that fair? To be consistent you should either admit matter or reject spirit. What do you say to this?

43

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

Phil: ·My answer falls into three parts·. (1) I don’t deny the existence of material substance merely because I have no notion of it, but because the notion of it is inconsistent—to have a notion of it would involve a self-contradiction. For all I know to the contrary, there may exist many things of which none of us has or can have any idea or notion whatsoever. But such things must be possible, i.e. nothing inconsistent must be included in their definition. (2) Although we believe in the existence of some things that we don’t perceive, we oughtn’t to believe that any particular thing exists without some reason for thinking so; but I have no reason for believing in the existence of matter. I have no immediate intuition of it; and I can’t infer it—rigorously or even by probable inference—from my sensations, ideas, notions, actions or passions. In contrast with this, I undeniably know by reflection the existence of myself, that is, my own soul, mind, or source of thought. You will forgive me if I repeat the same things in answer to the same objections. The notion or definition of •material substance includes an obvious inconsistency, and that is not so for the notion of •spirit. That ideas should exist in something that doesn’t perceive, or be produced by something that doesn’t act, is inconsistent. But there is no inconsistency in saying that a perceiving thing is the subject of ideas, or that an active thing causes them. I concede that the existence of other finite spirits is not immediately evident to us, nor have we any way of rigorously proving it; but that doesn’t put such spirits on a level with material substances, ·because there are the following three differences·. •It is inconsistent to suppose there is matter, but not to suppose there are finite spirits; •there is no argument for matter, while there are probable reasons in favour of spirits; •there are no signs or symptoms that make it reasonable to believe in matter, but we see signs and effects indicating that there are other finite agents like ourselves. (3) Although I don’t have an idea of spirit, if ‘idea’ is used strictly, I do have a notion of it. I don’t perceive it as an idea, or by means of an idea, but I know it by reflection ·on myself·.

Hyl: Despite all that you have said, it seems to me that according to your own way of thinking, and by your own principles, you should conclude that you are only a system of floating ideas without any substance to support them. Words shouldn’t be used without a meaning; and as there is no more meaning in ‘spiritual substance’ than in ‘material substance’, the former is to be exploded as well as the latter.

Phil: How often must I repeat it? I know or am conscious of my own existence; and I know that I myself am not my ideas but something else—a thinking, active principle [here = ‘force or source of energy’] which perceives, knows, wills and operates on ideas. I know that I, one and the same self, perceive both colours and sounds; that a colour cannot perceive a sound, nor a sound a colour; and therefore that I am one individual thing, distinct from colour and sound and (for the same reason) distinct from all other sensible things and inert ideas. But I am not in the same way conscious of either the existence or the essence of matter. On the contrary, I know that nothing inconsistent can exist, and that the existence of matter implies an inconsistency. Furthermore, I know what I mean when I assert that there is a spiritual substance or support of ideas, that is, that a spirit knows and perceives ideas. But I don’t know what people mean when they say that an unperceiving substance contains and supports either ideas or items of which ideas are copies. So there is no significant likeness between spirit and matter.

Hyl: I admit to being satisfied about this. But do you seriously think that the •real existence of sensible things consists in their •being actually perceived? If so, how does it

44

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

come about that all mankind distinguish between them? Ask the first man you meet, and he’ll tell you that to be perceived is one thing and to exist is another.

Phil: I am content, Hylas, to appeal to the common sense of the world for the truth of my view. Ask the gardener why he thinks that cherry tree over there exists in the garden, and he will tell you, because he sees and feels it—in short, because he perceives it by his senses. Ask him why he thinks there is no orange-tree there, and he will tell you, because he doesn’t perceive one. When he perceives something by sense, he terms it a real thing and says that it exists; and anything that isn’t perceivable he says doesn’t exist.

Hyl: Yes, Philonous, I agree that the existence of a sensible thing consists in being perceivable, but not in being actually perceived.

Phil: And what is perceivable but an idea? And can an idea exist without being actually perceived? These are points long since agreed between us.

Hyl: However true your view is, you must admit that it is shocking, and contrary to the common sense of men. Ask your gardener whether that tree has an existence out of his mind; what answer do you think he would give you?

Phil: The same answer that I would give, namely, that it does exist out of his mind. But then surely to a Christian it can’t be shocking to say that the real tree existing outside his mind is truly known and comprehended by (that is, exists in) the infinite mind of God. Probably the gardener won’t at first glance be aware of the direct and immediate proof there is of this—namely that the very existence of a tree or any other perceptible thing implies a mind that contains it. But the point itself is one that he can’t deny. What is at issue between the materialists and me is not whether things have a real existence outside the mind of this or that person, but whether they exist outside all minds, having an existence that doesn’t involve being perceived by God. Some heathens and philosophers have indeed affirmed this, but anyone whose notions of God are appropriate to the holy scriptures will think differently

Hyl: But how, according to your views, do real things differ from chimeras formed by the imagination or the visions of a dream, since ·according to you· they are all equally in the mind?

Phil: The ideas formed by the imagination are faint and indistinct; also, they are entirely dependent on the will. But the ideas perceived by sense—that is, real things—are more vivid and clear, and they don’t in that way depend on our will, because they are imprinted on our mind by a spirit other than us. So there’s no danger of mixing up these ·real things· with the foregoing ·ideas formed by the imagination·, and equally little danger of failing to distinguish them from the visions of a dream, which are dim, irregular, and confused. And even if dreams were very lively and natural, they could easily be distinguished from realities by their not being coherently connected with the preceding and subsequent episodes of our lives, In short, whatever method you use to distinguish things from chimeras is obviously available to me too. For any such method must, I presume, be based on some perceived difference, and I don’t want to deprive you of any one thing that you perceive.

Hyl: But still, Philonous, you hold that there is nothing in the world but spirits and ideas. You must admit that this sounds very odd.

Phil: I agree that the word ‘idea’, not being commonly used for ‘thing’, sounds a little peculiar. I used it because it implies

45

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

a necessary relation to the mind; and it is now commonly used by philosophers to stand for the immediate objects of the understanding. But however odd the proposition may sound in words, there’s nothing very strange or shocking in what it means, which in effect amounts merely to this: that •there are only perceiving things and perceived things; or that •every unthinking being is necessarily—from the very nature of its existence—perceived by some mind, if not by any finite created mind then certainly by the infinite mind of God, in whom ‘we live, and move, and have our being’. Is this as strange as to say that sensible qualities aren’t in the objects? Or that we can’t be sure of the existence of things, or know anything of their real natures, although we see and feel them and perceive them by all our senses?

Hyl: Don’t we have to infer from this that there are no such things as physical or corporeal causes, but that a spirit is the immediate cause of all the phenomena in nature? Can there be anything more extravagant than this?

Phil: Yes, there can! It is infinitely more extravagant to say that an inert thing operates on the mind, and an unperceiving thing causes our perceptions. Anyway, the view that you for some reason find so extravagant is no more than the holy scriptures assert in a hundred places. In them God is represented as the sole and immediate cause of all those effects that some heathens and philosophers customarily attribute to nature, matter, fate, or some such unthinking agent. There is no need for me to support this with particular citations—scripture is full of it.

Hyl: You aren’t aware, Philonous, that in making God the immediate cause of all the motions in nature you make him the author of murder, sacrilege, adultery, and the like heinous sins.

Phil: In answer to that, I remark first that a person’s guilt is the same whether he performs an action with or without an instrument. So if you think that God acts through the mediation of an instrument or ‘occasion’ called matter, you make him the author of sin just as much as I do through my view that he is immediate agent in all those operations that common people ascribe to ‘nature’. I further remark that sin or wickedness does not consist in the outward physical action or movement, but in something internal—the will’s departing from the laws of reason and religion. This is clearly so, from the fact that killing an enemy in a battle or putting a criminal legally to death is not thought sinful, although the outward acts are exactly the same as in murder. Sin therefore doesn’t consist in the physical action, so making God an immediate cause of all such actions isn’t making him the author of sin. Lastly, I have nowhere said that God is the only agent who produces all the motions in bodies. True, I have denied there are any agents other than spirits; but this is quite consistent with assigning to thinking, rational beings the use of limited powers in the production of motions. These powers are indeed ultimately derived from God, but they are immediately under the direction of the beings’ own wills, and that is sufficient to entitle them to all the guilt of their actions.

Hyl: But denying matter, Philonous, or corporeal substance! There is the ·sticking· point. You can never persuade me that this isn’t in conflict with the universal sense of mankind. If our dispute were to be settled by majority vote, I am confident that you would surrender without counting the votes.

Phil: I would like both our positions to be fairly stated and submitted to the judgment of men who had plain common sense, without the prejudices of a learned education. Let me be represented as one who trusts his senses, who thinks he knows the things he sees and feels, and has no doubts about

46

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

their existence; and you fairly present yourself, armed with all your doubts, your paradoxes, and your scepticism; and I shall willingly accept the decision of any unbiased person. To me it is obvious that •spirit is the only substance in which ideas can exist. And everyone agrees that •the objects we immediately perceive are ideas. And no-one can deny that •sensible qualities are objects that we immediately perceive. It is therefore evident there can’t be any substratum of those qualities; they can exist in a spirit, not as qualities of it but as things perceived by it. So I deny that there is any unthinking substratum of the objects of sense, and that is the meaning of my denial that there is any material substance. But if by ‘material substance’ is meant only sensible body, that which is seen and felt (and I dare say that unphilosophical people mean no more), then I am more certain of matter’s existence than you or any other philosopher claim to be. If there is anything that turns people in general off from the views that I support, it is the mistaken idea that I deny the reality of sensible things. But it is you who are guilty of that, not I, so what they are really hostile to are your notions, not mine. I do therefore assert—as something I am as certain of as I am of my own existence—that there are bodies or corporeal substances (meaning the things I perceive by my senses). Most people will agree with this, and will neither think nor care about the fate of those unknown natures and essences that some men are so fond of.

Hyl: What do you say to this? Since, according to you, men judge the reality of things by their senses, how can a man be mistaken in thinking that the moon is a plain shining surface, about a foot in diameter; or that a square tower seen at a distance is round; or that an oar with one end in the water is crooked?

Phil: He is mistaken not with regard to the ideas he actually perceives, but in what he infers from his present perceptions. Thus in the case of the oar, what he immediately perceives by sight is certainly crooked; and to that extent he is right. But if he infers from this that when he takes the oar out of the water he will see the same crookedness, or that it will affect his sense of touch as crooked things usually do, in that he is mistaken. Likewise, if from what he perceives in one place he infers that if he moves closer to the moon or tower he will still experience similar ideas, he is mistaken. But his mistake lies not in what he perceives immediately and at present (for it is a manifest contradiction to suppose he could err about that), but in the wrong judgment he makes concerning •the ideas he thinks to be connected with the ones he immediately perceives; or concerning •the ideas that—judging by what he perceives at present—he thinks would be perceived in other circumstances. The case is the same with regard to the Copernican system. We don’t perceive any motion of the earth while we are standing on it; but it would be wrong to infer from this that if we were placed at as great a distance from earth as we are now from the other planets we would not then perceive the earth’s motion.

Hyl: I understand you; and I have to admit that what you say is plausible enough. Still, let me remind you of something. Tell me, Philonous, weren’t you formerly as sure that matter exists as you are now that it does not?

Phil: I was. But here lies the difference. Before, my confidence was uncritically based on prejudice; but my confidence now, after enquiry, rests on evidence.

Hyl: After all, it seems that our dispute is about words rather than things. We agree in the thing, but differ in the name. It is obvious that we are affected with ideas from outside ourselves; and it is equally obvious that there must be powers outside the mind corresponding to those

47

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

ideas (I don’t say resembling them). And as these powers can’t exist by themselves, we have to postulate some subject of them—·some thing that has the powers·—which I call ‘matter’, and you call ‘spirit’. This is all the difference.

Phil: Hylas, is that powerful being, or subject of powers, extended?

Hyl: It isn’t; but it has the power to cause the idea of extension in you.

Phil: In itself, therefore, it is unextended.

Hyl: I grant it.

Phil: Is it not also active?

Hyl: Without doubt: otherwise, how could we attribute powers to it?

Phil: Now let me ask you two questions. First, does it conform to the usage of philosophers or of non-philosophers to give the name ‘matter’ to an unextended active being? Second, isn’t it ridiculously absurd to misapply names contrary to the common use of language?

Hyl: Well, then, let it not be called ‘matter’, since you insist, but some third nature distinct from matter and spirit. For, what reason do you have to call it ‘spirit’? Doesn’t the notion of spirit imply that it is thinking as well as active and unextended?

Phil: My reason is as follows. I want to have some notion or meaning in what I say; but I have no notion of any action other than volition, and I can’t conceive of volition as being anywhere but in a spirit; so when I speak of an active being, I am obliged to mean a spirit. Besides, it is quite obvious that a thing that can impart ideas to me must have ideas in itself; and if a thing has ideas, surely it must be a spirit. ·I shall state the case differently·, to enable you to understand the point still more clearly, if that is possible. I assert, as you do, that since we are affected from outside ourselves we must accept that there are powers outside us in some being that is distinct from ourselves. Up to here we are in agreement; but then we differ about what kind of powerful being it is. I say it is spirit; you say that it is matter or else some third kind of thing—I don’t know of what kind, and nor do you! Here is how I prove it to be spirit. •From the effects I see produced, I infer that there are actions; so there are volitions; so there must be a will. Again, •the things I perceive (or things they are copied from) must exist outside my mind: but because they are ideas, neither they nor things they are copied from can exist otherwise than in an understanding; there is therefore an understanding. •But will and understanding constitute in the strictest sense a mind or spirit. The powerful cause of my ideas is, therefore, something that it is strictly proper to call ‘a spirit’.

Hyl: I suppose you think you have made the point very clear, little suspecting that what you propose leads directly to a contradiction. It is an absurdity to imagine any imperfection in God, is it not?

Phil: Without doubt.

Hyl: To suffer pain is an imperfection.

Phil: It is.

Hyl: Are we not sometimes affected with pain and discomfort by some being other than ourselves?

Phil: We are.

Hyl: And haven’t you said that that being is a spirit, and is not that spirit God?

Phil: I agree.

48

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

Hyl: But you have asserted that any ideas that we perceive from outside ourselves are in the mind that affects us. It follows that the ideas of pain and discomfort are in God; or, in other words, God suffers pain. That is to say that there is an imperfection in the divine nature, which you agreed was absurd. So you are caught in a plain contradiction.

Phil: I don’t question that God knows or understands all things, including knowing what pain is; he even knows every sort of painful sensation, and what it is for his creatures to suffer pain. But I positively deny that God, though he knows and sometimes causes painful sensations in us, can himself suffer pain. We who are limited and dependent spirits are liable to sensory impressions—caused by an external agent and produced against our wills—that are sometimes painful and distressing. But God cannot suffer anything, or be affected with any painful sensation, or indeed with any sensation at all, because: •no external being can affect him, •he perceives nothing by sense as we do, •his will is absolute and independent, causing all things and incapable of being thwarted or resisted by anything. We are chained to a body; that is to say, our perceptions are connected with bodily motions. By the law of our nature we undergo changes ·in our minds· with every alteration in the nervous parts of our sensible [= ‘perceptible’] body; this sensible body is really nothing but a complex of qualities or ideas that have no existence other than through being perceived by a mind; so that this connection of sensations with bodily motions comes down to a mere correspondence in the order of nature between two sets of ideas or immediately perceivable things—·the set of ideas perceived by someone’s mind, and the set constituting his body·. In contrast with this, God is a pure spirit, disengaged from all such correspondences or linkages according to laws of nature. No bodily motions are accompanied by sensations of pain or pleasure in his mind. To know everything knowable is certainly a perfection; but to endure, or suffer, or feel anything through the senses is an imperfection. The former, I repeat, fits God, but not the latter. God knows or has ideas; but his ideas aren’t conveyed to him by sense as ours are. What led you to think you saw an absurdity where really there is none was your failure to attend to this obvious difference between God and his creatures.

Hyl: ·There is a well established scientific result which implies the existence of matter, and you have ignored it·. Throughout all this you haven’t considered the fact that the quantity of matter has been demonstrated [= ‘rigorously proved’] to be proportional to the gravity of bodies. And what can stand up against the force of a demonstration?

Phil: Let me see how you demonstrate that point.

Hyl: I lay it down for a principle that the quantities of motion in bodies are directly proportional to their velocities and the quantities of matter contained in them. When the velocities of two bodies are equal, therefore, their quantities of motion are directly proportional to the quantity of matter in each. But it has been found by experience that all bodies (not counting small inequalities arising from the resistance of the air) fall with an equal velocity; and so the motion of falling bodies (and consequently their gravity, which is the cause or source of that motion) is proportional to the quantity of matter they contain; which is what I was to demonstrate.

Phil: You lay it down as a self-evident principle that the quantity of motion in any body is proportional to the velocity and matter taken together; and this is used to prove a proposition from which the existence of matter is inferred. Isn’t this arguing in a circle?

49

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

Hyl: In the premise I only mean that the motion is proportional to the velocity jointly with the extension and solidity, ·so I don’t need to use the term ‘matter’ in the premise·.

Phil: But even if this is true, it doesn’t imply that gravity is proportional to matter in your philosophical sense of the word. To get that conclusion you have to take it for granted ·in your premise· that your unknown substratum or whatever else you call it is proportional to those sensible qualities (·velocity and quantity of motion·); but to suppose that is plainly assuming what was to be proved. I readily grant that there is size and solidity (or resistance) perceived by the senses; and I shan’t dispute the claim that gravity is proportional to those qualities. What I do deny is that these qualities as perceived by us, or the powers producing them, exist in a material substratum. You affirm this, but despite your ‘demonstration’ you haven’t yet proved it.

Hyl: I shan’t press that point any further. Do you expect, though, to persuade me that natural scientists have been dreaming all through the years? What becomes of all their hypotheses and explanations of the phenomena, which presuppose the existence of matter?

Phil: What do you mean by ‘the phenomena’?

Hyl: I mean the appearances that I perceive by my senses.

Phil: And the appearances perceived by the senses—aren’t they ideas?

Hyl: I have told you so a hundred times.

Phil: Therefore, to ‘explain the phenomena’ is to show how we come to be affected with ideas in the particular manner and order in which they are imprinted on our senses. Is it not?

Hyl: It is.

Phil: Now, if you can prove that any scientist has explained the production of any one idea in our minds with the help of matter, I shall capitulate, and regard all that I have said against matter as nothing; but if you can’t, you will get nowhere by urging the explanation of phenomena. It is easy to understand that a being endowed with knowledge and will should produce or display ideas; but I can never understand how a being that is utterly destitute of knowledge and will could produce ideas or in any way to affect a mind. Even if we had some positive conception of matter, knew its qualities, and could comprehend its existence, it would still be so far from explaining things that it would itself be the most inexplicable thing in the world. From all this, however, it doesn’t follow that scientists have been doing nothing; for by observing and reasoning about connections of ideas they discover the laws and methods of nature, which is a useful and interesting branch of knowledge.

Hyl: All the same, can it be supposed God would deceive all mankind? Do you imagine that he would have induced the whole world to believe in the existence of matter if there was no such thing?

Phil: I don’t think you will affirm that every widespread opinion arising from prejudice, or passion, or thoughtlessness, may be blamed on God as the author of it. We aren’t entitled to lay at his door an opinion ·of ours· unless either •he has shown it to us by supernatural revelation or •it is so evident to our natural faculties, which were formed and given to us by God, that we couldn’t possibly withhold our assent from it. But where is •the ·supernatural· revelation of matter, or where is •the evidence that compels us to believe in it? Indeed, what is the evidence that matter, taken for something distinct from what we perceive by our senses, is thought to exist by all mankind, or indeed by any except a

50

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

few philosophers who don’t know what they are saying? Your question presupposes that these points are clear. When you have made them so, I shall regard myself as obliged to give you another answer. In the meantime let it suffice that I tell you that I don’t suppose that God has deceived mankind at all.

Hyl: But the novelty, Philonous, the novelty! There lies the danger. New notions should always be discouraged; they unsettle men’s minds, and nobody knows what they will lead to.

Phil: I can’t imagine why rejecting a notion that has no basis in sense, or in reason, or in divine authority, should be thought to unsettle men’s hold on beliefs that are grounded on all or any of these. I freely grant that new opinions about •government and •religion are dangerous, and ought to be discountenanced. But is there any such reason why they should be discouraged in •philosophy? Making anything known that was unknown before introduces a new opinion; and if all such new opinions had been forbidden, what a notable progress men would have made in the arts and sciences! But it isn’t my concern to plead for novelties and paradoxes.

•That the qualities we perceive are not in the objects;

•that we mustn’t believe our senses;

•that we know nothing of the real nature of things, and can never be assured even that they exist;

•that real colours and sounds are nothing but certain unknown shapes and motions;

•that motions are in themselves neither swift nor slow;

•that bodies have absolute extensions, without any particular size or shape;

•that a stupid, thoughtless, and inactive thing operates on a spirit;

•that the tiniest particle of a body contains countless extended parts.

These are the novelties, these are the strange notions which shock the genuine uncorrupted judgment of all mankind and, having once been accepted, embarrass the mind with endless doubts and difficulties. And it is against these and their like that I try to vindicate common sense. It is true that in doing this I may have to express myself in some roundabout ways and to use uncommon turns of speech; but once my notions are thoroughly understood, what is strangest in them will be found to come down merely to this: It is absolutely impossible, and a plain contradiction to suppose, that any unthinking being should exist without being perceived by a mind. And if this view is found to be strange, it is a shame that it should be so in our age and in a Christian country.

Hyl: I shan’t question what you say about the difficulties that other opinions may be liable to; ·but· it is your business to defend your own opinion. Can anything be more obvious than that you support changing all things into ideas? Yes, you, who are not ashamed to charge me with scepticism! This is so obvious that there is no denying it.

Phil: You have me wrong. What I support is not changing things into ideas, but rather ideas into things; since those immediate objects of perception which you say are only appearances of things are what I take to be the real things themselves.

Hyl: Things! Say what you like, it’s certain that all you leave us with are the empty forms of things, their mere outsides that strike the senses.

Phil: What you call the ‘empty forms’ and ‘outsides’ of things seem to me to be the things themselves. And they aren’t

51

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

empty or incomplete, except on your supposition that matter is an essential part of all bodily things. So you and I agree that we perceive only sensible forms; but we differ in that you maintain them to be empty appearances, while I think they are real beings. In short, you don’t trust your senses, I do trust mine.

Hyl: You say that you believe your senses, and you seem to congratulate yourself on agreeing with common people about this. According to you, therefore, the true nature of a thing is discovered by the senses. If so, what is the source of the sensory disagreement ·that we experience·? Why do different ways of perceiving—·e.g. sight and touch·—indicate different shapes for the same object? And if the true nature of a body can be discovered by the naked eye, why should a microscope enable us to know it better?

Phil: Strictly speaking, Hylas, we don’t see the same object that we feel; and the object perceived through the microscope isn’t the same one that was perceived by the naked eye. But if every variation were thought sufficient to constitute a new kind or new individual, language would be made useless by the sheer number of names or by confusions amongst them. Therefore, to avoid this and other inconveniences (you’ll easily see what they are if you think about it), men in their thought and language treat as one thing a number of ideas that are observed to have some connection in nature (either occurring together or in sequence), although the ideas are ·certainly distinct from one another, because they are· perceived through different senses, or through one sense at different times or in different circumstances. So when I see a thing and then proceed to examine it by my other senses, I’m not trying to understand better the same object that I had seen. ·That can’t be what I am doing, because· the object of one sense can’t be perceived by the other senses. And when I look through a microscope, it isn’t so as to perceive more clearly what I had already perceived with my bare eyes, because the objects perceived in these two ways are quite different from one another. In each case, all I want is to know what ideas are connected together; and the more a man knows of the connection of ideas the more he is said to know of the nature of things. If our ideas are variable, and our senses are not always affected with the same appearances—what of it? It doesn’t follow that they aren’t to be trusted, or that they are inconsistent either with themselves or with anything else, except for your preconceived notion that each name stands for I know not what single, unchanged, unperceivable ‘real nature’; a prejudice that seems to have arisen from a failure to understand the common language that people use when speaking of several distinct ideas as united into one thing by the mind. There is reason to suspect that other erroneous views of the philosophers are due to the same source: they founded their theories not so much on notions as on words, which were invented by the common people merely for convenience and efficiency in the common actions of life, without any regard to theories.

Hyl: I think I follow you.

Phil: You hold that the ideas we perceive by our senses are not real things but images or copies of them. So our knowledge is real only to the extent that our ideas are the true representations of those originals. But as these supposed originals (·or real things·) are in themselves unknown, we can’t know how far our ideas resemble them, or indeed whether they resemble them at all. So we can’t be sure that we have any real knowledge. Furthermore, while the supposed real things remain unchanged our ideas keep changing; so they can’t all be true copies of the real things;

52

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

and if some are and others are not, we can’t tell which are which. This plunges us yet deeper into uncertainty. Again, when we think about it we can’t conceive how any idea, or anything like an idea, could have an absolute existence out of any mind; from which it follows, according to your views, that we can’t conceive how there should be any real thing in nature ·because you say that real things are like ideas·. The result of all this is that we are hopelessly lost in scepticism. Now let me ask you four questions. First, •doesn’t all this scepticism arise from your relating ideas to certain absolutely existing unperceived substances, as their originals? Secondly, •are you informed, either by sense or reason, of the existence of those unknown originals? And if you are not, isn’t it absurd to suppose that they exist? Thirdly, •when you look into it, do you find that there is anything distinctly conceived or meant by the absolute or external existence of unperceiving substances? Lastly, •having considered the premises ·that I have put to you·, isn’t it wisest to follow nature, trust your senses, lay aside all anxious thoughts about unknown natures or substances, and join the common people in taking the things that are perceived by the senses to be real things?

Hyl: Just now I am not inclined to answer your questions. I would much rather see how you can answer mine. Aren’t the objects perceived by one person’s senses also perceivable by others who are present? If there were a hundred more people here, they would all see the garden, the trees, and flowers as I see them. But they don’t experience in the same way the ideas that I form in my imagination. Doesn’t this make a difference between the former sort of objects and the latter?

Phil: I agree that it does; and I have never denied that the objects of sense are different from those of imagination. But what would you infer from this? You can’t say that sensible objects exist unperceived because they are perceived by many people.

Hyl: I admit that I can’t make anything of that objection ·of mine·; but it has led me to another. Isn’t it your opinion that all we perceive through our senses are the ideas existing in our minds?

Phil: It is.

Hyl: But the idea that is in my mind can’t be in yours, or in any other mind. So doesn’t it follow from your principles that no two people can see the same thing? And isn’t this highly absurd?

Phil: If the term ‘same’ be given its common meaning, it is certain (and not at all in conflict with the principles I maintain) that different persons may perceive the same thing; and that the same thing or idea can exist in different minds. The meanings of words are assigned by us; and since men customarily apply the word ‘same’ where no distinction or variety is perceived, and I don’t claim to alter their perceptions, it follows that as men have sometimes said ‘Several people saw the same thing’, they may continue to talk like that in similar situations, without deviating either from correctness of language or the truth of things. But if the term ‘same’ is used in a meaning given to it by philosophers who claim to have an abstracted notion of identity, then in that sense it may or may not be possible for different people to perceive the same thing—depending on their various definitions of this notion (for it isn’t yet agreed what that philosophical identity consists in). But whether philosophers shall think fit to call a thing ‘the same’ or not is of small importance, I think. Let us suppose a group of men together, all having the same faculties and

53

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

consequently affected in similar ways by their senses, but with no use of language. There is no doubt that they would agree in their perceptions. But when they came to the use of speech, ·they might go different ways in their use of ‘same’·. Some of them, impressed by •the uniformness of what was perceived, might speak of ‘the same thing’; while others, struck by •the diversity of the people whose perceptions were in question, might speak of ‘different things’. But can’t anyone see that all the dispute is about a word—namely, a dispute over whether what is perceived by different people can have the term ‘same’ applied to it? Or suppose a house whose outer walls remain unaltered while the rooms are all pulled down and new ones built in their place. If you were to say that we still have ‘the same’ house, and I said it wasn’t the same, wouldn’t we nevertheless perfectly agree in our thoughts about the house considered in itself? Wouldn’t all the difference consist in a sound? If you were to say that in that case we do differ in our notions, because your idea of the house includes the simple abstracted idea of identity whereas mine does not, I would tell you that I don’t know what you mean by that ‘abstracted idea of identity’; and I would invite you to look into your own thoughts, and make sure that you understood yourself.—Why so silent, Hylas? Aren’t you satisfied yet that men can dispute about identity and non-identity without any real difference in their thoughts and opinions, apart from names? Take this further thought with you: that this point still stands, whether matter exists or not. For the materialists themselves admit that what we immediately perceive by our senses are our own ideas. So your difficulty—that no two see the same thing—holds as much against the materialists as against me.

Hyl: But they suppose that an idea represents and copies an external thing, and they can say truly that several people ‘perceive the same thing’ meaning that their ideas all copy a single external thing.

Phil: You earlier gave up on those things that ideas were said to copy; but let that pass. Anyway, on my principles also you can suppose that ideas are copies of something external, by which I mean external to one’s own mind, though indeed it must be supposed to exist in that mind which includes all things. This thing-that-is-copied serves all the ends of identity—·providing a basis for saying ‘they perceived the same thing’·—as well as if it existed out of a mind. And I am sure you won’t say that it is less intelligible than the other.

Hyl: You have indeed clearly satisfied me that there is basically no difficulty in this point; or that if there is, it counts equally against both opinions.

Phil: But something that counts equally against two contradictory opinions can’t be a disproof of either of them.

Hyl: I agree. But after all, Philonous, when I consider the substance of what you say against scepticism, it amounts to no more than this: We are sure that we really see, hear, feel; in a word, ·we are sure· that we are affected with sensible impressions.

Phil: And what more should we be concerned with? I see this cherry, I feel it, I taste it; and I am sure nothing cannot be seen, or felt, or tasted; ·so the cherry is not nothing and· it is therefore real. Take away the sensations of softness, moisture, redness, tartness, and you take away the cherry. Since it is not a thing distinct from sensations, a cherry—I repeat—is nothing but a heap of sensible impressions, or ideas perceived by various senses. These ideas are united into one thing (or have one name given to them) by the mind, because they are observed to accompany each other. Thus when the palate is affected with a certain taste, the

54

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

sight is affected with a red colour, the sense of touch with roundness, softness, etc. And when I see and feel and taste in certain particular ways, I am sure that the cherry exists, or is real; because I don’t think its reality is anything apart from those sensations. But if by the word ‘cherry’ you mean an unknown nature distinct from all those sensible qualities, and by its ‘existence’ you mean something distinct from its being perceived, then indeed I agree that neither you nor I nor anyone else can be sure that it exists.

Hyl: But what would you say, Philonous, if I brought the very same reasons against the existence of sensible things in a mind that you have offered against their existing in a material substratum?

Phil: When I see your reasons I’ll tell you what I have to say to them.

Hyl: Is the mind extended or unextended?

Phil: Unextended, without doubt.

Hyl: Do you say the things you perceive are in your mind?

Phil: They are.

Hyl: Again, have I not heard you speak of sensible impressions?

Phil: I believe you may have.

Hyl: Explain to me now, Philonous, how there can possibly be room for all those trees and houses to exist in your mind! Can extended things be contained in something that ·has no size because it· is unextended? And are we to imagine impressions made on a thing that has no solidity? ·Obviously not!· You can’t say that objects are in your mind as books are in your study; or that things are ·impressed or· imprinted on your mind as the shape of a seal is imprinted on wax. In what sense therefore are we to understand those expressions? Explain this to me if you can; and I shall then be able to answer all those questions you earlier put to me about my substratum.

Phil: Come on, Hylas! When I speak of objects as existing ‘in’ the mind or ‘imprinted’ on the senses, I don’t mean these in the crude literal sense, as when bodies are said to exist ‘in’ a place or a seal to make an ‘impression’ on wax. I mean only that the mind comprehends or perceives them; and that it is affected from outside, or by some being other than itself. This is my explanation of your difficulty; I would like to know how it can help to make intelligible your thesis of an unperceiving material substratum.

Hyl: No, if that’s all there is to it, I admit that I don’t see what use can be made of it. But are you not guilty of some misuse of language in this?

Phil: None at all. I have merely followed what is authorized by common custom, which as you know is what sets the rules for language. For nothing is more usual than for philosophers to speak of the immediate objects of the understanding as things existing ‘in’ the mind. And this fits with the general analogy of language: most mental operations are signified by words borrowed from sensible things, as can be seen in the terms ‘comprehend’ [contain, understand], ‘reflect’ [bounce back, look inward], ‘discourse’, etc.. When these are applied to the mind, they must not be taken in their crude original sense. [The word ‘discourse’ comes from Latin meaning ‘run to and fro’, and in Berkeley’s day it could mean ‘reasoning’.]

Hyl: You have, I admit, satisfied me about this. But there still remains one great difficulty, which I don’t see how you can overcome. Indeed, it is of such importance that even if you can solve all others, if you can’t find a solution for this difficulty you mustn’t expect to make a convert out of me.

55

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

Phil: Let me know this mighty difficulty.

Hyl: The scriptural account of the creation appears to me to be utterly incompatible with your notions. Moses tells us of a creation: a creation of what? of ideas? No, certainly, but of things, of real things, solid corporeal substances. Get your principles to conform with this and I shall perhaps agree with you ·about them in general·.

Phil: Moses mentions the sun, moon, and stars, earth and sea, plants and animals: I don’t question that all these do really exist, and were in the beginning created by God. If by ‘ideas’ you mean fictions and fancies of the mind, then the sun, moon, etc. are no ideas. If by ‘ideas’ you mean immediate objects of the understanding, or sensible things that can’t exist unperceived or out of a mind, then those things are ideas. But it matters little whether you call them ‘ideas’ or not. That difference is only about a name. And whether that name be retained or rejected, the sense, the truth and reality of things, continues the same. In common talk, the objects of our senses are not called ‘ideas’, but ‘things’. You’ll have no quarrel with me if you go on calling them ‘things’, provided you don’t attribute to them any absolute external existence. So I accept that the creation was a creation of things, of real things. This isn’t in the least inconsistent with my principles, as is evident from what I have just been saying, and would have been evident to you without that, if you hadn’t forgotten what I so often said before. As for solid corporeal substances, please show where Moses makes any mention of them; and if they should be mentioned by him or any other inspired writer, it would still be up to you to show that in such texts those words were not used in the common meaning, as referring to things falling under our senses, but in the philosophical meaning as standing for matter, or an unknown something, with an absolute ·mind-independent· existence. When you have proved these points, then (and not till then) you may bring the authority of Moses into our dispute.

Hyl: It is useless to dispute about a point that is so clear. I am content to refer it to your own conscience. Can’t you see that your views conflict in a special way with Moses’ account of the creation?

Phil: If the first chapter of Genesis can be given any possible sense that makes it square with my principles as well as with any others, then that chapter has no special conflict with mine. And any such sense can be conceived by you, because you believe what I believe. All you can conceive apart from spirits are ideas, and their existence I don’t deny. And you ·like me· don’t claim that they exist outside the mind.

Hyl: Please let me see any sense in which you can understand that chapter.

Phil: Why, I imagine that if I had been present at the creation, I would have seen things come into existence—that is, become perceptible—in the order described by Moses. I have always believed Moses’ account of the creation, and I don’t find that my manner of believing it has altered in any way. When things are said to begin or end their existence, we mean this with regard not to God but to his creatures. All objects are eternally known by God, or (the same thing) have an eternal existence in his mind; but when things that were previously imperceptible to creatures are by a decree of God made perceptible to them, then are they said to ·‘come into existence’, in the sense that they· begin a relative existence with respect to created minds. So when I read Moses’ account of the creation, I understand that the various parts of the world gradually became perceivable to finite spirits that were endowed with proper faculties; so that when such spirits

56

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

were present, the things were in truth perceived by them. This is the literal, obvious sense suggested to me by the words of the holy scripture; and in it there is no mention and no thought of substratum, instrument, occasion, or absolute existence. And if you look into it I am sure you will find that most plain, honest men who believe the creation never think of those things any more than I do. What metaphysical sense you may understand the creation story in, only you can tell.

Hyl: But, Philonous, you seem not to be aware ·of a terrific problem confronting you, arising from the fact· that according to you created things in the beginning had only a relative existence, and thus a hypothetical existence; that is to say, they existed if there were men to perceive them. You don’t allow them any actuality of absolute existence that would have enabled God to create them and not taken the further step of creating men. So don’t you have to say that it’s plainly impossible that inanimate things were created before man was? And isn’t this directly contrary to Moses’ account?

Phil: In answer to that I say, first, created beings might begin to exist in the mind of other created intelligences besides men. To prove any contradiction between Moses’ account and my notions you must first show that there was no other order of finite created spirits in existence before men. For my second reply, let us think of the creation as it was at the end of the fourth day, a collection of plants of all sorts, produced by an invisible power, in a desert where nobody was present. I say •that this way of thinking about the creation is consistent with my principles, since they deprive you of nothing sensible and nothing imaginable; •that it exactly suits with the common, natural, uncorrupted notions of mankind; •that it brings out the dependence of all things on God, and consequently has all the good effect or influence which that important article of our faith could possibly have in making men humble, thankful, and resigned to their creator. I say, furthermore, •that in this naked conception of things, with words stripped off, you won’t find any notion of what you call the ‘actuality of absolute existence’. You may indeed raise a dust with those terms, and so pointlessly lengthen our dispute. But I beg you to look calmly into your own thoughts, and then tell me if they aren’t useless and unintelligible jargon.

Hyl: I admit that I have no very clear notion annexed to them. But what do you say to this? Don’t you make the existence of sensible things consist in their being in a mind? And weren’t all things eternally in the mind of God? Didn’t they therefore exist from all eternity, according to you? How could something that was eternal be created in time? Can anything be clearer or better reasoned than this?

Phil: Don’t you also think that God knew all things from eternity?

Hyl: I do.

Phil: Consequently they always had an existence in the divine intellect.

Hyl: This I acknowledge.

Phil: By your own admission, therefore, nothing is new, nothing begins to be, in respect of the mind of God. So we are agreed on that point.

Hyl: Then what are we to make of the creation?

Phil: Can’t we understand it to have been entirely in respect of finite spirits? On that understanding of it, things (with regard to us) can properly be said to begin their existence, or be created, when God decreed they should become perceptible to intelligent creatures in the order and manner which he then established and which we now call ‘the laws of nature’.

57

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

You may call this a relative or hypothetical existence if you please. But so long as •it supplies us with the most natural, obvious, and literal sense of Moses’ history of the creation; so long as •it answers all the religious ends of that great article of faith; in a word, so long as •you can assign no other sense or meaning in place of it; why should we reject this? Is it to comply with a ridiculous sceptical desire to make everything nonsense and unintelligible? I am sure you can’t say it is for the glory of God. For even if it were possible and conceivable that the physical world should have an absolute existence outside the mind of God, as well as of the minds of all created spirits, how could this display either the immensity or the omniscience of the Deity, or the necessary and immediate dependence of all things on him? Wouldn’t it indeed seem rather to detract from those attributes?

Hyl: Well, let us look into this decree of God’s that things should become perceptible. Isn’t it clear, Philonous, that either •God carried out that decree from all eternity or •at some particular time he began to will what he hadn’t actually willed before but only planned to will? If the former, then there could be no creation or beginning of existence for finite things. If the latter, then we must think that something new happened to God, which implies a sort of change; and all change points to imperfection.

Phil: Please think what you are doing! Isn’t it obvious that this objection counts equally against a creation in any sense; indeed, that it counts against every other act of God’s that we can discover by the light of nature? We can’t conceive any act of God’s otherwise than as performed in time, and having a beginning. God is a being of transcendent and unlimited perfections; so finite spirits can’t understand his nature. It isn’t to be expected, therefore, that any man, whether materialist or immaterialist, should have exactly correct notions of the Deity, his attributes, and his ways of doing things. So if you want to infer anything against me, your difficulty mustn’t be drawn from the inadequateness of our conceptions of the divine nature, which is unavoidable on any system; it must rather come from my denial of matter, of which there isn’t one word said or hinted in what you have just objected.

Hyl: I have to agree that the only difficulties you have to clear up are ones that arise from the non-existence of matter, and are special to that thesis. You are right about that. But I simply can’t bring myself to think there is no such special conflict between the creation and your opinion; though I am not clear about where exactly it is.

Phil: What more do you want? Don’t I acknowledge a twofold state of things, the one copied or natural, the other copied-from and eternal? The former was created in time; the latter existed from everlasting in the mind of God. Isn’t this in harmony with what theologians generally say? Is anything more than this necessary in order to conceive the creation? But you suspect some special conflict, though you cannot locate it. To take away all possibility of doubt about all this, just consider this one point. Either you can’t conceive the creation on any hypothesis whatsoever, in which case you have no ground for dislike or complaint against my thesis in particular; or you can conceive the creation, and in that case why not conceive it on my principles, since that would not take away anything conceivable? My principles have all along allowed you the full scope of sense, imagination, and reason. So anything that you could previously apprehend, either immediately by your senses or mediately by inferences from your senses, anything you could perceive, imagine, or understand, remains still with you ·on my principles·. If therefore the notion you have of the creation by other

58

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

principles is intelligible, you still have it on mine; if it isn’t intelligible, I don’t think it is a notion at all, and so the loss of it is no loss. And indeed it seems to me quite clear that the supposition of matter—something perfectly unknown and inconceivable—can’t enable us to conceive anything. And I hope I don’t need to prove to you that the inference from The creation is inconceivable without matter to Matter exists is no good if the existence of matter doesn’t make the creation conceivable.

Hyl: I admit, Philonous, you have almost satisfied me on this point of the creation.

Phil: I wonder why you aren’t entirely satisfied. You tell me indeed of an inconsistency between Moses’ history and immaterialism; but you don’t know where it lies. Is this reasonable, Hylas? Can you expect me to solve a difficulty without knowing what it is? But setting that aside, wouldn’t anyone think you are sure that the received notions of materialists are consistent with holy scripture?

Hyl: And so I am.

Phil: Ought the historical part of scripture to be understood in a plain, obvious sense, or in a sense that is metaphysical and out of the way?

Hyl: In the plain sense, doubtless.

Phil: When Moses speaks of ‘plants’, ‘earth’, ‘water’, etc. as having been created by God, don’t you think that what this suggests to every unphilosophical reader are the sensible things commonly signified by those words?

Hyl: I can’t help thinking so.

Phil: And doesn’t the doctrine of materialists deny a real existence to all ideas, that is, all things perceived by sense?

Hyl: I have already agreed to this.

Phil: According to them, therefore, the creation was not the creation of sensible things that have only a •relative existence, but of certain unknown natures that have an •absolute existence—·so that they could exist even if there were no spirit to perceive them·.

Hyl: True.

Phil: Isn’t it evident, therefore, that the friends of matter destroy the plain obvious sense of Moses, with which their notions are utterly inconsistent; and instead of it force on us I know not what, something equally unintelligible to themselves and me?

Hyl: I can’t contradict you.

Phil: Moses tells us of a creation. A creation of what? of unknown essences, of occasions, or substratums? No, certainly; but of things that are obvious to the senses. You must first reconcile this with your notions, if you want me to be reconciled to them.

Hyl: I see you can attack me with my own weapons.

Phil: Then as to absolute existence: was there ever known a more poverty-stricken notion than that? It is something so abstracted and unintelligible that you have frankly admitted to being unable to conceive it, much less to explain anything with its help. But even if we allow that matter exists and that the notion of absolute existence is as clear as daylight, has this ever been known to make the creation more credible? On the contrary, hasn’t it provided the atheists and infidels down through the centuries with their most plausible argument against a creation? This thesis:

A corporeal substance which has an absolute existence outside the minds of spirits was produced out of nothing by the mere will of a spirit,

59

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

has been seen as so contrary to all reason, so impossible and absurd, that not only the most celebrated among the ancients, but even a variety of modern and Christian philosophers, have thought matter ·not to have been created at all, but· to have existed for ever along with God. Put these points together, and then judge whether materialism disposes men to believe in the creation of things!

Hyl: I admit, Philonous, that I don’t think it does. This creation objection is the last one I can think of; and I have to admit that you have sufficiently answered it along with the rest. All that remains for me to overcome is a sort of unaccountable resistance that I find in myself towards your notions.

Phil: When a man is swayed to one side of a question, without knowing why, don’t you think that this must be the effect of prejudice, which always accompanies old and rooted notions? In this respect, indeed, I can’t deny that the belief in matter has very much the advantage over the contrary opinion, in the minds of educated men.

Hyl: I admit that that seems to be right.

Phil: Well, then, as a counter-balance to this weight of prejudice, let us throw into the scale the great advantages that arise from the belief in immaterialism, in regard to both religion and human learning. •The existence of a God, and the imperishable nature of the soul, those great articles of religion, aren’t they proved with the clearest and most immediate evidence? When I say the existence of a God, I don’t mean an obscure, general cause of things, of which we have no conception, but God in the strict and proper sense of the word. A being whose spirituality, omnipresence, providence, omniscience, infinite power and goodness are as conspicuous as the existence of sensible things, of which (despite the fallacious claims and pretended doubts of sceptics) there is no more reason to doubt than of our own existence. Then with relation to human knowledge, •in natural science what intricacies, what obscurities, what contradictions, has the belief in matter led men into! To say nothing of the numberless disputes about its extent, continuity, homogeneity, gravity, divisibility, etc., don’t they claim to explain everything in terms of bodies operating on bodies according to the laws of motion? And yet can they understand how one body might move another? Furthermore, even if there were no difficulty in

•reconciling the notion of an inert being ·such as matter· with the notion of a cause;

or in

•conceiving how a quality might pass from one body to another (·this being one theory about how one body can move another, namely by passing some motion along to it·);

yet by all their strained thoughts and extravagant suppositions have the materialists been able to understand the mechanical production of any one animal or plant body? Can they through the laws of motion account for sounds, tastes, smells, or colours, or for the regular course of events? Have they through physical principles accounted for the intricate ways in which even the most inconsiderable parts of the universe hang together? If on the other hand we set aside matter and corporeal causes, and admit only the effectiveness of an all-perfect mind, don’t all the effects of nature become easy and intelligible? •If the phenomena are nothing but ideas, ·the choice is obvious·: God is a spirit, but matter is unintelligent and unperceiving. •If the phenomena point to an unlimited power in their cause: God is active and omnipotent, but matter is an inert mass. •If the order, regularity, and usefulness of the effects of nature can never

60

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

be sufficiently admired: God is infinitely wise and provident, but matter doesn’t have plans and designs. These surely are great advantages in physics. Not to mention that the belief in a distant God naturally disposes men to be slack in their moral actions, which they would be more cautious about if they thought God to be immediately present and acting on their minds without the interposition of matter or unthinking ‘second causes’. Then •in metaphysics: what difficulties concerning

•thinghood in the abstract,

•substantial forms,

•‘hylarchic principles’,

•‘plastic natures’,

•substance and accident,

•principle of individuation,

•the possibility of matter’s thinking,

•the origin of ideas,

•the question of how two independent substances as widely different as spirit and matter could act on each other!

What difficulties, I say, and what endless treatises concerning these and countless other similar points do we escape by supposing only spirits and ideas? Even •mathematics becomes much easier and clearer if we take away the absolute existence of extended things. The most shocking paradoxes and intricate speculations in the mathematical sciences depend on the infinite divisibility of finite extended things, and that depends on the supposition of absolutely existing extended things. But what need is there to insist on particular sciences? Isn’t the opposition to all systematic knowledge whatsoever—that frenzy of the ancient and modern sceptics—built on the same foundation? Can you produce so much as one argument against the reality of bodies, or on behalf of that professed utter ignorance of their natures, which doesn’t presuppose that their reality consists in an external absolute existence? Once that presupposition is made, the objections from the change of colours in a pigeon’s neck, or the broken appearance of an oar in the water, do have weight. But objections like those vanish if we don’t maintain the existence of absolute external originals, but place the reality of things in ideas. Although these ideas are fleeting and changeable, they are changed not at random but according to the fixed order of nature. For it is that—·the orderliness of our sequences of ideas·—that the constancy and truth of things consists in. That is what secures all the concerns of life, and distinguishes what is real from the irregular visions of the imagination.

Hyl: I agree with everything you’ve just said, and must admit that nothing can incline me to embrace your opinion more than the advantages that I see come with it. I am by nature lazy, and this [= accepting immaterialism] would greatly simplify knowledge. What doubts, what hypotheses, what labyrinths of confusion, what fields of disputation, what an ocean of false learning, can be avoided by that single notion of immaterialism!

Phil: Is there now anything further to be done? You may remember that you promised to accept whatever opinion appeared on examination to be the most agreeable to common sense and furthest from scepticism. This, by your own admission, is the opinion that denies matter, or the absolute existence of bodily things. And we have gone further: this opinion has been proved in several ways, viewed from different angles, pursued in its consequences, and defended against all objections to it. Can there be a greater evidence of its truth? or could it have all the marks of a true opinion and yet be false?

Hyl: I admit that right now I am entirely satisfied in all

61

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

respects. But how can I be sure that I shall go on fully assenting to your opinion, and that no new objection or difficulty will turn up?

Phil: Tell me, Hylas, when in other cases a point has been clearly proved, do you withhold your assent on account of objections or difficulties it may be liable to? When you are confronted with a mathematical demonstration [= ‘rigorously valid proof’], do you hold out against it because of the difficulties involved in the doctrine of incommensurable quantities, of the angle of contact, of the asymptotes to curves, or the like? Or will you disbelieve the providence of God because there are some particular things which you don’t know how to reconcile with it? If there are difficulties in immaterialism, there are at the same time direct and evident proofs of it. But for the existence of matter there isn’t a single proof, and there are far more numerous and insurmountable objections count against it. Anyway, where are those mighty difficulties you insist on? Alas! you don’t know where or what they are; they’re merely something that may possibly turn up in the future. If this entitles you to withhold your full assent, you should never assent to any proposition, however free from objections it may be, and however clearly and solidly demonstrated.

Hyl: You have satisfied me, Philonous.

Phil: As armament against all future objections, do bear in mind that something bearing equally hard on two contradictory opinions cannot be a proof against either of them. So whenever any difficulty ·in immaterialism· occurs to you, see if you can find a solution for it on the hypothesis of the materialists. Don’t be deceived by words; but test your own thoughts. And if you don’t find it easier with the help of materialism, it obviously can’t be an objection against immaterialism. If you had followed this rule all along, you would probably have spared yourself much trouble in objecting ·because none of your objections conforms to the rule·. I challenge you to show one of your difficulties that is explained by matter; indeed, one that is not made even worse by supposing matter, and consequently counts against materialism rather than for it. In each particular case you should consider whether the difficulty arises from the non-existence of matter. If it doesn’t, then arguing from it to the falsity of immaterialism is ·arguing from a premise to a conclusion that has nothing to do with it·—no better than arguing from ‘Extension is infinitely divisible’ to ‘God does not have foreknowledge’! And yet if you think back I believe you will find this to have been often, if not always, the case ·in our conversation·. Be careful also not to argue by begging the question [that is, giving an argument that at the outset assumes the truth of the conclusion]. One is apt to say: ‘The unknown substances ought to be regarded as real things, rather than the ideas in our minds; and for all we know the unthinking external substance may operate as a cause or instrument in the production of our ideas.’ But doesn’t this assume that there are such external substances? And isn’t this begging the question? But above all things you should beware of misleading yourself by that common fallacy which is called ‘mistaking the question’—·that is, offering against one proposition an argument which really counts only against a quite different proposition·. You often talked as if you thought I maintained the non-existence of sensible things; whereas in truth no-one can be more thoroughly assured of their existence than I am, and it is you who doubt—no; it is you who positively deny—that they exist. Everything that is seen, felt, heard, or in any way perceived by the senses is a real being according to the principles I embrace, but not according to ·the principles that used to be· yours. Remember that the matter you ·used to· defend

62

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

is an unknown something (if indeed it can even be called a ‘something’), which is completely stripped of all sensible qualities, and can’t be perceived through the senses or grasped by the mind. Remember, I say, that your matter is not any object that is hard or soft, hot or cold, blue or white, round or square, etc. For I affirm that all these things do exist; though I do indeed deny that they exist in any way except by being perceived, or that they exist out of all minds whatsoever. Think about these points; consider them attentively and keep them in view. Otherwise you won’t be clear about the state of the question; and in that case your objections will always be wide of the mark, and instead of counting against my views they may possibly be directed (as more than once they have been) against yours.

Hyl: I have to admit, Philonous, that nothing seems to have kept me from agreeing with you more than this same mistaking the question ·that you have just warned me against·. When you deny matter I am tempted at first glance to think that you are denying the things we see and feel; but on reflection I find there is no ground for that. How about keeping the word ‘matter’, and applying it to sensible things? This could be done without any change in your views; and believe me it would reconcile your views to some people who are upset more by your use of words than by your opinions.

Phil: With all my heart: retain the word ‘matter’, and apply it to the objects of sense, if you please, but don’t credit them with existing apart from being perceived. I shan’t quarrel with you over a word. ‘Matter’ and ‘material substance’ are terms introduced by philosophers; and as used by them they imply a sort of independence, or an existence distinct from being perceived by a mind. But common people don’t use these terms, or if they do it is to signify the immediate objects of sense. So one would think that so long as the names of all particular things are retained, and also such terms as ‘sensible’, ‘substance’, ‘body’, and ‘stuff’, the word ‘matter’ would never be missed in common talk. And in philosophical discourses it seems best to leave it out altogether, since the use of that general confused term—more perhaps than any other one factor—has favoured and strengthened the depraved tendency of the mind towards atheism.

Hyl: Well now, Philonous, since I am content to give up the notion of an unthinking substance exterior to the mind, I think you should allow me the privilege of using the word ‘matter’ as I please, to signify a collection of sensible qualities existing only in the mind. I freely grant that strictly speaking there is no other substance than spirit. But I have been accustomed to the term ‘matter’ for so long that I don’t know how to get on without it. To say

There is no matter in the world

is still shocking to me. Whereas to say

There is no matter, if by ‘matter’ is meant an unthinking substance existing outside the mind; but if by ‘matter’ is meant some sensible thing whose existence consists in being perceived, then there is matter

comes across quite differently, and this formulation will bring men to your notions with little difficulty. For, after all, the controversy about matter in the strict sense of ‘matter’ ·is not a dispute between you and ordinary folk. It· lies altogether between you and the philosophers, whose principles are admittedly nowhere near so natural or so agreeable to the common sense of mankind and to holy scripture as yours are. All our desires are directed towards gaining happiness or avoiding misery. But what have happiness or misery, joy or grief, pleasure or pain, to do with absolute existence, or with unknown entities, abstracted from all relation to us? It is obvious that things concern us only insofar as they are

63

Three Dialogues George Berkeley Third Dialogue

pleasing or displeasing; and they can please or displease only to the extent that they are perceived. Beyond that, we are not concerned; and in this respect you leave things as you found them. But still there is something new in this doctrine ·of yours·. It is clear to me that I don’t now think with the philosophers, nor do I entirely think with the common people. I would like to know where I stand now—to know precisely what you have added to my former notions or altered in them.

Phil: I don’t claim to be a setter-up of new notions. All I’m trying to do is bring together and place in a clearer light a truth that used to be shared between •the common people and •the philosophers: the former being of the opinion that •the things they immediately perceive are the real things. and the latter that •the things they immediately perceive are ideas which exist only in the mind. These two notions, when put together, constitute the substance of what I advance.

Hyl: For a long time I have distrusted my senses: I thought I saw things by a dim light, and through false glasses. Now the glasses are removed, and a new light breaks in on my understanding. I am clearly convinced that I see things as they are, and am no longer troubled about their unknown natures or absolute existence. This is the state I find myself in at present, though indeed I don’t yet fully grasp the line of argument that brought me to it. You set out on the same principles that Academics [= sceptics in ancient Greece], Cartesians, and similar sects usually do; and for a long time it looked as if you were advancing their philosophical scepticism; but in the end your conclusions are directly opposite to theirs.

Phil: Hylas, look at the water of that fountain, how it is forced upwards, in a round column, to a certain height, at which it breaks and falls back into the basin from which it rose. Its ascent, as well as its descent, come from the same uniform law or principle of gravitation. In just that way the same principles which at first view lead to scepticism then, when pursued to a certain point, bring men back to common sense.

64

Five Sermons

Joseph Butler

Copyright ©2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are reported between brackets in normal-sized type.—This text consists of the Preface and numbers 1, 2, 3, 11, 12 from Butler’s Fifteen Sermons.
First launched: December 2010
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Preface 1
1: The Social Nature of Man 11
2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience 19
11–12: The Love of our Neighbour 30

Five Sermons Joseph Butler

Glossary

abstruse: ‘Difficult to conceive of or apprehend’ (OED).

affection: A state of mind that is directly relevant to behaviour: what a person likes, hungers for, is drawn to by curiosity, etc. It includes what he is fond of, but only as one in a longish list. Butler sometimes calls self-love ‘the contracted affection’, simply meaning that it is an affection concerning just one object, oneself.

competent: On page 41, but not elsewhere in this text, Butler is using ‘competent’ in an old sense in which it means something like ‘adequate and no more than adequate’.

curiosity: In Butler’s day this meant ‘inquiringness’, typically serious rather than trivial.

disinterested: In Butler’s day this meant—and when used by literate people it still means—‘not self -interested’.

economy: The economy of a complex thing is the set of facts about the regular interplay amongst its parts.

faculty: This can refer to an ability or to the machinery (as it were) that creates the ability—a vexatious ambiguity. When on pages 20 and 22 Butler says that the ‘faculty’ of conscience is different from certain ‘principles’ (see below) that he has listed, he pretty clearly implies that it is nevertheless a principle. So in that passage, at least, ‘faculty’ refers not to an ability but to whatever creates it.

lead: When Butler says that some aspect of our nature ‘leads us to’ behave in a certain way, he often doesn’t mean that we do behave in that way. Think of ‘leading us to behave virtuously’ as on a par with ‘leading a horse to water’.

movement: On pages 8 and 19 Butler uses this word in its old sense of ‘a mental impulse, an act of the will’ (OED).

occasion: The occasion of an event is something that triggers it, sets it going; but it’s not its real cause. When you and I find that we went in different decades to the same high school, that starts a friendship; but the same-school discovery is just a trigger or release mechanism for a drawing-together that is caused by a principle [see below] deep in our human nature. Thus Butler on page 16.

present: Like many other writers, Butler often uses ‘present’ to mean ‘before the life after death’.

principle: Butler’s 140 uses of this word in the present text all give it a sense, once common but now obsolete, in which ‘principle’ means ‘source’, ‘cause’, ‘energizer’, or the like. (Hume’s Enquiry Concerning the Principles of Morals is, as he explicitly tells us, an enquiry into the sources in human nature of our moral thinking and feeling.) For example, ‘principles of action’ (page 5) means ‘whatever it is in someone’s make-up that cause him to act’.

regards to: Several times on page 27 Butler speaks of our having or lacking ‘regards to’ other people. At first this seems to mean concern for other people’s welfare, happiness, etc.; but a little later it seems also to cover caring about what others think about us. You might care to consider whether Butler is here illegitimately exploiting an ambiguity.

selfish: In Butler’s day this meant merely ‘self-interested’; it didn’t have the extra implication, as it does today, of ‘... with a disregard (or worse) of the interests of others’.

temporal: The present [see above] world was often called ‘temporal’—meaning ‘in time’—because it was thought that our life after death will be ‘eternal’ in some sense that involves not being in time at all.

vice: Morally wrong conduct, not necessarily of the special kind that we reserve ‘vice’ for these days. Similarly vicious.

Five Sermons Joseph Butler Preface

Preface

·OBSCURITY·
It is hardly possible to avoid making some judgment on almost everything that comes into one’s mind; but there’s one sort of judgment that many people—for different reasons—never make on things that come before them; I mean a judgment that would answer the question ‘Is that argument conclusive?’ or ‘Does that opinion hold water?’ These people are entertained by some things and not others; they like some things and dislike others; ·so they are capable of some kinds of discriminations·. But when someone presents them with an •argument for some conclusion or with a •statement on some matter, they don’t ask themselves ‘Is that argument valid?’ or ‘Is that statement true?’, apparently because they regard validity and truth as trivial matters that aren’t worth thinking about. That attitude seems to be pretty general. Arguments are often wanted for some particular short-term purpose; but people in general don’t want proof as something good for themselves—for their own satisfaction of mind, or for their conduct in life. Not to mention the multitudes who read merely for the sake of talking, or to equip themselves for social life, or for some such reason; and of the few who read for the satisfaction of reading, and have a real curiosity [see Glossary] to see •what is said, there are some who—astonishingly—have no sort of curiosity to see •what is true. I say ‘curiosity’, because of the extent to which the religious and sacred attention that is owed to truth and to the question ‘What is the rule of life?’ has disappeared from the human scene. [Why is that a reason for choosing the word ‘curiosity’? Perhaps Butler thinks of ‘curiosity’ about something as the attitude of a researcher, a specialist inquirer, or the like; and the topic he is concerned with here looks like a specialism because so few people engage in it these days. Or perhaps his point is that ‘curiosity’—research—is needed because these are matters on which most people have given up, so that if you want results concerning them you’ll have to dig for them.]....

The great number of books and light magazines of various sorts that daily come to our attention have been one cause of....this idle way of reading and considering things. It’s a way in which even a solitary person can happily get rid of time without the trouble of focused thought. The most idle way of passing time—the least thoughtful way—is reading ·in the way that people read these days·.

Thus people get used to •letting things pass through their minds as distinct from •thinking about them; and this custom leads them to be satisfied with merely •seeing what is said, without •looking into it. They come to find it tiring to re-read and attend, and even to form a judgment; and to present them with anything that requires this is to interfere seriously with their way of life.

There are also people who take for granted—most of them wrongly—that they are acquainted with everything, and that any subject that is treated in the right way will be familiar and easy to them.

....Nothing can be understood without the degree of attention that the very nature of the topic requires. Now morals, •considered as a discipline in which theoretical difficulties come up all the time, and •treated with regard to those difficulties, plainly require a very special ·intensity of· attention. That is because the ideas that are used in thinking about morals are not determinate in themselves; they become determinate through how they are used, especially in reasoning; because it’s impossible for words always to stand

1

Five Sermons Joseph Butler Preface

for the same ideas [= ‘have the same meanings’], even within a single author let alone amongst several different authors. So an argument may be difficult to take in, which is different from its being mistaken; and sometimes a writer’s care to avoid being mistaken makes his argument harder than ever to grasp. It’s not acceptable for a work of imagination or entertainment to be hard to understand, but such difficulty may be unavoidable in a work of another kind, where the writer aims....to state things as he finds them.

I accept that some of the following discourses are very abstruse [see Glossary] and difficult—call them ‘obscure’, if you like. But let me add that the question of whether •this ‘obscurity’ is a fault can only be answered by people who can judge whether or not, and to what extent, •it could have been avoided—i.e. ones who will take the trouble to understand what I say here and to see how far the things I am saying—those things, not some other things!—could have been expressed more plainly. I am not at all saying that they couldn’t.

Regarding general complaints about •obscurity, regarded as distinct from •confusion and •tangles in thought: in some cases there may be a basis for them, but in other cases they may come down to nothing but the complaint that some things can’t be understood as easily as some other things can. Confusion and tangles in writing are indeed inexcusable, because anyone can (if he chooses) know whether he understands and sees through what he is writing; and it is unforgivable for a man to put his thoughts before others when he’s aware that he himself doesn’t know where he is or where he is going with his exposition. Doing that is like walking in the street in a state of disarray that he oughtn’t to be satisfied with even in his own home.

But obscurities are sometimes excusable; and I don’t mean only the ones arising from the abstruseness of the argument. For example, a subject may be treated in a way that assumes the reader to be already acquainted with what ancient and modern writers have said about it, and with the current state of opinion about it in the world. This will create a difficulty of a very special kind, and make the whole thing obscure, for those who are not thus informed; but those who are will be disposed to excuse this and similar ways of writing, as a way of saving their time.

[Butler says that the title ‘Sermons’ could lead readers to expect easy going, and he isn’t going to provide it. But he won’t spring to his own defence about this, and will simply say that he is offering this second edition of the Sermons because there was a demand for it. Rounding out this second-edition bit of the Preface, he adds:] The reader may think I have made amends to him by the following illustrations of what seemed most to require them, but whether he will is not something I can fairly judge.

·WHAT I PLAN TO DO IN THE FIRST THREE SERMONS·
There are two ways of treating the subject of morals. (1) One starts by inquiring into the abstract relations of things; (2) the other starts from a matter of fact, namely: what the particular nature of man is, its various parts, and how they are assembled and work together, from whence it proceeds to consider what course of life corresponds to this whole nature. In (1) the conclusion is expressed thus:

vice is contrary to the nature and reasons of things;

in (2) it is expressed as:

vice is a violation, or breaking in upon, our own nature.

Thus they both lead [see Glossary] us to the same thing, namely our obligation to behave virtuously; and thus they enormously strengthen and reinforce each other. (1) seems

2

Five Sermons Joseph Butler Preface

to be the more direct formal proof, and in some ways the less open to nit-picking disputes; (2) is especially apt to satisfy a fair mind, and is more easily applicable to various concrete relations and circumstances.

The following discourses are •mainly done in the manner of (2)—the first three •wholly in that way. I wrote them intending to explain

what the phrase ‘the nature of man’ means in the assertion that virtue consists in following the nature of man, and vice [see Glossary] consists in deviating from it;

and by explaining this to show that the assertion is true. The works of the ancient moralists show that they had some sort of inward feeling that they chose to express by saying:

•man is born to virtue,

•virtue consists in following nature, and

•vice is more contrary to this nature than tortures or death.

Now, if you find no mystery in this way of speaking that the ancients had; if without being very explicit with yourself about what you were doing you kept to •your natural feelings, went along with •them, and found yourself fully convinced that what the ancients said was just and true; you’ll probably wonder what the point is, in the second and third sermons, in labouring away at something that you have never had any difficulty with.... But it needn’t be thought strange that this way of talking—though familiar with the ancients and not uncommon (though usually in milder forms) among ourselves—should need to be explained. Many things that we commonly feel and talk about in everyday life are not very easy to explain, isolate, and identify. All the books that have been written about the passions are a proof of this; the writers who have undertaken to •lay bare the many complexities of the passions and •trace them back to their sources ·in the human mind and body· wouldn’t have taken this trouble if they had thought that what they were trying to show was obvious to everyone who felt and talked about those passions. Thus, though there seems no ground to doubt that people in general have the inward perception that the ancient moralists so often expressed in that way (any more than to doubt that people have the passions ·that books have been written about·), I thought it would be useful if I were to unfold that inward conviction ·about nature· and lay it open more explicitly than I had seen done; especially given that some people have expressed themselves as dissatisfied with it ·altogether·, clearly because they misunderstood it. [He cites William Wollaston, whose rejection of the virtue/nature way of talking as ‘loose’ and unacceptable was based. Butler says, on his taking ‘acting in accordance with your nature’ to mean something like ‘acting on whatever part of your nature happens to be pushing you at any given moment’.]

·THE IDEA OF SYSTEM·
Anyone who thinks it worthwhile to consider this matter thoroughly should begin by stating to himself exactly the idea of a •system, •economy [see Glossary], or •constitution of any particular nature (or any particular anything); and I think he will find this:

A system or economy or constitution is a whole made up of many parts; but those parts, even when considered as a whole, are not all there is to the idea of system etc. unless we take the notion of a whole to include the relations that the parts have to one another.

Each work of nature and each work of art is a system; and because every particular thing, whether natural or artificial, is for some use or purpose beyond itself, we could amplify the above account of the idea of system by adding the thing’s

3

Five Sermons Joseph Butler Preface

being conducive to one or more ends ·or purposes·. Take the example of a watch. If a watch is taken to pieces, and the pieces laid out in a row, someone who has a very exact notion of these parts of the watch still won’t have anything like the idea of the watch unless he brings into his thought the parts’ relations with one another. But if

he sees or thinks of those parts as put together, not in a jumble but in the right way for a watch;

and if also

he forms a notion of the relations those parts have to one other so that they all contribute to the purpose of telling the time;

then he has the idea of a watch. That’s how it is with regard to the inward frame—·the system or economy or constitution·—of man. Appetites, passions, affections [see Glossary], and the principle [see Glossary] of reflection, considered merely as the various parts of our inner nature, don’t give us any idea of the system or constitution of this nature, because the constitution also involves the relations that these different parts have to each other. The most important of these relations is that of •reflection or conscience to •everything else—the relation being that of ‘... has authority over...’. It’s from considering the relations that the various appetites and passions in the inward frame have to each other, and above all from considering the supremacy of reflection or conscience, that we get the idea of the system or constitution of human nature. And this idea will make it clear to us that this nature of ours, i.e. our constitution, is adapted to virtue, just as the idea of a watch shows that its nature, i.e. constitution or system, is adapted to the measuring of time. A watch may go out of order and fail to tell the time accurately, but that’s irrelevant to my present topic. Anything made by man is apt to go out of order; but when that happens it isn’t an expression of the thing’s system; rather, it conflicts with the system and if it goes far enough it will totally destroy it. All I’m doing here is to explain what an economy, system, or constitution is. And up to here the watch and the man are perfectly parallel. There is indeed a difference further down the line; though irrelevant to my present topic, it’s too important to be omitted: a machine is inanimate and •passive, but we are •active. We are in charge of our constitution, and are therefore accountable for any disorder or violation of it. Thus nothing can possibly be more contrary to nature than vice; meaning by ‘nature’ not only the various parts of our internal frame but also its constitution. Poverty and disgrace, torture and death, are not as contrary to our constitution as vice is. There are some parts of our nature which, taken singly, are in conflict with misery and injustice equally; but injustice is also contrary to the whole constitution of the nature.

You may ask: ‘Is this constitution really what those philosophers meant ·who connected •virtue with •nature·? Would they have explained themselves in this way?’ My answer is the same as the one I would give if you asked ‘Would someone who has often used the word “resentment”, and often felt resentment, explain this passion in exactly the way you do in the eighth of these sermons?’ Just as I am sure that what I have given is a true account of the passion which that person referred to and intended to express by the word ‘resentment’, so also I am sure that I have given the true account of the facts that led those philosophers to have the belief that they expressed by saying that vice is contrary to nature. Mightn’t they have meant merely that vice is contrary to the higher and better part of our nature? Well, even this implies a constitution such as I have tried to explain. The very terms ‘higher’ and ‘better’ imply a relation of parts to each other; and these related parts of a single nature form a constitution.... The philosophers had a

4

Five Sermons Joseph Butler Preface

perception (i) that injustice was contrary to their nature, and (ii) that pain was too. They saw that these two perceptions are totally different, not merely in degree but in kind. And by reflecting on each of them, as they thus stood in their nature, they came to a full intuitive conviction that more was due....to (i) than to (ii); that (i) demanded in all cases to govern such a creature as man. So what I have given is a fair and true account of the basis for their conviction, i.e. of what they intended to express when they said that virtue consists in following nature—this being a formulation that isn’t loose and indeterminate, but clear and distinct, strictly just and true.

·THE AUTHORITY OF REFLECTION OR CONSCIENCE·
I’m convinced that the force of this conviction is felt by almost everyone; but considered as an argument and put into words it seems rather abstruse, and the connection of it is broken in the first three of the following sermons; so it may be worthwhile for me to give the reader the whole argument here in a single sweep.

Mankind has various instincts and principles of action, as have the lower animals; some leading directly and immediately to the good of the community, and some directly to private good.

Man has several that the lower animals don’t—especially reflection or conscience, an approval of some principles or actions and disapproval of others.

The lower animals obey their instincts or principles of action, according to certain rules; suppose [=? ‘taking for granted’] the constitution of their body, and the objects around them.

Most human beings also obey their instincts and principles, all of them, the propensities we call ‘good’ as well as the bad, in ways that are governed by the constitution of their body and their external circumstances ·at the time of acting·. So it isn’t true that mankind are wholly governed by •self-love, •the love of power and •sensual appetites. It’s true that they are often driven by these, without any regard for right or wrong; but it’s an obvious fact that those same persons—the general run of human beings—are frequently influenced by friendship, compassion, gratitude; and even their general hatred of what is base and liking for what is fair and just takes its turn among the other motives for action. This is the partial, inadequate notion of human nature that is discussed in the first sermon; and it is by this nature, so to speak, that the world is influenced and kept in tolerable order.

Lower animals, in acting according to their bodily constitution and circumstances, act suitably to their whole nature. Why do I say ‘their whole nature’? Not simply because these animals act in ways that fit their nature, because that doesn’t settle whether their ways of behaving correspond to their whole nature. Still, they clearly act inconformity with something in their nature, and we can’t find empirical evidence for there being anything else in their nature that requires a different rule or course of action. That’s why I said ‘their whole nature’....

But what I have presented is not a complete account of man’s nature. Something further must be brought in to give us an adequate notion of it, namely this fact:

One of those principles of action, namely conscience or reflection, when set alongside the rest as they all stand together in the nature of man, clearly has on it marks of authority over all the rest; it claims the absolute direction of them all, to allow or forbid their gratification.

That is because a •disapproval of reflection is in itself a principle manifestly superior to a mere •propensity. And the conclusion is that this way of behaving—

5

Five Sermons Joseph Butler Preface

Allow to this superior principle or part of our nature no more than we grant to other parts; let it like all the others govern and guide us only occasionally, when its turn happens to come around, from the mood and circumstances one happens to be in

—is not acting in conformity with the constitution of man. No human creature can be said to act in conformity with his constitution or nature unless he gives that superior principle the absolute authority that is due to it. This conclusion is abundantly confirmed by the following fact: One can determine what course of action the economy of man’s nature requires, without so much as knowing how strongly the various principles prevail, or which of them actually have the greatest influence.

The practical reason for insisting so much upon this natural authority of the principle of reflection or conscience is that it seems to be largely overlooked by many people who are by no means the worst sort of men. They think that ·for virtue· it’s sufficient to abstain from gross wickedness, and to be humane and kind to such people as happen to cross one’s path. Whereas really the very constitution of our nature requires us to •bring our whole conduct before this superior faculty, ·this reflection or conscience·, to •wait for its decision, to •enforce its authority upon ourselves, and to •make it the business of our lives—as it is absolutely the whole business of a moral agent—to conform ourselves to it. This is the true meaning of the ancient precept Reverence yourself.

Lord Shaftesbury’s Inquiry concerning Virtue has what seems to be a substantial defect or omission, namely: it doesn’t take into consideration this authority that is implied in the idea of reflex approval or disapproval. He has shown conclusively that virtue is naturally the way to happiness, and vice [see Glossary] to misery, for a creature such as man when placed in the circumstances that we have in this world. But suppose there’s a particular state of affairs in which virtue doesn’t lead to happiness; Shaftesbury was unwilling to consider such cases, but surely they ought to be considered. There’s another ·awkward· case that he does discuss and give an answer to, namely the case of a sceptic who isn’t convinced of this happy tendency of virtue.... Shaftesbury’s reply to this is there would be no remedy for it! One may say more explicitly that such a sceptic, leaving out the authority of reflex approval or disapproval, would be under an obligation to act viciously; because one’s own happiness is an obvious obligation, and there is supposed to be no other obligation in the case. ·You might say·: ‘But does bringing in the natural authority of reflection help much? There would indeed be an obligation to virtue, but wouldn’t the obligation from supposed interest on the side of vice still remain?’ I reply that being under two contrary obligations—i.e. being under none—would not be exactly the same as being under a formal obligation to be vicious, or being in circumstances where the constitution of man’s nature plainly requires that vice should be preferred. But the obligation on the side of interest really doesn’t ‘still remain’. Why not? Because the natural authority of the principle of reflection is a near and intimate obligation, the most certain and best known, whereas the contrary obligation can’t seem more than probable, at most. No man can be sure in any circumstances that vice is his interest in the present world, much less can he be certain that it is in his interest in another world, ·the world of life after death·. So the certain obligation would entirely outrank and destroy the uncertain one, though the latter would otherwise have had real force.

Taking in this consideration totally changes the whole state of the case. It shows something that Shaftesbury doesn’t seem to have been aware of, namely that the highest

6

Five Sermons Joseph Butler Preface

degree of scepticism that he thought possible will still leave men—whatever their opinion may be—under the strictest moral obligation concerning the happiness of virtue. He rightly thought it to be a plain matter of fact that mankind, upon reflection, feels an approval of what is good and a disapproval of the contrary; no-one could deny this, except as an exercise in showing off. So if you take in the authority and obligation that is a constituent part of this reflex approval, ·you’ll see that· it undeniably follows that even if a man doubts everything else, he will still remain under the nearest and most certain obligation to act virtuously—an obligation implied in the very idea of virtue, in the very idea of reflex approval. [This is the first explicit mention in these sermons of the idea of virtue.]

[This paragraph expands what Butler wrote in ways that the ·small dots· convention can’t easily indicate. But the content is all his.] And however little influence this obligation alone can be expected to have on mankind, one can appeal merely to ·self·-interest and self-love, and ask a question for which I must first set the scene. On the one hand we have

the fact that because of man’s nature, his condition, and the brevity of his life, very little can possibly be gained by vice.

On the other we have

the fact that the call to virtue is the most intimate of all obligations—one that a man can’t defy without condemning himself and, unless he has corrupted his nature, disliking himself.

The question: Forgoing the tiny possible gain-from-vice so as to be on good terms with the call-to-virtue—is that such an enormous sacrifice? This question would have a bite even if the prospect of a future life were ever so uncertain.

·PUNISHMENT·
Thus, man is by his very nature a law unto himself; and this thesis, pursued to its just consequences, is of the utmost importance. Something that follows from it is this:

Even if a man—through stupidity, or theoretical scepticism—doesn’t know or doesn’t believe that there is any authority in the universe to punish the violation of this law; if there actually is such an authority, he is as liable to punishment as he would have been if he had been convinced in advance that such punishment would follow.

Whatever we understand justice to be—even if we presumptuously claim that the purpose of divine punishment is just the same as that of civil punishment, namely to prevent future wrong behaviour—it would still be the case that an offender wouldn’t be spared punishment if he didn’t know or didn’t believe that there would be punishment. Even on this system of justice, wrong behaviour wouldn’t at all be exempt from punishment if the offender didn’t know or didn’t believe that he was risking punishment; because what makes us regard conduct as punishable is not the person’s foreknowledge of the punishment, but merely his action’s violating a known obligation.

This is the place to take up an obvious error, or mistake, by Shaftesbury (unless he expressed himself so carelessly as to be misunderstood). He writes that ‘it is malice only, and not goodness, that can make us afraid’. Actually, goodness is the natural and proper object of the greatest fear to a man who has acted wrongly. Malice may be appeased or satisfied; mood may change; but goodness is a fixed, steady, immovable principle of action. If malice or mood holds the sword of justice, there’s clearly a basis for the greatest of

7

Five Sermons Joseph Butler Preface

crimes to hope for impunity. But if it is goodness, there can be no possible hope when the reason of things or the purposes of government call for punishment. Thus, everyone sees how much greater chance of impunity a bad man has in an administration where there is favouritism and corruption, than in a just and upright one....

[Butler says nothing in this Preface about sermon 4 (on loose talk) or sermons 5 and 6 (compassion) or 15 (human ignorance). But starting at the point we have now reached, he comments briefly on 7 (a puzzle about the book of Numbers) and 10 (self-deception); then on 8 (resentment) and 9 (forgiveness). The Preface ends with a paragraph relating to 13 and 14 (piety), followed by a disclaimer, saying that no special principle was at work in the selection of topics for this collection of sermons. Before coming to those final bits, Butler discusses self-love, relating this to sermon 11 though it equally concerns sermon 12.]

·WHAT I PLAN TO DO IN THE REMAINING TWO SERMONS·
The main purpose of the eleventh sermon is to set out the notions of •self-love and •disinterestedness [see Glossary], in order to show that benevolence is not more unfriendly to self-love than it is to any other particular affection. Many people make a show of explaining away all particular affections, representing the whole of life as nothing but one continuous exercise of self-love. This gives rise to a trouble-making confusion in the ancient Epicureans, in Hobbes, in La Rochefoucauld, and in other writers of this type. I’m referring to the confusion of labelling as ‘·self·-interested’ actions that are performed in contradiction to the most manifest known interest, merely for the gratification of a present passion.^1 Now, all this confusion could easily have been avoided by getting clear about what the general idea of (i) self-love is, as distinct from all particular movements [see Glossary] towards particular external objects—I mean (ii) the appetites of sense, resentment, compassion, curiosity, ambition, and the rest. When this is done, if the words ‘selfish’ [see Glossary] and ·‘self·-interested’ can’t be parted with but must be applied to everything, the total confusion of all language could still be avoided by the use of adjectives to distinguish (i) ‘cool’ or ‘settled’ selfishness from (ii) ‘passionate’ or ‘sensual’ selfishness. But the most natural way of speaking plainly is to restrict ‘self-love’ to (i) and restrict ·‘self·-interested’ to the actions that come from it; and to say of (ii) that they don’t involve love to ourselves but rather movements towards something outside ourselves—honour, power, harm to someone else, good to someone else. The pursuit of these external objects could come from self-love; but when it comes instead from one of these other movements it isn’t ·self·-interested except in a trivial sense in which every action of every creature must be ·self-interested·, merely because no-one can act on anything but a desire or choice or preference of his own.

Self-love can be combined with any particular passion, and this complication very often makes it impossible to determine precisely how far an action—even an action of one’s own—has for its principle general self-love, and how far some particular passion. But this needn’t create any confusion in the ideas of self-love and particular passions. We clearly see what one is and what the others are, though

^1 From Cicero’s first book, De Finibus, you can see how surprisingly the Epicureans made this mistake: explaining the desire for •praise and for •being beloved as upshots of the desire for •safety, and equating concern for our •country, even in the most virtuous character, with concern for •ourselves. La Rochefoucauld says ‘Curiosity comes from ·self·-interest or from pride’, and no doubt he would have explained the pride in terms of self-love; as though there were no such human passions as the desire for esteem, for being beloved, or for knowledge! Hobbes’s account of the affections of good-will and pity are instances of the same kind.

8

Five Sermons Joseph Butler Preface

we may be unsure how far one or the other influences us. Because of this uncertainty, there are bound to be different opinions concerning the extent to which mankind is governed by ·self·-interest; and there will be actions that some will ascribe to self-love and others will ascribe to particular passions. But it’s absurd to say that mankind are wholly actuated by either, because obviously both have their influence....

Besides, the very idea of a ·self·-interested pursuit necessarily presupposes particular passions or appetites, because the very idea of someone’s interests, or his happiness, consists in his having an appetite or affection that enjoys its object, ·i.e. is satisfied·. It’s not because we love ourselves that we find delight in such-and-such objects, but because we have particular affections towards them. If you take away these affections you leave self-love with nothing to work on—no end or goal for it to aim at except the avoidance of pain....

An important observation:

Benevolence is no more disinterested than any of the common particular passions.

This is worth noting in itself, but I emphasize it here as a protection against the scorn that one sees rising in the faces of people—ones who are said to ‘know the world’—when someone describes an action as disinterested, generous, or public-spirited. The truth of The Observation (·as I shall call it·) can be shown in a more formal way: consider all the possible relations that any particular affection can have to self-love and private ·self·-interest, and I think you will see demonstrably [Butler’s phrase] that benevolence is not in any respect more at variance with self-love than it is with any other particular affection....

If The Observation is true, it follows that •self-love and •benevolence are not opposed but only different. Similarly with •virtue and •·self·-interest. It’s the same with •virtue and •any other particular affection (e.g. love of the arts)—not opposed, only different. Everything is what it is, and not another thing. An action’s goodness or badness doesn’t come from

its being describable as ‘disinterested ‘or ·‘self·-interested’,

any more than from its being describable as ‘inquisitive’ or ‘jealous’ or whatever. Nor does it come from

its being accompanied by present or future pleasure or pain.

The action’s moral quality comes from its being what it is; that is, its being or not being appropriate for a creature like us, its being or not being what the state of the case requires. So we can judge and determine that an action is morally good or bad before giving the least thought to whether it was ·self·-interested or disinterested.... Self-love, in its proper degree, is as just and morally good as any affection whatever. Benevolence towards particular persons may be ·due· to a degree of weakness, and so be blameworthy. As for disinterestedness being in itself commendable: we can’t even imagine anything more depraved than disinterested cruelty.

Would it be better if self-love were weaker in people in general? There seems to be no reason to think so. Such influence as self-love has seems clearly to come from its being constant and habitual (which it is bound to be), and not to how intense or strong it is. ·In fact it isn’t strong·. Every whim of the imagination, every curiosity of the understanding, every affection of the heart, shows self-love’s weakness by prevailing over it. Men daily, hourly, sacrifice their greatest known interest to fancy, inquisitiveness, love, or hatred, any vagrant inclination. The thing to be lamented is not that

9

Five Sermons Joseph Butler Preface

men have so much regard for their own good or ·self·-interest in the present world,

for they don’t have enough; it is that

men they have so little regard for the good of others.

And why are they like that? It is because they are so much engaged in gratifying particular passions that •are unfriendly to benevolence and •happen to be most prevalent in them, much more than because of self-love. For a proof of this, consider:

There is no character more void of friendship, gratitude, natural affection, love of country and of common justice—no character more equally and uniformly hard-hearted—than that of someone who is abandoned in the so-called ‘way of pleasure’.

Such people are hard-hearted and totally without feelings on behalf of others; except when they can’t escape the sight of distress, and so are interrupted by it in their pleasures. But it’s ridiculous to call such an abandoned course of pleasure ·self·-interested; the person engaged in it •knows beforehand that it will be as ruinous to himself as to those who depend upon him, and conducts his life of ‘pleasure’ under a cloud created by his anxious sense of disaster ahead. [That last clause changes Butler’s words quite a lot.]

[Notice that in this next paragraph Butler speaks of happiness ‘in this life’ and of people’s ‘temporal [see Glossary] good’, explicitly leaving the after-life and divine rewards and punishments out of it.] If •people in general were to develop within themselves the principle of self-love; if •they were to develop the habit of sitting down to consider what was the greatest happiness they could attain for themselves in this life; and if •their self-love were strong and steady enough to keep them in pursuit of their supposed chief temporal good, not being side-tracked by any particular passion, this would obviously prevent countless follies and vices. This was in a great measure the Epicurean system of philosophy. It is far from being the religious—or even the moral—institution of life. Yet even with all the mistakes men would make regarding their interests, it would still be less damaging than the extravagances of mere appetite, will, and pleasure....

10

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 1: The Social Nature of Man

1: The Social Nature of Man

[Butler prefaces this sermon with a short passage from Paul’s letter to the Romans, in which something is said about Christians being ‘one body in Christ’ and ‘members one of another’. He contrasts •what that passage meant to the early Christians to whom it was addressed with •how it should be understood at the time when Butler was writing; and says that this contrast gives him a reason for treating the passage ‘in a more general way’ than its original recipients would have done. He takes it that he is confronted with a comparison between these two:

(1) the relation that the various parts or members of a natural body have to each other and to the whole body;

(2) the relation that each particular person in society has to other particular persons, and to the whole society

This isn’t a very good comparison he says, if the ‘body’ is thought of as not having a mind and thus as ‘a dead inactive thing’. He proposes then to replace that contrast by this one (the second item is unchanged):

(1) the relation that the various internal principles [see Glossary] in human nature have to ·each other and to· the whole nature of man;

(2) the relation that each particular person in society has to other particular persons, and to the whole society.

Butler gives a weak or obscure reason why ‘it cannot be thought an unallowable liberty’ to interpret what Paul wrote in this way. And then, with the tiresome Pauline distraction cleared away, the real business can begin.]

We are going to compare •the nature of man as an individual, aiming at his own private good, his own preservation and happiness with •the nature of man as a social being, aiming at public good, the happiness of that society. These goals do indeed perfectly coincide; aiming at public good and aiming at private good are so far from being inconsistent that they support one another. But in the following discussion they’ll have to be considered as entirely distinct from one another, otherwise we can’t compare the nature of man as tending to one with his nature as tending to the other. You can’t compare two things unless they really are two.

From my review of, and comparison between, these two aspects of the nature of man it will plainly appear that the indications in human nature that

(2) we were made for society and to do good to our fellow-creatures

are as real as the indications that

(1) we were intended to take care of our own life, health, and private good;

that the two sets of indications are very similar to one another; and that any objections that one of those two assertions is open to bear in the same way against the other. [A] There is a natural principle of benevolence... [At this point Butler has the key to a long footnote which is presented now as main text, ending on page 13.]

·THE START OF FIRST FOOTNOTE·
Suppose a learned man is writing a sober book about human nature, and shows in many parts of it that he has an insight into this topic. Among the things he has to give an account of is the appearance in men of •benevolence or •good-will towards each other when they are naturally related ·as father and son, brother and brother, etc.· or socially related in various ways. Not wanting to be taken in by outward show, our learned man digs down into himself to discover

11

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 1: The Social Nature of Man

what exactly it is in the mind of man that produces this appearance; and after deep reflection he announces that the principle [see Glossary] in the mind that does this work is only the love of power and delight in the exercise of it. [Butler has a note here, telling us that his target is Hobbes.] Wouldn’t everyone think he has mistaken one word for another? That this philosopher was surveying and explaining some other human actions, some other behaviour of man to man? Could anyone be thoroughly convinced that he really was talking about what is commonly called ‘benevolence’ or ‘good-will’ except by discovering that this learned person has a general hypothesis that can’t be made to square with the appearance of good-will except in this way? What has this appearance is often nothing but ambition, and the delight in superiority is often—or ·for purposes of argument· let’s suppose always—mixed in with benevolence; but these facts don’t make it right to say that benevolence is ambition; it’s •superficially more plausible to say this than to say that benevolence is (say) hunger, but it’s no more •right. Isn’t there often the appearance of one man’s wanting another to have some good that he himself can’t get for him, and rejoicing when it comes to him through some third person? Can love of power possibly explain this desire or this delight? Isn’t there often the appearance of someone’s distinguishing between two or more others and preferring to do good for one rather than the other(s), in cases where love of power can’t at all explain this distinction and this preference?.... And another point: Suppose that good-will in the mind of man is nothing but delight in the exercise of power: then men will be disposed to engage in and delight in wicked behaviour as an exercise and proof of power. (In particular cases they may be deterred by thoughts about bad consequences for them that could follow from such behaviour; but that depends on particular matters of fact, and on ‘the long run’; it is easy to suppose cases where nothing like that applies; and those are the ones I am talking about.) And this disposition and delight would arise from....the same principle in the mind as a disposition to and delight in charity. Thus cruelty, as distinct from envy and resentment, would be exactly the same as good-will in the mind of man; the fact that one tends to the happiness of our fellow-creatures and their other to the misery is, according to this theory, merely an accidental circumstance that the mind pays no attention to. These are the absurdities that even able men run into when something causes them to belie •their nature and perversely disclaim the image of God that was originally stamped on •it and is still plainly discernible upon the mind of man, even if only faintly.

The question is not about how •intensely benevolent people are, or about how •widely their benevolence extends; it is just about whether this affection [see Glossary] •exists at all. Suppose someone does seriously doubt whether there is any such thing as good-will in one man towards another. Well, whether man is or isn’t constituted like that is a mere question of fact or natural history, not provable immediately by reason. So the question has to be considered and answered in the same way as other ·questions of· fact or natural history are, namely

(a) by appealing to the •external senses or •inward perceptions,

(b) by arguing from acknowledged facts and actions, and

(c) by the testimony of mankind.

(A note on (a): whether it’s external senses or inward perception depends, of course, on what the particular question is about. A note on (b): When we have studied many actions of the same kind, in different circumstances and directed to different objects, we are in a position to draw certainly true conclusions about what principles they don’t come from,

12

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 1: The Social Nature of Man

and very probable conclusions about what principles they do come from.) Now, that there is some degree of benevolence in men can be as strongly and plainly shown in all these ways as it could possibly be shown.... Suppose someone claimed that

resentment in the mind of man is absolutely nothing but reasonable concern for our own safety,

how would we show him to be wrong? How would we show what the real nature of that passion is? In just the same way as, when someone claims that

there is no such a thing as real good-will in man towards man,

we can show him to be wrong. ·For us to have benevolence·, all that’s needed is for the seeds of it to implanted in our nature by God. There’s much left for us to do upon our own heart and temperament—to cultivate, improve, and call forth our principle of benevolence, and to exercise it in a steady uniform manner. This is our work: this is virtue and religion.
·END OF FIRST FOOTNOTE·

[A] There is a natural principle [see Glossary] of benevolence in man, which to some extent relates to society in the way that self-love relates to the individual. And if there is in mankind

•any disposition to friendship,

•any such thing as compassion (which is momentary love),

•any such thing as paternal or filial affection,

•any affection aiming at the good of someone else,

all this is benevolence, or the love of another. It may be brief, or of low intensity, or narrow in its range; but it still proves the assertion ·that there is such a thing as benevolence in man·, and indicates what we were designed for just as really as that would be indicated by a much more intense and wide-ranging benevolence. I must remind you, however, that although benevolence and self-love are different—although the former tends most directly to public good, and the latter to private good—yet they coincide so perfectly that •the greatest satisfactions to ourselves depend on our having an appropriate degree of benevolence, and that self-love is one chief security [Butler’s phrase] of our right behaviour towards society. It may be added that their coinciding so that we can hardly promote one without the other is equally a proof that we were made ·not just for benevolence, but· for both.

[B] This conclusion is confirmed by the fact that the various passions and affections that are distinct... [At this point Butler has the key to a longish footnote which is presented now as main text.]

·START OF SECOND FOOTNOTE·
Everybody distinguishes self-love from the various particular passions, appetites, and affections; and yet the distinction is often lost sight of. That they are totally different will be seen by anyone who distinguishes •the passions and appetites themselves from •attempts to satisfy them. Consider the appetite of hunger, and the desire for esteem (·which is a passion·); because each of these can lead to pleasure and to pain, the coolest self-love may set us to work doing what needs to be done to obtain that pleasure and avoid that pain; and so of course can the appetites and passions themselves. [At this point Butler gets himself side-tracked into laboriously distinguishing self-love from •‘the feelings themselves, the pain of hunger and shame, and the delight from esteem’. What he had set out to do was to distinguish self-love (which can be ‘cool’) from •appetites and passions such as hunger and the desire for esteem (which presumably are never ‘cool’ in that way). Then he gets back on track:] Just as self-love is totally different from the various particular passions and appetites, so also some of the actions coming from self-love are totally different from actions coming from the particular passions. To see that this is obviously so, consider these

13

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 1: The Social Nature of Man

two perfectly possible cases. (a) One man rushes to certain ruin in order to satisfy a present desire; nobody would call the principle of this action ‘self-love’. (b) Another man goes through some laborious work for which he has been promised a great reward, though he has no clear knowledge of what the reward will be; this course of action can’t be ascribed to any particular passion. The behaviour in (a) is obviously to be attributed to some particular passion or affection, while the behaviour in (b) equally obviously comes from the general affection or principle of self-love. The two principles are frequently mixed together, and run into each other, which is why we can’t always tell to what extent some particular pursuit or actions comes from self-love. I shall return to this in the eleventh sermon.
·END OF SECOND FOOTNOTE·

[B] This conclusion is confirmed by the fact that the various passions and affections that are distinct from benevolence and self-love also lead [see Glossary] us tend to further public good as really as they do private good. We could explore in detail the various passions or appetites other than benevolence whose primary use and intention is the security and good of society; and the various passions distinct from self-love, whose primary intention and design is the security and good of the individual. But it might be thought that this would take too long and get us into too much nit-picking detail. [Butler has a footnote here in which he undertakes to do this job for a single case, returning to the pair •hunger and •desire for esteem. They are in fact a bad pair for this purpose, and Butler’s treatment of them here is confusing and apparently confused; we are better off without it. His main text continues:] For present purposes it is enough that

•the desire for esteem from others,

•contempt for others,

•esteem for others,

•love of society (not a desire for the good of it), and

•indignation against successful vice,

are •public affections or passions, have an immediate bearing on others, and naturally lead us to behave in ways that will be helpful to our fellow-creatures. If any or all of these can be considered also as •private affections, as tending to private good, this doesn’t block them from being •public affections too, or destroy their good influence on society or their tendency to public good. And then there’s this point: just as someone who had no belief in the desirableness of life will still be led to preserve his own life merely from the appetite of hunger, so also someone acting merely in the pursuit of reputation, with no thought of the good of others, may well contribute to public good. In both cases they are clearly instruments in the hands of God, to carry out states of affairs—the preservation of the individual and the good of society—which they themselves don’t intend or have in view. The bottom line is this: Men have various appetites, passions, and particular affections that are quite distinct both from self-love and from benevolence; all of these have a tendency to promote both public and private good, and can be considered as relating to others and to ourselves equally; but some of them seem most immediately to concern others, i.e. tend to public good; while others most immediately concern oneself, i.e. tend to private good. The former are not benevolence, and the latter are not self-love: neither sort come from our love for ourselves or for others; both come from our Maker’s care and love both for the individual and for the ·human· species; and they show that he intended us to be instruments of good to each other, as well as that we should be instruments of good to ourselves.

[C] There is a principle of reflection in men that leads them to distinguish between, approve, and disapprove their own actions. We are obviously constituted in such a way that we

14

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 1: The Social Nature of Man

reflect upon our own nature. The mind can take a view of what happens within itself,

•its propensities, aversions, passions and affections,

•the goals they aim at,

•their varying degrees of intensity, and

•the various actions they give rise to.

In this survey it approves of one, disapproves of another, and towards a third is affected in neither of these ways, but is quite indifferent. This principle by which man approves or disapproves his heart, temperament, and action is conscience.... This faculty [see Glossary] tends to restrain men from harming one another, and leads them to do good—all that is too obvious to need special emphasis, ·but here’s an example of it, all the same·. A parent has the affection of love for his children, which leads him to take care of them, to educate and make due provision for them. His natural affection leads to this; but his •reflection that this is his proper business, that it’s up to him, that acting like this is right and commendable, when added to the •affection, becomes a much more settled principle, and carries him on through more labour and difficulties for the sake of his children than he would go through purely from that affection without support from his conscience.... It is impossible to do something good and not approve of it; but don’t think (as some do) that •doing x is the same as •approving of the doing of x: men often approve of actions by others that they wouldn’t imitate, and do things that they don’t approve of. ·So approval stands on its own feet, so to speak·: it can’t possibly be denied that there is this principle of reflection or conscience in human nature. Consider this case:

(1) A man gives help to an innocent person y who is in distress. (2) On a later occasion, the same man in a fury of anger does great harm to a person who has given no just cause of offence, and who is indeed a former friend who has been good to him. Now our man coolly thinks back on these two actions of his, thinking about them in themselves, without regard to their consequences for himself.

Is anyone going to say that any common man would have the same attitude towards these two actions? that he wouldn’t draw any line between them but would approve of both or disapprove of both? Of course not! That is too glaring a falsity to need to be confuted. So there is this principle of reflection or conscience in mankind. We needn’t compare its relation to •private good with its relation to •public good, because it obviously has as much to do with •the latter as with •the former—and is often thought to have more. I mention this faculty here merely •as another part of man’s inner frame, giving us some indication of what we are intended for, and •as something that will naturally and as a matter of course have some influence. The particular place assigned to it by nature, what authority it has, and how much influence it ought to have, are questions to be considered later.

From this comparison of benevolence and self-love—our public and private affections—of the courses of life they lead to, and of the bearing of the principle of reflection or conscience on each of them, it’s as obvious •that we were made for society and to promote its happiness as it is •that we were intended to take care of our own life, health, and private good.

This whole survey yields a picture of human nature different from the one we are often presented with. Human beings are by nature so closely united, there’s such a correspondence between one man’s inward sensations and those of another, that

•disgrace is avoided as much as bodily pain is,

•being esteemed and loved by others is desired as much as any external goods are, and

15

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 1: The Social Nature of Man

•people are often led to do good to others as something they simply want to do and find enjoyable and satisfying.

There is such a natural principle of attraction in man towards man that two men may be drawn together as close acquaintances by the slightest of bonds—e.g. their having years earlier walked the same tract of land, breathed in the same climate, merely been born in the same artificial district. [Because divisions into districts are ‘artificial’, a same-district relation is artificial, not natural; that is what Butler is getting at in the next sentence when he calls the relation ‘merely nominal’—not an accurate use of ‘nominal’.] Thus, merely nominal relations are sought and invented, not by governors but by the lowest of the people, and serve to hold mankind together in little fraternities and co-partnerships. They are weak ties indeed, and they would seem merely ridiculous if they were regarded as the real principles [see Glossary] of the union ·of the fraternities etc.·. But it would be absurd to credit them with that role. They are really just the occasions [see Glossary]—as anything can be the occasion of anything—upon which our nature carries us on according to its own previous bent and bias [Butler’s good phrase]. These occasions would be nothing at all if there weren’t this prior disposition and bias of ·human· nature. [Butler goes on to say, in a difficult sentence, something amounting to the following. Men are so strongly united with one another that one person may share another’s feelings—all sorts of feelings—being led to this by the ‘social nature’ that all humans have, with triggers or ‘occasions’ involving natural relations, acquaintance, protection, dependence; ‘each of these being distinct cements of society’. He continues:] Thus, to have no....regard for others in our behaviour is the factual error of considering ourselves as single and independent, as having nothing in our nature relating us to our fellow-creatures.... This is on a par with the absurdity of thinking that a hand has no natural relation to any other part of the body.

You may grant all this but then ask:

Doesn’t man have dispositions and principles within him that lead him to do evil to others, as well as the good he does? What other source can there be for the many miseries that men inflict on each other?

These questions, as far as they relate to what I have been saying, can be answered with another pair of questions:

Doesn’t man also have dispositions and principles within him that lead him to do evil to himself, as well as the good he does? What other source can there be for the many miseries—sickness, pain, and death—that men inflict upon themselves?

You may think that one of these questions is easier to answer than the other, but the answer to both is really the same. It is that human beings have ungoverned passions that they will gratify, come what may, harming others or damaging their own private ·self·-interest. But there’s no such thing as self-hatred, nor any such thing as ill-will in one man towards another, unless emulation or resentment comes into the picture; whereas there is clearly benevolence or good-will. There’s no such thing as love of injustice, oppression, treachery, ingratitude; there are only eager desires for particular external goods; and it’s an old saying that the worst people would choose to obtain those goods by innocent means if that were as easy and as effective. If you think about what emulation and resentment really are in nature,^2

^2 Emulation is merely the desire and hope to be equal with or superior to others with whom we compare ourselves. There doesn’t seem to be any downside to the natural passion apart from the •lack that is implied in •desire; though this may be so strong as to be the occasion of great suffering. To want to achieve this equality or superiority specifically by means of others being brought down to or below our own level is, I think, the distinct

16

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 1: The Social Nature of Man

you’ll find nothing that supports this objection; and that the principles and passions in the mind of man which are distinct both from self-love and benevolence, primarily and most directly lead to right behaviour with regard to others as well as himself, and only secondarily and accidentally to what is evil. It can happen that a man tries to avoid the shame of one villainy by perpetrating a greater one; but it’s easy to see that the basic function of shame is to prevent the performance of shameful actions; and when it leads men to conceal such actions when they have been performed, that is only because they have been performed, meaning that the passion ·of shame· hasn’t succeeded in its first purpose.

You may say: ‘There are people in the world who are pretty much devoid of the natural affections [see Glossary] towards their fellow-creatures.’ Well, there are also people devoid of the common natural affections towards themselves: but the nature of man is not to be judged by either of these, but by what appears in the common world in most of mankind.

I am afraid you’ll think this very strange, ·but I’m going to say it anyway·. My account of human nature, and my comparison between benevolence and self-love, are supported by this array of facts:

Men contradict the part of their nature relating to themselves, the part leading [see Glossary] to their own private good and happiness, as much and as often as they contradict the part of their nature relating to society and leading to public good. There are as few people who achieve the greatest satisfaction and enjoyment that they could achieve in the present [see Glossary] world, as who do the greatest good to others that they could do; indeed, there are as few who really seriously aim thoroughly to serve their own interests as there are people who aim thoroughly to help others.

Take a survey of mankind [= ‘a species-wide opinion poll’]: Very nearly everybody, good people and bad, agrees that if religion were out of the picture the happiness of the present life would consist....wholly in riches, honours, sensual gratifications; and this assumption forms the background to almost all reflections people make on prudence, life, conduct. But the assumption is false. Very rich people are no happier than ones who are financially merely comfortable; the cares and disappointments of ambition usually far exceed the satisfactions it brings; similarly with a dissolute course of life, with its miserable periods of intemperance and excess, and often the early death it brings. These things are all seen, acknowledged, by everyone acknowledged, yet they aren’t seen as objections to the general thesis that the happiness of our present life consists in wealth or ambition or sensual pleasure—despite the fact that they explicitly contradict it. What is the source of all this absurdity and contradiction? Isn’t the middle way obvious? Can anything be more obvious than that the happiness of life consists in having and enjoying these three things in moderation, that pursuing them immoderately always brings more inconvenience than advantage to a man, often with extreme misery and unhappiness? Where, I ask again, does all this absurdity and contradiction come from? Is it really the result of men’s thinking about how they can become most easy to themselves, most free from care, and enjoy the chief happiness attainable in this world? Isn’t it rather—obviously—a result of one or other of these two things? (a) They don’t have enough cool and reasonable concern for themselves to think about what their

notion of envy. It’s easy to see from this •that the real goal of the unlawful passion, envy, is exactly the same as the real goal of the natural passion, emulation, namely that of equality or superiority; and •that doing harm is not the goal of envy but merely the means it employs to achieve its goal. Resentment will be discussed in the eighth sermon.

17

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 1: The Social Nature of Man

chief happiness in the present life consists in. (b) They do think about it, but refuse to act in accordance with the outcome of that thinking; that is, reasonable concern for themselves, cool self-love, is swamped by passion and appetite. So there seems to be no evidence that the principles in the nature of man that most directly lead us to promote the good our fellow-creatures are more generally or more intensely violated than the principles that most directly lead us to promote our own private good and happiness.

The conclusion of all this is obvious.

(1) The nature of man, considered as an isolated individual and with respect only to the present world, is adapted to—and leads him to—his getting the greatest happiness he can for himself in the present world.

(2) The nature of man, considered as a member of a society, leads him to right behaviour in society, i.e. to the course of life that we call ‘virtue’.

[On ‘leads him to’ see Glossary.] In both these capacities men follow or obey their nature....to a certain degree, but not entirely; their actions don’t measure up to the whole of what their nature leads them to in either of these capacities; and they often violate their nature in both. They neglect the duties they owe to their fellow-creatures...., and they conspicuously neglect their real happiness or ·self-·interest in the present world, when that interest is inconsistent with a present gratification. For the sake of such gratification they negligently—even knowingly, indeed—are the authors and instruments of their own misery and ruin. Thus they are as often unjust to themselves as to others, and for the most part the two injustices are equal in severity and come from the same actions.

18

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

For when the Gentiles, which have not the law, do by nature the things contained in the law, these having not the law, are a law unto themselves. (Romans 2:14) ·Let us call this The Text·.

Truths about things other than morality can be proved in various different ways, and so can ·truths about· moral obligations. If the real nature of any creature leads [see Glossary] him to act in a certain way and is fitted for that kind of behaviour, this is a reason to believe that that’s what the Author of •that nature intended •it for. Thus there’s no doubt the eye was intended for us to see with. And the more complex any constitution is, and the greater variety of parts of it that tend to some one end, the stronger is the evidence that the thing in question was designed to produce that end. But when we are looking at man’s inner constitution as a guide in morals, we must be extremely careful

•not to regard as common to our species features of ourselves as individuals, or features that many people have but that are the effects of particular customs; and

•not to overlook or exclude the highest principle [see Glossary], the one whose job is to adjust and correct of all the other inward movements [see Glossary] and affections; ·I am talking, of course, about conscience·.

This highest principle will as a matter of course have some influence, but ought to preside over and govern all the rest, because it is in nature supreme, as I shall now show. There’s less agreement about what the internal nature is that all men have than about their common external form, and there seem to be three reasons for this. •The two warnings I have just given are hard to attend to adequately; •it appears that men do differ from one another a little with respect to their natural sense of moral good and evil, ·i.e. with respect to conscience·; and •it is difficult for us to get an exact picture of what goes on in our minds. ·But let’s not make too much of this·. We don’t have a precise account of what shape is possessed by all and only human bodies, either, and yet we understand one another when we speak of ‘the ·external· shape of a human body’; and so we do when we speak of ‘the heart and inner principles of a human being’, however far the standard is from being exact or precisely fixed. So it isn’t unreasonable to try to show men to themselves, show them what course of life and behaviour their real nature points out and would lead them to. [The next bit is expanded in ways that the ·small dots· convention can’t easily indicate. Its first sentence is a sheer addition. The paragraph gets back to being close to Butler’s words at ‘A man can no more...’.] It is sometimes said that morality is just a matter of individual feelings and attitudes, and that there’s no absolute right or wrong about it; let us get that error out of the way at the outset. This is indeed true:

When we show that men have obligations to behave virtuously, and try to reinforce their motives for doing so, doing all this on the basis of a review of the nature of man, we are appealing to (a) each individual person’s heart and natural conscience.

But then so is this:

When we offer support for non-moral propositions such as scientific theses, we are appealing to (b) each individual person’s external senses.

Now, our (a) inward feelings are every bit as real as (b) the perceptions we get through our external senses; so there can’t be any more objection to drawing conclusions about life

19

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

and conduct from (a) than there is to arguing for non-moral truths from (b). A man can no more doubt whether his eyes were given him to see with than he can doubt the truth of the science of optics that is derived from ocular experiments. And he can no more doubt that the inward feeling of shame was given him to prevent him from doing shameful actions than he can doubt that his eyes were given him to guide his steps.... Neither his •inward feelings nor his •external senses can be wholly mistaken, though •the former are to some extent liable to greater mistakes than •the latter.

There can be no doubt about this:

The heart of man contains a number of propensities or instincts—a number of principles—that take him into •society and lead him to contribute to •its happiness. The way in which this happens isn’t matched by any inward principle leading man to do evil.

These principles, propensities, or instincts that lead him to do good are approved of by a certain inner faculty [see Glossary] that is quite distinct from these propensities themselves. I have fully defended all this in the first sermon.

·THE OBJECTION·
An objector may say this: ‘Even if all this is true, what help does it give to virtue and religion? These require not only that

We do good to others when we are led to by the fact that at that moment benevolence or reflection happens to be stronger than ·our· other principles, passions, or appetites,

but also that

Our whole character is based on thought and reflection; everything we do is directed by some determinate rule—some other rule than the strength and prevalence of any principle or passion.

What evidence is there in •our nature (for that’s where we are looking for evidence) that this was intended by •its Author? How does the various and flighty temperament of man seem to be adapted to it? It may indeed be absurd and unnatural for men to act without any reflection—indeed, to act without consulting the particular kind of reflection that you call ‘conscience’, because this does belong to our nature.... Anyone would approve of a humane action more than a cruel one, if ·self·-interest and passion didn’t come into it. But ·self·-interest and passion do come into it; they are often too strong for reflection and conscience, and prevail over it. Now, just as the lower animals have various instincts that carry them on to the end the Author of their nature intended them for, isn’t man in the same condition except for the one difference that in addition to his instincts (i.e. appetites and passions) he has the principle of reflection or conscience? And just as lower animals act in conformity with their nature, following whatever principle or particular instinct is strongest in them at that moment, doesn’t man similarly act in conformity with his nature—or obey the law of his creation—by following the principle, whether a passion or conscience, that happens to be strongest in him at that moment? And so we have

•men whose particular nature bustles them along in the pursuit of honour, or riches, or pleasure;

•men whose temperament leads them to an unusual degree of kindness, compassion, doing good to their fellow-creatures; and

•men who are given to suspending their judgment, weighing and considering things, and acting on ·the basis of· thought and reflection.

Let everyone then quietly follow his own nature, according to which parts of it—passion, reflection, appetite—happen to the strongest; but let the virtuous man not take it upon himself to blame the ambitious, the greedy, the dissolute;

20

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

because these are obeying and following their natures, as he follows his. In some cases we follow our nature in doing the works contained in the law, and in others we follow nature in doing contrary.’
·END OF THE OBJECTION·

All this licentious [= ‘super-permissive’] talk depends entirely on the supposition that when someone

follows his nature in violating the known rules of justice and honesty for the sake of a present gratification,

and someone else

follows his nature in abiding by the rules of justice when he isn’t tempted to do otherwise,

this involves ‘following his nature’ in the same sense [Butler’s phrase]. And if that were true, St Paul couldn’t be right in asserting that men are ‘by nature a law to themselves.’ If ‘following nature’ merely meant ‘acting as we please’, there would be.... no distinction between following one’s nature and not following it; for no-one ever acts otherwise than as he pleases!.... Language itself should teach people another sense to the words ‘following nature’ than merely ‘acting as we please’. Now, we do have to get straight about the meaning of the phrase ‘human nature’, but my real purpose in this sermon is not to explain the meanings of any words except insofar as I have to do that in order to understand and explain the assertion that ‘every man is naturally a law to himself’; that ‘everyone can find within himself the rule of right, and obligations to follow it’. St Paul affirms this in the words of The Text ·on page 19·, and The Objection above really denies it by seeming to accept it. The Objection will be fully answered, and The Text explained, by •pointing out that nature is considered from different viewpoints, and ‘nature’ is used in different senses; and by •showing what viewpoint is being adopted, and in what sense the word ‘nature’ is used, when it is meant to intended to stand for that which is the guide of life, that by which men are a law to themselves. The explanation of the word will be enough, because it will enable you to see that in some senses of the word nature can’t be a law to us while in another sense it obviously is so.

(1) The word ‘nature’ is often used to mean no more than ‘some principle in man’, with no regard for its kind or its degree. Thus, the passion of anger and the affection of parents to their children would be called equally ‘natural’. And because one person often has contrary principles pulling him in opposite directions, he can by a single action both •follow his nature and •contradict his nature, in this sense of the word; he may follow one passion and contradict another.

(2) Nature is often spoken of as consisting in the strongest passions, the ones that most influence the ·person’s· actions; and because the strongest are the vicious ones, mankind is in this sense ‘naturally vicious’ or ‘vicious by nature’ [see Glossary]. Thus St Paul says of the Gentiles, who were dead in trespasses and sins and walked according to the spirit of disobedience that they were ‘by nature the children of wrath’ [Ephesians 2:3]. The only way they could be children of wrath by nature is by being vicious by nature.

Here, then, are two different senses of the word ‘nature’, in neither of which men can at all be said to be ·by their nature· a law to themselves. I mention them only to set them aside, so as to prevent their being mixed up—as (2) is in The Objection—with another sense of it, which I shall now inquire into and explain.

(3) ·In The Text· [page 19] the apostle says that the Gentiles ‘do by nature the things contained in the law’. He puts ‘nature’ in here to distinguish this from revelation, ·i.e. from the thesis that revelation leads them to do the things contained in the law·; but it isn’t a mere negative. St Paul is not only saying what didn’t lead them to conform to the law but also saying what did, namely nature. The word ‘nature’

21

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

clearly doesn’t mean the same in this passage as it did in the earlier one from Ephesians, where nature is spoken of as evil; for in this Romans passage it is spoken of as good, i.e. as something that did or could have led them to act virtuously. What that is in man by which he is naturally a law to himself is explained in the following words:

... which show the work of the law written in their hearts, their conscience also bearing witness, and their thoughts the meanwhile accusing or else excusing one another. [Romans 2:15, just after The Text]

If there’s any distinction to be made between (i) the ‘works written in their hearts’ and (ii) the witness of ‘conscience’ it will have to be this:
(i) What is written in their hearts must be the natural disposition to kindness and compassion, to do what is respected and praised, to which this apostle often refers; the part of the nature of man....that leads him—with very little reflection and as a matter of course—into society, and by means of which he naturally acts rightly and well in it except when other passions or ·self·-interest lead him astray. But other passions and concerns for our own interests, which lead us....astray, are themselves in a degree equally natural and often most prevalent; and we have no way of discovering the particular degrees in which one or the other is placed in us by nature; so the naturally kind content of our hearts can’t be a law to us, any more than the other passions and concerns can be. But there is a superior principle of reflection or
(ii) conscience in every man, •which distinguishes amongst the internal principles of his heart as well as amongst his external actions; •which passes judgment upon himself and them, crisply pronouncing some actions to be in themselves just, right, good and others to be in themselves evil, wrong, unjust; •which without being consulted or asked for advice magisterially exerts itself, and approves or condemns the person whose actions they are. (And •which if it isn’t forcibly stopped will naturally and as a matter of course always go on to anticipate a higher and more effective sentence that will at a later time confirm and affirm its own. But dealing explicitly with this ·last· part of the task of conscience—·the part of looking ahead to God’s eventual confirming judgment·—is beyond my present design.) It is through this natural faculty that man is a moral agent, a law to himself. Through this faculty, I repeat, not considered merely as one principle in man’s heart that is to have some influence along with the others; but considered as a faculty that •is in kind and in nature [Butler’s phrase] supreme over all the others, and •bears its own authority of being so.

This....natural supremacy of the faculty that surveys and approves or disapproves the various affections of our mind and actions of our lives....deserves to be further explained to you; and I hope you will find it explained if you attend to the following reflections.

A man can act according to the principle or inclination that is currently the strongest and yet act in a way that....violates his real personal nature. Suppose a ·fox or some other· lower animal is lured into a snare by some bait, and is then destroyed: he clearly follows the bent of his nature, leading him to satisfy his appetite. His action is natural, because it entirely corresponds to his whole nature. Now suppose that a man who foresees that same danger of certain ruin nevertheless rushes into it for the sake of a present gratification; he is following his strongest desire, as did the fox; but there’s a conspicuous disproportion [= ‘mis-match’, ‘failure of fit’] between this action and the man’s nature—as conspicuous as that between a random scribble by me and a masterpiece by Leonardo. I am not talking about •the action in itself, or about •its consequences, but

22

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

only about •its relation to the man’s nature. And since such an action is utterly disproportionate to the nature of man, it is unnatural, in the strictest and most proper sense of that word. So now we can replace the phrase ‘disproportionate to his nature’ by the more familiar term ‘unnatural’, but do bear in mind that those mean the exactly same thing.

Now, what makes such a rash action unnatural? That he went against the principle of reasonable cool self-love, considered merely as a part of his nature? No: for if he had acted differently he would equally have gone against a principle or part of his nature, namely passion or appetite—·the passion or appetite that did in fact lead to the action we are discussing·. But there’s nothing unnatural about

(a) denying a present appetite because one sees that satisfying it would immediate lead to ruin or extreme misery.

Whereas in the case we are discussing it is unnatural to

(b) contradict or go against cool self-love for the sake of satisfying a present appetite.

So the unnaturalness of the action in (b) doesn’t come from •the man’s going against some principle or desire, or from •his going against the principle or desire that happens to be currently the strongest; because each of those is equally true of (a). So passions and appetites must differ from cool self-love in some way that I haven’t yet mentioned. It’s not a difference in strength or degree; I call it a difference in nature and in kind. In our present cases, if (b) passion prevails over self-love, the action is unnatural; but if (a) self-love prevails over passion, the action is natural; so it’s clear that self-love is in human nature a superior principle to passion. A passion can, whereas self-love can’t, be contradicted without violating the man’s nature; so if we want to act in a way that fits, goes with, harmonizes with the economy [see Glossary] of man’s nature, reasonable self-love must govern. So we can have a clear conception of one inward principle’s superiority to another; we see that this is a natural superiority, quite distinct from degrees of strength; and we have reached this result without saying anything about conscience.

Let us now look at human nature as consisting partly of •appetites, passions, affections, and partly of •the principle of reflection or conscience; leaving out all consideration of the different degrees of strength they need in order to prevail; and we’ll see again that there is this natural superiority of one inner principle over another, or that this superiority is even part of the idea of reflection or conscience.

Passion or appetite implies a direct simple tendency towards such-and-such objects, with no thought of the means by which they are to be obtained. So there will often be a desire for some particular objects, in a situation where they can’t be had without obvious harm to others. Reflection—i.e. conscience—comes in, and disapproves the pursuit of them in these circumstances; but the desire remains. Which is to be obeyed, appetite or reflection? Can’t this question be answered just on the basis of the economy and constitution of human nature, without saying which is strongest? Wouldn’t the question be intelligibly and fully answered by saying this?—

The principle of reflection or conscience is obviously superior to men’s various appetites, passions, and affections, independently of how they may differ in strength. However often the passions etc. happen to prevail, when they do that is mere usurpation, ·i.e. seizing power that you aren’t entitled to·. Conscience is still in nature and in kind its superior; and every case of such prevalence of passion etc. is a case of breaking in upon and violating the constitution of man.

All this is just the distinction between mere (i) power

23

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

and (ii) authority. Everyone is familiar with this distinction, though usually to mark the difference between what is (i) possible and what is (ii) permitted by the law of the land; whereas I have been applying it to the various principles in the mind of man. Thus, the principle that leads us to survey our own heart, temperament, and actions and either approve or disapprove of them, is to be considered not only as (i) having some influence (you can say that much about every passion and appetite, even the lowest), but also as (ii) being superior—as from its very nature plainly claiming superiority over all others. You can’t form a notion of this faculty, conscience, without bringing in the notions of judgment, direction, supervision. This is a constituent part of the idea, i.e. of the faculty itself; the very economy and constitution of man requires that conscience presides and governs; if it had strength to match its right, if it had power to match its obvious authority, conscience would absolutely govern the world!

This tells us more about the nature of man. It shows us what course of life we were made for; not only that

•our real nature leads us to be influenced in some degree by reflection and conscience,

but similarly

•to what extent we are to be influenced by it if we are willing to go along with the constitution of our nature and act agreeably to it,

and also that

•this faculty was placed within us to be our personal governor—to direct and regulate all our under-principles, passions and motives of action.

This is its right and its assigned task; so its authority is sacred. And however often men violate it and rebelliously refuse to submit to it, for the sake of supposed personal interests that they can’t otherwise pursue, or for the sake of a passion that they can’t otherwise satisfy, this makes no difference to the natural right and the assigned task of conscience.

Let us now view the whole matter from a different angle. ·For purposes of inquiry·, suppose that this is true;

There is no such thing as this supremacy of conscience. The only difference between one inner principle and another is a difference ·not in authority but· in strength.

What would be the consequence of this?

·EXPLORING THE CONSEQUENCES OF A FALSEHOOD·

·For example·: How far can man go in his actions with regard to •himself, •his fellow-creatures, and •the Supreme Being? What limits are there other than those set by the limits on our natural power? With respect to the first two, the only further limits are these:

No man (c) seeks misery as such for himself, and no-one who hasn’t been provoked (b) does harm to someone else for the sake of doing it.

Within those bounds, men knowingly (from passion or wantonness) (a) bring ruin and misery upon themselves and (b) upon others; and (c) impiety and profaneness (I mean what would be counted as impiety and profaneness by everyone who believes that God exists) have absolutely no bounds at all. Men openly blaspheme against the Author of nature, renouncing in words their allegiance to their Creator. Now consider any concrete example of any one of these three (·I shall take just two of them·). (c) Even if we suppose that men don’t actually mean anything by it, their routinely profane swearing etc. implies wanton disregard and irreverence towards an infinite Being, our Creator. Is this as suitable to the nature of man as reverence and dutiful submission of heart towards that Almighty Being? (b) Or take the case of someone who murders his father in an utterly cruel way:

24

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

he will have done this because its principle [see Glossary] was at that moment the strongest; and if inner principles differ from one another only in strength, that’s all there is to be said about this man’s inner nature at the time of his crime. So his action clearly corresponds to the principle which at that moment had such-and-such a degree of strength, so it corresponds to the whole nature of the man. We set the action alongside the whole nature, and we see no disproportion, no unsuitableness between them, any more than there is a disproportion between an act of filial duty and the nature at that time of the man who performs it. We can’t distinguish the murder from the action of filial duty, considered as the actions of the men who perform them, and must in our coolest hours approve or disapprove them equally. Nothing could come down to a greater absurdity than that.

That ends sermon 2. Sermon 3 now flows straight on, under the same title and with no new Biblical text.

Having established the natural supremacy of reflection or conscience, we can use this to get a clear notion of what is meant by ‘human nature’ when virtue is said to consist in following human nature and vice in deviating from it.

·For purposes of comparison, let us start with· the idea of a civil constitution, ·i.e. an organised political entity of some kind·. This involves

•united strength, and

•various subordinations (·downward-sloping lines of authority·)

•under the sole direction of the supreme authority.

The different strengths of each particular member of the society doesn’t come into the idea of it; but if you leave out •the subordination, •the union, and •the one direction, nothing is left of the idea of a civil constitution. Similarly, the idea or notion of human nature doesn’t involve the different strengths of the various appetites, passions, and affections; but ·the idea of· human nature does involve •these principles considered as naturally related to each other, and the various passions’ being naturally •subordinate to the one superior principle of reflection or conscience. Every inner bias, instinct, and propensity is a real part of our nature, but ·the totality of those is· not the whole of human nature; add to them the naturally superior faculty whose role it is to adjust, manage, and preside over them, and you complete the idea of human nature. Just as

in civil government the constitution is broken in upon and violated when power and strength prevail over authority,

so also

the constitution of man is broken in upon and violated when the lower faculties or principles within prevail over the one that is naturally supreme over them all.

Thus, when the ancient writers said that torture and death are not as contrary to human nature as injustice is, they certainly didn’t mean that mankind are less averse to torture and death than to injustice! What they meant was that torture and death are contrary to our nature only on a partial view of it, a view that takes in only the lowest part of our nature, the part that we have in common with the lower animals; whereas injustice is contrary to our nature considered as a system and constitution, i.e. contrary to the whole economy of man. [The next paragraph is a footnote in the original.]

·A FOOTNOTE ABOUT ‘SYSTEM OR CONSTITUTION·’
Every man in his physical nature is one individual single agent. It’s also true that he has ·inner· properties and principles each of which can be considered separately, setting aside its relations to the others. Neither of these—·the physical

25

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

unity or the jumble of inner principles·—is the nature that we are considering. What makes human nature is the inner frame of man considered as a system or constitution, whose various parts are united not physically but by the relations they have to each other. And the chief relation is the subordination of •the appetites, passions, and particular affections to •the one supreme principle of reflection or conscience. These relations and this subordination create the system or constitution; they are the system or constitution. Thus, the ·human· body is a system or constitution; so is a tree; so is every machine. If you think about all the parts of a tree without bringing in their natural relations to one another, that won’t give you the idea of a tree; but if you add these relations, you do have that idea. The body can be impaired by sickness, a tree can decay, a machine can be out of order, without their system and constitution being totally dissolved. And there’s clearly something analogous to all this in the moral constitution of man. Consider your own nature and you’ll see that the various appetites, passions, and particular affections have different relations amongst themselves: they restrain one another, and are proportional to one another. This proportion is just and perfect when all the under-principles perfectly coincide with conscience as far as their nature permits, and are always under its absolute and entire direction. If any of the under-principles is out of proportion to others or in any way fails to square with conscience, even if this doesn’t generate any action it is still a degree of disorder [roughly = ‘sickness’] in the moral constitution. But perfection, though plainly intelligible and supposable, has never been achieved by any man. If the higher principle of reflection ·or conscience· keeps its place, and does what it can to correct any disorder, and hinders it from breaking out into action, that’s the most that can be expected in a creature such as man. And though the appetites and passions don’t have exactly the proportions to each other that they should—though they often try to overcome judgment or reflection ·or conscience·—as long as they fail in this, i.e. as long as conscience retains its superiority, the character, the man, is good and worthy and virtuous.
·END OF FOOTNOTE·

From all these things put together, nothing can be more obvious than that—quite apart from anything we know from revelation—man can’t be regarded as a creature left by his Maker to act at random, throwing himself around (to the extent of his natural power) in whatever direction he happens to be taken by passion, mood or wilfulness...., but that from his constitution or nature he is the strictest and most proper sense ‘a law to himself’. He has the rule of right within him; all that’s needed is for him honestly to attend to it.

Some men of leisure have searched for a general rule in terms of which to characterise our actions as good or bad—·according to whether they conform to it or clash with it·—and this work of theirs has been useful in many ways. [Why ‘men of leisure’? Perhaps this was a crack at Shaftesbury, who was wealthy and an earl. Butler was a hard-working clergyman.] ·But we don’t need any such rule·. Let any plain honest man ask himself ‘Is this thing that I am about to do right or is it wrong? Is it good or is it evil?’ I haven’t the slightest doubt that this question would be answered correctly—agreeably to truth and virtue—by almost any fair-minded man in almost any circumstances. The only apparent exceptions to this involve •superstition or •partiality to ourselves [= ‘letting ourselves down lightly’]. Perhaps superstition is something of an exception: ·an honest man might have some superstitious belief that leads him to think wrongly that what he is about to do is right—e.g. the belief that God had just told him to cut his son’s throat [Genesis 22:1–12]·. But partiality to ourselves is

26

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

not an exception ·to my generalisation about how an honest man would answer the right/wrong question·, because such partiality is itself dishonesty. For a man to think ‘What I am about to do is fair, moderate, right’ when it is an action that he would regard as hard, unjust, oppressive if someone else performed it—that is just plain bad behaviour and can only come from great unfairness of mind.

Granting that every man has the rule of right within himself, you may want to ask: ‘What obligations are we under to attend to this rule and to obey it?’ My answer comes from something I have already proved:

Man is by his nature a law unto himself, ·a law that he is aware of· without thinking explicitly about the rewards and punishments that we •feel to be associated with it or the ones that we are led by the light of •reason to believe are associated with it.

[Butler calls these rewards and punishments ‘positive sanctions’ of the law in question, where ‘positive’ means ‘decided by someone; in the present context the thought is ‘rewards/punishments’ associated with right/wrong behaviour by the decision of humans or of God.]
The question then carries its own answer along with it. What obliges you to obey this law?—its being the law of your nature. That your conscience approves of such a course of action is, just in itself, an obligation. Conscience doesn’t merely offer to show us the path we should take but also carries its own authority with it, that it is our natural guide. [In that sentence, the last bit—‘carries.... guide’—is verbatim Butler.] It is the guide assigned to us by the Author of our nature; so it belongs to our condition of being [Butler’s phrase]; it is our duty to walk that path and follow this guide, without looking to see whether we might get away with straying from the path.

Still, we should hear what is to he said against obeying this law of our nature. It boils down to merely this:

‘Why should we be concerned about anything but ourselves? If we do find within ourselves •regards to [see Glossary] others and •all sorts of different restraints, these are just obstacles the hinder us from going the shortest way to our own good; so why shouldn’t we try to suppress and get rid of them?’

That’s the sort of thing that some people say; but when we apply it to human nature and the condition it is placed in, these words are really meaningless. It all presupposes •that our happiness in this world consists in something other than regards to others, and •that vice has the privilege of not being restrained or confined. The truth is quite the opposite: our enjoyments—in a way, all the common enjoyments of life including the pleasures of vice!—involve one or another kind of regards to our fellow-creatures. If we threw off all regards to others, we would be quite indifferent to disgrace and honour; there could be no such thing as ambition, and hardly any such thing as the desire for wealth. Why not? Because we wouldn’t care about •the disgrace of poverty, the various neglects and kinds of contempt that come with poverty, or about •the reputation of riches, the attention and respect they usually procure. ·And don’t think of ‘restraint’ as a purely moral affair·. Far from its being a special feature of one course of life, restraint is made absolutely necessary by our very nature and our situation. We can’t achieve anything without restraining ourselves to the use of the proper means ·to our goal·, and that confinement is often painful and distressing. And in countless cases a present appetite can’t be satisfied without such obvious and immediate ruin and misery that the most dissolute man in the world chooses to forego the pleasure rather than endure the pain.

·So the people I am opposing can’t mean what their words mean·! Perhaps they really mean:

27

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

We should •indulge the regards to our fellow-creatures, and submit to the restraints, which on the whole bring more satisfaction than unpleasantness, and get rid of only the ones which bring more unpleasantness and inconvenience than satisfaction.

‘Doubtless this was our meaning’, ·they may say·. Well, then, you have changed sides! Keep to this—be consistent with yourselves—and your general position will be exactly the same as that of the men of virtue. But let’s be careful to avoid mistakes. Don’t take it for granted that a temperament of envy, rage, resentment, produces more delight than comes from meekness, forgiveness, compassion, and good-will, especially given that, as everyone admits,

•rage, envy, resentment, are in themselves mere misery; and the satisfaction you can get from a bout of rage or the like doesn’t amount to much more than the pleasure of having it come to an end; whereas

•the temperament of compassion and benevolence is in itself delightful; and when you indulge it by doing good you’ll get new positive delight and enjoyment.

Don’t take it for granted that your satisfaction in the reputation and respect you can get from being rich and powerful (however your wealth and power were obtained) is greater than the satisfaction you can get from a reputation for justice, honesty, charity, and from the esteem that everyone agrees to be their due. And if it’s doubtful which of these satisfactions is the greater (and some people think that neither of them amounts to much), there can’t be any doubt concerning •ambition and greed as contrasted with •virtue and a good mind, considered in themselves and as leading to different courses of life. There can be no doubt, I repeat, which of these two temperaments and courses of life is accompanied by more peace and tranquility of mind, and which by more perplexity, vexation, and inconvenience. And both the virtues and the vices that I have mentioned equally involve one or another sort of regards to our fellow-creatures. As for restraint and confinement: if you think about the restraints that come with almost every kind of vice you’ll soon be convinced that the man of virtue is by no means at a disadvantage in this respect! I mean such restraints as go with:

•fear and shame,

•dissimulation [= ‘faking’],

•low-down tricks of concealment,

•servile compliances [= ‘feebly going along with what someone else wants you to do’].

How often does it happen that men feel the chains of vice that grip them, admit that they are there, and cry aloud against them, yet won’t shake them off? How often does someone obviously suffer more pain and self-denial to •satisfy a vicious passion than would have been needed to •conquer it? And there’s also this point: when virtue has become habitual, when a virtuous temperament is acquired, ways of behaving that used to be confining stop being so because they come to be chosen and to give delight.... It is obvious that in everyday life there is rarely any inconsistency between our duty and what is •called ·self·-interest. It is even rarer for there to be an inconsistency between duty and what is •really our present interest; meaning by ‘interest’ happiness and satisfaction. Thus, even when we think of •self-love only in relation to our interests in the present [see Glossary] world, we still find that •it does in general perfectly coincide with virtue, so that self-love and virtue lead us to the very same course of life. Whatever exceptions there are to this (and there are nowhere near as many as is often thought), they’ll be set right at the final distribution of things. To think that in a world administered by a perfect mind, evil will finally prevail over good—what an absurd idea!

28

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 2–3: The Natural Supremacy of Conscience

The whole argument that I have been pressing can be summed up and given to you in one view, as follows. The nature of man is adapted to some course action or other. Some actions appear to be suitable to this nature, and to correspond to it; other actions show up as unsuitable to man’s nature, or disproportionate to it. The former set of actions are natural; the other set are unnatural. An action’s corresponding to the nature of the agent doesn’t come from its being agreeable to the currently strongest principle [see Glossary]; an action may be quite in tune with the strongest principle while also being quite disproportionate to the nature of the agent. So the correspondence or disproportion has some other source. What it must be is a difference in nature and kind between the inner principles ·that cause the actions in question·—and I don’t mean a difference in how strong they are. Therefore, some ·principles· are •superior in nature and kind to others. And the correspondence comes from the action’s being conformable to the •higher principle; and the unsuitableness from its being contrary to it. •Reasonable self-love and •conscience are the chief or superior principles in human nature, because an action can be suitable to this nature while violating every other principle, but an action by which either of those two is violated is unsuitable. Conscience and self-love, if we understand our true happiness, always lead us the same way. Duty and ·self·-interest are coincide—

•usually, in this world, and

•entirely and always if we take into account everything, including our life after death

because this is implied in the notion of a good and perfect administration of things. Thus, anyone who has been so worldly-wise as to be concerned only with his own supposed ·self·-interest, at the expense of others, will eventually discover that he hasn’t provided for his own ·self·-interest and happiness anything like as well as has someone who has given up all the advantages of the present [see Glossary] world, rather than violate his conscience and the relations of life.

29

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

And if there be any other commandment, it is briefly comprehended in this saying, namely, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. (Romans 13:9)
It is commonly observed that men are inclined to complain of the viciousness and corruption of the age in which they live, as being worse than that of former times; and this is usually followed by the observation that mankind has been in that respect much the same [= ‘has been vicious and corrupt’] all through the ages. When we look to history to see whether it supports this last claim, we can hardly doubt this much: vice and folly take different turns, and some kinds of it are more open and admitted in some ages than in others; and I think it can be said that our present time is notably marked out by people’s willingness to admit to a narrowed spirit and greater regard for self-interest than appears to have been the case at earlier times. So it seems worthwhile to ask:

•Is it the case that the more intensely self-love absorbs our energies and prevails over all other principles [see Glossary], the more our private ·self·-interest is likely to be promoted?

•Or is it instead the case that the contracted affection [see Glossary] is so prevalent that it disappoints itself, and even contradicts the good of the individual that is its whole purpose?

Now, there’s generally thought to be some special kind of opposition between self-love and the love of our neighbour, between the pursuit of private and of public good; so that when you recommend one of these you are taken to be speaking against the other; and that gives rise to a secret prejudice against all talk of public spirit and real good-will to our fellow-creatures—secret prejudice and frequently open scorn! So we should ask:

What relationship does benevolence have to self-love? How does the pursuit of private ·self·-interest relate to the pursuit of public interest? Is there any special opposition between them, over and above what there is between self-love and other passions and particular affections, and their respective pursuits?

I hope you will address these questions in a favourable frame of mind. I shall make all possible concessions made to ·self-love·, the passion which has so much allowed to it and whose cause is so universally pleaded; I shall treat it with the utmost tenderness and concern for its interests!

In order to do this, as well as to answer the questions I have presented, I’ll have to consider •the nature, •the object, and •the goal of self-love, as distinct from other principles or affections in the mind and their respective objects. Every man has

(a) a general desire for his own happiness,

along with a variety of

(b) particular affections, passions, and appetites

with particular external objects. (a) comes from self-love, or is self-love; it seems inseparable from all sensible creatures who can think about themselves and their own interest or happiness, so as to have that interest as an object they can mentally aim at. What is to be said of (b) is that they come from the particular nature of the man in question—come from his nature or jointly constitute his nature.

The object that (a) pursues is something internal, our own happiness, enjoyment, satisfaction, whether or not we have a distinct particular perception of what it is. The objects of (b) are this or that particular external thing that the affections

30

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

tend towards, and of which the man in question always has a particular idea or perception. When (a) the principle we call ‘self-love’ seeks an external thing, that is never for the sake of the thing itself but only as a means of happiness or good; (b) particular affections aim at the external things themselves. (a) belongs to man as a reasonable creature reflecting upon his own interest or happiness; (b), though quite distinct from reason, are as much a part of human nature as (a) is.

Why do I say that all (b) particular appetites and passions aim at external things themselves, as distinct from the pleasure they give? Because that pleasure occurs as an upshot of the prior suitableness between the object and the passion: there would be no enjoyment or delight in one thing more than another—in eating food more than in swallowing a stone—if there weren’t an affection or appetite for one thing more than another.

Every particular affection, even the love of our neighbour, is as really our own affection as self-love is; and the pleasure arising from its gratification—·e.g. from my knowing that what I have done will make you happy at some future time·—is as much my own pleasure as the pleasure that self-love would have from knowing that I would be happy at some later time would be my own pleasure. Because every particular affection is a man’s own, and the pleasure arising from its gratification is his own pleasure, you might think that any such particular affection must be called ‘self-love’. According to this way of speaking, •no creature whatever can possibly act from anything but self-love; and •every action and every affection whatever is to be traced back to this one principle. But this isn’t the way people generally talk about these matters; if it were, we would have no way to say how (a) the principle of an action based on the cool consideration that it will be to my own advantage differs from (b) an action—e.g. of revenge or of friendship—by which a man aims to harm or help someone else at the cost of certain ruin for himself. Obviously the principles of these actions are totally different; so we need different words to distinguish them by. All that the actions have in common is: coming from an inclination in a man’s self, and being performed in order to gratify that inclination. But the principle or inclination in one case is self-love, and in the other it is hatred or love of someone else. So

the cool principle of self-love, or general desire for our own happiness, considered as one part of our nature and one principle of action

is to be distinguished from

the particular affections towards particular external objects, as another part of our nature and another principle of action.

However much is to be allowed to self-love, therefore, it can’t be allowed to be the whole of •our inner constitution because, you see, other parts or principles come into •it.

Furthermore, private happiness or good is the only thing that self-love can make us desire or be concerned about. (a) Satisfying self-love consists in having this private happiness; it is an affection to ourselves, a regard for our own interest, happiness, and private good; and the extent to which a man has this is the extent to which he is ‘·self·-interested’ or ‘a lover of himself’. (Keep this in mind, because these phrases are commonly given a different sense; I’ll return to this later.) (b) On the other hand, particular affections tend towards particular external things; these are their objects; having these is their end; their gratification consists in this—whether or not it favours our interest or happiness on the whole. An action motivated by (a) is called a ·self·-interested action. An action that comes from any of (b) can be described as ‘passionate’, ‘ambitious’, ‘friendly’, ‘revengeful’ etc. on the basis of the particular appetite or affection that it comes

31

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

from....

From this it will be easy to see how—and how far—each of these can contribute to....the private good of the individual. Happiness doesn’t consist in self-love. The desire for happiness isn’t the thing itself, any more than the desire for riches is the possession or enjoyment of them. People may love themselves with the most entire and unbounded affection, and yet be extremely miserable. And self-love can’t in any way help them out except by stimulating them to work to get rid of the causes of their misery, to get or use the objects that are by nature adapted to provide ·them with· satisfaction. Happiness or satisfaction is simply the enjoyment of the objects that are suited by nature to our various particular appetites, passions, and affections. Thus, if we are so full of self-love that there’s no room left for any other principle, we can’t have any happiness or enjoyment of any kind, because happiness consists in the gratification of particular passions, which presupposes that the passions have been had. Self-love, then, doesn’t bring it about that this or that is in our interests or is good for us; what creates our interests and our good is nature, and all that our supposed self-love does is to set us to work getting it. So if it can happen that self-love prevails and exerts itself in a way that doesn’t serve this end, then it isn’t certain that our interests will be promoted in proportion to how intensely self-love engrosses us and prevails over other principles. And it goes further than that: the private and contracted affection [see Glossary], when it is not aimed at this goal of private good, may....have the effect of working directly against the person’s private good. And if we think about it we’ll see that it often really has done so. If we are to enjoy something, it is absolutely necessary for us to be disengaged—·i.e. to be in a free, loose, limber frame of mind·—and a person may have his eye fixed so steadily on his own interests (whatever those are) that he fails to attend to many available gratifications that others have their minds free and open to. Over-fondness for a child is not generally thought to be for its advantage; and to judge by appearances the character that we call ‘selfish’ is not the most promising for happiness. Such a temperament can exist and exert itself in such a way as to prevent the person from even •obtaining the means and materials of enjoyment, let alone •making use of them. Immoderate self-love does a very poor job of taking care of its own interests; and it is certainly true—however paradoxical it may seem—that our own self-love should make us try to get rid of all excessive •concern for and •thought about ourselves. Every one of our passions and affections has its natural limits, which can easily be exceeded; whereas our enjoyments can possibly be but in a determinate measure and degree. [That sentence, from ‘whereas...’ to the end, is exactly as Butler wrote it. His point seems to be: a certain moderateness is of the essence of enjoyment, which therefore can’t be achieved through an immoderately sweeping or intense passion.] Therefore such excess of the ·passion or· affection, since it can’t lead to any enjoyment, must •always be useless and is •usually worse than useless—accompanied by disadvantages and often by outright pain and misery. This is as true about self-love as it is about all the other affections. Self-love at its natural level of intensity can be really advantageous to us, by spurring us to work to acquire and use the materials of satisfaction; but beyond or beside this it is in several respects an inconvenience and disadvantage. Thus it appears that private ·self·-interest is so far from being likely to be promoted in proportion to how thoroughly self-love swamps our minds and prevails over all other principles, that the contracted affection [see Glossary] may be so prevalent as to disappoint itself and positively conflict with its own goal, private good.

32

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

·There is a fairly widespread theory or attitude that would lead its friends to comment on what I have been saying, like this·:

‘But who, except for the most sordidly greedy person, ever thought that •the love of greatness, honour, or power, or •sensual appetites were in any way rivals of •self-love? No; there’s a perfect harmony between them. It is by means of these particular appetites and affections that self-love is gratified in enjoyment, happiness, and satisfaction. The competition and rivalry is between •self-love and •the love of our neighbour, the affection that leads us out of ourselves and stops us from caring about our own interests and starts us caring about someone else’s interests instead.’

Whether there really is any special competition and contrariety in this case—·i.e. between self-love and love of our neighbour·—is what I shall now consider.

I said that self-love and ·self·-interestedness consisted in an affection towards ourselves, a regard for our own private good; so it is distinct from benevolence, which is an affection towards the good of our fellow-creatures. But the mere fact that •benevolence is not the same thing as self-love isn’t a reason to view •it with suspicion; because every principle through which self-love is gratified is distinct from it! And all things that are distinct from each other are equally so; ·it makes no sense to say ‘x is more distinct from y than z is from w’·. A man has an affection or aversion towards someone else; one of these tends to and is gratified by doing good, the other by doing harm; but these facts don’t make the slightest difference to how either of these inner feelings relates to self-love. We use the word ‘property’ in statements like ‘That bit of land is this man’s property’ as a way of excluding everyone else from having an interest in that bit of land; and we often use the word ‘selfish’ [see Glossary] as a way of excluding all concern for the good of others. But the cases are not parallel: the idea of property really does involve that of exclusion; but when we connect self-love with disregard for the good of others we are adding to it, changing it from what I earlier said it consists in, namely an affection towards ourselves. This being the whole idea of self-love, it can’t exclude good-will or love for others other than merely by not including it, and by that standard self-love also ‘excludes’ love of arts, reputation, and everything else! And there’s no exclusion the other way either: benevolence doesn’t exclude self-love any more than love of arts or of reputation does. Love of our neighbour, then, is no more distant from self-love than is hatred of our neighbour, or love or hatred of anything else—these are all equidistant from self-love. Consider

•the principle [see Glossary] that leads someone to rush toward his own certain ruin in order to destroy an enemy, and

•the principle that leads someone to rush toward his own certain ruin in order to rescue a friend;

these relate to the private affection ·of self-love· in exactly the same way: they are equally ·self·-interested or equally disinterested [see Glossary].... So to those who are surprised to hear virtue spoken of as ‘disinterested’ I grant that it is indeed absurd to speak of it thus, unless hatred and various instances of vice and all the common affections and aversions in mankind are also acknowledged to be disinterested. Is self-love any more inconsistent with the love of our neighbour than it is with the love of inanimate things or of creatures that are merely sensitive ·and not thinking·? Is self-love lessened by a desire for and delight in the •happiness of someone else any more than by a desire for and delight in the •admiration of someone else? They are both equally desire for and delight in something external to ourselves.... The object of self-love is expressed

33

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

in the word ‘self’; and every appetite of sense, and every particular affection of the heart, is equally ·self·-interested or disinterested, because the object of each of them is either self or something else. Thus. if you think it appropriate to ridicule the mention of a disinterested principle or action, you should take the same attitude to •ambition and to every appetite and particular affection, as much as to •benevolence. In fact all the ridicule that this subject has drawn on itself (and all the solemn puzzlement that has surrounded it) comes merely from words. The most intelligible way of speaking of it seems to be this: self-love and the actions done in consequence of it are ·self·-interested; particular affections towards external objects and the actions done in consequence of those affections are not ·self·-interested. But everyone is at liberty to use words as he pleases. All I am here insisting on is that ambition, revenge, benevolence, all particular passions whatever and the actions they produce, are equally ·self·-interested or disinterested.

So we find that that there is no special opposition between self-love and benevolence; no greater competition between these two than between self-love and any other particular affection. This relates to the affections themselves. Let us now see whether there is any special opposition between the respective courses of life that these affections lead to. The question is: Is there any greater competition between the pursuit of private and the pursuit of public good than between any other particular pursuits and that of private good?

The only reason I can find to suspect that there’s a special opposition is the fact that the course of action that benevolence leads to has a more direct tendency to promote the good of others than the course of action that any other particular affection (e.g. love of reputation) leads to. But that an affection’s tending to the happiness of someone else doesn’t block it from tending to one’s own happiness too. That others enjoy the benefit of air and sunlight doesn’t block me from getting private benefit from them just as I would if I owned them! So a pursuit of mine that tends to promote the good of someone else may have as great tendency to promote my own private interest as a pursuit that doesn’t tend to the good of anyone else or that is harmful to someone else. All particular affections—such as •resentment, •benevolence, •love of the arts—equally lead to a course of action for their own gratification, i.e. for our gratification; and the gratification of each of them gives delight; so clearly they all relate in the same way to private ·self·-interest. Now, think about the fact that of these three pursuits •one aims at harming someone else, •the second aims at doing good for someone else, and •the third doesn’t automatically tend either way. Do these additional considerations force us to change our previous view about how each of the three relates to private self-interest? ·Clearly not·. Thus, one man’s aim is to get honour for himself, and for that end he is willing to take any amount of trouble. A second man aims just as single-mindedly to do public good, and works just as hard to achieve this. If they both succeed, surely the man of benevolence has as much enjoyment as the man of ambition...., but if they both fail, the benevolent man is clearly better off than the man of ambition, because trying to do good, considered as a virtuous pursuit, is gratified by its own consciousness, i.e. is in a degree its own reward.

Now let us compare benevolence with ambition (or with any other particular passion) in respect of the temperament or general character that each is associated with: is either of them more likely than the other to dispose the person to enjoy all the common blessings of life, distinct from their own gratification? Is benevolence less the temperament of tranquility and freedom than ambition or greed? Does

34

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

the benevolent man’s love for his neighbour make him less easy with himself? Is he less apt to enjoy being alive? Is there any special gloom on his face? Is his mind less open to entertainment, to any particular enjoyment? Nothing is more manifest than that being in good humour, which is benevolence whilst it lasts, is itself the temperament of satisfaction and enjoyment. [The clause ‘which is benevolence whilst it lasts’ is Butler’s; it is offered here with no understanding of what it means.]

Suppose someone is sitting down to consider how he can become most easy with himself, and achieve the greatest pleasure he could—everything that is his real natural happiness. This can only consist in the enjoyment of the items that are by nature adapted to his various faculties. These particular enjoyments make up the sum total of his happiness; and they are supposed to arise from riches, honours, and the gratification of sensual appetites. So be it; but no-one declares himself to be so completely happy in these enjoyments that there’s no room left in his mind for others, if others were presented to him. Indeed, much as riches etc. engage us, they aren’t thought so high that human nature isn’t capable of going higher. Now, all through the ages there have been people who have declared that they found satisfaction

•in the exercise of charity,

•in the love of their neighbour,

•in trying to promote the happiness of everyone they had any contact with, and

•in the pursuit of what is just and right and good,

having all this as the general slant of their mind and the goal of their life; and who have also declared that doing something base or cruel would be as great a violence to their self, as much a break-in on their nature as any external force. People like this would add (if anyone would listen) that they consider themselves as acting while being viewed by an infinite Being who is the object of reverence and of love in a much higher sense than all the rest of the world is; so that they couldn’t get pleasure from a wicked action performed under his eye any more than the people to whom they are making this speech could get pleasure from a wicked action of which all mankind were spectators. And they could further declare that the satisfaction of approving themselves to the unerring judgment of the Being to whom they thus refer all their actions is a more continued settled satisfaction than any that this world can provide; and also that they have, as much as anyone has, a mind free and open to all the common innocent gratifications of it, such as they are. Let us stop there, and ask: Do we find any absurdity in this? Will anyone venture to say that a man can’t find satisfaction in •this general course of life as much as in •the most unbounded ambition or •the excesses of pleasure? Or that a temperamentally benevolent person has made a worse job of thinking about his own satisfaction and peace of mind than has the ambitious or the dissolute man? As for the consideration that God himself will in the end justify their taste and support their cause: I am not going to bring this explicitly into the argument ·because I am engaged in relating benevolence to self-love purely in terms of this present life·; but I do want to remark that all enjoyments are much more clear and unmixed when one is assured that they will end well. Is it certain, then, that there is nothing in these claims to happiness, especially when plenty of people have supported themselves with satisfactions of this kind in sickness, poverty, disgrace, and in the very pangs of death, whereas all other enjoyments obviously fail in these circumstances? This surely looks suspiciously like having something in it! Self-love, I think, should be alarmed. Mightn’t she be passing up greater pleasures than those

35

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

she is so wholly taken up with? [Butler is having fun here, but those last two sentences are misleading. His central thesis in these two sermons is precisely that self-love, understood deeply and thoroughly, has nothing to ‘be alarmed’ about.]

In brief: Happiness consists in the gratification of certain affections, appetites, passions, by objects that are by nature adapted to them. Self-love may indeed spur us to try to gratify these ·affections, etc.·; but happiness or enjoyment has no immediate connection with self-love, and arises solely from such gratification. Love of our neighbour is one of those affections. Considered as a virtuous principle, love of our neighbour is gratified by a consciousness of trying to promote the good of others; but considered as a natural affection, its gratification consists in actual success in this attempt. [This distinction between ‘virtuous principle’ and ‘natural affection’ echoes and is explained by the treatment of parental love starting on page 15.] Now, indulgence or gratification of this affection, whether in the consciousness of trying or in success, relates to ·self·-interest in the same way as the indulgence of any other affection; they all come from self-love or none of them do; they all include self-love or all exclude it. Thus it appears that benevolence and the pursuit of public good are related to self-love and the pursuit of private good at least as closely as any other particular passions and their respective pursuits.

Neither is greed, whether as a character-trait or an activity, any exception to this. If by ‘greed’ is meant the desire and pursuit of riches for their own sake, with no thought for the uses of them, this has as little to do with self-love as benevolence has. But ‘greed’ is usually used to refer not to that madness and total distraction of mind but rather to immoderate affection towards and pursuit of riches as possessions, as a means to some further end, namely satisfaction, interest, or good. So this isn’t a particular affection, or particular activity; rather, it is the general principle of self-love, and the general pursuit of our own interest.... Now, just as it is ridiculous to assert that self-love and the love of our neighbour are the same, so also it would be ridiculous to say—and I therefore don’t say—that acting on these different affections has the same effect on our own interest. The comparison is not between

•self-love and •the love of our neighbour, or between

•pursuit of our own interests and •pursuit of the interests of others;

rather, it is between

•human nature’s various particular affections towards external objects and •one particular affection, namely that towards the good of our neighbour.

And I have shown that all these have the same relation to self-love and private interest.

It does indeed often happen that self-love or private interest is interfered with by the various particular appetites, passions, affections, or the pursuits they lead to. But this competition or interference is merely accidental ·rather than systematic·, and it happens much oftener between •private interest and •pride, revenge, or sensual gratifications than it does between •private interest and •benevolence. We often see men give themselves up to some passion or affection in direct contradiction to •what are obviously their real interests and to •the loudest calls of self-love; whereas the seeming competitions and interference between benevolence and private interest relate much more to the materials or means of enjoyment than to enjoyment itself. There is often an interference in materials or means where there is none in enjoyment. Consider riches: however much money a man gives away, he will have that much less remaining in his possession; this is a real interference. But though a man can’t possibly give without lessening his fortune, many people could give without lessening their own enjoyment,

36

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

because they have more money than they can turn to any real use or advantage to themselves. Then consider thought and time: the more thought and time someone employs about the interests and good of others, the less he has to attend his own interests, but he may have such a large and accessible supply of the things he needs that such thought would be really useless to himself though of great service and assistance to others.

The widespread erroneous belief that •self-interest is more at odds with •trying to promote the good of someone else than it is with •anything else seems—as I hinted earlier—to arise from men’s identifying their interests and happiness with the means and materials of enjoyment rather than with the enjoyment of them. Our interest or good is supposed to consist in owning riches, houses, lands, gardens. Now if ‘riches’ and ‘happiness’ are identical terms, it may well be thought that just as by giving riches you lessen your own so also by promoting the happiness of someone else you lessen your own. If that were right, it would produce a real conflict between private and public good. [Most of this paragraph up to here was replaced in the second edition of this work by a difficult longer passage in which Butler goes on from •the mistaken view that property is happiness to •a whole ‘general way of thinking’ dominated by thoughts about property. His one example of this is unconvincing and unhelpful; we can do without it. Rejoining the first edition:] Anyway, whatever caused the erroneous belief, I hope I have fully proved that it is erroneous....

And there’s another point. Religion is the source of our strongest obligation to benevolence, and it is so far from disowning the principle of self-love that it often addresses itself to that very principle, and always does so when speaking to the mind in the state in which reason presides. ·It must do so, because· the only way to get through to men’s understandings is by convincing them that the course of life we are trying to persuade them to adopt is not contrary to their interests. It does no harm to the cause of virtue and religion if we allow that •our ideas of happiness and misery are nearer and more important to us than any of our other ideas; that •they will—that they ought to—prevail over the ideas of order, beauty, harmony, and proportion; or rather that they would deserve to prevail if there were ever any conflict here, which there can’t possibly be.... Virtue or moral rectitude does indeed consist in affection towards and pursuit of what is right and good, as such; but let us admit that when we sit down in a cool hour we can’t justify to ourselves this or any other pursuit until we are convinced that it will be for our happiness, or at least not contrary to it.

Common reason and humanity will have some influence on mankind, whatever the outcome is of theoretical disputes; but to the extent that the interests of virtue depend upon the theory of it [Butler’s phrase] being secured from open scorn, to that extent its very existence in the world depends on its being seen not to be opposed to private ·self·-interest and self-love. So I hope that what I have said in this sermon has gained a little ground in favour of the precept before us, ·namely ‘Love thy neighbour as thyself’·. Expounding this in detail will be the topic of the next sermon.

[Butler closes with a paragraph emphasizing the centrality of ‘Love thy neighbour’ in Christianity and in the ‘perfect example’ set by Jesus. He quotes this: ‘The night is far spent, the day is at hand: let us therefore cast off the works of darkness, and let us put on the armor of light.’ (Romans 13:12)]
That ends sermon 11.

37

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

Sermon 12 retains the same title and repeats the same Biblical text.

And if there be any other commandment, it is briefly comprehended in this saying, namely, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. (Romans 13:9)

Having removed the prejudices against public-spirit (i.e. the love of our neighbour) on the side of private ·self·-interest and self-love, I now turn to the detailed exposition of the precept that is now before us, by showing (1) who is our neighbour, (2) in what sense we are required to love him as ourselves, (3) the influence such love would have upon our behaviour in life, and lastly (4) how this commandment contains within it all the others.

[1] The objects and due extent of this affection will be understood by attending to the nature of it, and to the nature and circumstances of mankind in this world. The love of our neighbour is the same as charity, benevolence, or good-will. It is an affection towards the good and happiness of our fellow-creatures. This implies in it a disposition to produce happiness: and this is the simple notion of goodness, which strikes us as so lovable whenever we meet with it. It is easy to see from this that the perfection of goodness—·the ultimate kind of goodness·—consists in love for the whole universe. This is the perfection of Almighty God.

But it is not to be thought of that the universe should be the object of benevolence to such creatures as we are! We are too limited in our abilities, we can observe and influence too small a part of the creation, and we aren’t used to considering things in such a sweeping way.... For this reason, moral writers have substituted a less general object for our benevolence, namely mankind. But this is still too general for us, and very much out of our view. This has led more practical writers to replace ‘mankind’ by ‘our country’, implying that the principle [see Glossary] of virtue—of human virtue—consists in the entire uniform love for our country [Butler’s phrase]. This is what we call a ‘public spirit’, and in men in public positions it counts as being a patriot. But this is addressed to the upper part of the world—i.e. to rulers and governments and high officials. Kingdoms and governments are large; and the sphere of action of almost every individual is much narrower than that of the government he lives under; and anyway ordinary people don’t think of their actions as affecting the whole community of which they are members. So clearly we need a •less general and •nearer object of benevolence for most men than their country. That is why the Scripture, not being a book for theory-building but a plain rule of life for mankind, has with the utmost possible propriety taken as the principle of virtue the love of our neighbour, i.e. the part of the universe, of mankind, of our country, that we can directly observe, know, and influence—the part that we have dealings with.

This is clearly the true account or reason why our Saviour places the principle of virtue in the love of our neighbour; and the account itself shows who are to count as our neighbours.

[2] Let us now consider in what sense we are commanded to love our neighbour as ourselves.

When this precept was first issued by our Saviour, he introduced it like this: ‘Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thine heart, with all thy soul, and with all thy strength; and thy neighbour as thyself.’ (Matthew 23:37) These very different expressions—·‘with all thy heart...’, ‘... as thyself’·—don’t lead our thoughts to the same measure or degree of love common to both objects; but rather to one for ‘thy God’ and another for ‘thy neighbour’. So we have to take it that the words ‘as thyself’ mean something distinct and appropriate, but what is it? The precept we

38

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

are considering could be taken in any one of these senses: (a) we should have the same kind of affection towards our neighbour as we do towards ourselves; (b) the ·intensity of the· love we have for our neighbour should have some specific proportion to ·the intensity of· our self-love; (c) the intensity of the love we have for our neighbour should be exactly the same as that of our self-love.

(a) The precept can be understood as requiring only that we have the same kind of affection towards our fellow-creatures as we have towards ourselves: just as every man has the principle of self-love that disposes him to avoid misery and watch out for his own happiness, so also we should cultivate the affection of good-will towards our neighbour, letting it influence us to have the same kind of regard for him. This at least must be commanded; and it will not only prevent us from harming our neighbour but will require us to promote his good. There are blessings in life that we share with others: peace, plenty, freedom, healthful seasons. But real benevolence to our fellow-creatures would give us the notion of a ‘common interest’ in a stronger sense, because to the extent that we love someone else his interests, joys, and sorrows are our own. It is from self-love that we form the notion of private good, and consider it as our own; love of our neighbour will teach us in that way to take to ourselves his good and welfare, to consider ourselves as having a real share in his happiness. Thus the principle of benevolence would be an advocate within our own breasts, telling us to be careful for the interests of our fellow-creatures in all the interferings and competitions that are inevitable given the imperfections of our nature and world we live in. It would also to some extent lessen that interfering, and hinder men from forming as strong a notion of private good, distinct from the good of others, as we commonly do. Thus, as the private affection ·of self-love· makes us in a special way aware of humanity, and of justice or injustice, when exercised towards ourselves, so also love of our neighbour would give us the same kind of awareness on his behalf. This would be the best assurance of our always obeying that most equitable rule ‘Whatsoever ye would that men should do unto you, do ye even so unto them.’ (Matthew 7:12)

All that this comes down to is just that we should have a real love for our neighbour; but notice that the words ‘as thyself’ say this with great clarity.... The advantage which this principle of benevolence has over other remote considerations is that it is itself the temper of virtue [Butler’s phrase] and also the main security—actually the only effective security—for our performing the various acts of kindness that we owe to our fellow-creatures. When distant considerations lead men to decide on something that they have no liking for, or even that they actively dislike, they are perpetually digging up evasions and excuses (there are always plenty to be found if people look for them), and they play tricks on themselves with ambiguities in what are really the plainest cases in the world. This can happen over some one determinate act of virtue; but it happens much more when the ·unwanted· obligation is to a general course of behaviour, especially if that general course can’t be reduced to fixed determinate rules. This observation may account for the use of two different verbs in the well-known passage of the prophet Micah, ‘To do justly, and to love mercy.’ A man’s heart must be shaped to humanity and benevolence, he must love mercy; otherwise he won’t act mercifully in any settled course of behaviour. The only guarantee that we will persevere in our duty in the face of great temptation comes from our thought of the future sanctions of religion; and the only way to get us to act rightly in the familiar and daily relations with one another is to get our heart and temperament formed to a love and liking for what is good.

39

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

(b) The precept before us may be understood to require that we love our neighbour in some particular proportion to how we love ourselves. And indeed a man’s character can’t be determined by •the love he has for his neighbour, considered absolutely [i.e. not in relation to anything else]. The chief thing that forms the character and influences the actions is the proportion that •this has to his self-love.... For just as the form of the body is a composition of various parts, so also our inner structure is not simple or uniform, but is a composition of various passions, appetites, and affections—and also rationality, which includes both the awareness of what is right and a disposition to live by it. There is greater variety of parts in what we call a ‘character’ than there are features in a face; and the morality of the character isn’t settled by one part, any more than the beauty or ugliness of a face is settled by one feature.... In the inner frame the various passions, appetites and affections can relate in different ways to each other. One principle in someone’s mind may flatly oppose another, or it may merely restrain it and cool it down, or it may encourage it and give it help. And two principles that aren’t in themselves related to one another in any way may in a given case hinder or help one another because of temporary circumstances.

A result of this is that even if we could look into the inner structure of someone’s heart and see exactly how strong some one principle is there, that wouldn’t tell us •how far that principle would go towards forming the person’s character, or •what influence it would have on his actions, unless we could also see what other principles prevailed in him, and see how they all compare with one another in intensity. For example: two men x and y have the affection of compassion in exactly the same degree, but in x the principle of resentment (or of ambition) is so strong that it prevails over the principle of compassion and prevents it from having any influence on his actions, so that x may deserve to be described as ‘hard’ or ‘cruel’; whereas y, who has compassion in just the same degree as x, has a lower intensity-level of resentment (or ambition) so that his compassion can win out over them and thus influence his actions, which entitles him to qualify as ‘compassionate’....

Furthermore, the whole system of affections (including rationality) that constitute the heart (as ‘heart’ is used in Scripture and on moral subjects) may be stronger in some than in others. [Having said that, Butler oddly drops the point and repeats his thesis about the proportional strengths of two principles in one person’s ‘heart’, this time applying it specifically to self-love and benevolence. in particular. He ends this bit of the discussion thus:] This is like the way it is with scales: whether a scale-pan goes up or down depends not simply on the weight of what it contains but on how that weight compares with the weight of whatever is in the other pan.

So (i) it’s obvious that the influence of benevolence on our actions, and how far it goes towards forming our character, is determined not by the strength of this principle in our mind but by how its strength compares with that of self-love and other principles; and (ii) the text ·from Romans· that we are investigating tells us to compare our self-love and our love of our neighbour. Put these two points together and you get a sufficient basis for discussing that proportion here: it plainly is implied in the precept, even if it isn’t exactly contained in the meaning of the words ’as thyself’.

Love of our neighbour, then, must be in some proportion to self-love; and virtue consists in getting that proportion right. [The next two sentences are rather free versions of what Butler wrote, but they are true to its content.] We could be talking here about the relative strengths of self-love and benevolence •as they exist in the person’s mind, or about the relative

40

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

strengths of •their roles in his conduct. We have no way of measuring the former of these, so let us turn to the latter.

Our nature and our situation in the world both require each individual man to provide for himself in particular; and the question ‘What proportion should benevolence have to self-love?’, when handled in terms of conduct, becomes ‘What is a competent care and provision for ourselves?’ [For ‘competent’ see the Glossary.] Each man must answer this for himself; it would be ridiculous for anyone to try to answer it for anyone else; but the fact remains that there is an answer—there’s a limit to what can count as a competent provision for one’s needs, and the answer can’t be ‘As much as we can possibly get and keep hold of without breaking the criminal law’! Almost everyone in answering this will bring in things that are of no real value—things needed for a so-called ‘life of pleasure’, things catering to his greed or his imaginary notions of superiority over others—but anyone who wants to act well in society ought to ask himself ‘If it’s a question of what counts as “competent” from a moral point of view, are any of these things really needed for that?’ All I can say on the matter is this: On the (safe!) assumption that people don’t neglect what they really owe to themselves, the more of their care and thought and resources they put into doing good to their fellow-creatures, the nearer they come to obeying the law of perfection ‘Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself’.

(c) If the words ‘... as thyself’ were to be understood as meaning an equality of affection ·towards one’s neighbour and towards oneself·, it wouldn’t have all the consequences that might be thought to follow from it. Let’s consider someone who has the same settled concern for others as for himself; in every deliberate plan or activity he takes •their interests into account to the same extent as •his own, so far as an equality of affection—·an equality of self-love and neighbour-love·—produces this. Despite this, he will and ought to be much busier working on his own concerns than on the concerns of others. Why is that? Because in addition to the one •common affection towards himself and his neighbour, he will have many other particular affections, passions, appetites, which he couldn’t possibly feel in •common both for himself and others. Now, these affections etc. greatly preoccupy him, and may have as much influence ·on his conduct· as self-love does; the feeling of those affections, appetites, and passions will spur him to search out and use the means of satisfying them. And this part of his conduct must be exclusive to himself—he can’t match it with behaviour on behalf of others....

From moral considerations, our concern for ourselves ought to be more prevalent than attention to the concerns of others. We are, so to speak, entrusted with ourselves, so that each person’s care for his own interests—as well as his conduct—is especially his.

And there’s another point. Moral obligations can’t extend beyond what is naturally •possible; we carry around with us a perception of our own interests, like our awareness of our own existence; and it seems •impossible for us to have that kind and intensity and steadiness of awareness of the interests of others.

These points taken together pretty clearly show that even if we love our neighbour as much as we love ourselves (so far as this is possible), our individual care of our individual selves wouldn’t be neglected; and that removes what seems to be the only objection to understanding the precept in this strict sense.

[3] [The numeral ‘3’ refers to the numbered quartet of topics announced on page 38.] Our next topic is the general mind-set that the appropriate love of our neighbour would create in us, and the influence it would have on our everyday behaviour.

41

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

The mind-set and behaviour of charity is broadly described in this well-known passage of St. Paul:

‘Charity suffereth long, and is kind; charity envieth not..., doth not behave itself unseemly, seeketh not her own...., thinketh no evil..., beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things.’ (1 Corinthians 13:4–7)

As for the meaning of the expressions ‘seeketh not her own, thinketh no evil, believeth all things’: however those expressions may be explained away,

•this meekness and (to some extent) temperamental relaxedness, this

•willingness to forgo our rights—for the sake of peace and also as an expression of compassion, and this

•freedom from mistrust, and disposition to believe well of our neighbour

—this general temperament accompanies and is plainly an effect of love and good-will. It’s true that the world we live in is such that experience and knowledge of it is bound to give us more concern for ourselves and doubt about the characters of others—more, I mean, that is built into human nature—but these oughtn’t to be taken further than the nature and course of things make necessary. Even in the present state of things, bad as it is, it’s still true that a real good man [Butler’s phrase] would rather be deceived than be suspicious, would rather forgo his known right than run the risk of ·doing something unjust or· even of doing something harsh. This is the general frame of mind of the charity of which the apostle says that ‘though I give my body to be burned, and have not charity, it profiteth me nothing’, and that charity ‘never faileth’.

The good effects of this temperament extend to every different relation and circumstance in human life. They plainly make a man better, more to be desired, with regard to all the respects and relations we can have to one another. The benevolent man is disposed to use all his external advantages in ways that contribute to •the good of others as well as to •his own satisfaction. His own satisfaction consists in this. He will be relaxed and kind to his dependents, compassionate to the poor and distressed, friendly to all with whom he has to do. This includes the good neighbour, parent, master, magistrate; and such behaviour would clearly make life easier for people who were dependents, inferiors, even slaves. [Butler writes of making ‘servitude’ less burdensome, and that just did mean ‘slavery’. But he doesn’t speak of these beneficiaries of the conduct of the charitable man as his dependents, inferiors, or slaves.] Thus, a good or charitable man of superior rank in wisdom, fortune, authority, is a blessing to everyone in the place where he lives; happiness grows under his influence. This good principle would reveal itself in inferiors through their paying respect, gratitude, obedience as appropriate. So I think that one good way of testing one’s own character is to ask ourselves: ‘Am I really a better master or servant, a better friend, a better neighbour, than x?’, where x is someone whom I haven’t thought to deserve the descriptions ‘virtuous’ and ‘pious’ as much as I do.

As for the •partisanship that unfortunately prevails amongst mankind...., someone who is friendly to his fellow-creatures will automatically make appropriate allowances for •it, as something that is inevitable among such creatures like us in a world like this. The wrath and fury and bullying in these disputes comes from men’s feeling only on their own side (so to speak); so a common feeling for others as well as for ourselves would make us aware of the fact that we differ from others just as much as they differ from us. (It’s strange that this truth has so little influence!) The issues at stake in all those disputes and all that working up of partisanship are really nothing at all; but I am not pressing that point

42

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

here, because I can hardly expect that men in general can be induced to accept it. What I have said is based on my expectation that people in general, however much they are in earnest about their respective peculiarities, will allow humanity and common good-will to their fellow-creatures to moderate and restrain the wretched spirit of partisanship.

The charitable frame of mind would likewise prevent strife and enmity in other contexts; it would prevent our giving just cause of offence, and our taking offence without cause. And in cases of real injury, a good man will make all the allowances that should be made; and without trying to retaliate he will think only of future protection from injustice and wrong for himself and for other men.

[4] My last topic is the statement in the Romans passage that all the virtues are ‘briefly comprehended’ in the command to love our neighbour, i.e. that to love our neighbour as ourselves includes all the other virtues....

In almost everything that is said, there’s something to be understood beyond what is explicitly laid down—something that the listener or reader supplies automatically.... Thus, when benevolence is said to be ‘the sum of virtue’, this isn’t being said about benevolence as a blind propensity but about it as a principle in reasonable creatures, and thus as being under the direction of their reason, because reason and reflection come into our notion of a moral agent. And that will lead us to think about an action’s distant consequences as well as its immediate effect; it will teach us •that the care of some persons—e.g. children and families—is especially committed to our charge by nature and God; as also •that there in some cases—e.g. involving friendship or former obligations—that require us to do good to some people in preference to others. Reason, considered merely as subservient to benevolence, as assisting us to produce the greatest good, will teach us to have particular respect for these relations and circumstances, because it’s obviously plainly for the good of the world that they should be respected. Also, in countless cases we really aren’t competent judges of whether a particular action will upon the whole do good or harm; and reason will teach us to be cautious about how we act in these cases. It will suggest things for us to think about:

•which is the safer side;

•how liable we are to be led wrong by passion and ·self·-interest;

•what regard is due to laws, and

•what regard is due to the judgment of mankind.

All these things must be taken into account, even if only to determine which way of acting is likely to produce the greatest good. Thus, even if it were strictly, literally, absolutely true that •benevolence includes in it all the virtues, reason must still come in as the guide and director of benevolence, helping it to achieve its goal of the greatest public good. So, with reason on board, let us now consider the truth of the assertion itself. ·I have two main points to make·.

(1) Obviously nothing can be of consequence to mankind or to any creature except happiness. So this is all that anyone can be said, strictly speaking, to have a right to. Therefore, we can’t owe any man anything except to further and promote his happiness as best we can. So a disposition and endeavour to do good for everyone with whom we have any dealings, to the extent and in the way required by the different relations we have to them, is a fulfilment of all the obligations we have towards them.

Human nature is not one simple uniform thing, but a composition of various parts—body, spirit, appetites, particular passions and affections—and reasonable self-love would lead a man to attend to these and to provide for them, to a suitable extent. Well, society also consists of various

43

Five Sermons Joseph Butler 11–12: The Love of our Neighbour

parts to which we are related in various ways; and a just benevolence would lead us to attend to these in whatever way our relations with them might require. Reasonable good-will, and right behaviour towards our fellow-creatures, are in a way the same thing—it’s just that the former expresses the principle as it is in the mind, while the latter expresses the principle externally, in actions.

To the very considerable extent that temperance, sobriety, and moderation in sensual pleasures (and the contrary vices) have any influence on the quiet, the welfare, and the happiness our fellow-creatures, to that extent it is obvious those virtues can be produced by the love of our neighbour and that the contrary vices would be prevented by it. Indeed, if someone’s regard for himself doesn’t restrain him from excess, you won’t think it likely that his love for others will be sufficient; but that’s because his love for others—like his regard for himself—is not at its proper level. There are clear cases of men kept sober and temperate out of concern for their own affairs and the welfare of those who depend on them. And anyone can see that habitual excess, a dissolute course of life, implies a general neglect of the duties we owe to our friends, our families, and our country.

This shows clearly that the common virtues and the common vices of mankind can be tracked back to benevolence or the lack of it. And this entitles the precept ‘Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself’ to the pre-eminence given to it; and it justifies of the apostle’s assertion that all other commandments are ‘comprehended in’ it; whatever cautions and restrictions^3 there are that would have to be considered if we wanted to state in detail and at length what counts as virtue and right behaviour in mankind. But,

(2) In a higher and more general way of thinking about these matters, leaving out the special nature of creatures and the special circumstances in which they are placed, benevolence seems in the strictest sense to include in it all that is good and worthy—all that is good that we have any distinct particular notion of. We have no clear conception of any positive moral attribute in the Supreme Being except what can be resolved up into •benevolence. [That means something like ‘... except what can, metaphorically speaking, be boiled down into benevolence’. Butler wrote ‘... into goodness’, but presumably that was a slip.] And if we consider a thinking creature, i.e. a moral agent, without regard to the particular relations and circumstances in which he is placed, we can’t conceive anything to count for or against his being classed as virtuous except the higher or lower degree in which •that principle....prevails in him....

^3 For instance: because we aren’t competent judges of what is over-all for the good of the world, there may be other immediate ends that we should pursue besides the one of doing good or producing happiness. Though the good of the creation be the only goal of its Author, he may have laid us under particular obligations that we can discern and feel ourselves under, quite apart from any perception that observing (or violating) them makes for the happiness (or misery) of our fellow-creatures. He may have, and he did. Certain dispositions of mind, and certain actions, are in themselves approved or disapproved by mankind independently of any thought about their tendency to the happiness or misery of the world; approved or disapproved by reflection ·or conscience·, the inner principle that is the guide of life, the judge of right and wrong. Countless examples of this could be mentioned. There are acts of treachery that in themselves appear base and detestable to everyone. There are actions that are hard to describe except by the general name ‘indecencies’ that are odious and shocking to human nature. There is such a thing as small-mindedness, which raises a dislike and disapproval quite different from the contempt men are too apt to have of mere folly (which is a different thing altogether). And on the other side what we call greatness of mind ·or magnanimity· receives approval of a different sort from the approval of superior understanding. Fidelity, honour, strict justice, are themselves approved in the highest degree, independently of any thought about what they might cause....

44

Discourse on the Method of Rightly Conducting one’s Reason and Seeking

Truth in the Sciences

René Descartes

Copyright © 2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Given this work’s full title, you can see that it is wrong to call it, for short, ‘Discourse on Method’ with no ‘the’.
First launched: June 2005 Last amended: November 2007
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Part 1   1
Part 2   5
Part 3   11
Part 4   14
Part 5   18
Part 6   24

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 1

If this discourse seems too long to be read at a sitting you may divide it into six parts. In 1 you will find various considerations regarding the sciences; in 2 the main rules of the method that the author has sought; in 3 some of the moral rules he has derived from this method; in 4 the arguments by which he proves the existence of God and the human soul, on which his metaphysics is based; in 5 the order of the questions in physics that he has investigated, particularly the explanation of the movement of the heart and of some other problems in the medical sphere, and also the difference between our soul and that of the lower animals; and in 6 the things he believes are needed if we are to go further than he has in the investigation of nature, and his reasons for writing this discourse.

Part 1

•Good sense is the best shared-out thing in the world; for everyone thinks he has such a good supply of it that he doesn’t want more, even if he is extremely hard to please about other things. Since it’s not likely that everyone is mistaken about this, it is evidence that

the •power of judging well and of telling the true from the false—which is what we properly call •‘good sense’ or •‘reason’—is naturally equal in all men;

thus it is also evidence that

our opinions differ not because some of us are more reasonable than others, but solely because we take our thoughts along different paths and don’t attend to the same things.

For it isn’t enough to have a good mind; what matters most is using it well. ·Sheer quality of intellect doesn’t make the difference between good and bad·: the greatest souls are capable of the greatest vices as well as the greatest virtues. ·Nor is nimbleness of intellect the key to making discoveries·: those who go very slowly but always on the right path can make much greater progress than those who sprint and go astray.

As for me, I have never presumed my mind to be in any way better than the minds of people in general. Indeed, I have often ·had a sense of being less well endowed than others·: I have wished to be as •quick-witted as some others, or to match their •sharpness and clarity of imagination, or to have a •memory that is as capacious (or as promptly serviceable) as theirs is. And •these ·three· are the only qualities I know of that serve to perfect the mind, ·making one mind more perfect than another·. As for •reason or •·good· sense, I’m inclined to believe that it exists whole and complete in each of us, because it is the only thing that makes us men and distinguishes us from the lower animals. In this I am following the common opinion of the philosophers, who say that a quality that admits of differences in degree can’t be one that marks the difference between one species and another—it can only be an ‘accident’, a relatively trivial and superficial property, of anything that has it

But I don’t hesitate to report my opinion ·that in one respect I am above the common run of people·. Ever since my youth I have been lucky enough to find myself on certain paths that led me to thoughts and maxims from which I developed a method; and this method, it seems to me,

1

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 1

enables me to increase my knowledge gradually, raising it a little at a time to the highest point allowed by the averageness of my mind and the brevity of my life. ·There are two reasons, one •personal and the other •general, why I might expect that my method won’t amount to much·. •In making judgments about myself I always try to lean towards diffidence and away from arrogance; and •when I cast a philosophical eye on the various activities and undertakings of mankind, I regard almost all of them as pointless and useless. And yet, ·despite these two facts·, I have already achieved such results from this method that I’m extremely satisfied with how far I think I have already gone in the search for truth, and am so hopeful about the future that if any purely human occupation has solid worth and importance I venture to think it is the one I have chosen. [Here ‘purely human occupation’ = ‘occupation that doesn’t bring in revealed religion’.]

Still, I may be wrong: perhaps what I take to be gold and diamonds is merely copper and glass! I know how prone we are to err in matters that concern us, and also how cautious we should be in accepting the favourable judgments of our friends. But ·these thoughts won’t lead me to be secretive about my method. On the contrary·, I don’t mind revealing in this discourse what paths I have followed, laying bare my life as though in a picture, so that •everyone can make his own judgment on it, and •when I learn what people think of it I’ll be able to add that as a new source of instruction to the ones I’m accustomed to using.

So I don’t aim here to teach the method that everyone must follow if he is to direct •his reason correctly, but only to display how I have tried to direct •my own. People who go in for laying down rules for others must think they are more skillful than the others; and they are at fault if they make the slightest mistake. But ·I’m not one of those, and am not exposed to blame as they are·. I am presenting this work only as a history—or if you prefer, a fable—in which you may find certain examples that are worth imitating; and if along with those you also find various others that you would be right not to follow, ·that doesn’t mean that I’m at fault·. So I hope that what I’m offering will be useful for some without being harmful to anyone, and that everyone will give me credit for my openness.

From my childhood they fed me books, and because people convinced me that these could give me clear and certain knowledge of everything useful in life, I was extremely eager to learn them. But no sooner had I completed the whole course of study that normally takes one straight into the ranks of the ‘learned’ than I completely changed my mind ·about what this education could do for me·. For I found myself tangled in so many doubts and errors that I came to think that my attempts to become educated had done me no good except to give me a steadily widening view of my ignorance! ·Could I infer anything quite general from this failure on myself in particular? I couldn’t legitimately do so if •the college I attended was no good, or if •I was slack in my studies, or if •I wasn’t intelligent enough, or if •I happened to be living at a time when the life of the intellect was generally at a low ebb. But none of these seemed to me to be so·.

•I was in one of the most famous colleges in Europe: ‘If there are learned men anywhere in the world,’ I thought, ‘there must be some here.’ •I had learned there everything that the others were learning; indeed, not being satisfied with the sciences [here = ‘theoretically organised topics of study’] that they taught us, I had whipped through every book I could get my hands on concerning the sciences that are considered most abstruse and extraordinary. Along with that, •I knew how others judged me, and I didn’t see them regarding me as ·intellectually· inferior to my fellow students,

2

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 1

even though ·some at least of the students were regarded by their teachers as very able·: several of them had already been picked as future replacements for our teachers. And finally, •the present age seemed to me to be as flourishing, and as rich in good minds, as any before it.

This ·quartet of facts· encouraged me to take my own situation as a basis for judging how things stood for other people ·and other times·, and to think there was no knowledge in the world such as I had previously been led to hope for.

But I never lost my respect for the curriculum of the college. I knew that •the languages learned there are necessary if one wants to grasp the works of the ancients; that the charm of •fables awakens the mind; that the memorable deeds encountered in •histories uplift the mind and—if read with discretion—help to shape one’s judgment; that reading •good books is like having a conversation with the most distinguished men of past ages, namely their authors—indeed, a carefully prepared conversation in which they reveal to us only the best of their thoughts; that •oratory has incomparable powers and beauties; that •poetry has quite ravishing delicacy and sweetness; that •mathematics contains some very subtle devices that serve not only to satisfy those who are intrigued by mathematical problems but also to help with all practical and mechanical endeavours and to lessen men’s labours; that writings on •morals contain many very useful teachings and exhortations to virtue; that •theology teaches us the way to heaven; that •philosophy gives us the means of speaking plausibly about any subject and of being admired by the less learned; that •law, medicine, and other sciences bring honours and riches to those who study them; and, finally, that it is good to have studied •all these subjects—even those full of superstition and falsehood—in order to know their true value and guard against being deceived by them.

But I thought I had already spent long enough on languages and on reading the works of the ancients, both their •histories and their •fables. For conversing with people of past centuries is rather like travelling. ·The latter is all right in its way·: it is good to know something of various peoples’ ways of life, so that we may judge our own more soundly and not think—as those who have seen nothing of the world often do—that every departure from our way of life is ridiculous and irrational. But if you spend too much time travelling you will end up being a stranger in your own country; and someone who is too absorbed in studying the practices of past ages usually remains quite ignorant about those of the present century. ·And such studies, whether or not carried to excess, have their own inherent dangers·. •Fables make us imagine many events as possible when they are not. And even the most accurate •histories, if they don’t alter or exaggerate things’ importance so as to provide a better ‘read’, are likely to falsify things in a different way: such histories omit most of the meaner and the less striking factors in a situation, so that what they do include appears in a false light, ·looking grander than it really was·. And a result of that is that those who regulate their conduct by examples drawn from these works are liable to fall into the excesses of the knights-errant in our tales of chivalry, and make plans that they haven’t the power to carry out.

I valued oratory and loved poetry; but I thought that each of these was a mental gift rather than something to be achieved through study. People with the strongest reasoning and the most skill at ordering their thoughts so as to make them clear and intelligible are always the most persuasive, even if they speak only a provincial dialect and have never learned rhetoric. And those who have the most pleasing fancies and know how to express them with the

3

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 1

most embellishment and sweetness would be the best poets even if they knew nothing of poetry as a discipline.

I especially enjoyed mathematics, because of the certainty and evidentness of its reasonings. But I hadn’t yet seen what its real use is: I thought it was of service only in the mechanical arts, and was surprised that on such firm and solid foundations nothing had been built that was more exalted ·than the likes of engineering, road-building, and so on·. I contrasted this situation (·minor structures on a magnificently firm foundation·) with the moral writings of the ancient pagans, which I likened to very proud and magnificent palaces built only on sand and mud (·wonderful structures on shaky foundations·). They praise the virtues, making them appear more admirable than anything else in the world; but they don’t adequately explain how to tell when something is a virtue, and often what they call by this fine name ‘virtue’ is merely an instance of callousness, or vanity, or despair—or parricide!

I revered our theology, and thought I had as much right to reach heaven as anyone. But having learned as a certain fact that the way to heaven is as open to the most ignorant as to the most learned, and that the revealed truths that guide us there are above our intellect, I wouldn’t have ventured to submit them to my weak reasonings. To examine them and succeed in this, I thought, I would need to get special help from heaven and to be more than a mere man.

All I want to say about philosophy are these two things. •Philosophy has been pursued for many centuries by the best minds, and yet everything in it is still disputed and hence doubtful; and I wasn’t so arrogant as to hope to achieve more in philosophy than others had done. •Considering how many different opinions learned men may maintain on a single question—where at most one can be true—I regarded everything that was merely probable as being near enough to false. ·In short, taking the two points in reverse order: I had no confidence in •any of philosophy’s ‘results’ or •in my ability to improve that situation·.

As for the other sciences, in so far as they take their principles from philosophy I thought that nothing solid could have been built on such shaky foundations; and I wasn’t induced to learn them by the honour or the riches they offered. For I had no feeling, thank God, that my circumstances obliged me to make science my profession so as to ease my financial condition; and although I didn’t make a parade of scorning glory, like a Cynic, I wasn’t going to count on glory that I couldn’t hope to get except through false pretences. Finally, as for the false sciences, ·I saw no need to learn more about them in intellectual self-defence·: I thought I already knew their worth well enough not to be open to deception by the promises of an alchemist or the predictions of an astrologer, the tricks of a magician, or the frauds and boasts of those who profess to know more than they do.

That is why, as soon as I was old enough to emerge from the control of my teachers, I entirely abandoned scholarship. Resolving to seek no knowledge except what I could find in myself or read in the great book of the world, I spent the rest of my youth •travelling, •visiting courts and armies, •mixing with people of different temperaments and ranks, •gathering various experiences, •testing myself in the situations that luck put me into, and always •reflecting on whatever came my way so as to profit from it. For it seemed to me that I could find much more truth in the •reasonings that people make about matters that concern their interests than in •a scholar’s closeted reasonings about theoretical matters. In the •former case, if a person judges wrongly he will soon be punished for this by the upshot; whereas in the •latter case there are no practical consequences, and there is nothing

4

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 2

at stake for the scholar except perhaps that the further his conclusions are from common sense the prouder he will be of them because he will have had to use so much more skill and ingenuity in trying to make them plausible! All through this I had an intense desire to learn to distinguish the true from the false, in order to understand my own actions and to proceed with confidence in this life.

It is true that so long as I merely considered the ways of life of other men I found little basis for confidence, observing in them almost as much variation as I had found previously in the opinions of philosophers. The greatest benefit I extracted from these observations was their showing me many things which, although seeming wild and ridiculous to us, are nevertheless commonly accepted and approved in other great nations; which taught me not to believe too firmly anything I had been convinced of only by example and custom. This would gradually free me from many errors that may obscure our natural light and make us less capable of heeding reason. But after I had spent some years pursuing these studies •in the book of the world, and trying to gain some experience, I made a decision one day to undertake studies •within myself too and to use all the powers of my mind in choosing the paths I should follow. This has worked better for me, I think, than if I had never left my country or my books.

Part 2

I was in Germany at the time, having been called by the wars that are still going on there. I was returning to the army from the Emperor’s coronation when the onset of winter held me in one place ·until the weather should clear·. Finding no conversation to help me pass the time, and fortunately having no cares or passions to trouble me, I stayed all day shut up alone in a heated room where I was completely free to talk with myself about my own thoughts. One of the first thoughts to come to me was this: there is usually less perfection in •works composed of several parts and produced by various different craftsmen than there is in •the works of one man. Thus we see that a building started and completed by a single architect will usually be finer and better organized than one that several people have tried to patch up by adapting old walls that had been built for other purposes. Again, these old cities ·of Europe· that have gradually grown from mere villages into large towns are usually less well laid out than the orderly towns that planners lay out as they wish on level ground; so much less that from •the way the buildings are arranged in the old cities—a tall one here, a small one there—and •the way they make the streets crooked and irregular, you would think they had been placed where they are by chance rather than by the will of thinking men. (This isn’t to deny that if you look at the buildings in the old cities individually you will often find that at least as much skill has gone into the making of

5

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 2

them as into those of the planned towns.) And when you consider that ·this is how things stand in old cities although· there have always been officials whose job is to oversee private buildings so as to ensure that they add beauty to public places, you’ll grasp that it’s hard to achieve something perfect by working only on what others have produced. So it seemed to me that peoples who have grown gradually from a half-savage to a civilized state, and have made their laws only when pushed to do so by the troubles that crimes and quarrels have caused, won’t have as good a civil order as do those who from the beginning of their society have observed the basic laws laid down by some wise law-giver. Similarly, the true religion, whose rules are purely God’s work, must certainly be ever so much better ordered than any other religion. And in the human sphere: I believe that if Sparta was at one time very flourishing, this wasn’t because each of its laws was good (seeing that many were very strange and even contrary to good morals), but because they were devised by a single man and hence were all conducive to the same end. And so I thought that since the sciences contained in books—at least those based on merely probable reasoning and not on demonstrations [= ‘strictly, logically, rigorously valid arguments’]—are put together and enlarged piecemeal from the opinions of many different people, they never get as close to the truth as do the simple reasonings that one man of good sense can naturally make concerning anything that comes up. This led me to the thought that because

we were all children before being men, and for years had to be governed by our •desires and our •teachers, which were often in conflict and neither of which always gave us the best advice,

it is almost impossible that our judgments should be as unclouded and as well grounded as they would have been if from the moment of our birth we had had the full use of our reason and had always been guided by it alone.

Admittedly, we never see people pulling down all the houses of a city just so as to rebuild them in a different style to make the streets more attractive; but we do see many individuals having their houses pulled down so as to rebuild them, some even being forced to do so when the houses are in danger of falling down and their foundations are weak. This example convinced me that

it would be truly unreasonable for an individual to •plan to reform a state by changing it from the foundations up, overturning it in order to rebuild it; or to •plan to reform the content of the sciences or the established ways of teaching them in the schools;

but I thought nevertheless that ·something radical could be done at the level of personal intellectual hygiene, namely·:

Regarding the opinions which I had previously held, I couldn’t do better than set out to get rid of them all at one go, so as then to replace them afterwards with better opinions or even with the same ones after I had straightened them out using reason’s plumb-line.

I firmly believed that this would let me conduct my life much better than if I were to build only on old foundations and rely only on principles that I had accepted in my youth without ever examining whether they were true. Even if I were to see various difficulties in this project, they weren’t insurmountable, and weren’t comparable with the difficulties involved in reforming even minor matters affecting public institutions. These large bodies are too difficult to reconstruct once they are overthrown—indeed, too difficult to prop up once they have been shaken—and when they fall there is bound to be a crash. Furthermore, if they have imperfections—and their very diversity ensures that many of them do—these have doubtless been much smoothed over by custom; and custom has even prevented or imperceptibly corrected many

6

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 2

imperfections that couldn’t be dealt with so well by conscious planning. And a last point: it is almost always easier to put up with their imperfections than to put up with changes in them, just as it is much better to follow •the main roads that wind through mountains, which have gradually become smooth and convenient through frequent use, than to try to follow a •straighter route that has one clambering over rocks and descending into canyons.

That is why I can’t in any way approve of those meddlesome and restless characters who, without being called by birth or by fortune to the management of •public affairs, are yet forever thinking up some new reform. If I thought this present work contained the slightest ground for suspecting me of such folly, I would shrink from allowing it to be published. My plan has never gone beyond trying to reform •my own thoughts and to build on a foundation that is all •my own. If I’m pleased enough with my work to present you with this sketch of it, it’s not because I would advise anyone to imitate it. Those on whom God has bestowed more of his favours ·than he has on me· will perhaps have higher aims; but I’m afraid that this project of mine may be too bold for many people. The mere decision to rid myself all the opinions I have hitherto accepted isn’t an example that everyone ought to follow! The world is mostly made up of two types of minds for whom it is quite unsuitable. (1) There are those who, believing themselves cleverer than they are, can’t help •rushing to judgment and can’t •muster the patience to direct all their thoughts in an orderly manner. So that if they once took the liberty of doubting the principles they have accepted and leaving the common path, they would never be able to stay on the straighter path that they ought to take, and would remain lost all their lives. (2) And there are those who are reasonable enough, or modest enough, to think that they can’t distinguish true from false as well as some other people by whom they can be taught. These should be content to follow the opinions of those others rather than to seek better opinions themselves.

As for myself, I would undoubtedly have been among the (2) modest followers if I had had only one teacher, or if I had never known how learned people have always differed from one another in their opinions. ·As things were, I was saved from being a follower by my having no idea of whom to follow·. Back in my college days I discovered that

•nothing can be imagined that is too strange or incredible to have been said by some philosopher!

And since then my travels have taught me that

•when people have views quite contrary to ours, that doesn’t make them barbarians or savages, and that many of them make use of reason at least as much as we do.

I thought, too, that

•someone who has been brought up from infancy among the French or Germans develops into something different from what he would have been if he—the same man, with the same mind—had always lived among the Chinese or among cannibals;

and

•how even in our fashions of dress the very thing that pleased us ten years ago and may please us again ten years hence strikes us now as extravagant and ridiculous.

·These thoughts convinced me that·

•our convictions come much more from custom and example than from any certain knowledge; and •yet when it comes to proving truths that are hard to discover, a majority vote is downright worthless, because one man on his own is much more likely to hit upon such truths than a whole population is.

7

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 2

So I couldn’t choose anyone whose opinions seemed to me preferable to those of all others, and I found myself pretty much forced to become my own guide.

But, like a man walking alone in the dark, I resolved to go so slowly and to keep looking around me so warily that even if I didn’t get far I would at least be sure not to fall. And I wouldn’t even •start ·my project of· completely rejecting opinions that had slipped into my belief system without being introduced there by reason, until I had •first spent long enough planning the work I was undertaking and looking for the true method of getting all the knowledge my mind was capable of having.

In my younger days my philosophical studies had included some •logic, and my mathematical studies some •geometrical analysis and •algebra. These three skills or sciences, it seemed to me, ought to contribute something to my plan. But on further examination I observed with regard to •logic that syllogisms and most of its other techniques are of less use for learning things than for explaining to others the things they already know (or even, as in Lully’s system, for speaking without judgment about matters about which one knows nothing). Logic does contain many excellent and true precepts, but these are mixed in with so much other harmful or superfluous stuff that it is almost as difficult to separate out the truth from the rest as it is to pull a Diana or a Minerva from a rough block of marble ·by separating out the wanted goddess-shaped marble from the unwanted remainder·. As to the •·geometrical· analysis of the ancients and the •algebra of the moderns, they cover only highly abstract matters and seem not to be useful for anything; besides which ancient geometrical analysis is always so closely tied to the study of figures [here = ‘shapes’] that it can’t exercise the intellect without greatly tiring the imagination; and modern algebra is so confined to certain rules and symbols that what emerges from this is not •a science that develops the mind but rather •a confused and obscure art [here = ‘set of techniques’] that entangles it. So I thought I should look for some other method that would have the advantages of these three without their defects. Now, just as a state is much better governed when it has only a few laws that are strictly obeyed than when it has a great many laws that can provide an excuse for vices, so I thought that in place of the large number of rules that make up logic I would find the following four to be sufficient, provided that I made and kept to a strong resolution always to obey them. (1) The first was never to accept anything as true if I didn’t have evident knowledge of its truth: that is, carefully to avoid jumping to conclusions and preserving old opinions, and to include in my judgments only what presented itself to my mind so vividly and so clearly that I had no basis for calling it in question. [That last sentence involves a crucial translation point that should be explained. It concerns the French adjectives

clair and distinct

and their Latin cousins clarus and distinctus, and of course their corresponding adverbs. Those two have always been translated by

‘clear’ and ‘distinct’,

in that order, but this time-honoured translation is demonstrably wrong. A better translation is ‘vivid and clear’ (in that order), which is adopted here. The crucial point concerns clair. The word can mean ‘clear’ in our sense, and when Descartes uses it outside the clair et distinct phrase, it sometimes seems to be in that sense. But in that phrase he uses clair in its other meaning—its more common meaning in French—of ‘bright’ or ‘vivid’ or the like, as in lumière claire = ‘broad daylight’. If in the phrase clair et distinct Descartes meant clair in its lesser meaning of ‘clear’, then what is there left for distinct to mean? Descartes’s one explanation of the two parts this phrase, in his Principles of Philosophy 1:45–6, completely condemns the usual translation. He writes:

I call a perception claire when it is present and accessible to the attentive mind—just as we say that we see something clairement when it is present to the eye’s gaze and stimulates it with a sufficient degree of strength and accessibility. I call a perception

8

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 2

distincte if, as well as being claire, it is so sharply separated from all other perceptions that every part of it is claire..... The example of pain shows that a perception can be claire without being distincte but not vice versa. When someone feels an intense pain, his perception of it is claire, but it isn’t always distincte, because people often get this perception muddled with an obscure judgment they make about something that they think exists in the painful spot....and so on.

He can’t be saying anything as stupid as that intense pain is always clear! His point is that pain is vivid, up-front, not shady or obscure. And for an idea to be distincte is for every nook and cranny of it to be vivid; which is not a bad way of saying that it is in our sense ‘clear’. •Three times in this version, ‘see clearly’ will occur as a translation of voir clairement; perhaps on these occasions Descartes has in mind partly the thought of seeing something in a sharply detailed way, but he certain has in mind the thought of seeing something right out in the open, this being the notion that also goes with ‘vivid’. •The time-honoured wrong translation has, among its other mischiefs, tended to mask the great extent to which Descartes thought in terms of openness, removal of obscurity, letting light shine on things.]

(2) The second ·was· to divide each of the difficulties I examined into as many parts as possible and as might be required in order to resolve them better.

(3) The third ·was· to direct my thoughts in an orderly manner, by •starting with the simplest and most easily known objects in order to move up gradually to knowledge of the most complex, and •by stipulating some order even among objects that have no natural order of precedence.

(4) And the last ·was· to make all my enumerations so complete, and my reviews so comprehensive, that I could be sure that I hadn’t overlooked anything.

Those long chains of very simple and easy inferences that geometers customarily use to arrive at their most difficult demonstrations had led me to think that •all the things that human beings can know are inter-deducible in that same way, and that •nothing can be too remote to be reached eventually, or too well hidden to be discovered—just as long as we refrain from accepting as true anything that isn’t, and always keep to the order required for deducing one thing from another. And I didn’t have to look far for the things to start with, for I knew already that it must be with the things that are simplest and most easily known. Bearing in mind also that of all those who have pursued truth in the sciences only the mathematicians have been able to find any demonstrations—that is to say, certain and evident reasonings—I had no doubt that I should start with the very things they studied, though only so as to get my mind used to nourishing itself on truths and not being satisfied with bad reasoning. But in this I wasn’t aiming to try to learn all the special sciences—·such as astronomy, music, and optics·—that are commonly called ‘mathematical’. For I saw that although they deal with different objects they are alike in considering nothing but the various relations or proportions that hold between these objects, and I thought it would be better to study only these proportions taken generally. When I thought of them as proportions amongst objects of some kind, it would only be so as to make it easier for me to know the proportions themselves; and I wouldn’t tie the proportions down to these objects, because I wanted to be able later on to apply them all the better to any others that they might fit. Next I observed that in order to know these proportions I would need sometimes to consider them separately, and sometimes merely to remember or understand many together; and this led me to think that in order the better to consider them separately I should take them to be proportions between lines, because I didn’t find anything simpler, or anything I could represent more clearly to my imagination and senses. But in order to remember or understand several together, I needed to designate them by

9

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 2

the briefest possible symbols. This would enable me to take over all that is best in geometrical analysis and in algebra, using the one to correct all the defects of the other.

Strictly observing the few rules I had chosen, I began to tackle problems in •geometry and •algebra, beginning with the simplest and most general and using each truth I found as a rule for finding further truths. And I venture to say that just by proceeding in this manner I became really good at unravelling all the questions that fall under •these two sciences—so good that in the two or three months I spent on this work not only did I solve many problems that I had previously thought very difficult but also, it seemed to me towards the end, even with problems where I was still in the dark I could work out how and how far it was possible to find a solution. This claim won’t appear too arrogant if you consider that since there is only one truth concerning any matter, whoever discovers it knows as much about the matter as can be known (if a child who has been taught arithmetic does an addition sum following the rules, he can be sure of having found everything the human mind could find regarding that particular sum). It comes down to this: the method—·my method·—that tells us to follow the correct order, and to enumerate exactly all the relevant factors, contains everything that gives certainty to the rules of arithmetic.

But what I liked best about this method was that by following it I was sure always to use my reason as well as was in my power (perhaps not perfectly). Moreover, as I employed the method I felt my mind getting more and more into the habit of conceiving things sharply and clearly; and as I didn’t restrict the method to any particular subject-matter, I hoped to apply it to the problems of the •other sciences as usefully as I had to those of algebra. Not that I would have ventured at the outset to tackle every problem that might arise, for that would in itself have been contrary to the order that the method prescribes. But observing that the principles of •these sciences must all be derived from philosophy, in which I hadn’t yet discovered anything certain, I thought that the first need was to try to establish some certain principles in philosophy. And since this is the most important thing in the world, and the one that is most endangered by rushing to conclusions and holding on to ungrounded old opinions, I thought I shouldn’t try to pull it off until I had •reached a more mature age than twenty-three (my age at the time), and had •spent a long time preparing myself for this. The preparation was to involve uprooting from my mind all the wrong opinions I had accepted up till then, amassing a variety of experiences to serve later as the subject-matter of my reasonings, and constantly employing the method I had imposed on myself, in order to become increasingly assured in my use of it.

10

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 3

Part 3

If you want to rebuild the house you live in, it isn’t enough just to •pull it down, to •arrange for materials and architects (or else train yourself in architecture), and to •have carefully drawn up the plans; you must also •provide yourself with somewhere else to live comfortably while the work is going on. Similarly, so as not to be indecisive in my actions during the time when reason obliged me to be so in my judgments, and in order to live as well as I could during this time, I formed for myself a provisional moral code consisting of just three or four maxims, which I should like to tell you about.

(1) The first was to obey the laws and customs of my country, holding constantly to the religion in which by God’s grace I had been instructed from my childhood, and governing myself in all other matters—·i.e. all the ones not settled by the law of the land or my religion·—on the basis of the most moderate and least extreme opinions, the opinions commonly accepted in practice by the most sensible of the people with whom I would have to live. For I had begun at this time to count my own opinions as worthless, because I wanted to examine them all, and didn’t see how I could do better than ·in the meantime· to follow those of the most sensible men. And although the Persians or Chinese may have men as sensible as any of ours, I thought •that it would serve me best to be guided by those with whom I was going to live, and—·a second reason for going this way·—•that in order to discover what opinions people really held I had to attend to their actions rather than their words. ·There are two reasons for this last point·. With our declining standards of behaviour, few people are willing to say everything that they believe; and anyway many people don’t know what they believe, since •believing something and •knowing that you believe it are different acts of thinking, and you could have one without the other. Where many opinions were equally well accepted, I chose only the most moderate, both because

these are always the most convenient in practice, and probably the best (excess being usually bad),

and also so that

if I made a mistake, it wouldn’t take me as far from the right path as if I had chosen one extreme when I ought to have adopted the other.

Coming down to details: I counted as excessive all promises by which we give up some of our freedom. Not that I disapproved of laws that allow people to make vows or contracts that •oblige them to persevere in some worthy project (or even, for the security of commerce, in something that is neither good nor bad)—this being a remedy for the inconstancy of weak minds. ·But I didn’t see myself as bound by any contract to remain faithful to any of my earlier beliefs·. I saw nothing in the world that remained always in the same state, and for my part I was determined to make my judgments ever more perfect, rather than worse; so I thought I would be sinning against good sense if I took my previous approval of something as •obliging me to regard it as good later on, when it had perhaps ceased to be good or I no longer regarded it as such.

(2) My second maxim was to be as firm and decisive in my actions as I could, and to follow even the most doubtful opinions, once I had adopted them, as constantly as if they had been quite certain. In this I would be imitating travellers who find themselves lost in a forest: rather than •wandering about in all directions or (even worse) •staying in one place, they should •keep walking as straight as they can in one

11

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 3

direction, not turning aside for slight reasons, even if their choice of direction was a matter of mere chance in the first place; for even if this doesn’t bring them to where they want to go it will at least bring them to somewhere that is probably better for them than the middle of a forest. Similarly, since in everyday life we often have to act without delay, it is a most certain truth that when we can’t pick out the truest opinions we should follow the most probable ones. And when no opinions appear more probable than any others, we should nevertheless adopt some; and then we should regard those as being—from a practical point of view—not doubtful but most true and certain, because the reason that made us pick on them is itself true and certain. This maxim could free me from all the regrets and remorse that usually trouble the consciences of those weak and stumbling characters who set out on some supposedly good course of action and then later, in their inconstancy, judge it to be bad.

(3) My third maxim was to try always to master •myself rather than •fortune, and change •my desires rather than changing •how things stand in the world. This involved getting the habit of believing that nothing lies entirely within our power except our thoughts, so that after we have done our best in dealing with matters external to us, whatever we fail to achieve is absolutely impossible so far as we are concerned. This seemed to me to be enough, all by itself, to •prevent me from having unsatisfied desires and thus to •make me content. For it is the nature of our will to want only what our intellect presents to it as somehow possible; so if we regard all external goods as equally beyond our power, that will certainly save us from regrets over not having goods that seem to be our birthright but which we are deprived of through no fault of our own, any more than we regret not owning the kingdom of China or of Mexico! ‘Making a virtue of necessity’—as the phrase goes—we shan’t want to be healthy when ill, or free when imprisoned, any more than we now want to have bodies as hard as diamonds or wings to fly like the birds. But I admit that it takes long practice and repeated meditation to get used to seeing everything in this light. I think this was the secret of those philosophers of old who could escape from being dominated by fortune and, despite suffering and poverty, could rival their gods in happiness. By constantly busying themselves with thoughts about the limits that nature had placed on them, they became thoroughly convinced that nothing was in their power except their own thoughts, which was enough to prevent them from being attracted to other things. They were so absolutely in control of their thoughts that this gave them some reason to think themselves richer, more powerful, freer and happier than any men who—however favoured by nature and fortune they may be—don’t have this philosophy and so never get such control over all their desires.

[We now come to Descartes’s fourth rule of conduct (he didn’t head them with numerals). Why at the start of Part 3 did he say that he had adopted ‘three or four’ moral rules? The excellent editor Ferdinand Alquié conjectures that this is because Descartes sees the fourth as radically unlike the others: they could be generalised to any reasonable person, whereas the fourth is strictly personal to Descartes himself.]

(4) Finally, to conclude this moral code, I decided to review the various occupations of human life, so as to try to choose the best. Without wanting to say anything about other people’s occupations, I thought it would be best for me to continue with the very one I was then engaged in, and devote my whole life to cultivating my reason and advancing as far as I could in the knowledge of the truth, following my self-imposed method. Since beginning to use this method I had felt such extreme satisfactions that I didn’t think one could enjoy any sweeter or purer ones in this life [= ‘before we get to heaven’]. Every day my method led me to discover truths

12

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 3

that seemed to me to be quite important and not widely known; my pleasure in this so filled my mind that nothing else mattered to me. The sole basis for maxims (1)-(3) was my plan to continue my self-instruction, ·i.e. the course of action decided on in (4)·. For God has given each of us a light to distinguish truth from falsehood, and I wouldn’t have (1) thought myself obliged to rest content for a single moment with the opinions of others if I hadn’t intended in due course to bring my own judgment to bear on them; I couldn’t have (2) avoided having scruples about following these opinions, if I hadn’t hoped to take every opportunity to discover better ones if there were any; and I couldn’t have (3) limited my desires, or been happy, if I hadn’t been following a path that I thought was sure to lead me to

all the knowledge of which I was capable,

and in this way to lead me to

all the true goods that were within my power.

For our will tends to pursue (or avoid) only what our intellect represents as good (or bad), so all we need in order to act well is to judge well; and judging as well as we can is all we need to •act as well as we can—that is to say, •to acquire all the virtues and in general all the other attainable goods. With this certainty, one cannot fail to be happy.

Having assured myself of these maxims and set them on one side—·out of harm’s way, so to speak·—along with the truths of faith, which have always been foremost among my beliefs, I judged that I could freely go about ridding myself of all my other opinions. As I hoped to be able to carry this through better by talking with other men than by staying shut up in the stove-heated room where I had all these thoughts, I resumed my travels before the winter was over. For the next nine years [1619–28] I did nothing but roam from place to place, trying to be a spectator rather than an actor in all the dramas that are played out on the world’s stage. Concentrating on the points in every subject that might make it suspect and lead us into mistakes, I kept uprooting from my mind any errors that might previously have slipped into it. In this I wasn’t copying the sceptics, who doubt purely for the sake of doubting and pretend to be always undecided; on the contrary, my whole aim was to reach certainty—to push away the loose earth and sand so as to get to rock or clay. I had pretty fair success in this, I think. ·Here are three features of my procedure that contributed to its success·. •When trying to expose the falsity or uncertainty of any proposition, what I brought against it were arguments that were open and certain, not feeble conjectures. •I never encountered any proposition so doubtful that I couldn’t get from it some fairly certain conclusion, even if it was only the conclusion that it contained nothing certain! •Just as in demolishing an old house we usually keep the materials for use in building a new one, so in destroying all those opinions of mine that I judged to be ill-founded I made various observations and acquired many experiences that I have since used in establishing more certain opinions. Moreover, I continued following my self-imposed method; as well as taking care in general to conduct all my thoughts according to its rules, I occasionally set aside a few hours for ·practice, training exercises·, applying it to mathematical problems and to certain other problems that I could put into something like mathematical form by separating out from them all the principles of other sciences that I didn’t find sufficiently secure. (You will see me perform that kind of separating-out in several of the problems discussed later in this book). Thus, while appearing to live like those who, with no aim except to lead an agreeable and blameless life and to keep their pleasures free from vices, pursue pleasure and fight off boredom by engaging in every honest pastime, I still pursued my project and may have gone further in

13

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 4

the knowledge of the truth than I would have if I had done nothing but read books or mix with educated men.

Those nine years passed by, however, without my •taking a side on any of the questions that are commonly debated among the learned, or •starting to look for the basis of any philosophy more certain than the commonly accepted one. The example of many fine intellects who had previously had this project, but hadn’t met with success (it seemed to me), made me imagine that the task was so hard that I wouldn’t have ventured to •undertake it so soon if I hadn’t become aware that some people were spreading the rumour that I had already •completed it. I can’t say what basis the rumour had. If my conversation contributed anything to it, that must have been because I admitted my ignorance more openly than is customary for those with a little learning, and perhaps also because I showed the reasons I had for doubting many things that others regard as certain; it won’t have been because I boasted of some positive doctrine. But being honest enough not to want to be taken for what I was not, I thought I should try by every means to become worthy of the reputation that was given me ·by the rumours·. Exactly eight years ago this desire made me resolve to move away from any place where I might have acquaintances and retire to this country [Holland], •where the long duration of the war has led to such a high level of ·civil· discipline that the armies maintained here seem to serve only to make the pleasures of peace all the more secure, and •where, amidst this great mass of busy people who are more concerned with their own affairs than curious about other people’s, I have been able to lead a life as solitary and withdrawn as if I were in the most remote desert, while lacking none of the comforts found in the most populous cities.

Part 4

I don’t know whether I should tell you of the first meditations that I had there, for they are perhaps too metaphysical [here = ‘abstract’] and uncommon for everyone’s taste. But I have to report on them if you are to judge whether the foundations I have chosen are firm enough. I had long been aware that in practical life one sometimes has to act on opinions that one knows to be quite uncertain just as if they were unquestionably •true (I remarked on this above). But now that I wanted to devote myself solely to the search for truth, I thought I needed to do the exact opposite—to reject as if it were absolutely •false everything regarding which I could imagine the least doubt, so as to see whether this left me with anything entirely indubitable to believe. Thus,

•I chose to suppose that nothing was such as our senses led us to imagine,

because our senses sometimes deceive us. Also,

•I rejected as unsound all the arguments I had previously taken as demonstrative [= ‘absolutely rigorous’] proofs,

because some men make mistakes in reasoning, even in the simplest questions in geometry, and commit logical fallacies; and I judged that I was as open to this as anyone else. Lastly,

14

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 4

•I decided to pretend that everything that had ever entered my mind was no more true than the illusions of my dreams,

because all the mental states we are in while awake can also occur while we sleep ·and dream·, without having any truth in them. But no sooner had I embarked on this project than I noticed that while I was trying in this way to think everything to be false it had to be the case that •I, who was thinking this, was •something. And observing that this truth

I am thinking, therefore I exist

was so firm and sure that not even the most extravagant suppositions of the sceptics could shake it, I decided that I could accept it without scruple as the first principle of the philosophy I was seeking. [This ‘first principle’ could be (1) ‘I exist’ or (2) the connection between ‘I am thinking’ and ‘I exist’—the uncertainty in this version echoes that in Descartes’s French.]

Then I looked carefully into what I was. I saw that while I could pretend that I had no body and that there was no world and no place for me to be in, I still couldn’t pretend that I didn’t exist. I saw on the contrary that from the mere fact that I thought about doubting the truth of other things, it followed quite evidently and certainly that I existed; whereas if I had merely stopped thinking altogether [here = ‘stopped being in any conscious mental state’], even if everything else I had ever imagined had been true, I ·would have· had no reason to believe that I existed. This taught me that I was a substance whose whole essence or nature is simply to think [here = ‘to be in conscious mental states’], and which doesn’t need any place, or depend on any material thing, in order to exist. Accordingly this me—this soul that makes me what I am—•is entirely distinct from the body, •is easier to know than the body, and •would still be just what it is even if the body didn’t exist.

After that I considered in general what is needed for a proposition to be true and certain: I had just found one that I knew was true and certain, I thought that I ought also to know what this certainty consists in. I observed that the proposition ‘I am thinking, therefore I exist’ has nothing about it to assure me that I am speaking the truth ·when I assert it· except that I see very clearly that in order to think it is necessary to exist. This convinced me that I could take it as a general rule that the things we conceive very vividly and very clearly are all true; but ·this isn’t as powerfully simple a rule as you might think, because· there is some difficulty in telling which conceptions are really clear.

Next, I reflected on the fact that I was doubting, and that consequently I wasn’t wholly perfect (for I saw clearly that it is a greater perfection to know than to doubt). This led me to the question:

Where did I get my ability to think of something more perfect than I am?

and I drew the obvious conclusion that this ability had to come from—·had to be caused by·—something that was in fact more perfect than me. ·To explain why I reached that conclusion, I should first explain why· I wasn’t exercised about such questions as

Where did I get my ability to think of the heavens, the earth, light, heat (and so on)?

It was because I saw nothing in those thoughts that seemed to make them superior to me, ·i.e. more perfect than I am·; and ·that opened the door to a pair of possible explanations for my ability to have them·. (1) If the thoughts in question were true, they could depend on—·i.e. come from·—some perfection in my own nature. (2) If they weren’t true, I could have derived them from •nothingness - meaning that they could be in me because I had some •defect. But neither of these explanations could hold for the idea of a being more

15

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 4

perfect than me. For it was obviously impossible (2) to get this from nothingness; and I couldn’t have (1) derived it from myself, because the proposition

(1) Something resulted from and depends on something less perfect than it is

is just as contradictory as

(2) Something resulted from nothingness.

So the only possibility left was that the idea had been put into me by •something that truly was more perfect than I was, •something indeed having every perfection of which I could have any idea, that is—to explain myself in one word—by •God. To this I added that since I knew of some perfections that I didn’t myself have, I wasn’t the only being that existed....,and there had to be some other more perfect being on which I depended and from which I had acquired everything that I had. For if I had existed alone, not depending on anything else, so that my meagre ration of perfections had come from myself, then by that same line of reasoning

•I could have derived from myself all the remaining perfections that I knew I lacked,

and thus

•I could myself have been infinite, eternal, unchanging, omniscient, omnipotent;

in short,

•I could have had all the perfections that I had been able to discover in God.

[What follows starts with the word Car = ‘For’. Descartes seems to be promising a reason for what he has just said, but the promise isn’t kept.] For, according to the arguments I have just presented: in order to know as much of God’s nature as my nature allows me to know, all I needed was to consider, for each property of which I had some idea, whether having it was a perfection or not; and I was sure that God doesn’t have any of the properties that indicate any imperfection, but that he does have all the others. Thus I saw that God could not have doubt, inconstancy, sadness and the like, since I myself would have been very glad to be free from them, ·which shows that they are imperfections·. Furthermore, I had ideas of many perceptible bodies (even if I was dreaming, and everything that I saw or imagined was false, I still couldn’t deny that the ideas of bodies were in my mind). But since I had already recognized very clearly in my own case that intellectual nature is distinct from bodily nature, and as I observed that

•if a thing is composed ·of simpler elements· in any way, that shows that it is dependent on something else,

and that

•dependence is obviously a defect,

I concluded that

•it couldn’t be a perfection in God to be composed of these two natures—·the intellectual and the bodily·—and consequently that he was not composed of them;

and also that if there were any bodies in the world, or any intelligences or other natures that weren’t wholly perfect, their being must depend on God’s power in such a way that they couldn’t stay in existence for a single moment without him.

After that, I wanted to seek other truths: I took up the subject-matter of geometry, which I conceived of as •a continuous body, or •a space indefinitely extended in length, breadth and height or depth, and divisible into different parts that can have various shapes and sizes, and can be moved and swapped around in all sorts of way (geometers assume that their subject-matter has all these properties). I went through some of their simpler proofs, and noted that it’s because we conceive them as evident [= ‘obviously true’] that

16

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 4

we all regard them as utterly certain. I noted also that these demonstrations gave no assurance—none—of the existence of their subject-matter. For example, I saw that given a triangle its three angles of must equal two right angles; but I saw nothing assuring me that there are any triangles in the world. In contrast with that, when I returned to the scrutiny of the idea I had of a perfect being, I found that

this idea of a perfect being included existence

in the same way as—or even more evidently than—

the idea of a triangle includes the equality of its three angles to two right angles

or

the idea of a sphere includes the equidistance from the centre of all the points on the surface.

Thus I concluded that the existence of this perfect being, God, is at least as certain as any geometrical proof.

Why are many people convinced that there is some difficulty in knowing God, and even in knowing what their soul is? It’s because they never raise their minds above things that can be perceived by the senses: they are so used to •thinking of things only in the way that is specially suited to material things, namely by •imagining ·or picturing· them, that they regard as unintelligible ·or •unthinkable· anything that they can’t •imagine. This shows up in the fact that even the scholastic philosophers take it as a maxim that there is nothing in the intellect that wasn’t previously in the senses; ·which leads people to find God and the soul problematic, because· it is certain that the ideas of God and of the soul have never been ‘in the senses’! Trying to •understand these ideas through one’s •imagination strikes me as being like trying to •hear sounds or smell odours through •the use of one’s eyes. ·Actually, trying-to-understand-through-imagination is even more absurd than trying-to-hear-or-smell-with-theeyes, because· there is this difference: the sense of sight gives us as much assurance of the reality of its objects as do the senses of smell and hearing, whereas our imagination and our senses could never assure us of anything without the aid of our understanding.

Finally, if you are still not really convinced of the existence of God and of your soul by the arguments I have presented, I tell you this: everything else of which you may think you are •more sure—such as your having a body, there being stars and an earth, and the like—is •less certain. For although we have enough certainty for everyday practical purposes about these things, so that it seems wild and irresponsible to call them in question, nevertheless when it is a question of metaphysical certainty we have to admit that there are good reasons for not being entirely sure about them. We need only observe that in sleep we may imagine that we have a different body and see different stars and a different earth, without any of these things being real. ·This is a reason for having some uncertainty about the existence of our body, the stars, and so on·, because: how do we know that the mental states that come to us in dreams are any more false than the others, seeing that they are often just as lively and sharp? Let the best minds study this question as much as they like, I don’t think they’ll be able to give any reason that removes this doubt unless they presuppose the existence of God. For, in the first place, what I took just now as a rule, namely that whatever we conceive very vividly and clearly is true, is assured only because •God exists and •is a perfect being, and because •everything in us comes from him. It follows that our ideas or notions, being real things that get from God everything that is vivid and clear in them, must be true in every respect in which they are vivid and clear. So if we quite often have ideas containing some falsity, this can only be because there is something confused and shadowy in them; for their confusion etc. is something they share

17

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 5

with nothingness, which means that they are in us in this confused state only because we aren’t completely perfect. And it is evident that it’s just as contradictory to suppose that falsity or imperfection as such should come from God as to suppose that truth or perfection should come from nothingness. But if we didn’t know that everything real and true within us comes from a perfect and infinite being, then, however vivid and clear our ideas were, we would have no reason to be sure that they had the perfection of being true.

But once the knowledge of God and the soul has made us certain of this rule, it is easy to recognize that the things we imagine in dreams shouldn’t make us doubt the truth of the experiences we have when awake. For if someone happened even in sleep to have some very clear idea (if, say, a ·dreaming· geometer devised some new proof), his being asleep wouldn’t prevent the idea from being true. The commonest error of our dreams consists in their representing various objects to us in the same way as our external senses do; but it doesn’t matter—·i.e. it doesn’t imply anything specially about dreams·—that this may lead us to doubt the truth of such ideas, for often they can also mislead us without our being asleep; for example, people with jaundice see everything as yellow, and stars or other very distant bodies appear to us much smaller than they are. For after all, whether we are awake or asleep, we ought never to let ourselves be convinced except by the evidentness of our reason. Note that I say ‘our reason’, not ‘our imagination’ or ‘our senses’. Even though we •have a vividly open view of the sun, we mustn’t judge on that account that it is only as large as we see it; and we can clearly •imagine a lion’s head on a goat’s body without having to conclude from this that a chimera exists in the world. For reason doesn’t insist that what we thus •see or •imagine is true. But it does insist that all our ideas or notions must have some foundation of truth; for otherwise it wouldn’t be possible that God, who is all-perfect and all-truthful, should have placed them in us. Now, sometimes our imaginings in sleep are at least as lively and detailed as in waking life, but our reasonings when we are asleep are never so evident or complete as when we are awake; so reason also insists that, since our thoughts can’t all be true because we aren’t perfect, what truth they do possess must inevitably be found in the thoughts we have when awake, rather than in our dreams.

Part 5

I would like to go on with this, and present the whole chain of other •truths that I deduced from these first ones. But this would involve me in discussing here many questions that are being debated among the learned, and I don’t want to get into those quarrels. [This presumably refers to Descartes’s views in physics, which contradicted the Aristotelian physics that was still dominant in the universities.] So I think it will be better if I don’t follow my inclination and merely say in general what •those other truths are, and leave it to wiser heads to decide whether it would be useful for the public to be told about them in more detail. I have always stuck by my resolve •not to assume any principles except the one I have just used to demonstrate the existence of God and of the soul, and •not to accept anything as true unless it struck me as more open

18

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 5

and more certain than the demonstrations of the geometers once seemed to be. And yet I venture to say that ·even under those constraints· it didn’t take me long to satisfy myself regarding all the chief difficulties usually discussed in philosophy. And I discovered certain laws that God has established in nature; he has implanted notions of these laws in our minds, in such a way that after adequate reflection we can’t doubt that the laws are exactly observed in everything that exists or occurs in the world. Moreover, by considering what follows from these laws I have discovered (it seems to me) many truths that are more useful and important than anything I had previously learned or even hoped to learn.

I tried to explain the most important of these truths in a treatise that certain considerations prevent me from publishing, and I know of no better way to make them known than by summarizing its contents. [Descartes’s treatise The World was completed in about 1632—five years before the present work. His reasons for not publishing it are given starting on page 26.] I had planned to include in that work everything I thought I knew about the nature of material things at the time when I was poised to start writing it, ·but that turned out to be too much to tackle all at once·. A painter can’t represent all the different sides of a solid body equally well on his flat canvas, and so he chooses one principal side, sets it facing the light, and shades the others so that they are seen only in the course of looking at the favoured side. Well, in just the same way, fearing that I couldn’t put into my discourse everything that I wanted to, ·I started by (so to speak) letting daylight shine on just •one face of it; specifically·, I undertook merely to expound quite fully what I understood about •light, and then, as the occasions arose, ·to let the shaded sides of my object (so to speak) enter the picture, one at a time. That is·, I planned to add something about •the sun and fixed stars, because almost all light comes from them; about •the heavens, because they transmit light; about •planets, comets and the earth, because they reflect light; about •the bodies on this planet, because they are either coloured or transparent or luminous, and finally about •man, because it is he who sees light. But I wanted to keep these matters still somewhat in the shadows, so as to be free to say what I thought about them without having to follow or to refute the opinions of the learned. My plan for doing this was to leave •our world wholly to the learned folk to argue about, and to speak solely about what would be the case in •a new world that would exist if

God now •created somewhere in imaginary spaces enough matter to compose a world; variously and randomly •agitated the different parts of this matter so as to create as confused a chaos as any poets could dream up; and then did nothing but •allow nature to unfold in accordance with the laws he had established.

·I shall sketch what I did with this supposition, in seven episodes·. (1) I described this matter, giving an account of it that I tried—successfully, it seems to me—to make as openly plain and intelligible as anything except what I have just said about God and the soul. ·As part of this search for clarity·, I explicitly stipulated that this matter had none of those ‘forms’ or ‘qualities’ that the scholastics argue about; allowed it to have only properties that our mind knows so naturally that no-one could even pretend not to. (2) I showed what the laws of nature were [= ‘are’?], and arguing solely from the infinite perfections of God I tried to demonstrate all those laws that might have been called into question, and to show that they are such that even if God created many worlds there couldn’t have been any in which these laws didn’t hold. (3) I then showed how •these laws had the result that most of the matter of this chaos had to resolve itself

19

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 5

into a certain orderly arrangement that made it resemble our heavens [here = ‘sky’]; and how at the same time •some of the parts of matter had to form an earth, some to form planets and comets, and yet other parts to form a sun and fixed stars. (4) And here I spread myself on the subject of light, explaining at some length •the nature of the light that had to be present in the sun and the stars, •how from there it travelled instantaneously across the immense distances of the heavens, and •how it bounced off the planets and comets towards the earth. (5) To this I added many points about the substance, position, movement and all the various qualities of these heavens and stars; and I thought I took this far enough to show that any features observed in the heavens and stars of our world would—or at least could—also be features of the ·imaginary· world I was describing. (6) I went on from there to speak of the earth in particular: •how, although I had explicitly stipulated that God had put no gravity into the matter of which it was formed, all its parts nevertheless tended exactly towards its centre; •how, there being water and air on the earth’s surface, the lay-out of the heavens and heavenly bodies and especially the moon had to cause an ebb and flow exactly like that of our tides, and also an east-to-west current of both water and air like the one we observe between the tropics; •how mountains, seas, springs and rivers could be formed naturally there, and •how metals could appear in mines, plants grow in fields, and generally •how all the bodies we call ‘mixed’ or ‘composite’ could come into being there. (7) Among other things, I worked hard to get out into the open and fully understood everything about the nature of fire, because as far I know it’s the world’s only source of light other than the stars. Thus I showed •how fire is formed, •how it is fuelled, •how sometimes it gives off heat but no light, and sometimes light without heat; •how it can produce different colours and other qualities in different bodies; •how it melts some bodies and hardens others; •how it can consume almost all bodies, or turn them into ashes and smoke; and finally •how it can through the sheer power of its action turn these ashes into glass. I took special pleasure in describing the formation of glass, because it seems to me as wonderful a transmutation as any in nature.

Still, I didn’t mean to infer from all this that our world was created in the way I had been describing, for it is much more likely that from the beginning God made our world just as it had to be. But if we think of material things as developing gradually out of chaos, their nature is easier to grasp than if we considered them only in their ·present· completed form. And there is nothing wrong with believing that God could have brought them about in that manner, starting with chaos, establishing the laws of nature, and then allowing nature to develop in a normal way in accordance with those laws. In particular, that belief doesn’t malign the miracle of God’s creation of the world. It is certain—and theologians generally agree—that God’s activity in now preserving the world is just the same as his earlier activity of creating it, ·so the ‘miracle of creation’ is with us in full strength even now, whether or not the material world began in chaos·.

[A long tradition, going back to Plato, held that plants are special in having ‘vegetative souls’, lower animals in also having ‘sensitive souls’, and humans in having ‘rational souls’ as well as the other two. In this paragraph, Descartes describes a thought-experiment concerning a possible living human body which he takes not to be equipped with a rational soul or any substitute for one; he tacitly rules out the other kinds of soul as well, but allows that something in this human body—namely, fire in the heart—might play the role that earlier thinkers assigned to the vegetative and sensitive souls.] Moving on from •inanimate bodies and •plants, I describe •animals and in particular •men. But I didn’t yet know enough to speak of human bodies in the same way as I did of the other things—that is,

20

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 5

by demonstrating effects from causes, and showing how and from what seeds nature must produce them. So I ·settled for a second supposition, comparable with my supposition of a chaotic material world. Specifically, I· supposed that God formed the body of a man exactly like yours or mine both in outward shape and in the internal lay-out of its organs, making it out of nothing but the matter that I had described and not at first putting into it any rational soul or anything else to function as a vegetative or sensitive soul, except for his kindling in the human body’s heart one of those fires without light that I had already explained, and whose nature I understood to be just the same as that of the fire that heats hay when it has been stored while wet.... And when I looked into what functions could occur in such a body I found precisely the ones that can occur in us without our thinking of them and hence without any co-operation from our soul—i.e. from that part of us, distinct from the body, whose nature is as I have pointed out simply to think. These functions are just the ones in which animals without reason may be said to resemble us. But I could find ·in my supposed living human body· none of the functions that we have only because we are men, the ones that depend on thought; though these all turned up later on, once I had supposed God to create a rational soul and join it to this body in a certain way that I described.

So that you can see how I went about doing this, I shall give my explanation of the movement of the heart and the arteries. [The next few pages—making nearly half of Part 5—are devoted to the circulation of the blood, and the function of the heart. They are of only historical interest, and are omitted here, except for three isolated fragments which help to convey the intellectual tone of the whole passage. [In the second of the three, the phrase ‘mathematical demonstrations’ means merely ‘explanations conducted in terms of materialistic mechanism’. Descartes isn’t claiming to have done this work a priori; he is well aware that it is thoroughly empirical.]] •To readers who don’t know any anatomy: before going on, please arrange to observe someone dissecting the heart of some large animal with lungs (for such a heart is in all respects enough like that of a man), and get him to show you its two chambers or cavities.... •Those who don’t know the force of mathematical demonstrations and aren’t used to distinguishing true reasons from mere probabilities may be tempted to reject this explanation without examining it. To head them off, I would advise them that the movement I have just explained follows purely from

the layout of the organs of the heart, which can be seen with the naked eye, the heat in the heart, which can be felt with the fingers, and the nature of the blood, which can be discovered empirically;

and it follows just as necessarily from those three elements as does the movement of a clock from the force, position, and shape of its counterweights and wheels.... •An English physician—·William Harvey·—must be praised for having made the break-through on this subject. He is the first to teach that at the extremities of the arteries there are many small passages through which the blood they receive from the heart enters the small branches of the veins, from there going immediately back to the heart, so that its course is nothing but a perpetual circulation.

[Two technical terms in this paragraph: ‘animal spirits’ is the name for a supposed superfine fluid which acts as the body’s hydraulic system. The ‘common sense’ was a supposed department of the mind in which inputs from different senses come together and are organized in relation to one another.] I had explained all these matters in enough detail in the treatise I had previously intended to publish. And then I had showed •how the nerves and muscles of the human body must be structured if the animal spirits inside them are to convey enough force to move its limbs....; •what

21

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 5

changes must occur in the brain as causes of waking, sleep and dreams; •how light, sounds, smells, tastes, heat and the other qualities of external objects can imprint various ideas on the brain through the mediation of the senses; •how hunger, thirst, and the other internal passions can also send their ideas there. And I explained which part of the brain must be ·identified with various supposed mental faculties—specifically, which part of the brain must be· taken to be the •‘common sense’, where these ideas are received; the •memory, which preserves them; and the •imagination, which can change them in various ways, form them into new ideas, and, by distributing the animal spirits to the muscles, make the parts of this body move in as many different ways, and as appropriately to the objects of the senses and the internal passions, as the parts of our bodies can move without being guided by the will. You won’t find that at all strange if •you know how many kinds of automata or moving machines the skill of man can construct with the use of very few parts, in comparison with the great multitude of bones, muscles, nerves, arteries, veins and all the other parts that are in the body of any animal, and if •this knowledge leads you to regard an animal body as a machine. Having been made by the hands of God, it is incomparably better organised—and capable of movements that are much more wonderful—than any that can be devised by man, ·but still it is just a machine·.

I worked especially hard to show that if any such machines had the organs and outward shape of a monkey or of some other animal that doesn’t have reason, we couldn’t tell that they didn’t possess entirely the same nature as these animals; whereas if any such machines bore a resemblance to our bodies and imitated as many of our actions as was practically possible, we would still have two very sure signs that they were nevertheless not real men. (1) The first is that they could never use words or other constructed signs, as we do to declare our thoughts to others. We can easily conceive of a machine so constructed that it utters words, and even utters words that correspond to bodily actions that will cause a change in its organs (touch it in one spot and it asks ‘What do you mean?’, touch it in another and it cries out ‘That hurts!’, and so on); but not that such a machine should produce different sequences of words so as to give an appropriately meaningful answer to whatever is said in its presence—which is something that the dullest of men can do. (2) Secondly, even though such machines might do some things as well as we do them, or perhaps even better, they would be bound to fail in others; and that would show us that they weren’t acting through understanding but only from the disposition of their organs. For whereas reason is a universal instrument that can be used in all kinds of situations, these organs need some particular disposition for each particular action; hence it is practically impossible for a machine to have enough different •organs to make •it act in all the contingencies of life in the way our •reason makes •us act.

These two factors also tell us how men differ from beasts [= ‘non-human animals’]. For it’s a remarkable fact no men (including even madmen) are so dull-witted or stupid that they can’t arrange different words together so as to form an utterance that makes their thoughts understood; whereas no other animal, however perfect and well-endowed it may be, can do anything like that. It’s not because they lack organs of speech; for we see that magpies and parrots can •utter words as we do yet can’t •speak as we do—i.e. utter words while showing that they are thinking what they are saying. Whereas men who are born deaf and dumb, and thus at least as lacking in speech-organs as the beasts are, usually invent their own signs to make themselves understood by those

22

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 6

whom they live with, who have the opportunity to learn their language. This doesn’t show merely that the beasts have less reason than men; it shows that they don’t have reason at all. Here is why. [This indented passage is faithful to Descartes’s thought at this point, but it expands his words in a way that can’t easily be indicated by ·dots·.]

Animals of a given species are unequal, as least to the extent that human beings are unequal; some of them, for instance, are much more easily trained than others. So we have the notion of beasts that are abler than or superior to their fellows. Now, obviously the ability to talk doesn’t require much reason; so if any of the beasts had reason at all, we would expect the superior members of some species—high-grade monkeys or parrots, for example—to speak as well as the stupidest child, or at least as well as a child with a defective brain. But none of them do; which shows that their souls are completely different in nature from ours, and don’t include any capacity to reason.

Don’t confuse speech with the natural movements that are evidence of passions and can be imitated by machines as well as by animals. And don’t think, as some of the ancients did, that the beasts speak a language that we don’t understand! For if that were true, then since they have many organs that are analogous to ours, they could make themselves understood by us as well as by their fellows. It is another remarkable fact that although many animals show more skill than we do in some of their actions, yet the same animals show no skill at all in plenty of others; so what they do better doesn’t prove that they have minds, for if it did, they would have better minds than any of us and would out-perform us in everything. It shows rather that they don’t have minds at all, and that it is nature that acts in them according to the disposition of their organs. Similarly, we with all our skill can’t count the hours and measure time as accurately as a clock consisting only of wheels and springs!

I went on to describe the rational soul, and showed that, unlike the other things of which I had spoken, it can’t be derived from the powers of matter, but must be specially created ·as a sheer addition to the human body·. The soul has been thought to be lodged in the human body like a helmsman in his ship, and this comparison may hold some of the way, specifically in the soul’s ability to move the body’s limbs; but I showed that the comparison doesn’t tell the whole story, and that the soul must be more closely united with the body ·than the helmsman is with his ship·, because if it is to make up a real man it must have not only the power to move the body but also feelings and appetites like ours. I went on at some length about the soul, because it is one of the most important topics. Second only to the error of those who deny God—which I think I have adequately refuted above—there is no error that leads weak minds further from the straight path of virtue than that of imagining that the souls of the beasts are of the same nature as ours, and hence that after this present life we have nothing to fear or to hope for, any more than flies and ants do. When we know how different the beasts are from us, we are better placed to understand the arguments proving that our soul is of a nature entirely independent of the body, and thus not liable to die with it. And since we can’t see any other causes that destroy the soul, we are naturally led to think that it is immortal.

23

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 6

Part 6

It is now three years since I finished the treatise containing all these things. I was starting to revise it so as to put it in the hands of a publisher, when I learned that a scientific theory published a little while before by someone else had been condemned by people to whom I defer, giving them almost as much authority over my actions as my own reason has over my thoughts. [This refers to a work of Galileo’s that was condemned by the Roman Catholic authorities in 1633.] I won’t say that I accepted this theory, but only that until they censured it I hadn’t noticed in it •anything that I could imagine to be threatening either to religion or to the state, or, therefore, •anything that would have prevented me from putting it in writing if reason had convinced me of it. This made me fear that I might have gone wrong in one of my own theories, despite the care I had always taken never to adopt any new opinion that I couldn’t conclusively demonstrate, and never to write anything that might work to anyone’s disadvantage. That ·fear· was enough to push me into changing my previous decision to publish my views. I had had very strong reasons for this previous decision, but my temperamental hatred of the business of writing books made it easy for me to find reasons for letting myself off. The reasons for and against are ones that I would like to state here, and perhaps you will be interested to know them. [The reasons for will occupy two paragraphs, ending on page 26.]

I have never claimed any great importance for the products of my own mind; and so long as the only fruits I gathered from the method I use were (1) solutions that I found satisfying for certain problems in the speculative sciences, and (2) my attempts to govern my own conduct by the principles I learned from my method, I didn’t think I was obliged to write anything about it. For as regards (2) conduct: everyone is so full of his own wisdom that if changes in these matters could be made by people whom God hadn’t set up as sovereigns over his people or to whom he has given enough grace and zeal to be prophets, we might find as many reformers as there are people! As regards (1): my speculations, much as I liked them I thought that other people had their own and perhaps liked them even more. But I acquired some general notions in physics and realized, as I began to test them in various special problems, how far-reaching they were and how different from the principles used up to now; and as soon as I saw that I thought I couldn’t keep them to myself without offending gravely against the law that requires us to do all we can for the general welfare of mankind. For they—·these scientific notions of mine·—showed me that we can get knowledge that would be very useful in life, and that in place of the •speculative philosophy taught in the schools we might find a •practical philosophy through which

knowing the power and the actions of fire, water, air, the stars, the heavens and all the other bodies in our environment as clearly as we know the various crafts of our artisans, we could (like artisans) put these bodies to use in all the appropriate ways, and thus make ourselves the masters and (as it were) owners of nature.

This is desirable not only for the invention of innumerable devices that would give us trouble-free use of the fruits of the earth and all the goods we find there, but also, and most importantly, for the preservation of health, which is certainly the chief good and the basis for all the other goods in this life. For even the mind depends so much on the state of the

24

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 6

bodily organs that if there is to be found a means of making men in general wiser and cleverer than they have been so far, I believe we should look for it in medicine. It is true that medicine as currently practised doesn’t contain much of any significant use; but without wanting to put it down I’m sure that everyone, even its own practitioners, would admit •that all we know in medicine is almost nothing compared with what remains to be known, and •that we might free ourselves from countless diseases of body and of mind, and perhaps even from the infirmity of old age, if we knew enough about their causes and about all the remedies that nature has provided for us. Well then, having intended to spend my life in the pursuit of such indispensable knowledge, and having come upon a path that seemed to me to be bound to lead to it unless prevented by •the brevity of life or •the lack of experiments, I reached a conclusion about the best remedy against •these two difficulties. It was that I should give to the public a scrupulous account of everything I had discovered, little as it was; and should invite •the best minds to try to make further progress by helping with the necessary experiments, each according to his preference and his ability, and by communicating to the public everything •they learn. In this way, some could take over where others had left off; and thus, by combining the lives and labours of many people, we might get much further working together than anyone could do on his own.

[An expérience can be an experiment or a mere informal experience. This paragraph is mostly about experiments, but when Descartes refers to ‘ones that just happen’ he is clearly thinking of experiences, informal observations.] I also noticed something about experiments: the more we know, the more we need experiments. At the beginning, it is better to avail oneself only of •ones that just happen around us, ones that we can’t be ignorant of unless we don’t think at all; better, that is, than resorting to •more out-of-the-way and contrived experiments. Why? Because the more out-of-the-way events often mislead us when we don’t yet know the causes of the more ordinary ones, and the factors they depend on are nearly always so special and so minute that it is very hard to spot them. But I went about things in the following order. •First I tried to discover in general the principles or first causes of everything that does or can exist in the world. For this I didn’t look beyond God, who created the world; and I derived these principles only from certain seeds of truth that are naturally in our souls. •Next I examined the first and most ordinary effects deducible from these causes; and it seems to me that this procedure led me to the heavens, the stars, and an earth; and on the earth water, air, fire, minerals, and other such things that are the easiest to know because they are the most common and the simplest. •Then, when I wanted to move down to more particular things, I was confronted by such a variety that I didn’t think the human mind could possibly sort out the forms or species of bodies that are on the earth from an infinity of others that could be there if God had chosen to put them there; from which I inferred that the only way of making these bodies useful to us was to reach the causes by way of the effects, and to make use of many special experiments. Later on, reviewing in my mind all the objects that have ever been present to my senses, I venture to say that I have never noticed anything in them that I couldn’t quite easily explain by the principles I had discovered. But I must also admit that the power of nature is so ample and so vast, and these principles so simple and so general, that with almost any particular effect I know from the outset that it can be deduced from the principles in various different ways; my greatest difficulty usually being to •discover which of them actually applies. The only way I know to do •this is by returning to experiments, looking for ones whose outcomes

25

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 6

would differ according to which explanation was the right one. I have now reached a point where I think I can see pretty well what line we should follow in devising most of the experiments that could help in this way; but I see also that I couldn’t do them all myself, and couldn’t afford to even if my income were a thousand times greater than it is, because there are so many of them and they are so difficult to do. And so ·I have had to give up the idea of completing physical science all by myself·; how far I get in the knowledge of nature will from now on depend on how many of these ·crucial experiments· I am able to conduct. I was going to make this [meaning ‘this whole situation’?] known in the book I had written, and to show there how generally beneficial such experiments could be, presenting this so openly and plainly that virtuous people would be obliged both to report to me the experimental results they had already achieved and to help me to work on the experiments that remained to be made. I mean really virtuous people—ones who desire the general good of mankind—not ones who merely claim to be virtuous or are merely thought to be so. [So much for the reasons for publishing; now for the reasons against. They end on page 29. In a moment or two we’ll see Descartes speaking of ‘this volume’, referring to the book that was to include not just this Discourse but also three scientific essays: Optics, Meteorology, and Geometry.]

Since then, however, other thoughts have occurred to me that have made me change my mind, and think that my policy should be this:

I should go on writing down any of my discoveries that I consider to be at all important, doing do this as carefully as I would if I intended to have them published. ·There are two reasons for this comprehensiveness and care·. (1) It will give me all the more reason to examine them closely, as undoubtedly we always look more carefully at something we expect to be seen by others than at something we do only for ourselves (I have often found that something that seemed true when I first conceived it came to look false when I tried to write it down). (2) This plan will also ensure that I lose no opportunity to benefit the public if I can, and that if my writings have any value, those who get them after my death can use them as they see fit.

But I’m determined not to let them be published during my lifetime, so that I shan’t lose any of the time I plan to devote to my self-instruction, being distracted either by opposition and controversy that my published works might arouse, or by whatever reputation they might gain for me. It’s true that each of us is bound to do what he can to procure the good of others, and someone who doesn’t help anyone else is strictly worthless; but it’s also true that our concern ·for others· should look beyond the present time, and that it is right to pass up chances to profit the living in order to do other things that will benefit later generations even more. ·My present topic is an example of the latter theme·: I’m willing to tell you that the little I have learned so far is almost nothing compared with what I don’t know but hope to be able to learn. ·I expect my rate of success to accelerate because· gradually discovering truth in the sciences is like making money: a rich man has less trouble making large profits than he had making much smaller ones when he was poorer. Or the scientist may be compared with a military commander whose forces tend to grow in proportion to his victories, and who needs less skill to •take towns and provinces after •winning a battle than he needs just to •hold on after •losing one. For trying to overcome all the difficulties and errors that prevent our arriving at knowledge of the truth is a matter of fighting battles: when we accept some false opinion on an important question of general significance, that is a defeat, and we need much more skill to recover from it than we do to

26

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 6

make good progress when we already have principles that are well-founded. Take my own case: if I have already discovered a few truths in the sciences (and I hope the contents of this volume will make you think I have found some), I can say that these discoveries are merely upshots of my having overcome five or six principal difficulties—and I see these as five or six battles in which luck was on my side. I even go so far as to say that I think I need to win only two or three more such battles in order to achieve my aims completely, and ·at 41· I’m not too old to have remaining to me, in the normal course of nature, the time needed to do this. [He died at the age of 54.] But the more hopeful I am of being able to use my remaining years effectively, the more I think I am obliged to plan my time carefully; and I was certainly going to lose a lot of time if I published the basic principles of my physics. For although these principles are nearly all so evident that you need only understand them to believe them, and although I think I can demonstrate them all, there is no chance at all that they will square with the various opinions that others have, so that I foresee that ·if I published them· I would often be distracted by the opposition they would arouse.

You may want to say:

That sort of opposition would be useful. Not only would it make you aware of your mistakes, but it would also enable others to have a better understanding of anything worthwhile that you may have discovered; and, as many heads are better than one, so these others might begin to use your results and to help you in turn with theirs.

Well, I recognize that I’m extremely prone to error, and I hardly ever trust the first thoughts that come to me; but I have seen how people can object ·to my scientific work·, and that experience prevents me from expecting any benefit from that direction. For I have often already examined the judgments of •people whom I took to be my friends, of •others whom I thought to be neither friend nor foe, and of •others again whose malice and envy would, I knew, make them eager enough to reveal ·faults in my work· that my friends hadn’t noticed because of their affection for me. But hardly ever has an objection been raised that I hadn’t wholly foreseen, except for ones that were wildly irrelevant! Thus I have almost never encountered a critic of my views who didn’t strike me as either less rigorous or less fair-minded than I am. Nor has it been my experience that previously unknown truths have been discovered through the disputations they carry on in the schools. For so long as each side is straining for victory, they try harder for plausibility than for good reasons; and being a good advocate for many years doesn’t enable one to go on to be a better judge.

As for the benefit that others might get from learning about my thoughts, this couldn’t amount to much because they’re still not very developed: much more has to be done before they are ready for practical application. And I think I can say without vanity that if anyone is capable of making these further developments it must be myself rather than someone else—not that the world may not contain minds incomparably better than mine, but because no-one can conceive something as well when he learns it from someone else as when it’s his own discovery. This is true in the present case—so true that I have often •explained some of my opinions to highly intelligent persons who seemed to understand them really clearly at the time and then •found, when they repeated them back to me, that they almost always changed them in such a way that I could no longer acknowledge them as my own. I take this occasion to address a plea to future generations: Please don’t ever believe that I am the source of an opinion you hear, unless I myself have made it public. I’m not in the least surprised

27

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 6

by the absurdities attributed to all the ancient philosophers whose writings we don’t possess, and what I conclude from these attributions is not •that their thoughts were highly unreasonable (they were some of the best minds of their time) but rather •that their thoughts have been misreported. ·I shall add some remarks about how the work of the ancients is used and viewed by later generations; you’ll soon see how this bears on my present theme·.

We see that it hardly ever happens that the followers of •an ancient philosopher surpass •him; and I’m sure that most of Aristotle’s disciples of today would be happy to know as much about nature as he did, even if that meant never knowing anything that he didn’t. They are like ivy, which doesn’t tend to climb higher than the tree that supports it, and often even grows downward after reaching the treetop. It seems to me that philosophical disciples also ‘grow downwards’, or become somehow less knowledgeable than if they refrained from study, when, not content with knowing everything that is intelligibly explained in their author’s writings, they want further to find there the solution to many problems about which he says nothing and about which perhaps he never thought. But this manner of philosophizing is very convenient for those with merely average minds, for the obscurity of the distinctions and principles they use enables them to speak about everything as confidently as if they knew what they are talking about, and to defend all they say against the subtlest and cleverest thinkers, and there’s no convincing them that they are wrong. In this they seem to me like a blind man who lures his adversary into the depths of a very dark cellar so as to level the odds in their fight. These philosophers, I may say, have a reason for not wanting me to publish the philosophical principles that I use; for these are so very simple and evident that in publishing them I should, as it were, be opening windows and letting daylight into the cellar where the philosophers have gone down to fight. But even the best minds have no cause to want to know my views. For if they want to be able to speak about everything and acquire the reputation of being learned, they’ll achieve this more readily by settling for •plausibility, which is pretty easy to find in all kinds of subjects, than by seeking the •truth; for in some subjects the truth comes to light only gradually, while in others it forces us to own up to our ignorance. But if instead of vainly •seeming to know everything they prefer—as of course they should—•knowing a few truths, and if they wish to follow a plan like mine, then I needn’t tell them anything more than I have already said in this Discourse. For if they are capable of getting further than I have done, then of course they’ll be capable of discovering for themselves everything I think I have discovered. Also, because I have examined everything in an orderly manner, what still remains for me to discover is bound to be intrinsically harder and more hidden than anything I have been able to discover up to now; and they—·the philosophers I’m speaking of·—would have much less pleasure in learning it from me than in learning it for themselves. Besides, the practice they will get by first looking into easy matters and then gradually moving on to more difficult ones will be more useful to them than any instructions from me could be. For my part, I am convinced that if from my youth I had been •taught all the truths I have since tried to •demonstrate, and so had learned them easily, I might never have known any others; or at least I would never have acquired what I think I do have—a practised ability to find new truths whenever I set myself to look for them. In short, if there is any project that is best carried out by the person who began it, it is this one of mine.

True, one man can’t possibly conduct all the experiments that may help in this work; but he can’t usefully employ

28

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 6

other hands than his own, except those of artisans or other such people, whom he could pay and who would be led by the hope of making money (a most effective motive!) to follow his instructions exactly. Voluntary helpers, who might offer to help him from curiosity or a desire to learn, usually promise more than they deliver, producing nothing but fine proposals that never come to anything. Also, any amount of time that they •saved for him by their efforts would be exceeded by the time they would •take in collecting their expected reward—having certain difficulties explained to them, or at least receiving compliments and useless conversation. What about experiments that others have already made? Well, even if those others were willing to tell him about them (and those who call them ‘secrets’ never would)), the experiments in question are mostly made up of so many details or superfluous ingredients that it would be very hard for him to make out the truth in them. Besides, he would find most of these experiments were so badly explained—or indeed so wrong because the experimenters were straining to get results that appeared to conform with their principles—that if some of them were ·potentially· useful to him, the task of sorting those ones out would take more of his time than they were worth. Suppose this were the case:

There is someone in the world whom we know for sure to be capable of making discoveries of the greatest possible importance and public utility. Other men are accordingly eager to help him in every way to achieve his ends.

I don’t see how they could do anything for him except •contribute towards the costs of the experiments he would need to conduct, and •prevent unwelcome visitors from wasting his free time. But ·I’m not casting myself in that role·: I am not so presumptuous as to want to promise anything extraordinary, nor do I feed on any vain idea that the public should take a great interest in my plans; and in any case I have too much self-respect to be willing to accept from anyone a favour that I might be thought not to deserve.

All these considerations taken together led me to decide three years ago that I didn’t want to publish the treatise I had ready then, and even to resolve not to publish during my lifetime any other work that was as •general in scope as that one, or any which would enable people to grasp the fundamentals of my physics. Since then, however, two further reasons have forced me to publish ·along with this Discourse· some essays on •particular topics—·Optics, Meteorology and Geometry·—and to give to the public some account of my actions and plans. (1) If I didn’t, many people who knew of my earlier intention to have certain of my writings printed might suppose that my reasons for not doing so were more discreditable to me than they are. I’m not excessively fond of glory—I even venture to say that I dislike it, seeing it as opposed to the tranquillity that I value above everything else—but I have never tried to hide my actions as though they were crimes, or gone to a lot of •trouble to remain unknown. If I had done this, I thought, I would have been doing myself an injustice; and moreover that •trouble would have created a kind of disturbance which would—·like fame·—have been opposed to the perfect peace of mind I am seeking. And since my indifference about whether I was well-known or not made it unavoidable that I should gain some sort of reputation, I thought I should do my best at least to avoid getting a bad one. (2) Every day increases my awareness of how my project of self-instruction is being held back by the need for innumerable experiments that I need and can’t possibly conduct without the help of others. Although I don’t flatter myself with any expectation that the public will share my interests, still I’m unwilling to let myself down by giving those who come after me cause to reproach me some day

29

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 6

on the grounds that I could have left them many far better things if I hadn’t neglected to show them how they could contribute to my projects.

I thought it convenient for me to choose certain subjects which, without being highly controversial or revealing more of my principles than I wanted to, would still reveal well enough my scientific ability or lack of it. I can’t tell if I have succeeded in this, and I don’t want to get in ahead of anyone else’s judgments on my writings by speaking about them myself. But I shall be very glad if they are examined; and so that people should feel invited to do this, I beg all who have any objections to send them to my publisher; when he informs me about them I’ll try to bring it about that my replies are appended to them ·when they are published·, so that readers can see both sides together, and be better judges of which is true. I don’t promise to make very long replies, but only to admit my errors very frankly if I recognize them; and where I can’t see that I have gone wrong I shall simply say what I consider is required for defending what I have written. I shan’t introduce any new material, so as not to get endlessly caught up in one topic after another.

If you are startled at first by some of the statements I make at the beginning of the Optics and Meteorology, because I call them ‘suppositions’ and seem not to be interested in proving them, please have the patience to read the whole book attentively, and I trust you will be satisfied. For it seems to me that reasons are interlaced in such a way that just as the last are proved by the first, which are their causes, so the first are proved by the last, which are their effects. Don’t think that I am here committing the fallacy that logicians call ‘arguing in a circle’; for experience makes most of these effects quite certain, so that the causes from which I deduce them serve not so much to •prove them as to •explain them—indeed, on the contrary, it is the effects that prove the causes. I used the term ‘suppositions’ simply to indicate that although I think I can deduce them from the primary truths expounded above, I have particularly wanted not to do so. Why? Because I wanted to prevent certain people from taking the opportunity to construct, on what they believe to be my principles, some extravagant philosophy for which I would be blamed. (I’m talking about the kind of person who imagines that when someone else has pondered something for twenty years and sketched it to him in two or three words, he can learn it in a single day; the kind of person who, the more penetrating and lively his mind is, the more prone to error he is and the less capable of truth!) As for the views that are entirely mine, I don’t apologize for their novelty, especially because careful attention to the reasons for them will show them to be simple and in agreement with common sense—so much so that they will seem less extraordinary and strange than any other views that might be taken on the same subjects. I don’t boast of being the first to discover any of them, but I do claim this: When I accept something, it is because reason has convinced me of it, not because it has already been said by someone else or because it hasn’t!

If workmen can’t manage, straight off, to put into operation the invention ·for cutting lenses· explained in the Optics, I don’t think that that shows it to be defective. For much skill and practice are needed for making and adjusting the machines I have described; and although my description provides all the details, it would be astonishing if someone succeeded at the first attempt.... I’m writing in French, my native language, rather than in Latin, the language of my teachers, because I hope for a better judgment of my opinions from •those who use only their natural reason in all its purity than I would get from •those who only trust old books. As for those who combine •good sense with •learning—the only judges I wish to have—I’m sure they won’t be so partial

30

Discourse on the Method René Descartes Part 6

to Latin as to refuse to listen to my arguments because I expound them in the vernacular.

For the rest, I don’t want to speak here in detail about the further progress I hope to make in the sciences, or to make any public promise that I am not sure of keeping. I will say only that I have resolved to devote my remaining years purely to trying to acquire knowledge of nature from which we can be derived rules in medicine that are more reliable than those we have had up till now. I’m temperamentally strongly opposed to any other projects, especially to any that can help some people only by harming others; so that if circumstances forced me to engage in one like that, I don’t think I could succeed in it. Of this I make here a public declaration, fully recognizing that it can’t serve to make me eminent in the world—but then I don’t in the least want to be. And I shall always hold myself more obliged to those whose favour enables me to enjoy uninterrupted leisure than to any who might offer me the most honourable employments in the world.

31

Meditations on First Philosophy

in which are demonstrated the existence of God and the distinction between

the human soul and body

René Descartes

Copyright ©2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth.—In his title for this work, Descartes is following a tradition (started by Aristotle) which uses ‘first philosophy’ as a label for metaphysics.
First launched: July 2004 Last amended: April 2007
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

First Meditation 1
Second Meditation 3
Third Meditation 9
Fourth Meditation 17
Fifth Meditation 23
Sixth Meditation 27

Meditations René Descartes First Meditation

First Meditation:

On what can be called into doubt

Some years ago I was struck by how many false things I had believed, and by how doubtful was the structure of beliefs that I had based on them. I realized that if I wanted to establish anything in the sciences that was stable and likely to last, I needed—just once in my life—to demolish everything completely and start again from the foundations. It looked like an enormous task, and I decided to wait until I was old enough to be sure that there was nothing to be gained from putting it off any longer. I have now delayed it for so long that I have no excuse for going on planning to do it rather than getting to work. So today I have set all my worries aside and arranged for myself a clear stretch of free time. I am here quite alone, and at last I will devote myself, sincerely and without holding back, to demolishing my opinions.

I can do this without showing that all my beliefs are false, which is probably more than I could ever manage. My reason tells me that as well as withholding assent from propositions that are obviously •false, I should also withhold it from ones that are •not completely certain and indubitable. So all I need, for the purpose of rejecting all my opinions, is to find in each of them at least some reason for doubt. I can do this without going through them one by one, which would take forever: once the foundations of a building have been undermined, the rest collapses of its own accord; so I will go straight for the basic principles on which all my former beliefs rested.

Whatever I have accepted until now as most true has come to me through my senses. But occasionally I have found that they have deceived me, and it is unwise to trust completely those who have deceived us even once.

[The next paragraph presents a series of considerations back and forth. It is set out here as a discussion between two people, but that isn’t how Descartes presented it.]

Hopeful: Yet although the senses sometimes deceive us about objects that are very small or distant, that doesn’t apply to my belief that I am here, sitting by the fire, wearing a winter dressing-gown, holding this piece of paper in my hands, and so on. It seems to be quite impossible to doubt beliefs like these, which come from the senses. Another example: how can I doubt that these hands or this whole body are mine? To doubt such things I would have to liken myself to brain-damaged madmen who are convinced they are kings when really they are paupers, or say they are dressed in purple when they are naked, or that they are pumpkins, or made of glass. Such people are insane, and I would be thought equally mad if I modelled myself on them.

Doubtful (sarcastically): What a brilliant piece of reasoning! As if I were not a man who sleeps at night and often has all the same experiences while asleep as madmen do when awake—indeed sometimes even more improbable ones. Often in my dreams I am convinced of just such familiar events—that I am sitting by the fire in my dressing-gown—when in fact I am lying undressed in bed!

Hopeful: Yet right now my eyes are certainly wide open when I look at this piece of paper; I shake my head and it isn’t asleep; when I rub one hand against the other, I do it deliberately and know what I am doing. This wouldn’t all happen with such clarity to someone asleep.

1

Meditations René Descartes First Meditation

Doubtful: Indeed! As if I didn’t remember other occasions when I have been tricked by exactly similar thoughts while asleep! As I think about this more carefully, I realize that there is never any reliable way of distinguishing being awake from being asleep. This discovery makes me feel dizzy, [joke:] which itself reinforces the notion that I may be asleep!

Suppose then that I am dreaming—it isn’t true that I, with my eyes open, am moving my head and stretching out my hands. Suppose, indeed that I don’t even have hands or any body at all. Still, it has to be admitted that the visions that come in sleep are like paintings: they must have been made as copies of real things; so at least these general kinds of things—eyes, head, hands and the body as a whole—must be real and not imaginary. For even when painters try to depict sirens and satyrs with the most extraordinary bodies, they simply jumble up the limbs of different kinds of real animals, rather than inventing natures that are entirely new. If they do succeed in thinking up something completely fictitious and unreal—not remotely like anything ever seen before—at least the colours used in the picture must be real. Similarly, although these general kinds of things—eyes, head, hands and so on—could be imaginary, there is no denying that certain even simpler and more universal kinds of things are real. These are the elements out of which we make all our mental images of things—the true and also the false ones.

These simpler and more universal kinds include body, and extension; the shape of extended things; their quantity, size and number; the places things can be in, the time through which they can last, and so on.

So it seems reasonable to conclude that physics, astronomy, medicine, and all other sciences dealing with things that have complex structures are doubtful; while arithmetic, geometry and other studies of the simplest and most general things—whether they really exist in nature or not—contain something certain and indubitable. For whether I am awake or asleep, two plus three makes five, and a square has only four sides. It seems impossible to suspect that such obvious truths might be false.

However, I have for many years been sure that there is an all-powerful God who made me to be the sort of creature that I am. How do I know that he hasn’t brought it about that there is no earth, no sky, nothing that takes up space, no shape, no size, no place, while making sure that all these things appear to me to exist? Anyway, I sometimes think that others go wrong even when they think they have the most perfect knowledge; so how do I know that I myself don’t go wrong every time I add two and three or count the sides of a square? Well, ·you might say·, God would not let me be deceived like that, because he is said to be supremely good. But, ·I reply·, if God’s goodness would stop him from letting me be deceived •all the time, you would expect it to stop him from allowing me to be deceived even •occasionally; yet clearly I sometimes am deceived.

Some people would deny the existence of such a powerful God rather than believe that everything else is uncertain. Let us grant them—for purposes of argument—that there is no God, and theology is fiction. On their view, then, I am a product of fate or chance or a long chain of causes and effects. But the less powerful they make my original cause, the more likely it is that I am so imperfect as to be deceived all the time—because deception and error seem to be imperfections. Having no answer to these arguments, I am driven back to the position that doubts can properly be raised about any of my former beliefs. I don’t reach this conclusion in a flippant or casual manner, but on the basis of powerful and well thought-out reasons. So in future, if I want to discover any certainty, I must withhold my assent

2

Meditations René Descartes Second Meditation

from these former beliefs just as carefully as I withhold it from obvious falsehoods.

It isn’t enough merely to have noticed this, though; I must make an effort to remember it. My old familiar opinions keep coming back, and against my will they capture my belief. It is as though they had a right to a place in my belief-system as a result of long occupation and the law of custom. These habitual opinions of mine are indeed highly probable; although they are in a sense doubtful, as I have shown, it is more reasonable to believe than to deny them. But if I go on viewing them in that light I shall never get out of the habit of confidently assenting to them. To conquer that habit, therefore, I had better switch right around and pretend (for a while) that these former opinions of mine are utterly false and imaginary. I shall do this until I have something to counter-balance the weight of old opinion, and the distorting influence of habit no longer prevents me from judging correctly. However far I go in my distrustful attitude, no actual harm will come of it, because my project won’t affect how I •act, but only how I •go about acquiring knowledge.

So I shall suppose that some malicious, powerful, cunning demon has done all he can to deceive me—rather than this being done by God, who is supremely good and the source of truth. I shall think that the sky, the air, the earth, colours, shapes, sounds and all external things are merely dreams that the demon has contrived as traps for my judgment. I shall consider myself as having no hands or eyes, or flesh, or blood or senses, but as having falsely believed that I had all these things. I shall stubbornly persist in this train of thought; and even if I can’t learn any truth, I shall at least do what I can do, which is to be on my guard against accepting any falsehoods, so that the deceiver—however powerful and cunning he may be—will be unable to affect me in the slightest. This will be hard work, though, and a kind of laziness pulls me back into my old ways. Like a prisoner who dreams that he is free, starts to suspect that it is merely a dream, and wants to go on dreaming rather than waking up, so I am content to slide back into my old opinions; I fear being shaken out of them because I am afraid that my peaceful sleep may be followed by hard labour when I wake, and that I shall have to struggle not in the light but in the imprisoning darkness of the problems I have raised.

Second Meditation:

The nature of the human mind, and how it is better known than the body

Yesterday’s meditation raised doubts—ones that are too serious to be ignored—which I can see no way of resolving. I feel like someone who is suddenly dropped into a deep whirlpool that tumbles him around so that he can neither stand on the bottom nor swim to the top. However, I shall force my way up, and try once more to carry out the project

3

Meditations René Descartes Second Meditation

that I started on yesterday. I will set aside anything that admits of the slightest doubt, treating it as though I had found it to be outright false; and I will carry on like that until I find something certain, or—at worst—until I become certain that there is no certainty. Archimedes said that if he had one firm and immovable point he could lift the world ·with a long enough lever·; so I too can hope for great things if I manage to find just one little thing that is solid and certain.

I will suppose, then, that everything I see is fictitious. I will believe that my memory tells me nothing but lies. I have no senses. Body, shape, extension, movement and place are illusions. So what remains true? Perhaps just the one fact that nothing is certain!

[This paragraph is presented as a further to-and-fro argument between two people. Remember that this isn’t how Descartes wrote it.]

Hopeful: Still, how do I know that there isn’t something—not on that list—about which there is no room for even the slightest doubt? Isn’t there a God (call him what you will) who gives me the thoughts I am now having?

Doubtful: But why do I think this, since I might myself be the author of these thoughts?

Hopeful: But then doesn’t it follow that I am, at least, something?

Doubtful: This is very confusing, because I have just said that I have no senses and no body, and I am so bound up with a body and with senses that one would think that I can’t exist without them. Now that I have convinced myself that there is nothing in the world—no sky, no earth, no minds, no bodies—does it follow that I don’t exist either?

Hopeful: No it does not follow; for if I convinced myself of something then I certainly existed.

Doubtful: But there is a supremely powerful and cunning deceiver who deliberately deceives me all the time!

Hopeful: Even then, if he is deceiving me I undoubtedly exist: let him deceive me all he can, he will never bring it about that I am nothing while I think I am something. So after thoroughly thinking the matter through I conclude that this proposition, I am, I exist, must be true whenever I assert it or think it.

But this ‘I’ that must exist—I still don’t properly understand what it is; so I am at risk of confusing it with something else, thereby falling into error in the very item of knowledge that I maintain is the most certain and obvious of all. To get straight about what this ‘I’ is, I shall go back and think some more about what I believed myself to be before I started this meditation. I will eliminate from those beliefs anything that could be even slightly called into question by the arguments I have been using, which will leave me with only beliefs about myself that are certain and unshakable.

Well, then, what did I think I was? A man. But what is a man? Shall I say ‘a rational animal’? No; for then I should have to ask what an animal is, and what rationality is—each question would lead me on to other still harder ones, and this would take more time than I can spare. Let me focus instead on the beliefs that spontaneously and naturally came to me whenever I thought about what I was. The first such belief was that I had a face, hands, arms and the whole structure of bodily parts that corpses also have—I call it the body. The next belief was that I ate and drank, that I moved about, and that I engaged in sense-perception and thinking; these things, I thought, were done by the soul. [In this work ‘the soul’ = ‘the mind’; it has no religious implications.] If I gave any thought to what this soul was like, I imagined it to be something thin and filmy—like a wind or fire or ether—permeating my more solid parts. I was more sure about the body, though, thinking that I knew exactly what sort of thing it was. If I had tried to put my conception of the body into words, I would have said this:

4

Meditations René Descartes Second Meditation

By a ‘body’ I understand whatever has a definite shape and position, and can occupy a ·region of· space in such a way as to keep every other body out of it; it can be perceived by touch, sight, hearing, taste or smell, and can be moved in various ways.

I would have added that a body can’t start up movements by itself, and can move only through being moved by other things that bump into it. It seemed to me quite out of character for a body to be able to •initiate movements, or to able to •sense and think, and I was amazed that certain bodies—·namely, human ones·—could do those things.

But now that I am supposing there is a supremely powerful and malicious deceiver who has set out to trick me in every way he can—now what shall I say that I am? Can I now claim to have any of the features that I used to think belong to a body? When I think about them really carefully, I find that they are all open to doubt: I shan’t waste time by showing this about each of them separately. Now, what about the features that I attributed to the soul? Nutrition or movement? Since now ·I am pretending that· I don’t have a body, these are mere fictions. Sense-perception? One needs a body in order to perceive; and, besides, when dreaming I have seemed to perceive through the senses many things that I later realized I had not perceived in that way. Thinking? At last I have discovered it—thought! This is the one thing that can’t be separated from me. I am, I exist—that is certain. But for how long? For as long as I am thinking. But perhaps no longer than that; for it might be that if I stopped thinking I would stop existing; and ·I have to treat that possibility as though it were actual, because· my present policy is to reject everything that isn’t necessarily true. Strictly speaking, then, I am simply a thing that thinks—a mind, or soul, or intellect, or reason, these being words whose meaning I have only just come to know. Still, I am a real, existing thing. What kind of a thing? I have answered that: a thinking thing.

What else am I? I will use my imagination to see if I am anything more. I am not that structure of limbs and organs that is called a human body; nor am I a thin vapour that permeates the limbs—a wind, fire, air, breath, or whatever I imagine; for I have supposed all these things to be nothing ·because I have supposed all bodies to be nothing·. Even if I go on supposing them to be nothing, I am still something. But these things that I suppose to be nothing because they are unknown to me—might they not in fact be identical with the I of which I am aware? I don’t know; and just now I shan’t discuss the matter, because I can form opinions only about things that I know. I know that I exist, and I am asking: what is this I that I know? My knowledge of it can’t depend on things of whose existence I am still unaware; so it can’t depend on anything that I invent in my imagination. The word ‘invent’ points to what is wrong with relying on my imagination in this matter: if I used imagination to show that I was something or other, that would be mere invention, mere story-telling; for imagining is simply contemplating the shape or image of a bodily thing. [Descartes here relies on a theory of his about the psychology of imagination.] That makes imagination suspect, for while I know for sure that I exist, I know that everything relating to the nature of body ·including imagination· could be mere dreams; so it would be silly for me to say ‘I will use my imagination to get a clearer understanding of what I am’—as silly, indeed, as to say ‘I am now awake, and see some truth; but I shall deliberately fall asleep so as to see even more, and more truly, in my dreams’! If my mind is to get a clear understanding of its own nature, it had better not look to the imagination for it.

Well, then, what am I? A thing that thinks. What is that? A thing that doubts, understands, affirms, denies, wants, refuses, and also imagines and senses.

5

Meditations René Descartes Second Meditation

That is a long list of attributes for me to have—and it really is I who have them all. Why should it not be? Isn’t it one and the same ‘I’ who now

doubts almost everything,

understands some things,

affirms this one thing—·namely, that I exist and think·,

denies everything else,

wants to know more,

refuses to be deceived,

imagines many things involuntarily, and

is aware of others that seem to come from the senses?

Isn’t all this just as true as the fact that I exist, even if I am in a perpetual dream, and even if my creator is doing his best to deceive me? Which of all these activities is distinct from my thinking? Which of them can be said to be separate from myself? The fact that it is I who doubt and understand and want is so obvious that I can’t see how to make it any clearer. But the ‘I’ who imagines is also this same ‘I’. For even if (as I am pretending) none of the things that I imagine really exist, I really do imagine them, and this is part of my thinking. Lastly, it is also this same ‘I’ who senses, or is aware of bodily things seemingly through the senses. Because I may be dreaming, I can’t say for sure that I now see the flames, hear the wood crackling, and feel the heat of the fire; but I certainly seem to see, to hear, and to be warmed. This cannot be false; what is called ‘sensing’ is strictly just this seeming, and when ‘sensing’ is understood in this restricted sense of the word it too is simply thinking.

All this is starting to give me a better understanding of what I am. But I still can’t help thinking that bodies—of which I form mental images and which the senses investigate—are much more clearly known to me than is this puzzling ‘I’ that can’t be pictured in the imagination. It would be surprising if this were right, though; for it would be surprising if I had a clearer grasp of things that I realize are doubtful, unknown and foreign to me—·namely, bodies·—than I have of what is true and known—namely my own self. But I see what the trouble is: I keep drifting towards that error because my mind likes to wander freely, refusing to respect the boundaries that truth lays down. Very well, then; I shall let it run free for a while, so that when the time comes to rein it in it won’t be so resistant to being pulled back.

Let us consider the things that people ordinarily think they understand best of all, namely the bodies that we touch and see. I don’t mean bodies in general—for our general thoughts are apt to be confused—but one particular body: this piece of wax, for example. It has just been taken from the honeycomb; it still tastes of honey and has the scent of the flowers from which the honey was gathered; its colour, shape and size are plain to see; it is hard, cold and can be handled easily; if you rap it with your knuckle it makes a sound. In short, it has everything that seems to be needed for a body to be known perfectly clearly. But as I speak these words I hold the wax near to the fire, and look! The taste and smell vanish, the colour changes, the shape is lost, the size increases; the wax becomes liquid and hot; you can hardly touch it, and it no longer makes a sound when you strike it. But is it still the same wax? Of course it is; no-one denies this. So what was it about the wax that I understood so clearly? Evidently it was not any of the features that the senses told me of; for all of them—brought to me through taste, smell, sight, touch or hearing—have now altered, yet it is still the same wax.

Perhaps what I now think about the wax indicates what its nature was all along. If that is right, then the wax was not the sweetness of the honey, the scent of the flowers, the whiteness, the shape, or the sound, but was rather a body

6

Meditations René Descartes Second Meditation

that recently presented itself to me in those ways but now appears differently. But what exactly is this thing that I am now imagining? Well, if we take away whatever doesn’t belong to the wax (·that is, everything that the wax could be without·), what is left is merely something extended, flexible and changeable. What do ‘flexible’ and ‘changeable’ mean here? I can imaginatively picture this piece of wax changing from round to square, from square to triangular, and so on. But that isn’t what changeability is. In knowing that the wax is changeable I understand that it can go through endlessly many changes of that kind, far more than I can depict in my imagination; so it isn’t my imagination that gives me my grasp of the wax as flexible and changeable. Also, what does ‘extended’ mean? Is the wax’s extension also unknown? It increases if the wax melts, and increases again if it boils; the wax can be extended in many more ways (·that is, with many more shapes·) than I will ever bring before my imagination. I am forced to conclude that the nature of this piece of wax isn’t revealed by my imagination, but is perceived by the mind alone. (I am speaking of •this particular piece of wax; the point is even clearer with regard to •wax in general.) This wax that is perceived by the mind alone is, of course, the same wax that I see, touch, and picture in my imagination—in short the same wax I thought it to be from the start. But although my perception of it seemed to be a case of vision and touch and imagination, it isn’t so and it never was. Rather, it is purely a scrutiny by the mind alone—formerly an imperfect and confused one, but now vivid and clear because I am now concentrating carefully on what the wax consists in.

As I reach this conclusion I am amazed at how prone to error my mind is. For although I am thinking all this out within myself, silently, I do it with the help of words, and I am at risk of being led astray by them. When the wax is in front of us, we say that we see it, not that we judge it to be there from its colour or shape; and this might make me think that knowledge of the wax comes from what the eye sees rather than from the perception of the mind alone. But ·this is clearly wrong, as the following example shows·. If I look out of the window and see men crossing the square, as I have just done, I say that I see the men themselves, just as I say that I see the wax; yet do I see any more than hats and coats that could conceal robots? I judge that they are men. Something that I thought I saw with my eyes, therefore, was really grasped solely by my mind’s faculty of judgment [= ‘ability or capacity to make judgments’].

However, someone who wants to know more than the common crowd should be ashamed to base his doubts on ordinary ways of talking. Let us push ahead, then, and ask: When was my perception of the wax’s nature more perfect and clear? Was it •when I first looked at the wax, and thought I knew it through my senses? Or is it •now, after I have enquired more carefully into the wax’s nature and into how it is known? It would be absurd to hesitate in answering the question; for what clarity and sharpness was there in my earlier perception of the wax? Was there anything in it that •a lower animal couldn’t have? But when I consider the wax apart from its outward forms—take its clothes off, so to speak, and consider it naked—then although my judgment may still contain errors, at least I am now having a perception of a sort that requires •a human mind.

But what am I to say about this mind, or about myself? (So far, remember, I don’t admit that there is anything to me except a mind.) What, I ask, is this ‘I’ that seems to perceive the wax so clearly? Surely, I am aware of •my own self in a truer and more certain way than I am of •the wax, and also in a much more distinct and evident way. What leads me to think that •the wax exists—namely, that I see—leads much

7

Meditations René Descartes Second Meditation

more obviously to the conclusion that •I exist. What I see might not really be the wax; perhaps I don’t even have eyes with which to see anything. But when I see or think I see (I am not here distinguishing the two), it is simply not possible that I who am now thinking am not something. Similarly, that •I exist follows from the other bases for judging that •the wax exists - that I touch it, that I imagine it, or any other basis—and similarly for my bases for judging that anything else exists outside me. As I came to perceive the wax more distinctly by applying not just sight and touch but other considerations, all this too contributed to my knowing myself even more distinctly, because whatever goes into my perception of •the wax or of any other body must do even more to establish the nature of •my own mind. What comes to my mind from bodies, therefore, helps me to know my mind distinctly; yet all of that pales into insignificance—it is hardly worth mentioning—when compared with what my mind contains within itself that enables me to know it distinctly.

See! With no effort I have reached the place where I wanted to be! I now know that even bodies are perceived not by the senses or by imagination but by the intellect alone, not through their being touched or seen but through their being understood; and this helps me to know plainly that I can perceive my own mind more easily and clearly than I can anything else. Since the grip of old opinions is hard to shake off, however, I want to pause and meditate for a while on this new knowledge of mine, fixing it more deeply in my memory.

8

Meditations René Descartes Third Meditation

Third Meditation:

God

[Before we move on, a translation matter should be confronted. It concerns the Latin adjectives

clarus and distinctus

the corresponding French adjectives

clair and distinct

and the corresponding English adjectives

‘vivid’ and ‘clear’.

Every other translator of this work into English has put

‘clear’ and ‘distinct’

and for a while the present translator in cowardly fashion followed suit. But the usual translation is simply wrong, and we ought to free ourselves from it. The crucial point concerns clarus (and everything said about that here is equally true of the French clair). The word can mean ‘clear’ in our sense, and when Descartes uses it outside the clarus et distinctus phrase, it seems usually to be in that sense. But in that phrase he uses clarus in its other meaning—its more common meaning in Latin—of ‘bright’ or ‘vivid’ or the like, as in clara lux = ‘broad daylight’. If in the phrase clarus et distinctus Descartes meant clarus in its lesser meaning of ‘clear’, then what is there left for ‘distinctus’ to mean? Descartes doesn’t explain these terms here, but in his Principles of Philosophy 1:45–6 he does so—in a manner that completely condemns the usual translation. He writes: ‘I call a perception claram when it is present and accessible to the attentive mind—just as we say that we see something clare when it is present to the eye’s gaze and stimulates it with a sufficient degree of strength and accessibility. I call a perception distinctam if, as well as being clara, it is so sharply separated from all other perceptions that every part of it is clarum..... The example of pain shows that a perception can be clara without being distincta but not vice versa. When for example someone feels an intense pain, his perception of it is clarissima, but it isn’t always clear, because people often get this perception muddled with an obscure judgment they make about something that they think exists in the painful spot....’ and so on. Of course he is not saying anything as stupid as that intense pain is always clear! His point is that pain is vivid, up-front, not shady or obscure. And for an idea to be distincta is for every nook and cranny of it to be vivid; which is not a bad way of saying that it is in our sense ‘clear’.]

I will now shut my eyes, block my ears, cut off all my senses. I will regard all my mental images of bodily things as empty, false and worthless (if I could, I would clear them out of my mind altogether). I will get into conversation with myself, examine myself more deeply, and try in this way gradually to know myself more intimately. I am a thing that thinks, i.e that doubts, affirms, denies, understands some things, is ignorant of many others, wills, and refuses. This thing also imagines and has sensory perceptions; for, as I remarked before, even if the objects of my sensory experience and imagination don’t exist outside me, still sensory perception and imagination themselves, considered simply as mental events, certainly do occur in me.

That lists everything that I truly know, or at least everything I have, up to now, discovered that I know. Now I will look more carefully to see whether I have overlooked other facts about myself. I am certain that I am a thinking thing. Doesn’t that tell me what it takes for me to be certain about anything? In this first item of knowledge there is simply a vivid and clear perception of what I am asserting; this wouldn’t be enough to make me certain of its truth if it could ever turn out that something that I perceived so vividly and clearly was false. So I now seem to be able to lay it down as a general rule that whatever I perceive very vividly and clearly is true.

9

Meditations René Descartes Third Meditation

I previously accepted as perfectly certain and evident many things that I afterwards realized were doubtful—the earth, sky, stars, and everything else that I took in through the senses—but in those cases what I perceived clearly were merely the ideas or thoughts of those things that came into my mind; and I am still not denying that those ideas occur within me. But I used also to believe that my ideas came from things outside that resembled them in all respects. Indeed, I believed this for so long that I wrongly came to think that I perceived it clearly. In fact, it was false; or anyway if it was true it was not thanks to the strength of my perceptions.

But what about when I was considering something simple and straightforward in arithmetic or geometry, for example that two plus three makes five? Didn’t I see these things clearly enough to accept them as true? Indeed, the only reason I could find for doubting them was this: Perhaps some God could have made me so as to be deceived even in those matters that seemed most obvious. Whenever I bring to mind my old belief in the supreme power of God, I have to admit that God could, if he wanted to, easily make me go wrong even about things that I think I see perfectly clearly. But when I turn my thought onto the things themselves—the ones I think I perceive clearly—I find them so convincing that I spontaneously exclaim: ‘Let him do his best to deceive me! He will never bring it about that I am nothing while I think I am something; or make it true in the future that I have never existed, given that I do now exist; or bring it about that two plus three make more or less than five, or anything else like this in which I see a plain contradiction.’ Also, since I have no evidence that there is a deceiving God, and don’t even know for sure that there is a God at all, the reason for doubt that depends purely on this supposition of a deceiving God is a very slight and theoretical one. However, I shall want to remove even this slight reason for doubt; so when I get the opportunity I shall examine whether there is a God, and (if there is) whether he can be a deceiver. If I don’t settle this, it seems, then I can never be quite certain about anything else.

First, if I am to proceed in an orderly way I should classify my thoughts into definite kinds, and ask which kinds can properly be said to be true or false. Some of my thoughts are, so to speak, images or pictures of things—as when I think of a man, or a chimera, or the sky, or an angel, or God—and strictly speaking these are the only thoughts that should be called ‘ideas’. Other thoughts have more to them than that: for example when I will, or am afraid, or affirm, or deny, my thought represents some particular thing but it also includes something more than merely the likeness of that thing. Some thoughts in this category are called volitions or emotions, while others are called judgments.

When ideas are considered solely in themselves and not taken to be connected to anything else, they can’t be false; for whether it is •a goat that I am imagining or •a chimera, either way it is true that I do imagine it. Nor is there falsity in the will or the emotions; for even if the things I want are wicked or non-existent, it is still true that I want them. All that is left—the only kind of thought where I must watch out for mistakes—are judgments. And the mistake they most commonly involve is to judge that my ideas resemble things outside me. Of course, if I considered the ideas themselves simply as aspects of my thought and not as connected to anything else, they could hardly lead me into any error.

Among my ideas, some seem to be •innate, some to be •caused from the outside, and others to have been •invented by me. As I see it, •my understanding of what a thing is, what truth is, and what thought is, derives purely from my own nature, ·which means that it is innate·; •my hearing a noise or seeing the sun or feeling the fire comes from things outside me; and •sirens, hippogriffs and the like are my own

10

Meditations René Descartes Third Meditation

invention. But perhaps really all my ideas are caused from the outside, or all are innate, or all are made up; for I still have not clearly perceived their true origin.

But my main question now concerns the ideas that I take to come from things outside me: why do I think they resemble these things? Nature has apparently taught me to think that they do. But also I know from experience that these ideas don’t depend on my will, and thus don’t depend simply on me. They often come into my mind without my willing them to: right now, for example, I have a feeling of warmth, whether I want to or not, and that leads me to think that this sensation or idea of heat comes from something other than myself, namely the heat of a fire by which I am sitting. And it seems natural to suppose that what comes to me from that external thing will be like it rather than unlike it.

Now let me see if these arguments are strong enough. When I say ‘Nature taught me to think this’, all I mean is that •I have a spontaneous impulse to believe it, not that •I am shown its truth by some natural light. There is a great difference between those. Things that are revealed by the natural light—for example, that if I am doubting then I exist—are not open to any doubt, because no other faculty that might show them to be false could be as trustworthy as the natural light. My natural impulses, however, have no such privilege: I have often come to think that they had pushed me the wrong way on moral questions, and I don’t see any reason to trust them in other things.

Then again, although these ideas don’t depend on my will, it doesn’t follow that they must come from things located outside me. Perhaps they come from some faculty of mine other than my will—one that I don’t fully know about—which produces these ideas without help from external things; this is, after all, just how I have always thought ideas are produced in me when I am dreaming. Similarly, the natural impulses that I have been talking about, though they seem opposed to my will, come from within me; ·which provides evidence that I can cause things that my will does not cause·.

Finally, even if these ideas do come from things other than myself, it doesn’t follow that they must resemble those things. Indeed, I think I have often discovered objects to be very unlike my ideas of them. For example, I find within me two different ideas of the sun: •one seems to come from the senses—it is a prime example of an idea that I reckon to have an external source—and it makes the sun appear very small; •the other is based on astronomical reasoning—i.e. it is based on notions that are innate in me (or else it is constructed by me in some other way)—and it shows the sun to be many times larger than the earth. Obviously these ideas cannot both resemble the external sun; and reason convinces me that the idea that seems to have come most directly from the sun itself in fact does not resemble it at all.

These considerations show that it isn’t reliable judgment but merely some blind impulse that has led me to think that there exist outside me things that give ideas or images [= ‘likenesses’] of themselves through the sense organs or in some other way.

Perhaps, though, there is another way of investigating whether some of the things of which I have ideas really do exist outside me. Considered simply as mental events, my ideas seem to be all on a par: they all appear to come from inside me in the same way. But considered as images representing things other than themselves, it is clear that they differ widely. Undoubtedly, the •ideas that represent substances amount to something more—they contain within themselves more representative reality—than do the •ideas that merely represent modes [= ‘qualities’]. Again, the •idea that gives me my understanding of a supreme God—eternal,

11

Meditations René Descartes Third Meditation

infinite, unchangeable, omniscient, omnipotent and the creator of everything that exists except for himself—certainly has in it more representative reality than the •ideas that represent merely finite substances.

Now it is obvious by the natural light that the total cause of something must contain at least as much reality as does the effect. For where could the effect get its reality from if not from the cause? And how could the cause give reality to the effect unless it first had that reality itself? Two things follow from this: that something can’t arise from nothing, and that what is more perfect—that is, contains in itself more reality—can’t arise from what is less perfect. And this is plainly true not only for ‘actual’ or ‘intrinsic’ reality (as philosophers call it) but also for the representative reality of ideas—that is, the reality that a idea represents. A stone, for example, can begin to exist only if it is produced by something that contains—either straightforwardly or in some higher form—everything that is to be found in the stone; similarly, heat can’t be produced in a previously cold object except by something of at least the same order of perfection as heat, and so on. (·I don’t say simply ‘except by something that is hot’, because that is not necessary. The thing could be caused to be hot by something that doesn’t itself straightforwardly contain heat—i.e. that isn’t itself hot—but contains heat in a higher form, that is, something of a higher order of perfection than heat. Thus, for example, although God is obviously not himself hot, he can cause something to be hot because he contains heat not straightforwardly but in a higher form·.) But it is also true that the idea of heat or of a stone can be caused in me only by something that contains at least as much reality as I conceive to be in the heat or in the stone. For although this cause does not transfer any of its actual or intrinsic reality to my idea, it still can’t be less real. An idea need have no intrinsic reality except what it derives from my thought, of which it is a mode. But any idea that has representative reality must surely come from a cause that contains at least as much intrinsic reality as there is representative reality in the idea. For if we suppose that an idea contains something that was not in its cause, it must have got this from nothing; yet the kind of reality that is involved in something’s being represented in the mind by an idea, though it may not be very perfect, certainly isn’t nothing, and so it can’t come from nothing.

It might be thought that since the reality that I am considering in my ideas is merely representative, it might be possessed by its cause only representatively and not intrinsically. ·That would mean that the cause is itself an idea, because only ideas have representative reality·. But that would be wrong. Although one idea may perhaps originate from another, there can’t be an infinite regress of such ideas; eventually one must come back to an idea whose cause isn’t an idea, and this cause must be a kind of archetype [= ‘pattern or model, from which copies are made’] containing intrinsically all the reality or perfection that the idea contains only representatively. So the natural light makes it clear to me that my ideas are like pictures or images that can easily •fall short of the perfection of the things from which they are taken, but which can’t •exceed it.

The longer and more carefully I examine all these points, the more vividly and clearly I recognize their truth. But what is my conclusion to be? If I find that

•some idea of mine has so much representative reality that I am sure the same reality doesn’t reside in me, either straightforwardly or in a higher form, and hence that I myself can’t be the cause of the idea,

then, ·because everything must have some cause·, it will necessarily follow that

12

Meditations René Descartes Third Meditation

•I am not alone in the world: there exists some other thing that is the cause of that idea.

If no such idea is to be found in me, I shall have no argument to show that anything exists apart from myself; for, despite a most careful and wide-ranging survey, this is the only argument I have so far been able to find.

Among my ideas, apart from the one that gives me a representation of myself, which can’t present any difficulty in this context, there are ideas that variously represent God, inanimate bodies, angels, animals and finally other men like myself.

As regards my ideas of other men, or animals, or angels, I can easily understand that they could be put together from the ideas I have of myself, of bodies and of God, even if the world contained no men besides me, no animals and no angels.

As to my ideas of bodies, so far as I can see they contain nothing that is so great or excellent that it couldn’t have originated in myself. For if I examine them thoroughly, one by one, as I did the idea of the wax yesterday, I realize that the following short list gives everything that I perceive vividly and clearly in them:

•size, or extension in length, breadth and depth;

•shape, which is a function of the boundaries of this extension;

•position, which is a relation between various items possessing shape;

•motion, or change in position.

To these may be added

•substance, duration and number.

But as for all the rest, including light and colours, sounds, smells, tastes, heat and cold and the other qualities that can be known by touch, I think of these in such a confused and obscure way that I don’t even know whether they are true or false, that is, whether my ideas of them are ideas of real things or of non-things. Strictly speaking, only judgments can be true or false; but we can also speak of an idea as ‘false’ in a certain sense—we call it ‘materially false’—if it represents a non-thing as a thing. For example, my ideas of heat and cold have so little clarity and distinctness that they don’t enable me to know whether

•cold is merely the absence of heat, or

•heat is merely the absence of cold, or

•heat and cold are both real ·positive· qualities, or

•neither heat nor cold is a real ·positive· quality.

If the right answer is that cold is nothing but the absence of heat, the idea that represents it to me as something real and positive deserves to be called ‘false’; and the same goes for other ideas of this kind.

Such ideas obviously don’t have to be caused by something other than myself. •If they are false—that is, if they represent non-things—then they are in me only because of a deficiency or lack of perfection in my nature, which is to say that they arise from nothing; I know this by the natural light. •If on the other hand they are true, there is no reason why they shouldn’t arise from myself, since they represent such a slight reality that I can’t even distinguish it from a non-thing.

With regard to the vivid and clear elements in my ideas of bodies, it appears that I could have borrowed some of these from my idea of myself, namely substance, duration, number and anything else of this kind. For example, I think that a stone is a substance, or is a thing capable of existing independently, and I also think that I am a substance. Admittedly I conceive of myself as a thing that thinks and isn’t extended, and of the stone as a thing that is extended and doesn’t think, so that the two conceptions differ enormously; but

13

Meditations René Descartes Third Meditation

they seem to have the classification ‘substance’ in common. Again, I perceive that I now exist, and remember that I have existed •for some time; moreover, I have various thoughts that I can •count; it is in these ways that I acquire the ideas of •duration and •number that I can then transfer to other things. As for all the other elements that make up the ideas of bodies—extension, shape, position and movement—these are not straightforwardly contained in me, since I am nothing but a thinking thing; but since they are merely modes of a substance, and I am a substance, it seems possible that they are contained in me in some higher form. ·That is, I am not myself extended, shaped etc., but because I am a substance I am (so to speak) metaphysically one up on these mere modes, which implies that I can contain within me whatever it takes to cause the ideas of them·.

So there remains only the idea of God: is there anything in that which couldn’t have originated in myself? By the word ‘God’ I understand a substance that is infinite, eternal, unchangeable, independent, supremely intelligent, supremely powerful, which created myself and anything else that may exist. The more carefully I concentrate on these attributes, the less possible it seems that any of them could have originated from me alone. So this whole discussion implies that God necessarily exists.

It is true that my being a substance explains my having the idea of substance; but it does not explain my having the idea of an infinite substance. That must come from some substance that is itself infinite. I am finite.

It might be thought that ·this is wrong, because· my notion of the •infinite is arrived at merely by negating the •finite, just as my conceptions of •rest and •darkness are arrived at by negating •movement and •light. ·That would be a mistake, however·. I clearly understand that there is more reality in an infinite substance than in a finite one, and hence that my perception of the infinite, i.e. God, is in some way prior to my perception of the finite, i.e. myself. Whenever I know that I doubt something or want something, I understand that I lack something and am therefore not wholly perfect. How could I grasp this unless I had an idea of a more perfect being that enabled me to recognize my own defects by comparison?

Nor can it be said that this idea of God could be ‘materially false’, and thus have come from nothing, as may be the case (I noted this a few moments ago) with the ideas of heat and cold. On the contrary, it is utterly vivid and clear, and contains in itself more representative reality than any other idea; ·that is, it stands for something that is grander, more powerful, more real, than any other idea stands for·; so it is more true—less open to the suspicion of falsehood—than any other idea. This idea of a supremely perfect and infinite being is, I say, true in the highest degree; for although one might imagine that such a being does not exist, it can’t be supposed that the idea of such a being represents something unreal in the way that the idea of cold perhaps does. The idea is, moreover, utterly vivid and clear. It does not matter that I don’t grasp the infinite, or that there are countless additional attributes of God that I can’t grasp and perhaps can’t even touch in my thought; for it is in the nature of the infinite not to be grasped by a finite being like myself. It is enough that I understand the infinite, and that I judge that all the attributes that I clearly perceive and know to imply some perfection—and perhaps countless others of which I am ignorant—are present in God either straightforwardly or in some higher form. This is enough to make the idea that I have of God the truest and most vivid and clear of all my ideas.

·Here is a possible objection to that line of thought·. Perhaps I am greater than I myself understand: perhaps

14

Meditations René Descartes Third Meditation

all the perfections that I attribute to God are ones that I do have in some potential form, and they merely haven’t yet shown themselves in actuality. My knowledge is gradually increasing, and I see no obstacle to its going on increasing to infinity. I might then be able to use this increased ·and eventually infinite· knowledge to acquire all the other perfections of God. In that case, I already have the potentiality for these perfections—why shouldn’t this ·potentiality· be enough to enable me to have caused the idea of them ·that is, to have caused my idea of God·?

But all this [that is, the whole of the preceding paragraph] is impossible ·for three reasons·. •First, though it is true that my knowledge is increasing, and that I have many potentialities that are not yet actual, this is all quite irrelevant to the idea of God, which contains absolutely nothing that is potential. Indeed, this gradual increase in knowledge is itself the surest sign of imperfection, ·because if I am learning more, that shows that there are things I don’t know, and that is an imperfection in me·. •What is more, even if my knowledge increases for ever, it will never actually be infinite, since it will never reach the point where it isn’t capable of a further increase; God, on the other hand, I take to be actually infinite, so that nothing can be added to his perfection. •And, thirdly, strictly speaking potential being is nothing; what it takes to cause the representative being of an idea is actual being.

If one concentrates carefully, all this is quite evident by the natural light. But when I relax my concentration, and my mental vision is blurred by the images of things I perceive by the senses, I lose sight of the reasons why my idea of more perfect being has to come from a being that really is more perfect. So I want to push on with my enquiry, now asking a new question: If the more perfect being didn’t exist, could I exist? ·My hope is that the answer to this will yield a new proof of the existence of a perfect being—a proof that it will be easier for me to keep in mind even when I relax my concentration·.

Well, if God didn’t exist, from what would I derive my existence? It would have to come from myself, or from my parents, or from some other beings less perfect than God (a being more perfect than God, or even one as perfect, is unthinkable).

If I had derived my existence from myself, I would not now doubt or want or lack anything at all; for I would have given myself all the perfections of which I have any idea. So I would be God. I mustn’t suppose that the items I lack would be harder to get than the ones I now have. On the contrary, it would have been far more difficult for me—a thinking thing or substance—to emerge out of nothing than merely to acquire knowledge of the many things I’m ignorant about, because that would merely be giving the substance certain accidents. If I had derived my existence from myself—the greater achievement—I certainly wouldn’t have denied myself the knowledge in question, which is something much easier to acquire, or indeed any of the attributes that I perceive to be contained in the idea of God; for none of them seem any harder to achieve....

Here is a thought that might seem to undercut that argument. Perhaps I have always existed as I do now. Then wouldn’t it follow that there need be no cause for my existence? No, it does not follow. For a life-span can be divided into countless parts, each completely independent of the others, so that from my existing at one time it doesn’t follow that I exist at later times, unless some cause keeps me in existence—one might say that it creates me afresh at each moment. Anyone who thinks hard about the nature of time will understand that what it takes to •bring a thing into existence is also needed to •keep it in existence at each mo-

15

Meditations René Descartes Third Meditation

ment of its duration. So there’s no real distinction between •preservation and •creation—only a conceptual one—and this is something that the natural light makes evident.

So I have to ask myself whether I have the power to bring it about that I, who now exist, will still exist a minute from now. For since I am nothing but a thinking thing—or anyway that is the only part of me that I am now concerned with—if I had such a power I would undoubtedly be aware of it. But I experience no such power, and this shows me quite clearly that I depend ·for my continued existence· on some being other than myself.

Perhaps this being is not God, though. Perhaps I was produced by causes less perfect than God, such as my parents. No; for as I have said before, it is quite clear that there must be at least as much reality or perfection in the cause as in the effect. And therefore, given that I am a thinking thing and have within me some idea of God, the cause of me—whatever it is—must itself be a thinking thing and must have the idea of all the perfections that I attribute to God. What is the cause of this cause of me? If it is the cause of its own existence, then it is God; for if it has the power of existing through its own strength, then undoubtedly it also has the power of actually possessing all the perfections of which it has an idea—that is, all the perfections that I conceive to be in God. If on the other hand it gets its existence from another cause, then the question arises all over again regarding this further cause: Does it get its existence from itself or from another cause? Eventually we must reach the ultimate cause, and this will be God.

It is clear enough that this sequence of causes of causes can’t run back to infinity, especially since I am dealing with the cause that not only produced me in the past but also preserves me at the present moment.

One might think this:

Several partial causes contributed to my creation; I received the idea of one of the perfections that I attribute to God from one cause, and the idea of another from another. Each perfection is to be found somewhere in the universe, but no one thing has them all.

That can’t be right, because God’s simplicity—that is, the unity or inseparability of all his attributes—is one of the most important of the perfections that I understand him to have. The idea of his perfections as united in a single substance couldn’t have been placed in me by any cause that didn’t also provide me with the ideas of the perfections themselves; for no cause could have made me understand that the perfections are united without at the same time showing me what they are.

Lastly, as regards my parents, even if everything I have ever believed about them is true, it is certainly not they who keep me in existence. Insofar as I am a thinking thing, indeed, they did not even make me; they merely brought about an arrangement of matter that I have always regarded as containing me (that is, containing my mind, for that is all I now take myself to be). So my parents can’t be the cause-of-me that I am enquiring about.

·Given the failure of every other candidacy for the role of cause of me and of my idea of a most perfect being, I infer that the only successful candidacy is God’s·. Thus, I conclude that the mere fact that I exist and have within me an idea of a most perfect being—that is, God—provides a clear proof that God does indeed exist.

It remains for me only to ask how I received this idea from God. I didn’t get it from the senses: it has never come to me unexpectedly, as do most of the ideas that occur when I seem to see and touch and hear things. And it’s not something

16

Meditations René Descartes Fourth Meditation

that I invented, either; for clearly I can’t take anything away from it or to add anything to it. ·When an idea is sheerly invented, the inventor is free to fiddle with it—add a bit here, subtract a bit there—whereas my idea of God is a natural unit that doesn’t invite or even permit such interference·. The only remaining alternative is that my idea of God is innate in me, just as the idea of myself is innate in me.

It is no surprise that God in creating me should have placed this idea in me, to serve as a mark of the craftsman stamped on his work. The mark need not be anything distinct from the work itself. But the mere fact that God created me makes it very believable that I am somehow made in his image and likeness, and that I perceive that likeness in the same way that I perceive myself. That is, when I turn my mind’s eye upon myself, I understand that I am a thing that •is incomplete and •dependent on something else, and that •aspires without limit to ever greater and better things; but I also understand at the same time that he on whom I depend has within him all those greater things—not just indefinitely but infinitely, not just potentially but actually—and hence that he is God. The core of the argument is this: I couldn’t exist with the nature that I have—that is, containing within me the idea of God—if God didn’t really exist. By ‘God’ I mean the very being the idea of whom is within me—the one that has no defects and has all those perfections that I can’t grasp but can somehow touch with my thought. This shows clearly that it is not possible for him to be a deceiver, since the natural light makes it clear that all fraud and deception depend on some defect.

But before examining this point more carefully and investigating other truths that may be derived from it, I want to pause here and spend some time contemplating God; to reflect on his attributes and to gaze with wonder and adoration on the beauty of this immense light, so far as the eye of my darkened intellect can bear it. For just as we believe through faith that the supreme happiness of •the next life consists in contemplating the divine majesty, so experience tells us that this same contemplation, though much less perfect, provides the greatest joy we can have in •this life.

Fourth Meditation:

Truth and falsity

In these past few days I have become used to keeping my mind away from the senses; and I have become strongly aware that very little is truly known about bodies, whereas much more is known about the human mind and still more about God. So now I find it easy to turn my mind away from objects of the senses and the imagination, towards objects of the intellect alone; these are quite separate from matter, ·whereas the objects of sense and imagination are mostly made of matter·. Indeed, none of my ideas of corporeal [= ‘bodily’] things is as distinct as my idea of the human mind,

17

Meditations René Descartes Fourth Meditation

considered purely as a thinking thing with no size or shape or other bodily characteristics. Now, when I consider the fact that I have doubts—which means that I am incomplete and dependent—that leads to my having a vivid and clear idea of a being who is independent and complete, that is, an idea of God. And from the mere fact that •I exist and have such an idea, I infer that •God exists and that every moment of my existence depends on him. This follows clearly; I am sure, indeed, that the human intellect can’t know anything that is more evident or more certain. And now that I can take into account the true God, in whom all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge lie hidden, I think I can see a way through to knowledge of other things in the universe.

To begin with, I see that it is impossible that God should ever deceive me. Only someone who has something wrong with him will engage in trickery or deception. That someone is able to deceive others may be a sign of his skill or power, but his wanting to deceive them is a sign of his malice or weakness; and those are not to be found in God.

Next, I know from experience that I have a faculty of judgment; and this, like everything else I have, was given to me by God. Since God doesn’t want to deceive me, I am sure that he didn’t give me a faculty of judgment that would lead me into error while I was using it correctly.

That would settle the matter, except for one difficulty: what I have just said seems to imply that I can never be in error. If everything that is in me comes from God, and he didn’t equip me with a capacity for making mistakes, doesn’t it follow that I can never go wrong in my beliefs? Well, I know by experience that I am greatly given to errors; but when I focus on God to the exclusion of everything else, I find in him no cause of error or falsity. In looking for the cause of my errors, I am helped by this thought: as well as having a real and positive idea of God (a being who is supremely perfect), I also have what you might call a negative idea of nothingness (that which is furthest from all perfection). I realize that I am somewhere in between God and nothingness, or between supreme being and non-being. Now, the positive reality that I have been given by the supreme being contains nothing that could lead me astray in my beliefs. I make mistakes, not surprisingly, because my nature involves nothingness or non-being—that is, because I am not myself the supreme being, and lack countless perfections. So error is not something real that depends on God, but is merely ·something negative, a lack·, a defect. There is, therefore, nothing positively error-producing in the faculty of judgment that God gave me. When I go wrong I do so because the faculty of true judgment that I have from God is in my case not free of all limitations, ·that is, because it partly involves nothingness·.

That is still not quite right. For error isn’t a mere negation. ·Pebbles and glaciers lack knowledge, and in them that lack is a mere negation—the absence of something that there is no reason for them to possess. I have lacks of that kind too, mere negations such my lack of the ability to fly, or to multiply two 30-digit prime numbers in my head. But my tendency to error isn’t like that·. Rather, it is a privation, that is, a lack of some knowledge that I should have, ·which means that I still have a problem about how it relates to God·. When I think hard about God, it seems impossible that he should have given me a faculty that lacks some perfection that it should have. The more skilled the craftsman, the more perfect the thing that he makes; so one would expect something made by the supreme creator to be complete and perfect in every way. It is clear, furthermore, that God could have made me in such a way that I was never mistaken; and there is no doubt that he always chooses to do what is best. Does this show that my making mistakes is better than my

18

Meditations René Descartes Fourth Meditation

not doing so?

Thinking harder about this, ·three helpful thoughts come to me. Two concern our knowledge of God’s reasons generally; the third is specifically about human error·. (1) I realize that it is no cause for surprise if I don’t always understand why God acts as he does. I may well find other things he has done whose reasons elude me; and that is no reason to doubt his existence. I am now aware that my nature is very weak and limited, whereas God’s nature is immense, incomprehensible and infinite; so of course he can do countless things whose reasons I can’t know. That alone is reason enough to give up, as totally useless, the attempt that physicists make to understand the world in terms of what things are for, ·that is, in terms of God’s purposes·. Only a very rash man would think he could discover what God’s impenetrable purposes are.

(2) In estimating whether God’s works are perfect, we should look at the universe as a whole, not at created things one by one. Something that might seem very imperfect if it existed on its own has a function in relation to the rest of the universe, and may be perfect when seen in that light. My decision to doubt everything has left me sure of the existence of only two things, God and myself; but when I think about God’s immense power I have to admit that he did or could have made many things in addition to myself, so that there may be a universal scheme of things in which I have a place. ·If that is so, then judgments about what is perfect or imperfect in me should be made on the basis not just of my intrinsic nature but also of my role or function in the universe as a whole·.

(3) My errors are the only evidence I have that I am imperfect. When I look more closely into these errors of mine, I discover that they have two co-operating causes—my faculty of knowledge and my faculty of choice or freedom of the will. My errors, that is, depend on both (a) my intellect and (b) my will. ·Let us consider these separately·. (a) The intellect doesn’t affirm or deny anything; its role is only to present me with ideas regarding which I can make judgments; so strictly speaking it doesn’t involve any error at all. There may be many existing things of which my intellect gives me no ideas, but it isn’t strictly correct to say that I am deprived of such ideas, as it would be if my nature somehow entitled me to have them. I can give no reason why God ought to have given me more ideas than he did. Just because I understand someone to be a skilled craftsman, I don’t infer that he ought to have put into each of his works all the perfections he can give to some of them. So all I can say is that there are some ideas that I don’t have; this is a purely negative fact about me ·like the fact that I can’t fly; it doesn’t mean that there is anything wrong with my nature·. (b) I can’t complain that God gave me a will or freedom of choice that isn’t extensive or perfect enough, since I know by experience that will is entirely without limits. My will is so perfect and so great that I can’t conceive of its becoming even greater and more perfect; it is a striking fact that this is true of •my will and not of •any other aspect of my nature. I can easily see that my faculty of understanding is finite, to put it mildly; and I immediately conceive of a much greater •understanding—indeed, of a supremely great and infinite one; and the fact that I can form such an idea shows me that God actually has such an understanding. Similarly, if I examine •memory and •imagination and the rest, I discover that in my case these faculties are weak and limited, while in God they are immeasurable. It is only the will, or freedom of choice, which I experience as so great that I can’t make sense of the idea of its being even greater: indeed, my thought of myself as being somehow like God depends primarily upon my will. God’s will is incomparably

19

Meditations René Descartes Fourth Meditation

greater than mine in two respects: •it is accompanied by, and made firm and effective by, much more knowledge and power than I have; and •it has far more objects than my will does—·that is, God makes more choices and decisions than I do. But these comparisons—having to do with •the amount of knowledge that accompanies and helps the will, or with •the number of states of affairs to which it is applied—do not concern the will in itself, but rather its relations to other things·. When the will is considered ·not relationally, but· strictly in itself, God’s will does not seem any greater than mine. The will is simply one’s ability to do or not do something—to accept or reject a proposition, to pursue a goal or avoid something. More accurately: the ·freedom of the· will consists in the fact that when the intellect presents us with a candidate for acceptance or denial, or for pursuit or avoidance, we have no sense that we are pushed one way or the other by any external force. I can be free without being inclined both ways. Indeed, the more strongly I incline in one direction the more free my choice is—if my inclination comes from •natural knowledge (that is, from my seeing clearly that reasons of truth and goodness point that way) or from •divine grace (that is, from some mental disposition that God has given me). Freedom is never lessened—indeed it is increased and strengthened—by •natural knowledge and •divine grace. When no reason inclines me in one direction rather than another, I have a feeling of indifference—·that is, of its not mattering which way I go·—and that is the poorest kind of freedom. What it displays is freedom, considered not as a perfection but rather as a lack of knowledge—a kind of negation. If I always saw clearly what was true and good, I should never have to spend time thinking about what to believe or do; and then I would be wholly free although I was never in a state of indifference.

So the power of willing that God has given me, being extremely broad in its scope and also perfect of its kind, is not the cause of my mistakes. Nor is my power of understanding to blame: God gave it to me, so there can be no error in its activities; when I understand something I undoubtedly understand it correctly. Well, then, where do my mistakes come from? Their source is the fact that my will has a wider scope than my intellect has, ·so that I am free to form beliefs on topics that I don’t understand·. Instead of ·behaving as I ought to, namely by· restricting my will to the territory that my understanding covers, ·that is, suspending judgment when I am not intellectually in control·, I let my will run loose, applying it to matters that I don’t understand. In such cases there is nothing to stop the will from veering this way or that, so it easily turns away from what is true and good. That is the source of my error and sin.

Here is an example ·of how (1) the will’s behaviour when there is true understanding contrasts with (2) its behaviour when there isn’t·. (1) A while ago I asked whether anything in the world exists, and I came to realize that the fact of my raising this question shows quite clearly that I exist. I understood this so vividly that I couldn’t help judging that it was true. This was not the ‘couldn’t help’ that comes from being compelled by some external force. What happened was just this: a great light in the intellect was followed by a great inclination in the will. I was not in a state of indifference, ·feeling that I could as well go one way as the other·; but this lack of indifference was a measure of how spontaneous and free my belief was. ·It would have indicated unfreedom only if it had come from the compulsion of something external, rather than coming from within myself·. (2) As well as knowing that I exist, at least as a thinking thing, I have in my mind an idea of corporeal nature; and I am not sure whether my thinking nature—which makes me what I am—is

20

Meditations René Descartes Fourth Meditation

the same as this corporeal nature or different from it. I take it that my intellect has not yet found any convincing reason for either answer; so I am indifferent with regard to this question—nothing pushes or pulls me towards one answer or the other, or indeed towards giving any answer.

The will is indifferent not only when the intellect is wholly ignorant but also when it doesn’t have clear enough knowledge at the time when the will is trying to reach a decision. A probable conjecture may pull me one way; but when I realize that it is a mere conjecture and not a certain and indubitable reason, that in itself will push me the other way. My experience in the last few days confirms this: the mere fact that I found all my previous beliefs to be somewhat open to doubt was enough to switch me from confidently believing them to supposing them to be wholly false.

If when I don’t perceive the truth vividly and clearly enough I simply suspend judgment, it’s clear that I am behaving correctly and avoiding error. It is a misuse of my free will to have an opinion in such cases: if I choose the wrong side I shall be in error; and even if I choose the right side, I shall be at fault because I’ll have come to the truth by sheer chance and not through a perception of my intellect. The latter, as the natural light shows me clearly, should be what influences my will when I affirm things. I have said that error is essentially a privation—a lack of something that I should have—and now I know what this privation consists in. It doesn’t lie in •the will that God has given me, or even in •the mode of operation that God has built into it; rather it consists in •my misuse of my will. ·Specifically, it consists in •my lack of restraint in the exercise of my will, when I form opinions on matters that I don’t clearly understand·.

I can’t complain that God did not give me a greater power of understanding than he did: created intellects are naturally finite, and so they naturally lack understanding of many things. God has never owed me anything, so I should thank him for his great generosity to me, rather than feeling cheated because he did not give me everything.

Nor can I reasonably complain that God gave me a will that extends more widely than my intellect. The will is a single unitary thing; its nature is such, it seems, that there could be no way of taking away parts of it. Anyway, should not the great extent of my will be a cause for further thanks to him who gave it to me?

Finally, I must not complain that God consents to the acts of will in which I go wrong. What there is in these acts that comes from God is wholly true and good; and it is a perfection in me that I can perform them. Falsity and error are essentially a privation; and this privation isn’t something to which God consents, because it isn’t a thing at all. Indeed, when it is considered in relation to God as its cause, it isn’t really a privation but rather a mere negation. ·That is, it is a mere fact about something that is not the case; it does not involve the notion that it ought to be the case. I ought to restrain my will when I don’t understand, but it isn’t true that God ought to have forced such restraint on me·. God has given me the freedom to assent or not assent in cases where he did not give me clear understanding; he is surely not to blame for that. But I am to blame for misusing that freedom by coming to conclusions on matters that I don’t fully understand. Of course God easily could have arranged things so that, while keeping all my freedom and still being limited in what I understand, I never made a mistake. He could do this either by •giving me a vivid and clear understanding of everything that I was ever likely to think about; or by •forcing me always to remember that I ought not to form opinions on matters I don’t vividly and clearly understand. I can see that if God had made me this way, I would—considered just in myself, as if nothing else

21

Meditations René Descartes Fourth Meditation

existed—have been more perfect than I actually am. But the universe as a whole may have some perfection that requires that some parts of it be capable of error while others are not, so that it would be a worse universe if all its parts were exactly alike ·in being immune from error·. I am not entitled to complain about God’s giving me a lower role in his scheme of things ·by selecting me as one of the creatures that isn’t protected from error·.

What is more, even if I have no power to avoid error by •having a vivid perception of everything I have to think about, I can avoid it simply by •remembering to withhold judgment on anything that isn’t clear to me. I admit to having the weakness that I can’t keep my attention fixed on a single item of knowledge (·such as the no-judgment-when-clarity-of-perception-is-lacking rule·); but by attentive and repeated meditation I can get myself to remember it as often as the need arises, and thus to get into the habit of avoiding error.

This is where man’s greatest and most important perfection is to be found; so today’s meditation, with its enquiry into the cause of error, has been very profitable. I must be right in my explanation of the cause of error. If I restrain my will so that I form opinions only on what the intellect vividly and clearly reveals, I cannot possibly go wrong. Here is why. Every vivid and clear perception is undoubtedly something real and positive; so it can’t come from nothing, and must come from God. He is supremely perfect; it would be downright contradictory to suppose that he is a deceiver. So the vivid and clear perception must be true. So today I have learned not only how to avoid error but also how to arrive at the truth. It is beyond question that I shall reach the truth if I think hard enough about •the things that I perfectly understand, keeping them separate from •all the other matters in which my thoughts are more confused and obscure. That is what I shall be really careful to do from now on.

22

Meditations René Descartes Fifth Meditation

Fifth Meditation:

The essence of material things, and the existence of God considered a second time

There are many enquiries still to be made about God’s attributes, and many about my own nature (that is, the nature of my mind). I may take these up at some time; but right now I have a more pressing task. Now that I have seen how to reach the truth—what to do and what to avoid—I must try to escape from the doubts that beset me a few days ago, and see whether anything can be known for certain about material objects.

Before enquiring into whether there are any such things, I should consider the ideas of them in my thought, in order to see which of those ideas are distinct and which confused.

I distinctly imagine quantity—that is, the length, breadth and depth of the quantity, or rather of the thing that is quantified. I also enumerate the thing’s parts, to which I attribute various sizes, shapes, positions and movements; and to the movements I attribute various durations, ·that is, I say how long each movement lasts·.

Size, shape, position and so on are well known and transparent to me as general kinds of phenomenon, but there are also countless particular facts involving them that I perceive when I attend to them. The truths about all these matters are so open to me, and so much in harmony with my nature, that when I first discover any of them it feels less like •learning something new than like •remembering something I had known before, or •noticing for the first time something that was already in my mind without my having turned my mental gaze onto it.

The most important point is that I find in myself countless ideas of things that can’t be called nothing, even if they don’t exist anywhere outside me. For although I am free to think of these ideas or not, as I choose, I didn’t invent them: they have their own true and immutable natures, ·which are not under my control·. Even if there are not and never were any triangles outside my thought, still, when I imagine a triangle ·I am constrained in how I do this, because· there is a determinate nature or essence or form of triangle that is eternal, unchanging, and independent of my mind. Consider the things that I can prove about the triangle—that its three angles equal two right angles, that its longest side is opposite its greatest angle, and so on. I now clearly recognize these properties of the triangle, whether I want to or not, even if I didn’t give them a thought when the triangle first came into my mind. So they can’t have been invented by me.

It does not help to point out that I have sometimes seen triangular bodies, so that the idea of the triangle might have come to me from them through my sense organs. I can prove truths about the properties not only of triangles but of countless other shapes that I know I have never encountered through the senses. These properties must be something, not pure nothing: whatever is true is something; and these properties are true because I am clearly aware of them. (I have already proved that everything of which I am clearly aware is true; and even if I hadn’t proved it, my mind is so constituted that I have to assent to these ·geometrical· propositions as long as I perceive them.) I remember, too, that even back in the times when the objects of the senses held my attention, I regarded the clearly apprehended propositions of pure mathematics—including arithmetic and geometry—as the most certain of all.

23

Meditations René Descartes Fifth Meditation

·The preceding two paragraphs lead to this conclusion·: The mere fact that I find in my thought an idea of something x, and vividly and clearly perceive x to have a certain property, it follows that x really does have that property. Can I not turn this to account in a second argument to prove the existence of God? The idea of God (that is, of a supremely perfect being) is certainly one that I find within me, just as I find the ideas of shapes and numbers; and I understand ·from this idea· that it belongs to God’s nature that he always exists. This understanding is just as vivid and clear as what is involved in ·mathematical· proofs of the properties of shapes and numbers. So even if I have sometimes gone wrong in my meditations in these past days, I ought still to regard the existence of God as being at least as certain as I have taken the truths of mathematics to be.

At first sight, this looks like a trick. Where things other than God are involved, I have been accustomed to distinguish a thing’s existence from its essence. ·The question ‘What is the essence of triangles (or flames or sparrows)?’ asks what it takes for something to qualify as a triangle (or flame or sparrow). Answering this still leaves open the existence question, which asks whether there are any triangles (or flames or sparrows)·. I can easily believe that in the case of God, also, existence can be separated from essence, ·letting us answer the •essence question about God while leaving the •existence question open·, so that God can be thought of as not existing. But on more careful reflection it becomes quite evident that, just as having-internal-angles-equal-to-180° can’t be separated from the idea ·or essence· of a triangle, and as the idea of highlands can’t be separated from the idea of lowlands, so existence can’t be separated from the essence of God. Just as it is self-contradictory to think of highlands in a world where there are no lowlands, so it is self-contradictory to think of God as not existing—that is, to think of a supremely perfect being as lacking a perfection, namely the perfection of existence. [What Descartes wrote is usually translated as ‘mountains in a world where there are no valleys’, but that is obviously not self-contradictory. The Latin provides no escape from this, but Descartes may have been thinking in French, in which vallée can mean ‘valley’ in our sense but can be used to refer to foothills, the lower slopes of a mountain, or the plain immediately surrounding the mountain. So ‘highlands’/‘lowlands’ has been adopted as a compromise: compact and fairly close to what he presumably meant.]

·Here is a possible objection to the preceding two paragraphs·:

I can’t think of God except as existing, just as I can’t think of a river without banks. From the latter fact, though, it certainly doesn’t follow that there are any rivers in the world; so why should it follow from the former fact that God exists? How things are in reality is not settled by my thought; and just as I can imagine a winged horse even though no horse has wings, so I can attach existence to God in my thought even if no God exists.

This involves false reasoning. From the fact that I can’t think of a river without banks, it does not follow that a river with banks exists anywhere, but simply that river and banks—whether or not there are any in reality—are inseparable. On the other hand, from the fact that I can’t think of God except as existing it follows that God and existence are inseparable, which is to say that God really exists. My thought doesn’t make it so; it doesn’t create necessities. The influence runs the opposite way: the necessity of the thing constrains how I can think, depriving me of the freedom to think of God without existence (that is, a supremely perfect being without a supreme perfection), like my freedom to imagine a horse with or without wings.

24

Meditations René Descartes Fifth Meditation

Here is a ·further· possible objection to this line of thought:

Admittedly, once I have supposed that •all perfections belong to God, I must suppose that he exists, because existence is one of the perfections. But what entitles me to suppose God to have all perfections? Similarly, if I suppose that •all quadrilaterals can be inscribed in a circle, I have to conclude that a rhombus can be inscribed in a circle; but that is plainly false, which shows that the original supposition was wrong.

I agree that I don’t have to think about God at all; but whenever I do choose to think of him, bringing the idea of the first and supreme being out of my mind’s store, I must attribute all perfections to him, even if I don’t attend to them individually straight away. This necessity ·in my thought· guarantees that, when I later realize that existence is a perfection, I am right to conclude then that the first and supreme being exists. Similarly, I don’t ever have to imagine a triangle; but whenever I do wish to consider a figure with straight sides and three angles, I must attribute to it properties from which it follows that its three angles equal no more than 180°, even if I don’t notice this at the time. When on the other hand I examine what figures can be inscribed in a circle, I am not compelled to think that this class includes all quadrilaterals. Indeed, I cannot—while thinking vividly and clearly—even pretend that all quadrilaterals can be inscribed in a circle. This kind of false pretence is vastly different from the true ideas that are innate in me, of which the first and chief is the idea of God. This idea isn’t a fiction, a creature of my thought, but rather an image of a true and unchanging nature; and I have several indications that this is so. •God is the only thing I can think of whose existence necessarily belongs to its essence. •I can’t make sense of there being two or more Gods of this kind; and after supposing that one God exists, I plainly see that it is necessary that he has existed from eternity and will stay in existence for eternity. •I perceive many other attributes of God, none of which I can remove or alter.

Whatever method of proof I use, though, I am always brought back to the fact that nothing completely convinces me except what I vividly and clearly perceive. Some things that I vividly and clearly perceive are obvious to everyone; others can be learned only through more careful investigation, but once they are discovered they are judged to be just as certain as the obvious ones. (Compare these two truths about right-angled triangles: ‘The square on the hypotenuse equals the sum of the squares on the other two sides’ and ‘The hypotenuse is opposite the largest angle’. The former is less obvious than the latter; but once one has seen it, one believes it just as strongly.) ·Truths about God are not in the immediately obvious class, but they ought to be·. If I were not swamped by preconceived opinions, and if my thoughts were not hemmed in and pushed around by images of things perceived by the senses, I would acknowledge God sooner and more easily than anything else. The supreme being exists; God, the only being whose essence includes existence, exists; what is more self-evident than that?

Although I came to see this only through careful thought, I am now just as certain of it as I am of anything at all. Not only that, but I see that all other certainties depend on this one, so that without it I can’t know anything for sure. ·The next two paragraphs explain why this is so·.

While I am perceiving something vividly and clearly, I can’t help believing it to be true. That is a fact about my nature. Here is another: I can’t fix my mind’s eye continually on the same thing, so as to keep perceiving it clearly; so that sometimes the arguments that led me to a certain conclusion slip out of my focus of attention, though I remember the

25

Meditations René Descartes Fifth Meditation

conclusion itself. That threatens me with the following state of affairs, from which I am protected only by being aware of the existence of God:

In a case where I am not attending to the arguments that led me to a conclusion, my confidence in the conclusion might be undermined by arguments going the other way. When I think hard about triangles, for instance, it seems quite obvious to me—steeped as I am in the principles of geometry—that a triangle’s three angles are equal to 180°; and while I am attending to the proof of this I can’t help believing it. But as soon as I turn my mind’s eye away from the proof, then in spite of still remembering that I perceived it very clearly ·but without now getting it clear in my mind again·, I can easily doubt its truth. So nothing is ever finally established and settled—I can have no true and certain knowledge, but only shifting and changeable opinions. For I can convince myself that I am naturally liable to go wrong sometimes in matters that I think I perceive as evidently as can be. This seems even more likely when I remember that I have often regarded as certainly true some propositions that other arguments have later led me to think false.

That is what my situation would be if I were not aware of the existence of God.

But now I have seen that God exists, and have understood that everything else depends on him and that he is not a deceiver; from which I have inferred that everything that I vividly and clearly perceive must be true. So even when I am no longer attending to the arguments that led me to accept this (·i.e. the proposition about triangles·), as long as I remember that I vividly and clearly perceived it no counter-arguments can make me doubt it. It is something that I know for certain ·and in an unshakable way· to be true. That applies not only to this one proposition but to anything that I remember ever having proved in geometry and the like. Why should I call these matters into doubt? •Because I am so built as to be prone to frequent error? No: I now know that when I have something in mind in a transparently clear way I cannot be in error about it. •Because I have in the past regarded as certainly true many things that I afterwards recognized to be false? No: the things that I later came to doubt had not been vividly and clearly perceived in the first place: I had come to accept them for reasons that I later found to be unreliable, because I hadn’t yet discovered this rule for establishing the truth. •Because I may be dreaming, so that my present thoughts have as little truth as those of a person who is asleep? I put this objection to myself a while ago. It doesn’t change anything, because if something is evident to my intellect, even when I am dreaming, then it is true.

Thus I see plainly that the certainty and truth of all knowledge depends strictly on my awareness of the true God. So much so that until I became aware of him I couldn’t perfectly know anything. Now I can achieve full and certain knowledge of countless matters, both concerning God himself and other things whose nature is intellectual, and also concerning the whole of the corporeal nature that is the subject-matter of pure mathematics.

26

Meditations René Descartes Sixth Meditation

Sixth Meditation:

The existence of material things, and the real distinction between mind and body

The remaining task is to consider whether material things exist. Insofar as they are the subject-matter of pure mathematics, I perceive [here = ‘conceive’] them vividly and clearly; so I at least know that they could exist, because anything that I perceive in that way could be created by God. (The only reason I have ever accepted for thinking that •something could not be made by him is that there would be a contradiction in my perceiving •it distinctly.) My faculty of imagination, which I am aware of using when I turn my mind to material things, also suggests that they really exist. For when I think harder about what imagination is, it seems to be simply an application of •the faculty of knowing to •a body that is intimately present to it—and that has to be a body that exists.

To make this clear, I will first examine how •imagination differs from •pure understanding. When I imagine a triangle, for example, I don’t merely •understand that it is a three-sided figure, but I also •see the three lines with my mind’s eye as if they were present to me; that is what imagining is. But if I think of a chiliagon [= ‘thousand-sided figure’, pronounced kill-ee-a-gon], although I •understand quite well that it is a figure with a thousand sides, I don’t •imagine the thousand sides or see them as if they were present to me. When I think of a body, I usually form some kind of image; so in thinking of a chiliagon I may construct in my mind—·strictly speaking, in my imagination·—a confused representation of some figure. But obviously it won’t be a chiliagon, for it is the very same image that I would form if I were thinking of, say, a figure with ten thousand sides. So it wouldn’t help me to recognize the properties that distinguish a chiliagon from other many-sided figures. In the case of a pentagon, the situation is different. I can of course understand this figure without the help of the imagination (just as I can understand a chiliagon); but I can also imagine a pentagon, by applying my mind’s eye to its five sides and the area they enclose. This imagining, I find, takes more mental effort than understanding does; and that is enough to show clearly that imagination is different from pure understanding.

Being able to imagine isn’t essential to me, as being able to understand is; for even if I had no power of imagination I would still be the same individual that I am. This seems to imply that my power of imagining depends on something other than myself; and I can easily understand that ·if there is such a thing as my body—that is·, if my mind is joined to a certain body in such a way that it can contemplate that body whenever it wants to—then it might be this very body that enables me to imagine corporeal things. So it may be that imagining differs from pure understanding purely like this: •when the mind understands, it somehow turns in on itself and inspects one of its own ideas; but •when it imagines, it turns away from itself and looks at something in the body (something that conforms to an idea—either one understood by the mind or one perceived by the senses). I can, I repeat, easily see that this might be how imagination comes about if the body exists; and since I can think of no other equally good way of explaining what imagination is, I can conjecture that the body exists. But this is only a probability. Even after all my careful enquiry I still can’t see how, on the basis of the idea of corporeal nature that I find in my imagination, to prove for sure that some body exists.

27

Meditations René Descartes Sixth Meditation

As well as the corporeal nature that is the subject-matter of pure mathematics, I am also accustomed to imagining colours, sounds, tastes, pain and so on—though not so distinctly. Now, I perceive these much better by means of the senses, which is how (helped by memory) they appear to have reached the imagination. So in order to deal with them more fully, I must attend to the senses—that is, to the kind of thinking [here = ‘mental activity’] that I call ‘sensory perception’. I want to know whether the things that are perceived through the senses provide me with any sure argument for the existence of bodies.

To begin with, I will (1) go back over everything that I originally took to be perceived by the senses, and reckoned to be true; and I will go over my reasons for thinking this. Next, I will (2) set out my reasons for later doubting these things. Finally, I will (3) consider what I should now believe about them.

(1) First of all, then, I perceived by my senses that I had a head, hands, feet and other limbs making up the body that I regarded as part of myself, or perhaps even as my whole self. I also perceived by my senses that this body was situated among many other bodies that could harm or help it; and I detected the favourable effects by a sensation of pleasure and the unfavourable ones by pain. As well as pain and pleasure, I also had sensations of hunger, thirst, and other such appetites, and also of bodily states tending towards cheerfulness, sadness, anger and similar emotions. Outside myself, besides the extension, shapes and movements of bodies, I also had sensations of their hardness and heat, and of the other qualities that can be known by touch. In addition, I had sensations of light, colours, smells, tastes and sounds, and differences amongst these enabled me to sort out the sky, the earth, the seas and other bodies from one another. All I was immediately aware of in each case were my ideas, but it was reasonable for me to think that what I was perceiving through the senses were external bodies that caused the ideas. For I found that these ideas came to me quite without my consent: I couldn’t have that kind of idea of any object, even if I wanted to, if the object was not present to my sense organs; and I couldn’t avoid having the idea when the object was present. Also, since the ideas that came through the senses were much more lively and vivid and sharp than •ones that I formed voluntarily when thinking about things, and than •ones that I found impressed on my memory, it seemed impossible that sensory ideas were coming from within me; so I had to conclude that they came from external things. My only way of knowing about these things was through the ideas themselves, so it was bound to occur to me that the things might resemble the ideas. In addition, I remembered that I had the use of my senses before I ever had the use of reason; and I saw that the ideas that I formed were, for the most part, made up of elements of sensory ideas. This convinced me that I had nothing at all in my intellect that I had not previously had in sensation. As for the body that by some special right I called ‘mine’: I had reason to think that it belonged to me in a way that no other body did. ·There were three reasons for this·. •I could never be separated from it, as I could from other bodies; •I felt all my appetites and emotions in it and on account of it; and •I was aware of pain and pleasurable ticklings in parts of this body but not in any other body. But why should that curious sensation of pain give rise to a particular distress of mind; and why should a certain kind of delight follow on a tickling sensation? Again, why should that curious tugging in the stomach that I call ‘hunger’ tell me that I should eat, or a dryness of the throat tell me to drink, and so on? I couldn’t explain any of this, except to say that nature taught me so. For there is no connection (or

28

Meditations René Descartes Sixth Meditation

none that I understand) between the tugging sensation and the decision to eat, or between the sensation of something causing pain and the mental distress that arises from it. It seems that nature taught me to make these judgments about objects of the senses, for I was making them before I had any arguments to support them.

(2) Later on, however, my experiences gradually undermined all my faith in the senses. A tower that had looked round from a distance appeared square from close up; an enormous statue standing on a high column didn’t look large from the ground. In countless such cases I found that the judgments of the external senses were mistaken, and the same was true of the internal senses. What can be more internal than pain? Yet I heard that an amputee might occasionally seem to feel pain in the missing limb. So even in my own case, I had to conclude, it was not quite certain that a particular limb was hurting, even if I felt pain in it. To these reasons for doubting, I recently added two very general ones. •The first was that every sensory experience I ever thought I was having while awake I can also think of myself as having while asleep; and since I don’t believe that what I seem to perceive in sleep comes from things outside me, I didn’t see why I should be any more inclined to believe this of what I think I perceive while awake. •The second reason for doubt was that for all I knew to the contrary I might be so constituted that I am liable to error even in matters that seem to me most true. (I couldn’t rule this out, because I did not know—or at least was pretending not to know—who made me.) And it was easy to refute the reasons for my earlier confidence about the truth of what I perceived by the senses. Since I seemed to be naturally drawn towards many things that reason told me to avoid, I reckoned that I should not place much confidence in what I was taught by nature. Also, I decided, the mere fact that the perceptions of the senses didn’t depend on my will was not enough to show that they came from outside me; for they might have been produced by some faculty of mine that I didn’t yet know.

(3) But now, when I am beginning to know myself and my maker better, although I don’t think I should recklessly accept everything I seem to have acquired from the senses, neither do I think it should all be called into doubt.

First, I know that if I have a vivid and clear thought of something, God could have created it in a way that exactly corresponds to my thought. So the fact that I can vividly and clearly think of one thing apart from another assures me that the two things are distinct from one another—·that is, that they are two·—since they can be separated by God. Never mind how they could be separated; that does not affect the judgment that they are distinct. ·So my mind is a distinct thing from my body. Furthermore, my mind is me, for the following reason·. I know that I exist and that nothing else belongs to my nature or essence except that I am a thinking thing; from this it follows that my essence consists solely in my being a thinking thing, even though there may be a body that is very closely joined to me. I have a vivid and clear idea of •myself as something that thinks and isn’t extended, and one of •body as something that is extended and does not think. So it is certain that •I am really distinct from •my body and can exist without it.

Besides this, I find that I am capable of certain special kinds of thinking [= ‘mental activity’], namely imagination and sensory perception. Now, I can vividly and clearly understand •myself as a whole without •these faculties; but I can’t understand •them without •me, that is, without an intellectual substance for them to belong to. A faculty or ability essentially involves acts, so it involves some thing that acts; so I see that •I differ from •my faculties as •a thing differs from •its properties. Of course there are other

29

Meditations René Descartes Sixth Meditation

faculties—such as those of moving around, changing shape, and so on—which also need a substance to belong to; but it must be a bodily or extended substance and not a thinking one, because a vivid and clear conception of those faculties includes extension but not thought. Now, I have a passive faculty of sensory perception, that is, an ability to receive and recognize ideas of perceptible objects; but I would have no use for this unless something—myself or something else—had an active faculty for producing those ideas in the first place. But this faculty can’t be in me, since clearly it does not presuppose any thought on my part, and sensory ideas are produced without my cooperation and often even against my will. So sensory ideas must be produced by some substance other than me—a substance that actually has (either in a straightforward way or in a higher form) all the reality that is represented in the ideas that it produces. Either (a) this substance is a body, in which case it will •straightforwardly contain everything that is represented in the ideas; or else (b) it is God, or some creature more noble than a body, in which case it will contain •in a higher form whatever is to be found in the ideas. I can ·reject (b), and· be confident that God does not transmit sensory ideas to me either directly from himself or through some creature that does not straightforwardly contain what is represented in the ideas. God has given me no way of recognizing any such ‘higher form’ source for these ideas; on the contrary, he has strongly inclined me to believe that bodies produce them. So if the ideas were transmitted from a source other than corporeal things, God would be a deceiver; and he is not. So bodies exist. They may not all correspond exactly with my sensory intake of them, for much of what comes in through the senses is obscure and confused. But at least bodies have all the properties that I vividly and clearly understand, that is, all that fall within the province of pure mathematics.

·Those are the •clearly understood properties of bodies •in general·. What about •less clearly understood properties (for example light or sound or pain), and properties of •particular bodies (for example the size or shape of the sun)? Although there is much doubt and uncertainty about them, I have a sure hope that I can reach the truth even in these matters. That is because God isn’t a deceiver, which implies that he has given me the ability to correct any falsity there may be in my opinions. Indeed, everything that I am ‘taught by nature’ certainly contains some truth. For the term ‘nature’, understood in the most general way, refers to God himself or to the ordered system of created things established by him. And my own nature is simply the totality of things bestowed on me by God.

As vividly as it teaches me anything, my own nature teaches me that I have a body, that when I feel pain there is something wrong with this body, that when I am hungry or thirsty it needs food and drink, and so on. So I shouldn’t doubt that there is some truth in this.

Nature also teaches me, through these sensations of pain, hunger, thirst and so on, that I (a thinking thing) am not merely in my body as a sailor is in a ship. Rather, I am closely joined to it—intermingled with it, so to speak—so that it and I form a unit. If this were not so, I wouldn’t feel pain when the body was hurt but would perceive the damage in an intellectual way, like a sailor seeing that his ship needs repairs. And when the body needed food or drink I would intellectually understand this fact instead of (as I do) having confused sensations of hunger and thirst. These sensations are confused mental events that arise from the union—the intermingling, as it were—of the mind with the body.

Nature also teaches me that various other bodies exist in the vicinity of my body, and that I should seek out some of these and avoid others. Also, I perceive by my senses a

30

Meditations René Descartes Sixth Meditation

great variety of colours, sounds, smells and tastes, as well as differences in heat, hardness and so on; from which I infer that the bodies that cause these sensory perceptions differ from one another in ways that correspond to the sensory differences, though perhaps they don’t resemble them. Furthermore, some perceptions are pleasant while others are nasty, which shows that my body—or rather my whole self insofar as I am a combination of body and mind—can be affected by the various helpful or harmful bodies that surround it.

However, some of what I thought I had learned from nature really came not from nature but from a habit of rushing to conclusions; and those beliefs could be false. Here are a few examples:

•that if a region contains nothing that stimulates my senses, then it must be empty;

•that the heat in a body resembles my idea of heat;

•that the colour I perceive through my senses is also present in the body that I perceive;

•that in a body that is bitter or sweet there is the same taste that I experience, and so on;

•that stars and towers and other distant bodies have the same size and shape that they present to my senses.

To think clearly about this matter, I need to define exactly what I mean when I say that ‘nature teaches me’ something. I am not at this point taking ‘nature’ to refer to the totality of what God has given me. From that totality I am excluding things that belong to the mind alone, such as my knowledge that what has been done can’t be undone (I know this through the natural light, without help from the body). I am also excluding things that relate to the body alone, such as the tendency bodies have to fall downwards. My sole concern here is with what God has given to me as a combination of mind and body. My ‘nature’, then, in this limited sense, does indeed teach me to avoid what hurts and to seek out what gives pleasure, and so on. But it doesn’t appear to teach us to rush to conclusions about things located outside us without pausing to think about the question; for knowledge of the truth about such things seems to belong to the mind alone, not to the combination of mind and body. So, although a star has no more effect on my eye than a candle’s flame, my thinking of the star as no bigger than the flame does not come from any positive ·‘natural’· inclination to believe this; it’s just a habit of thought that I have had ever since childhood, with no rational basis for it. Similarly, although I feel heat when I approach a fire and feel pain when I go too near, there is no good reason to think that something in the fire resembles the heat, or resembles the pain. There is merely reason to suppose that something or other in the fire causes feelings of heat or pain in us. Again, even when a region contains nothing that stimulates my senses, it does not follow that it contains no bodies. I now realize that in these cases and many others I have been in the habit of misusing the order of nature. The right way to use the sensory perceptions that nature gives me is as a guide to what is beneficial or harmful for my mind-body complex; and they are vivid and clear enough for that. But it is a misuse of them to treat them as reliable guides to the essential nature of the bodies located outside me, for on that topic they give only very obscure and confused information.

I have already looked closely enough at how I may come to make false judgments, even though God is good. Now it occurs to me that there is a problem about •mistakes I make regarding the things that nature tells me to seek out or avoid, and also regarding •some of my internal sensations. Some cases of this are unproblematic. Someone may be tricked into eating pleasant-tasting food that has poison

31

Meditations René Descartes Sixth Meditation

concealed in it; but here nature urges the person towards the pleasant food, not towards the poison, which it doesn’t know about. All this shows is that the person’s nature doesn’t know everything, and that is no surprise.

·Other cases, however, raise problems. They are ones where· nature urges us towards something that harms us ·and this can’t be explained through nature’s not knowing something·. Sick people, for example, may want food or drink that is bad for them. ‘They go wrong because they are ill’—true, but the difficulty remains. A sick man is one of God’s creatures just as a healthy one is, and in each case it seems a contradiction to suppose that God has given him a nature that deceives him. A badly made clock conforms to the laws of its nature in telling the wrong time, just as a well made and accurate clock does; and we might look at the human body in the same way. We could see it as a kind of machine made up of bones, nerves, muscles, veins, blood and skin in such a way that, even if there were no mind in it, it would still move exactly as it now does in all the cases where movement isn’t under the control of the will or, therefore, of the mind. If such a body suffers from dropsy [a disease in which abnormal quantities of water accumulate in the body], for example, and is affected by the dryness of the throat that normally produces in the mind a sensation of thirst, that will affect the nerves and other bodily parts in such a way as to dispose the body to take a drink, which will make the disease worse. Yet this is as natural as a healthy body’s being stimulated by a similar dryness of the throat to take a drink that is good for it. ·In a way, we might say, it is not natural·. Just as we could say that a clock that works badly is ‘departing from its nature’, we might say that the dropsical body that takes a harmful drink is ‘departing from its nature’, that is, from the pattern of movements that usually occur in human bodies. But that involves using ‘nature’ as a way of comparing one thing with another—a sick man with a healthy one, a badly made clock with an accurate one—whereas I have been using ‘nature’ not to make comparisons but to speak of what can be found in the things themselves; and this usage is legitimate.

When we describe a dropsical body as having ‘a disordered nature’, therefore, we are using the term ‘nature’ merely to compare sick with healthy. What has gone wrong in the mind-body complex that suffers from dropsy, however, is not a mere matter of comparison with something else. There is here a real, intrinsic error of nature, namely that the body is thirsty at a time when drink will cause it harm. We have to enquire how it is that the goodness of God does not prevent nature from deceiving us in this way. ·This enquiry will fall into four main parts·.

•There is a great difference between the mind and the body. Every body is by its nature divisible, but the mind can’t be divided. When I consider the mind—i.e. consider myself purely as a thinking thing—I can’t detect any parts within myself; I understand myself to be something single and complete. The whole mind seems to be united to the whole body, ·but not by a uniting of parts to parts, because:· If a foot or arm or any other part of the body is cut off, nothing is thereby taken away from the mind. As for the faculties of willing, of understanding, of sensory perception and so on, these are not parts of the mind, since it is one and the same mind that wills, understands and perceives. ·They are (I repeat) not parts of the mind, because they are properties or powers of it·. By contrast, any corporeal thing can easily be divided into parts in my thought; and this shows me that it is really divisible. This one argument would be enough to show me that the mind is completely different from the body, even if I did not already know as much from other considerations ·in (3) on page 29·.

32

Meditations René Descartes Sixth Meditation

•The mind isn’t immediately affected by all parts of the body but only by the brain—or perhaps just by the small part of it which is said to contain the ‘common sense’. [Descartes is referring to the pineal gland. The ‘common sense’ was a supposed faculty, postulated by Aristotle, whose role was to integrate the data from the five specialized senses.] The signals that reach the mind depend upon what state this part of the brain is in, irrespective of the condition of the other parts of the body. There is abundant experimental evidence for this, which I needn’t review here.

•Whenever any part of the body is moved by another part that is some distance away, it can be moved in the same fashion by any of the parts that lie in between, without the more distant part doing anything. For example, in a cord ABCD, if one end D is pulled so that the other end A moves, A could have been moved in just the same way if B or C had been pulled and D had not moved at all. Similarly, when I feel a pain in my foot, this happens by means of nerves that run from the foot up to the brain. When the nerves are pulled in the foot, they pull on inner parts of the brain and make them move; and nature has laid it down that this motion should produce in the mind a sensation of pain as though occurring in the foot. But since these nerves stretch from the foot to the brain through the calf, the thigh, the lumbar region, the back and the neck, that same sensation of ‘pain in the foot’ can come about when one of the intermediate parts is pulled, even if nothing happens in the foot. This presumably holds for any other sensation.

•One kind of movement in the part of the brain that immediately affects the mind always produces just one kind of sensation; and it would be best for us if it were always the kind that would contribute the most to keeping us alive and well. Experience shows that the sensations that nature has given us are all of just such kinds; so everything about them bears witness to the power and goodness of God. For example, when the nerves in the foot are set in motion in a violent and unusual manner, this motion reaches the inner parts of the brain via the spinal cord, and gives the mind its signal for having a sensation of a pain as occurring in the foot. This stimulates the mind to do its best to remove the cause of the pain, which it takes to be harmful to the foot. God could have made our nature such that this motion in the brain indicated something else to the mind—for example, making the mind aware of the actual motion occurring in the brain, or in the foot, or in any of the intermediate regions. [Descartes is here contrasting the foot with other parts of the body, and contrasting a feeling of pain with a merely intellectual awareness that a movement is occurring.] But nothing else would have been so conducive to the continued well-being of the body. In the same way, when we need drink a certain dryness arises in the throat; this moves the nerves of the throat, which in turn move the inner parts of the brain. That produces in the mind a sensation of thirst, because the most useful thing for us to know at this point is that we need drink in order to stay healthy. Similarly in the other cases.

All of this makes it clear that, despite God’s immense goodness, the nature of man as a combination of mind and body is such that it is bound to mislead him from time to time. For along the route of the nerves from the foot to the brain, or even in the brain itself, something may happen that produces the same motion that is usually caused by injury to the foot; and then pain will be felt as if it were in the foot. This deception of the senses is natural, because a given kind of motion in the brain must always produce the same kind of sensation in the mind; and, given that this kind of motion usually originates in the foot, it is reasonable that it should produce a sensation indicating a pain in the foot. Similarly with dryness of the throat: it is much better that it should

33

Meditations René Descartes Sixth Meditation

mislead on the rare occasion when the person has dropsy than that it should always mislead when the body is in good health. The same holds for the other cases.

This line of thought greatly helps me to be aware of all the errors to which my nature is liable, and also to correct or avoid them. For I know that so far as bodily well-being is concerned my senses usually tell the truth. Also, I can usually employ more than one sense to investigate the same thing; and I can get further help from my memory, which connects present experiences with past ones, and from my intellect, which has by now examined all the sources of error. So I should have no more fears about the falsity of what my senses tell me every day; on the contrary, the exaggerated doubts of the last few days should be dismissed as laughable. This applies especially to the chief reason for doubt, namely my inability to distinguish dreams from waking experience. For I now notice that the two are vastly different, in that dreams are never linked by memory with all the other actions of life as waking experiences are. If, while I am awake, a man were suddenly to appear to me and then disappear immediately, as happens in sleep, so that I couldn’t see where he had come from or where he had gone to, I could reasonably judge that he was a ghost or an hallucination rather than a real man. But if I have a firm grasp of when, where and whence something comes to me, and if I can connect my perception of it with the whole of the rest of my life without a break, then I am sure that in encountering it I am not asleep but awake. And I ought not to have any doubt of its reality if that is unanimously confirmed by all my senses as well as my memory and intellect. From the fact that God isn’t a deceiver it follows that in cases like this I am completely free from error. But since everyday pressures don’t always allow us to pause and check so carefully, it must be admitted that human life is vulnerable to error about particular things, and we must acknowledge the weakness of our nature.

34

Objections to the Meditations and Descartes’s Replies

René Descartes

Copyright ©2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are reported between brackets in normal-sized type. The seventh set of objections is long, bad, and omitted. Originally only Hobbes’s comments were inter-leaved with Descartes’s replies; but that format is adopted here for all six sets, creating a little strain only with the replies to Caterus. Unadorned surnames in this version usually replace something less blunt—‘Dominus Cartesius’, ‘the author’, ‘my critic’, ‘the learned theologian’ and so on.
First launched: July 2006 Last amended: November 2007
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

First Objections (Caterus) and Descartes’s replies   1

Can God cause God to exist?.......... 3

Inferring God’s existence from his essence.......... 10

‘Proving’ the existence of a lion.......... 14

Second Objections (mainly Mersenne) and Descartes’s Replies   18

The cause of our idea of God.......... 20

Two challenges concerning basic certainty........... 25

Can God lie?.......... 26

Two more objections........ 31

Objections and Replies René Descartes

Methods of presenting results.......... 34

A ‘geometrical’ argument for God’s existence and the soul’s distinctness from the body........ 36

Third Objections (Hobbes), and Descartes’s Replies   42

First Meditation: ‘On what can be called into doubt’......... 42

Second Meditation, ‘The nature of the human mind’......... 42

Third Meditation, ‘The existence of God’...... 46

Fourth Meditation, ‘Truth and Falsity’....... 50

Fifth Meditation, ‘The Essence of Material Things’.......... 52

Sixth Meditation, ‘The existence of material things’......... 53

Fourth Objections (Arnauld) and Descartes’s Replies   54

Objections concerning the human mind....... 54

Objections concerning God............ 64

Points that may give difficulty to theologians........... 75

Fifth Objections (Gassendi) and Descartes’s Replies   83

Objections to the first meditation........... 84

Objections to the second meditation........ 86

Objections to the third meditation.......... 101

Objections to the fourth meditation.......... 121

Objections to the fifth meditation.......... 129

Objections to the sixth meditation......... 135

Sixth Objections (Mersenne and others) and Descartes’s replies   147

Distinctness of mind from body........... 147

Animal thought.......... 149

God as a liar........... 151

Freedom........... 153

Surfaces........... 155

Modality and God’s will............. 156

Senses versus intellect.......... 157

Thought-experiments....... 159

Appendix.......... 162

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

First Objections (Caterus) and Descartes’s replies

Objection
(1) [Caterus—a Dutch theologian—is writing to two friends who had asked him to comment on the Meditations.] Since you strongly urged me to examine the writings of Descartes in some detail, my friends, I felt that I couldn’t say No.... I regard him as having the highest intellect and the utmost modesty.... He writes:

•‘I am thinking, therefore I exist; indeed, I am thought itself—I am a mind.’

Granted.

•‘But in virtue of thinking, I have within me ideas of things, and in particular an idea of a supremely perfect and infinite being.’

True again.

•‘However, I am not the cause of this idea, because I don’t measure up to its representative reality—·that is, the idea in question represents something that has more reality, more perfection, than I have·. So something more perfect than myself is its cause, and thus there exists something besides myself, something more perfect than I am. This is someone who is not ‘a being’ in any ordinary sense, but who simply and without qualification embraces the whole of being within himself, and is as it were the ultimate original cause....’

But here I am forced to stop for a while, to avoid becoming exhausted. My mind ebbs and flows: first I accept, but then I deny; I give my approval, then I withdraw it; I don’t like disagreeing with Descartes, but I can’t agree with him. My question is this: what sort of cause does an idea need? ·To answer that properly, we need first to answer another question·: what is an idea? It is a thing that is thought of, considered as existing representatively in the intellect. But what does that mean? According to what I was taught, for x to ‘exist representatively in the intellect’ is simply for some act of the intellect to be shaped up in the manner of x. And this is merely an extraneous label that tells us nothing about x itself. Just as x’s ‘being seen’ is someone’s performing an act of vision, so also x’s ‘being thought of’, or having representative being in the intellect, is some mind’s having a thought—it is just a thought in that mind, and stops there. It can occur without any movement or change in x itself, and indeed without there being any such thing as x being represented. So why should I look for a cause of something that isn’t actual, something that is simply an empty label, a non-entity?

‘Nevertheless,’ says our ingenious author, ‘in order for a given idea to have such-and-such representative reality, it must surely derive it from some cause.’ Not so! It doesn’t need any cause, because ‘representative reality’ is merely a label, not anything actual. A cause passes on a real, actual influence; but something that doesn’t actually exist can’t be on the receiving end of any actual causal influence! Thus, I do have ideas but I don’t have any cause for them, let alone a cause that is greater than I am, indeed infinite.

‘But if you don’t grant that ideas have a cause, you must at least give a reason why a given idea contains such-andsuch representative reality.’ Certainly; I don’t usually grudge things to my friends, and am indeed as lavish as possible! I take the same general view about •all ideas that Descartes takes about ·the idea of· •a triangle. He says: ‘Even if there aren’t any triangles outside my thought, and never were, still

1

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

there is a determinate nature or essence or form of triangle that is eternal and unchanging.’ What we have here is an eternal truth, which doesn’t need a cause. ·Any more than you need a cause for such eternal truths as that· a boat is a boat and nothing else, Davus is Davus and not Oedipus. But if you insist on an explanation, the answer lies in the imperfection of our finite intellect: because it doesn’t take in, all at once, the totality of everything there is, it divides up the universal good and conceives of it piecemeal—or, as they say, inadequately.

Reply
(1) [Descartes is writing to the same two men to whom Caterus’s objections were addressed.] Well, you have called up a mighty opponent to challenge me! His intelligence and learning might well have created great embarrassments for me if he weren’t an earnest and kind-hearted theologian who chose to side with God and with me as God’s counsel for the defence, rather than fighting in earnest. But though it was extremely kind of him to pretend to be opposing me ·when really he wasn’t·, it would wrong of me to go along with this pretence. So I plan to bring into the open his carefully disguised assistance to me, rather than answering him as though he were an adversary.

•First he summarizes my main argument for the existence of God, thus helping readers to remember it better. •Then he concedes the claims that he thinks I have demonstrated clearly enough, thereby adding the weight of his own authority to them. •Finally he comes to the matter that generates the chief difficulty, namely ·these two questions·:

What should we take ‘idea’ to mean in this context?
What cause does an idea require?

Now, I wrote that an idea is a thing that is thought of, considered as existing representatively in the intellect. But Caterus, wanting to draw me into explaining this more clearly, pretends to understand it in a quite different way from what I meant. ‘For x to exist representatively in the intellect’, he says, ‘is simply for some act of the intellect to be shaped up in the manner of x. And this is merely an extraneous label that tells us nothing about x itself.’ Notice that he refers to ‘x itself’, as though x were located outside the intellect; and when ‘x exists representatively in the intellect’ is taken in this way, it certainly is an extraneous label ·pinned on x; because in this sense ‘The sun exists representatively in Henri’s intellect’ says something purely about Henri, implying nothing about the sun. But that isn’t at all what I meant·. I was speaking of the idea, which is never outside the intellect; and in this sense ‘existing representatively’ simply means being in the intellect in the way that objects normally are there. For example, if someone asks me ‘What happens to the sun when it comes to exist representatively in my intellect?’, the best answer is that the only thing that happens to it is that it comes to fit an extraneous label—·i.e. comes to answer to the description ‘is thought about by so-and-so’·—and this is indeed a mere matter of some act of the intellect’s being shaped up in the manner of an object. But when I am asked ‘What is the idea of the sun?’ and I answer that it is

•the sun considered as existing representatively in the intellect,

no-one will take this to mean

•the sun itself considered as having an extraneous label pinned to it.

And now ‘the sun exists representatively in the intellect’ won’t mean ‘some act of the intellect is shaped up in the manner of the sun’; rather, it will signify the sun’s being in the intellect in the way that its objects are normally there. I mean that the idea of the sun is the sun itself existing in the

2

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

intellect—not of course existing there as a real blazing star, as it exists in the heavens, but existing representatively, i.e. in the way in which objects normally exist in the intellect. This way of existing is of course much less perfect than the way of existing of things that exist outside the intellect; but, as I did explain, that doesn’t make it simply nothing.

Can God cause God to exist?

Objection
(2) Descartes goes on to say ‘The kind of reality involved in something’s being represented in the mind by an idea, though it may not be very perfect, certainly isn’t nothing, and so it can’t come from nothing.’ The word ‘nothing’ as used here is ambiguous. ·On either way of taking it, Descartes is wrong at this point; but the different readings of ‘nothing’ make a difference to why he is wrong·. (a) If ‘nothing’ means not an entity that actually exists, then what’s represented in the mind—not being actual—really is nothing at all, and therefore does come from nothing, i.e. doesn’t need any cause. (b) But if ‘nothing’ means something imaginary, or what they commonly call a ‘being of reason’, then ·Descartes is half-right, because on this reading of ‘nothing’ what is represented in the mind· is not ‘nothing’ but rather is something real that is clearly conceived. But ·Descartes is still half-wrong, because· since it is merely conceived and is not actual, although it can be conceived it can’t in any way be caused.
[This excessively compact and (in the original) unclear paragraph should perhaps be unpacked further. Its basic thrust is this: Descartes says that his idea of a supreme being

is not nothing, and must be caused by something.

Caterus says that on one reading of ‘nothing’ the idea in question

is nothing, and isn’t caused by anything;

whereas on the other reading the idea

isn’t nothing, but still doesn’t have to be caused by anything.

Now let us continue.] He further explores the suggestion that his idea of a being more perfect than himself is not caused by some more perfect being:

I want to push on with my enquiry, now asking a new question: If the more perfect being didn’t exist, could I exist? Well, if God didn’t exist, where would I get my existence from? It would have to come from myself, or from my parents, or from some other beings ·less perfect than God·. But if I had derived my existence from myself, I wouldn’t now doubt or want or lack anything at all; for I would have given myself all the perfections of which I have any idea. So I would be God.... But if I derive my existence from something other than myself, then if I trace the series ·of causes· back I will eventually come to a being that gets its existence from itself; and so the argument here becomes the same as the argument based on the supposition that I derive my existence from myself.

Aquinas took exactly the same approach; he called it ‘the way ·to God· based on the causality of the efficient cause’. He took the argument from Aristotle, although neither he nor Aristotle was bothered about the causes of ideas. And perhaps they didn’t need to be; for can’t I take a much shorter and more direct line of argument ·in which causes of ideas don’t play any part·? ‘I am thinking, therefore I exist; indeed, I am thought itself, I am a mind. But this mind and thought derives its existence either •from itself, or •from something else. If •the latter, then we continue to repeat the question—where does this other being get its existence from? And if •the former, then this mind that gets its existence from itself is God. For anything that gets its existence from itself will have no trouble endowing itself with all ·perfections·.

I beg our author not to hide his meaning from a reader

3

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

who, though perhaps less intelligent, is eager to follow. The phrase ‘from itself’ has two senses. In the first (positive) sense it means from itself as from a cause. What gets its existence ‘from itself’ in this sense bestows its own existence on itself; so if by an act of premeditated choice it were to give itself what it whatever it wanted to have, no doubt it would give itself everything, and so it would be God. But in the second (negative) sense ‘from itself’ simply means not from anything else; and I can’t remember anyone taking the phrase in any other sense.

But now, if •something gets its existence ‘from itself’ in the ·second· sense of not getting it from anything else, how can we prove that •this being takes in everything and is infinite? Don’t tell me: ‘If it derived its existence from itself, it could easily have given itself everything.’ For the thing we are now talking about didn’t get its existence ‘from itself’ ·in the first sense, i.e.· as a cause; it didn’t exist prior to itself so as to be able choose in advance what it would come to be. I heard that Suarez argued like this: ‘Every limitation comes from some cause; so if something is limited and finite, that’s because its cause couldn’t or wouldn’t make it greater and more perfect; so if something gets its existence from itself and not from an ·external· cause, it will indeed be unlimited and infinite.’

I’m not convinced by this argument, ·in Suarez’s form of it or in yours·. What about the case where a thing’s limitation arises from the thing’s own constitutional make-up, i.e. its essence or form? (Remember that you haven’t yet proved this essence to be unlimited; the thing has acquired its existence ‘from itself’ only in the sense that it hasn’t acquired it from anything else.) For example, if we suppose that there such a thing as something that is hot, it will be hot rather than cold as a result of forces at work in its internal constitution; and this isn’t interfered with by the supposition that its being what it is doesn’t depend on anything else. ·But· I’m sure that Descartes has plenty of arguments to support a thesis that others may not have presented clearly enough.

Reply
(2) When Caterus says that there’s an ambiguity in what I say here, he apparently means to remind me of the point I have just made, for fear that I might let it slip my mind. He says first that when something exists in the intellect through an idea, it isn’t an actual entity, i.e. it isn’t something outside the intellect; and this is true. He says next that ‘it isn’t something made up, or a so-called being of reason, but something real that is distinctly conceived’; here he concedes everything that I have assumed. But he then adds ‘since it is merely conceived and is not actual’—i.e. since it is merely an idea, and not something outside the intellect—‘although it can be conceived there’s no way it can be caused’. This is to say that it doesn’t need a cause of its •existing outside the intellect. This I accept; but it surely does need a cause of its •being conceived, and that is the sole point at issue. Suppose for example that someone has in his intellect the idea of a machine of a highly intricate design: there’s nothing wrong with asking ‘What is the cause of this idea?’ And this won’t be properly answered by saying that the idea isn’t something outside the intellect, and therefore can’t be •caused but can merely be •conceived! For the question is asking for the cause of its being conceived. Nor will it do to answer that the idea is something •done by the intellect and is therefore •caused by the intellect. For what is at issue is not this, ·i.e. not the cause of the idea considered as mental event·, but rather the cause of the intricacy that is represented in the idea. For the idea of the machine to contain a representation of such great intricacy, it must get it from some cause. Of course there could be various causes of this intricacy:

4

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

•it was caused by the person’s seeing a real machine with this design, or

•the person had an extensive knowledge of mechanics, or

•he had a very subtle intelligence that enabled him to invent the idea without any previous knowledge.

But notice that all the intricacy that occurs representatively in the idea must necessarily be found, intrinsically (either straightforwardly or in a higher form), in whatever turns out to be it cause.
[‘In a higher form’—Latin eminenter—should be explained. My idea of triangles possesses triangularity representatively, and so—according to Descartes—its cause must intrinsically have triangularity, which taken •straightforwardly means that the cause must be triangular. But perhaps God caused my idea of triangularity, and we don’t want to suppose that God is triangular; so Descartes would say that God possesses triangularity •in a higher form. He sometimes writes as though there were a clean distinction between ‘intrinsic’ and ‘in a higher form’, but that wasn’t his actual view, and those slips are silently corrected in this version. What he really thought was that there is a clean distinction between ‘representatively’ and ‘intrinsically’, and then within ‘intrinsically’ there is a distinction between ‘straightforwardly’ and ‘in a higher form’.]
And what I have just said about the represented •intricacy belonging to •this idea also applies to the represented •reality belonging to •the idea of God. And where can the corresponding ·actual· reality be found, if not in a really existing God? But Caterus knows all this perfectly well, which is why he agrees that we can ask ‘Why does this idea contain that represented reality?’. His answer applies to all ideas what I wrote about the idea of a triangle: ‘Even if there aren’t any triangles anywhere, still there is a determinate nature or essence or form of triangle that is eternal and unchanging’. And this, he says, doesn’t need a cause. But he is well aware that that reply isn’t good enough; for even if the nature of the triangle is unchanging and eternal, that doesn’t rule out the question of why there is an idea of it within us. So he adds: ‘If you insist on an explanation, the answer lies in the imperfection of our intellect etc.’. What he means by this, I think, is simply that those who have wanted to differ from me on this issue have no plausible reply to make—·i.e. that the imperfection of their intellects is the cause of their insisting on an explanation! That interpretation of Caterus may itself seem implausible, but what else can he have meant? He can’t have meant· to claim that •the imperfection of our intellect is the cause of •our having the idea of God, ·because that· would be as implausible as claiming that •our lack of experience in mechanics is the cause of •our imagining some very intricate machine rather than a less perfect one. That would be flatly wrong. If someone has the idea of a machine, an idea containing every imaginable intricacy of design, then clearly this idea originally came from some cause in which every imaginable intricacy •really did exist, even though the intricacy now •has only representative existence in the idea. By the same line of thought, since we have within us the idea of God, containing ·representatively· every perfection that can be thought of, it obviously follows that this idea depends on some cause that ·intrinsically· has all this perfection, namely a really existing God. If the ‘God’ inference seems more problematic than the ‘machine’ one, that’s because of this pair of facts about ourselves: (1) We aren’t all equally experienced in mechanics, so not everyone can have an idea of a very intricate machine; ·and when someone does have such an idea we find it natural to ask Why? What caused this idea to occur in his mind?· (2) We all equal in our ability to conceive of the idea of God, and we don’t notice it coming into our minds from any external source; and this leads us to suppose that it’s just natural for our intellect to have

5

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

such an idea. This is correct as far as it goes, but something very important has to be added—something on which all the power and illumination of the argument depends—namely that our intellect, being finite, couldn’t have this ability to contain the idea of God unless God were its cause. When I went on to inquire ‘whether I could exist if God didn’t exist’, I wasn’t trying to produce a second proof ·of God’s existence·, but merely wanted to explain the first proof more thoroughly.

At this point my critic’s enormous kindness to me has put me in an uncomfortable position. He compares my argument with one taken from Aquinas and Aristotle, and seems to be asking why I, after starting on the same road as they do, haven’t stayed on it all the way. But I hope he’ll let me off from commenting on the work of others, and simply give an account of what I have written myself. ·I have four main things to say·. (1) I didn’t base my argument on the fact that I observed among perceptible objects an order or succession of efficient causes.
[There is a centuries-old bit of terminology in which ‘[adjective] cause’ stands for different things that could enter into a complete explanation of something. Thus:

•material cause: the stuff the thing is made of (e.g. the silver of a coin)

•formal cause: the pattern or design of the thing (the coin’s flatness, circularity, inscriptions, etc.)

•final cause: the thing’s purpose (the use of the coin in commerce)

•efficient cause: what made the thing exist (the impact of a die on hot silver).

clearly, ‘efficient cause’ is what you and I mean by ‘cause’, though we’ll see Descartes stretching it a little.]
I regarded God’s existence as much more evident than the existence of anything perceptible through the senses; and in any case I didn’t think that such a succession of causes could get me to anything except to a recognition of the limitedness of my intellect. ·The argument is supposed to be: either the causal series has been running for ever, or there was a first cause; the former alternative is impossible; so there must have been a first cause. But· an infinite chain of causes from eternity, without any first cause, is ·not something I am entitled to reject, it is simply· beyond my grasp. From the fact that

•I can’t grasp the thought of an infinite series

it certainly doesn’t follow that

•·the series must be finite, i.e.· there must be a first cause;

just as from the fact that

•I can’t grasp the thought of infinitely many divisions in a finite quantity

it doesn’t follow that

•there is a final division beyond which any further division is impossible.

All that follows ·in each case· is that my finite intellect can’t take in the infinite. That’s why I preferred to base my argument on my own existence, which doesn’t drag in any chain of causes, and is better known to me than anything else could possibly be. And the question I asked regarding myself was not

What cause originally produced me?

but rather

What is the cause that keeps me in existence now?

In this way I aimed to escape the whole issue of the succession of causes.

(2) In asking what caused me, I was asking about myself purely considered as a thinking thing—my body didn’t come into it. This is crucial to my line of thought. By going about things in this way, I could more easily •free myself from my preconceived opinions, •attend to the light of nature, •ask myself questions, and •affirm with certainty that there couldn’t be anything in me that I wasn’t in some way aware of. This is plainly very different from •observing that my

6

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

father begot me, •judging that my grandfather begot my father, •finding it impossible for me to track down parents of parents... to infinity, and thus bringing the inquiry to a close by •deciding that there is a first cause!

(3) In asking what caused me, I was asking about myself not merely considered as a thinking thing but—principally and most importantly—considered as someone who has among his other thoughts the •idea of a supremely perfect being. The whole force of my demonstration depends ·in three different ways· on this one fact. (a) This •idea contains the essence of God, at least as far as I can understand it; and according to the laws of true logic we should never ask of anything whether it is without first asking what it is—·i.e. we shouldn’t ask about its existence until we understand its essence·. (b) This •idea prompts me to ask whether I derive my existence from myself or from something else, and to recognize my defects. (c) This •idea shows me not just that I have a cause but that this cause contains every perfection, and hence that it is God.

(4) I didn’t say that nothing could possibly be its own efficient cause. This is obviously true when the term ‘efficient’ is taken to apply only to causes that are temporally prior to or different from their effects. But in the present context that seems not to be the best way of interpreting ‘efficient’, ·for two reasons·. (a) It makes the question ‘Am I the cause of myself?’ futile; who needs to be told that nothing can be prior to itself or distinct from itself? (b) The natural light doesn’t demand that we think of an efficient cause as having to be always prior in time to its effect. On the contrary! Strictly speaking, x is a cause of y only while it is producing y, which means that an efficient cause is never prior to its effect. However, the light of nature does ordain that we may always ask, of any existing thing, ‘Why does it exist?’—i.e. ‘What was its efficient cause, and if it didn’t have one why didn’t it need one?’ So if I thought that nothing could possibly relate to itself in the way an efficient cause relates to its effect, I certainly would not conclude that there was a first cause! On the contrary, if someone postulated a ‘first cause’ I would ask what its cause was, so I would ·go on asking for causes of causes of... etc., and· never arrive at a genuine first cause of everything. But I freely admit that there could be something with such great and inexhaustible power that it needed no help from anything else in order to exist, or in order to stay in existence. Such a thing would be, in a way, its own cause, and I understand God to be like that. ·God’s place in my philosophical system starts with his role as the cause of myself, and the case for this does not depend on that stuff about not being able to track causes back in time to infinity·. Even if I had existed from eternity, so that nothing had existed before I did, I couldn’t stay in existence unless something ·kept me in existence at each moment, which is as though it· created me anew at each moment; and I wouldn’t hesitate to call that the ‘efficient’ cause ·of myself·. Why must there be a cause for my staying in existence? Well, in my view the parts of time are separable from each other—·meaning that the existence of one stretch of time doesn’t logically necessitate the existence of any others·—and so my existing •now doesn’t imply that I’ll still exist •in a minute from now. Now apply this line of thinking to God: he has always existed (·which removes one possible reason for his needing to be caused by something else·), and he keeps himself in existence (·which removes the other possible reason, the one that did apply in the case of myself·). So it seems reasonably appropriate to call God ‘the cause of himself’. But don’t think that God’s keeping himself in existence involves the positive influence of an efficient cause; all it amounts to is that God’s essence is such that he must always exist.

7

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

Now I am in a position to answer, easily, the point about the ambiguity in the phrase ‘from itself’, which the learned theologian says ought to be explained. Those who attend only to the literal and strict meaning of ‘efficient cause’ think that nothing could be the efficient cause of itself. It hasn’t occurred to them that there is room for another kind of cause, analogous to an efficient cause ·strictly so-called·, so when they say that something derives its existence ‘from itself’ they mean simply that •it has no cause. But if they would look at the facts rather than the words, they would quickly see that their negative sense of ‘from itself’ comes merely from the limitations of the human intellect and has no basis in reality. For example, if we think that a given body gets its existence ‘from itself’, meaning merely that it has no cause, what we are saying isn’t based positively on any reason, but negatively way from the mere fact that we don’t know of any cause ·for the body in question·. To see that this is a limitation in us, consider the following: The parts of time don’t depend on one another; so the supposed fact that

•this body has existed until now ‘from itself’, i.e. without a cause,

isn’t sufficient to make it the case that

•this body will continue to exist in future,

unless the body has some power which (as it were) re-creates it continuously. But when we see that no such power is to be found in the idea of a body, and immediately conclude that the body doesn’t derive its existence from itself, we shall then be taking the phrase ‘from itself’ in the positive sense. Similarly, when we say that God derives his existence ‘from himself’, we can understand the phrase in the negative sense, in which case we shall merely mean that he has no cause. But if we

•inquire into the cause of God’s existing or staying in existence, then •attend to the immense and incomprehensible power that the idea of God contains, then •recognize that this power is so vast that it is plainly the cause of his continuing existence, and that nothing else can be the cause;

and if because of all this

•we say that God derives his existence from himself,

then we’ll be using ‘from himself’ not in its negative sense but in a sense that is utterly positive. For there is this positive sense of the phrase, which is derived from the true nature of things, and it is this sense alone that is employed in my argument. We needn’t say that God is the ‘efficient cause’ of himself, thus starting up verbal disputes. But we can be quite entitled to think that in a certain way God relates to himself as an efficient cause relates to its effect, and hence that he derives his existence from himself in the positive sense. That is because this fact:

God derives his existence from himself, or has no cause apart from himself,

doesn’t come from nothingness—·i.e. isn’t merely the negative fact that there is no other cause of God·—but comes from the real immensity of his power. Each of us may ask himself ‘Am I being kept in existence “by myself” in this sense?’ (This is a question concerning now; there is no chance of being launched on an infinite regress.) When you find within yourself no power sufficient to keep you in existence throughout one second, you will rightly conclude that you get your existence from something else—indeed, from something that does get its existence from itself. ·What is my case for that last clause? In answering that·, I’ll add something that I haven’t put down in writing before, namely that a cause that is powerful enough to be able to keep in existence •something other than itself must have at least

8

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

enough power to keep •itself in existence; and so the cause of our staying in existence can’t be merely a secondary cause, ·i.e. a cause that has been caused by something else·.
[At this point a paragraph was inserted in the second edition of the French version of the work, which appeared after Descartes had died. It was probably written by his literary executor Clerselier. It faces the objection: ‘Perhaps someone might be keeping himself in existence without being aware of it; not finding a power within yourself isn’t the same as finding that you don’t have that power.’ The reply is that self-preservation of the sort in question would be an act of the mind, and as such would necessarily be revealed to consciousness, which would lead to an awareness also of the power to perform it.]
As for the dictum ‘Every limitation comes from some cause’ [see page 4], I think that what Suarez meant by this is true but not well expressed, and that it doesn’t solve the difficulty ·it was meant to solve·. Strictly speaking, a limitation is merely the negation of any further perfection; a thing that has a limitation comes from a cause, but the limitation—the negation—does not. And even if everything that is limited does come from a cause, it isn’t self-evident that this is so, and needs to be proved from other premises. For, as Caterus points out, a thing can be regarded as limited in various ways; for example, it can have a limitation that is part of its nature, as it belongs to the nature of a triangle that it is limited to three sides. What does seem to me self-evident is that whatever exists gets its existence either from a cause or from itself as from a cause. We have a good understanding both of existence and of the negative non-existence; so we can’t make sense of any story about something’s getting it existence from itself, unless the story includes there being some reason why the thing should exist rather than not exist. [Descartes expresses that in terms not of making sense of a story, but rather of being able to ‘feign’ or make up something—using a verb that is the Latin source for our word ‘fiction’.] So in such a case we should interpret ‘from itself’ in a causal way, because of the superabundance of power involved—a superabundance that can easily be demonstrated to be possessed by God alone.

[We are about to meet the first of many occurrences of Latin clara et distincta or French claire et distincte. (The feminine forms are given here because nearly always the subject is a feminine noun, usually idea or idée. Every previous translator of Descartes has rendered this phrase by ‘clear and distinct’, a translation that is demonstrably wrong. A better translation is ‘vivid and clear’ (in that order), which is adopted throughout this version. The crucial point concerns clara (and all this holds equally for the French claire). The word can mean ‘clear’ in our sense, and when Descartes uses it outside the clara et distincta phrase, it very often seems to be in that sense. But in that phrase he uses clara in its other meaning—its more common meaning in Latin—of ‘bright’ or ‘vivid’ or the like, as in clara lux = ‘broad daylight’. If in the phrase clara et distincta Descartes meant clara in its lesser meaning of ‘clear’, then what is there left for ‘distincta’ to mean? Descartes’s one explanation of the two parts this phrase, in his Principles of Philosophy 1:45–6, completely condemns the usual translation. He writes:

I call a perception claram when it is present and accessible to the attentive mind—just as we say that we see something clare when it is present to the eye’s gaze and stimulates it with a sufficient degree of strength and accessibility. I call a perception distinctam if, as well as being clara, it is so sharply separated from all other perceptions that every part of it is clara..... The example of pain shows that a perception can be clara without being distincta but not vice versa. When for example someone feels an intense pain, his perception of it is clarissima, but it isn’t always distincta, because people often get this perception muddled with an obscure judgment they make about something that they think exists in the painful spot....and so on.

He can’t be saying anything as stupid as that intense pain is always clear! His point is that pain is vivid, up-front, not shady or obscure. And for an idea to be distincta is for every nook and cranny of it to be vivid; which is not a bad way of saying that it is in our sense ‘clear’.]

9

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

Inferring God’s existence from his essence

Objection
(3) At last I find something to agree with! Descartes has laid it down as a general rule that ‘everything of which I am vividly and clearly aware is something true’. Indeed, I go further: I hold that whatever I think of is true. For from our boyhood onwards we have totally outlawed all chimeras and similar mental inventions. No faculty can be diverted from its proper object. When the will is exercised, it tends towards the good. Not even the senses are guilty of error: sight sees what it sees; the ears hear what they hear. If you see fool’s gold and take it to be the real thing, there’s nothing wrong with your •vision—the error arises from your •judgment. So Descartes is quite right to put all error down to the ·faculties of· judgment and will. [This paragraph will introduce the word ‘chiliagon’; it means ‘thousand-sided figure’, and is pronounced kill-ee-agon.] But now—·I’m addressing Descartes directly·—use this rule to get the conclusion you wanted: ‘I am vividly and clearly aware of an infinite being; so this being is a true entity and something real.’ But someone will ask: ‘Are you vividly and clearly aware of an infinite being? If so, what becomes of the well-known well-worn maxim that all we can know about an infinite thing are aspects of it that don’t involve its infinity—or, ·in more technical language·, the infinite qua infinite is unknown? ·There is good reason to think that the maxim is true·. When I am thinking about a chiliagon, and construct for myself a confused representation of some figure ·that I take to be a chiliagon·, I don’t clearly imagine the chiliagon itself, since I don’t clearly see the thousand sides. And if this is so, ·i.e. if I am to be defeated by a mere thousand·, then how can I clearly rather than confusedly think of the infinite?....

Perhaps that’s what Aquinas meant when he denied that the proposition ‘God exists’ is self-evident. He considers Damascene’s objection to that: ‘The knowledge of God’s existence is naturally implanted in all men; so the existence of God is self-evident.’ Aquinas replied that what is naturally implanted in us is knowledge that •God exists, with this understood only in a general or ‘somewhat confused’ manner, as he puts it; it is just the knowledge that •God-i.e.-the-ultimate-felicity-of-man exists. But this, he says, isn’t straightforwardly knowledge that •God exists; any more than knowing that •someone is coming isn’t the same as knowing ·anything about· •Peter, even though it is Peter who is coming. He says in effect that God is known under some general conception, as

the ultimate end, or as
the first and most perfect being,

or even (this being a conception that is confused as well as general) as

the thing that includes all things;

but he is not known through the precise concept of his own essence, for in essence God is infinite and so unknown to us. I know that Descartes will have a ready answer to this line of questioning. But I think that these objections, put forward here purely for discussion, may remind him of Boethius’s remark that some things ‘are self-evident only to the wise’! So Descartes should expect that people who want to become wiser will ask many questions and spend a long time on these topics....
[One of Descartes’s standard examples of truths of the form ‘There can’t be an F without a G’ is always translated as ‘There can’t be a mountain without a valley’, which is too obviously false to be what he meant. The Latin provides no escape from it, but Descartes may have been thinking in French, in which vallée, as well as meaning ‘valley’ in our sense, can also used to refer to foothills, the lower slopes of a mountain, or the plain

10

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

immediately surrounding the mountain. The translation used here is a compromise: compact and fairly close to what he presumably meant.]
Let us concede, then, that someone does possess a vivid and clear idea of a supreme and utterly perfect being. Where do you go from there? You’ll say that this infinite being exists, and that this is so certain that

I ought to regard the existence of God as being at least as certain as I have taken the truths of mathematics to be. Just as it is self-contradictory to think of highlands in a world where there are no lowlands, so it is self-contradictory to think of God as not existing—that is, to think of a supremely perfect being as lacking a perfection, namely the perfection of existence.

This is the heart of the matter: if I give in on this point I have to admit ·comprehensive· defeat. ·I shan’t give in just yet·. I want to push on against my abler opponent, so as to delay for a while his inevitable victory.

I know we are arguing on the basis of reason alone, not on appeals to authority. But I want to bring in Aquinas here, so that you won’t think that in taking issue with such an outstanding thinker as Descartes I am merely flailing around. Aquinas presents the following objection to his own position:

As soon as we understand the meaning of the word ‘God’, we immediately grasp that God exists. For the word ‘God’ means ‘something such that nothing greater than it can be conceived’. Now anything that exists •in the intellect and in reality and is greater than anything that exists •in the intellect alone. Therefore, since the instant I understand the word ‘God’, God exists in my intellect, it follows that he also exists in reality.

Here is that argument set out formally:

(1) God is something such that nothing greater than it can be conceived. (2) Being such that nothing greater can be conceived involves existing. (3) Therefore, God, in virtue of the very word ‘God’ or concept of God, contains existence; and so he can’t not exist and can’t even be conceived as not existing.

Now tell me, please: isn’t this the very same argument as Descartes’s? (1a) Aquinas defines God as ‘something such that nothing greater than it can be conceived’. (1d) Descartes calls him ‘a supremely perfect being’—which is of course something nothing greater than which can be conceived. (2a) Aquinas’s next step is to say that ‘being such that nothing greater can be conceived involves existing’, for otherwise something greater could be conceived, namely a being conceived of as also including existence. And surely Descartes’s next step is identical to this. (2d) ‘God’, he says, ‘is a supremely perfect being; and as such he must include existence, because otherwise he wouldn’t be supremely perfect’. (3a) Aquinas’s conclusion is that ‘since the instant I understand the word “God”, God exists in my intellect, it follows that he also exists in reality’. In other words, because the concept or •essence of a being such that nothing greater than it can be conceived implies existence, it follows that this very being •exists. (3d) Descartes’s conclusion is the same: ‘From the very fact that I can’t think of God except as existing, it follows that existence is inseparable from God and hence that he really exists.’ But now let Aquinas reply both to himself and to Descartes:

Let it be granted that the word ‘God’ means to everyone what this argument says it means, namely ‘something such that nothing greater than it can be thought of’. But it doesn’t follow from this that everyone understands that ‘God’ signifies something that exists in the real world. All that follows is that everyone understands that ‘God’ signifies something that exists in the thought of the intellect. To show

11

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

that this being exists in the real world you need the premise that there really is something such that nothing greater than it can be thought of; and that premise won’t be allowed by ·the very people you are trying to argue against, namely· those who maintain that God doesn’t exist.

Putting this, briefly, in my own way: Even if it is granted that a supremely perfect being brings existence with him because of his very title, it still doesn’t follow that •the existence in question is anything actual in the real world; all that follows is that •the concept of existence is inseparably linked to the concept of a supreme being. So you can’t infer that the existence of God is something actual (unless you help yourself to the premise that the supreme being actually exists, in which case he will actually contain all perfections, including the perfection of real existence; ·the only trouble being that that form of the ‘argument’ has the conclusion as one of its premises!·).

Reply
(3) My opponent grants me a principle which, though it doesn’t admit of any doubt, is usually not much attended to. ·It is the principle ‘Everything that I am vividly and clearly aware of is something true’·. This is so important for rescuing the whole of philosophy from darkness that Caterus, by supporting it with his authority, has greatly helped me in my enterprise.

But then he goes on to confront me with a good question: ‘Are you vividly and clearly aware of the infinite?’ I did try to meet this objection in advance, but I had better deal with it now more fully—it occurs so spontaneously to everyone! [In what is to come, ‘grasped’ translates comprehendi, which for Descartes implies getting one’s mind around something; this being more than merely understanding it.] I start by saying that the infinite, qua infinite, can’t possibly be •grasped. But it can be •understood, because we can vividly and clearly understand x’s being such that no limitations could be found in it, which amounts to understanding clearly that x is infinite.

I am here distinguishing the •indefinite from the •infinite. The term ‘infinite’ strictly applies only to something in which no limits of any kind could be found; and in this sense God alone is infinite. But ‘indefinite’ is the word I use for answering questions such as

•How large is imaginary space?

•How many numbers are there?

•How far can one go in dividing and subdividing any quantity ·of stuff·?

Each of these is unlimited in some respect, so I call them ‘indefinite’. I don’t call them ‘infinite’ because they aren’t unlimited in every respect.

Moreover, I distinguish the •abstract concept of the infinite, i.e. infinity, from the •thing that is infinite. Even if we understand infinity to be utterly positive, our way of understanding infinity is negative, because it depends on our not finding any limitation in the thing. Whereas our way of understanding the infinite thing itself is positive, but it isn’t adequate, i.e. we don’t have a complete grasp of everything in it that could be understood. ·Don’t say ‘If we don’t understand all of it, we don’t understand it at all’·. When we look at the ocean, our vision doesn’t take it all in, and we get no sense of its vastness, but we are still said to ‘see the ocean’. ·And this very partial view of the ocean may be the best we can have·. If we backed off enough to have almost the entire ocean in our field of vision all at once, we would be seeing it only in a confused manner.... But if we stare at some part of the ocean from close up, then our view can be vivid and clear.... Similarly, the human mind can’t take in God ·in his entirety·—I join

12

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

all the theologians in admitting this. Moreover, God can’t be clearly known by those who look at him from a distance, as it were, and try to make their minds take in the whole of him all at once. That is the sense in which Aquinas meant his quoted statement that the knowledge of God is within us in a ‘somewhat confused’ manner. But if you try to attend to God’s individual perfections, aiming not so much to •capture them as to •capitulate to them [the semi-pun exists in the Latin—capi and capere], using all the strength of your intellect to contemplate them, you’ll certainly find that God provides much richer and more manageable material for vivid and clear knowledge than any created thing does.

Aquinas didn’t deny this in the passage from which Caterus quoted, as is clear from his saying in his very next section that God’s existence can be demonstrated. But when I say that we can have ‘vivid and clear knowledge’ of God, I mean this as a statement about knowledge of the finite kind that I have just described, knowledge that fits the capacity of our minds. That is the only meaning I needed for my arguments ·in the Meditations· to succeed, as you’ll quickly see if you recall that I made the point about vivid and clear knowledge of God in only two places. (a) Once when the question had arisen as to whether our idea of God contains something real, or only the negation of the real (as the idea of cold contains no more than the negation of heat); and this is a point on which there can be no doubt, ·however high- or low-grade one’s knowledge of God is·. (b) And again when I asserted that •existence belongs to the •concept of a supremely perfect being just as much as •having-three-sides belongs to the •concept of a triangle; and this point can also be understood without adequate knowledge of God.

Caterus here again compares one of my arguments with one of Aquinas’s, virtually forcing me to explain how one argument can have more force than the other. I think I can do this without stirring up trouble, because

•Aquinas didn’t offer the argument as one of his, •‘his’ argument and mine have different conclusions, and

•my position on this matter doesn’t differ from his in any respect.

He confronts the question ‘Is the existence of God self-evident to us, i.e. obvious to every single one of us?’ and he rightly answers No. The argument that he then puts forward, as an objection to his own position, can be put like this:

•Once we have understood the meaning of the word ‘God’, we understand it to mean something such that nothing greater than it can be conceived. •To exist in reality as well as in the intellect is greater than to exist in the intellect alone. Therefore, •once we have understood the meaning of the word ‘God’ we understand that God exists in reality as well as in the understanding.

Set out like this, the argument is plainly invalid. Understanding the meaning of the word ‘God’ enables us to understand not that •God exists in reality as well as in the understanding, but rather that that •the word conveys that God exists in reality as well as in the understanding. Just because a word conveys something, this doesn’t show that the thing is true! But my argument was as follows:

•What we vividly and clearly understand to belong to the true and unchanging nature (i.e. the essence, the form) of a thing can truly be asserted of it. •Once we have investigated carefully enough what God is, we vividly and clearly understand that existence belongs to his true and unchanging nature. Therefore, •we can truly assert of God that he does exist.

Here at least the conclusion follows from the premises! And the first premise can’t be denied, because it has already been conceded that whatever we vividly and clearly understand is

13

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

true. That leaves only the second premise, and I confess that there’s a lot of difficulty about that. ·There are two sources of difficulty·. (a) We have become so used to distinguishing existence from essence in the case of everything else that we fail to notice that the essence of God—unlike every other essence—has existence unbreakably attached to it. (b) We don’t distinguish what belongs to •the true and immutable essence of a thing from what is attributed to it merely on the basis of •something made up by our mind. So even if we see clearly enough that existence belongs to the essence of God, we don’t infer that God exists, because we don’t know whether his essence is •unchanging and true or merely •invented by us.

(a) To remove the first part of the difficulty we must distinguish possible existence from necessary existence. It must be noted that the concept or •idea of anything that we vividly and clearly understand contains possible existence, but it is only the •idea of God that contains necessary existence. If you attend carefully to this difference between the idea of God and every other idea, you’ll undoubtedly see that even though our understanding of other things always involves thinking of them as if they existed, it doesn’t follow that they do exist but only that they could. Our understanding doesn’t show us that actual existence must be conjoined with their other properties; but from our understanding that actual existence is conjoined, necessarily and always, with God’s other attributes, it certainly does follow that God exists.

‘Proving’ the existence of a lion

Objection
(4) I am now rather tired ·from all this arguing·, and hope you won’t mind if I relax a little. The complex existing lion includes both lion and existence, and it includes them essentially, for if you take away either element it won’t be the same complex. But tell me now, hasn’t God had a vivid and clear grasp of this complex from all eternity? And doesn’t the idea of this composite....essentially involve both elements? In other words, doesn’t existence belong to the essence of the composite existing lion? And yet God’s having from eternity a clear knowledge ·of this complex· doesn’t force either element in the complex to exist, unless we assume that the composite itself actually exists (in which case it will contain all its essential perfections including actual existence). What goes for the lion goes for God! Although I have distinct knowledge of a supreme being, and although the supremely perfect being includes existence as an essential part of his concept, it doesn’t follow that the existence in question is something actual, unless we assume that the supreme being exists (in which case it will include actual existence along with all its other perfections). So we must look elsewhere for a proof that the supremely perfect being exists.

Reply
(4) ·I can best answer this by going back to (b) the second part of the difficulty I was discussing at the end of my previous Reply·. To overcome that difficulty ·we need a guide to whether a given essence or nature is •true and unchanging or merely •humanly invented, and I now provide one·. Here is a fact about ideas that don’t contain •true and immutable natures but merely •ones invented and assembled by the intellect: such ideas can always be split up by the same intellect—not by mere abstraction, but through a vivid and clear intellectual operation. So any idea that the intellect can’t split up in this way clearly wasn’t assembled by the intellect ·in the first place·. For example, when I think of

14

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

•a winged horse,

•an actually existing lion, or

•a triangle inscribed in a square,

it is easy for me to understand that I can also think of

•a horse without wings,

•a lion that doesn’t exist, or

•a triangle that isn’t inscribed in a square,

and so on. So these things don’t have true and unchanging natures. But if I think of a triangle or a square, then whatever I see to be contained in the idea of a triangle—for example that its three angles are equal to two right angles—I can truthfully assert of the triangle. (And the same holds for anything that I see to be contained in the idea of a square. I have dropped the lion and the horse because their natures aren’t transparently clear to us.) I can understand what a triangle is while excluding from my thought its having three angles equal to two right angles; but I can’t deny that this property applies to the triangle—I mean that I can’t deny it by a vivid and clear intellectual operation, i.e. understanding what I mean by my denial. Moreover, if I consider a triangle inscribed in a square, not intending to attribute to the square properties of the triangle or vice versa, but only wanting to examine the properties arising out of the conjunction of the two, then the nature of •this composite will be just as true and unchangeable as the nature of •the triangle alone or of •the square alone. So it will be all right for me to affirm that the area of square is at least twice the area of the triangle inscribed in it, and to affirm other similar properties that belong to the nature of this composite figure.

Now consider the thought:

The idea of a supremely perfect body contains existence, because it is a greater perfection to exist both in reality and in the intellect than it is to exist in the intellect alone.

The most I can infer from this is that a supremely perfect body could exist. I can’t infer that it actually does exist, •because I can see quite well that this idea has been assembled by my own intellect, which has linked together all bodily perfections; and •because existence doesn’t arise out of the other bodily perfections—it can equally well be affirmed or denied of them. ·Actually, that case for rejecting the inference to the actual existence of a supremely perfect body can be strengthened even further·. The only existence that is at issue here is necessary existence, which gives the thing that has it the power to create itself or keep itself in existence; and when I examine the idea of a body, I perceive that no body has such a power as that. From this I infer that necessary existence doesn’t belong to •the nature of a body—however perfect it may be—any more than •being without lowlands belongs to •the nature of highlands, or •having angles greater than two right angles belongs to •the nature of a triangle! ·And my choice of those examples is my hint that what I’m really saying is that necessary existence is inconsistent with the nature of a body·.

Now let us turn from body and consider ·the idea of· a thing—whatever it turns out to be—that has all the perfections that can exist together. Is existence one of these perfections? We will be in some doubt about this at first, because our finite mind is accustomed to thinking of these perfections only separately, so that it may not immediately notice the necessity of their being joined together. But if we address ourselves attentively to the questions

Does existence belong to a supremely powerful being? and ·if it does·, what sort of existence is it?

we’ll be able to perceive vividly and clearly the following facts. (1) Possible existence, at the very least, belongs to such a being, just as it belongs to everything else of which we have a distinct idea, even if it’s an idea put together through a

15

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

fiction of the intellect. (2) When we attend to the immense power of this ·supremely powerful· being, we shan’t be able to think of its existence as possible without also recognizing that the being can exist by its own power; from which we’ll infer that it really does exist and has existed from eternity (the natural light makes it obvious that what •can exist by its own power •always exists). (3) Necessary existence is contained in the idea of a supremely powerful being, not because of anything made up by the intellect but because it belongs to the true and immutable nature of such a being that it exists.

(4) This supremely powerful being can’t not have all the other perfections that are contained in the idea of God, so that these perfections do exist in God and are joined together not by any construction of the intellect but by their very nature. All this is obvious if we give the matter our careful attention; and the only difference between it and what I have written previously is in the manner of explanation, which I have painstakingly altered so as to appeal to a variety of different minds. I freely admit that this is a kind of argument that may easily be regarded as fallacious by people who don’t keep in mind all the elements making up the proof. For that reason I hesitated to use it, fearing that it might induce those who didn’t grasp it to distrust the rest of my reasoning. But there are only two ways of proving the existence of God, •one through his effects, •the other through his nature or essence; and having put my best efforts into expounding •the first proof in the Third Meditation, I thought I should include •the second proof later on.

Objection
(5) With regard to the essence of the soul, and its distinctness from the body, I have only a little to say. (Our highly gifted author has, I admit, so exhausted me already that I can hardly go on.) He seems to infer that the soul is distinct from the body from the premise that the two can be distinctly conceived apart from each other. On this point I’ll get him to fight it out with Scotus, who says that for one object to be clearly conceived as distinct and apart from another, all that’s needed is what he calls a •formal and representative distinctness between them (which he says is intermediate between their being •really distinct and their being •only conceptually distinct). The distinctness of God’s justice from his mercy is of this kind. For, says Scotus, ‘the intrinsic concepts of the two are distinct, independently of what any mind does, so that one is not the same as the other. But it would be a bad argument to say: ‘Justice and mercy can be conceived apart from one another, therefore they can exist apart’.

But I’ve gone far beyond the normal limits of a letter. These, gentlemen, are the matters that I thought needed to be raised on this subject, and I leave it to you to judge which are the best points. If you take my side, then Descartes’s friendship with you will lead him not to think too badly of me for having contradicted him on a few points. But if you take his side, I’ll give up, and admit defeat. In that case you won’t pass my comments on to Descartes, and ·I confess that· I’ll be only too happy to avoid a second defeat.

Reply
(5) As for the ‘formal distincness’ that Caterus introduces on the authority of Scotus, let me say briefly that it doesn’t differ from modal distinctness; and it applies only to incomplete entities, which I have precisely distinguished from complete entities. All that is needed for this ‘formal’ or modal way of distinguishing x from y is that x be conceived distinctly and separately from y by an abstraction of the intellect, an abstraction that conceives x inadequately. A •‘formal’ or

16

Objections and Replies René Descartes First Objections (Caterus)

modal distinction doesn’t have to involve such a distinct and separate conception of x and of y that we can understand each as an entity in its own right, different from everything else; for that is the hall-mark of •real distinctness. For example, the distinctness of a given body’s •motion from its •shape is ‘formal’: I can thoroughly understand the motion apart from the shape, and the shape apart from the motion, and I can understand either of them in abstraction from the body. But I can’t have a complete understanding of the motion apart from the thing that moves, or of the shape apart from the thing that has it; and I can’t make up a story about motion in something that can’t have a shape, or about shape in something that can’t move. In the same way, I can’t understand justice apart from the person who is just, or mercy apart from the person who is merciful; and I can’t entertain as a possibility a just person who is incapable of mercy. In contrast with that, when I •think of a body as merely something having extension, shape and motion, and •deny that it has anything belonging ·also· to the nature of mind, this involves me in a complete understanding of what a body is, i.e. understanding a body to be a complete thing [the ‘i.e.’ clause added in the French version]. Conversely, I understand the mind to be a complete thing that doubts, understands, wills, and so on, while denying that it has any of the attributes contained in the idea of a body. This would be quite impossible if the mind weren’t really distinct from the body. ·That is: it is only because •a body is one thing and a mind is another (i.e. they are really distinct, distinct as things) that •my thought of a body in all its completeness can exclude any attributes of mind and my thought of a mind in all its completeness can exclude any attributes of body·....

17

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

Second Objections (mainly Mersenne) and Descartes’s Replies

Objection
You have tackled so successfully the task of defending ·God·, the author of all things, against a new race of giants, and of demonstrating his existence, that decent people can hope that anyone who carefully reads your Meditations will acknowledge the existence of an eternal power on whom every single thing depends. Just because of that, we wanted to call to your attention to certain passages and ask you to clarify them, so that if possible there will be nothing left in your work that isn’t clearly demonstrated. You have trained your mind by continual meditations for several years, so that what seems dubious and very obscure to others is quite clear to you; indeed, you may have a clear mental intuition of these matters and perceive them as the primary and principal objects of the natural light, ·i.e. as so utterly obvious that they don’t need support or explanation·. We are simply pointing out the issues on which it seems worthwhile to lay on you the task of providing clearer and fuller explanations and demonstrations.... When you’ve provided them, hardly anyone will deny that your arguments do indeed have the force of demonstrations. ·We have seven main things to say·.

(1) You’ll remember that you didn’t •actually reject the images of all bodies as delusive; all you did was vigorously to adopt the •fiction that you were doing this, so as to reach the conclusion that you were exclusively a thinking thing. We remind you of this lest you should think you could go on to draw the conclusion that you really are in fact nothing more than a mind, or thought, or a thinking thing. This concerns only the first two Meditations, in which you clearly show at least that you, a thinking thing, certainly exist. But let us pause a little here. At this point ·in the Meditations· you recognize that you are a thinking thing, but you don’t know what this thinking thing is. What if it turned out to be a body that produces what we call ‘thought’ through its various motions and interactions? You think you have ruled out all bodies, but you may be wrong about that because you didn’t exclude yourself, and you may be a body. How do you demonstrate that a body can’t think? or that thought doesn’t consist in bodily motions? It may be that the whole system of your body (which you think you have excluded) or else some of its parts—the parts of the brain, for example—work together to produce the motions that we call ‘thoughts’. You say ‘I am a thinking thing’; but how do you know that you aren’t a bodily motion or a moving body?

Reply
Gentlemen, I read with pleasure your comments on my little book on first philosophy. They show your good will towards me, and your piety towards God and zeal to further his glory. And I rejoice in the fact that you have thought my arguments worth examining and that you think I can reply well enough to all your criticisms. (1) You warn me to remember that I didn’t actually reject the images of all bodies as delusive, but merely adopted the fiction that I was doing this, so as to reach the conclusion that I am a thinking thing; and you said that I shouldn’t think it followed from this that I am in fact nothing more than a mind. But I showed that I was well aware of this in the second Meditation, where I wrote:

But these things that I am supposing to be nothing because they are unknown to me—might they not in fact be identical with the I of which I am aware? I don’t know; and just now I shan’t discuss the matter.

I wanted to warn the reader openly that at that stage I was

18

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

not yet •asking whether the mind is distinct from the body, but was merely •examining those of its properties that I can have certain and evident knowledge about. And since I did become aware of many such properties, I can’t without qualification admit your claim that I didn’t yet ‘know what a thinking thing is’. I admit that I didn’t yet know whether this thinking thing is identical with the body or with something else; but I don’t concede that I had no knowledge of it. Has anyone ever known anything so fully that he knew he had nothing more to learn about it? The more attributes of a thing we perceive, the better we are said to know it; for example, we are said to know our close friends better than casual acquaintances. I think I have demonstrated that the mind, considered apart from attributes that are customarily thought of as the body’s, is better known (in the above sense of ‘know’) than is the body when considered apart from the mind. That is all I wanted to establish in the passage in question.

But I see what you are suggesting. You think that •my readers will be surprised that in the course of the first two Meditations (when there are only six altogether!) the only achieved result is the one I have just mentioned right here; and that •this will lead them to think that the work as a whole is extremely thin and not worth publishing. Well, I was not short of material; and no-one who intelligently reads the rest of what I have written will have reason to suspect that I was! ·There is a good reason why you don’t find a host of topics dealt with in the first two Meditations·: it seemed reasonable to deal separately, in separate Meditations, with topics requiring individual attention and needing to be considered on their own.

Now, the best way to get secure knowledge of reality is first to get used to doubting everything, especially things concerning bodies. I had seen many ancient writings by the platonists and the sceptics on this subject, and didn’t fancy re-heating that old cabbage, but I had to devote a whole Meditation to it. And I would like my readers not just to whip through it briskly but to spend several months (or at least weeks) considering the topics dealt with, before proceeding to the other Meditations. This would certainly enable them to get much more benefit from the rest.

Next point: Until now all our ideas relating to the mind have been very confused, and mixed up with the ideas of things that can be perceived by the senses. This is the first and chief reason why we can’t get a clear enough understanding of the things that are said about the soul and God. So I thought it would be useful if I were to explain how the mind’s properties or qualities are to be distinguished from the body’s. ‘To understand metaphysical matters, the mind must be pulled away from the senses’—there’s nothing new about that; plenty of people had said it; but I don’t know of anyone who had shown how this could be done. My second Meditation presents the right way—I think the only way—of achieving this ·withdrawal from the senses·. But it isn’t a method that you can master by going through it carefully just once. You need protracted and repeated study if you are to •eradicate a lifetime’s habit of confusing things related to the intellect with corporeal things, and •replace it with the opposite habit of distinguishing the two; it will take you at least a few days to acquire this. That seems to me the best justification for spending the whole of the second Meditation on this one topic.

You go on to ask how I demonstrate that a body can’t think. Well, excuse me, but ·at the second-Meditation stage where we now are· I haven’t said anything that would raise this question. I don’t deal with it until the sixth Meditation, where I write: ‘The fact that I can vividly and clearly think of one thing apart from another assures me that the two things

19

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

are distinct’ and so on. And a little later on I said:

Although there’s a body that is very closely joined to me, I have a vivid and clear idea of myself as something that thinks and isn’t extended, and one of body as something that is extended and doesn’t think. So it is certain that I am (that is, my mind is) really distinct from my body and can exist without it.

We can easily add to that: ‘Anything that can think is a mind, or is called “a mind”; but since mind and body are distinct things, no body is a mind, so no body can think.’

I don’t see what you can deny in that. Do you claim that clearly understanding one thing apart from another isn’t enough to show that they are really distinct? In that case, provide a more reliable criterion for distinctness of things—and I’m confident that you can’t. What will you say? That two things are really distinct if one can exist apart from the other? But then how do you know that one thing can exist apart from another? You have to able to know this ·first· if it’s to serve as the criterion for real distinctness. You may say that you get this knowledge from the senses, because you can see, or touch etc. one of the things when the other isn’t present. But the senses are less trustworthy than the intellect: there are many ways for it to happen that a single thing appears in different forms or in different places or in different ways, and so be thought to be two things. And anyway, if you remember my discussion of the wax at the end of the second Meditation you’ll realize that strictly speaking bodies aren’t perceived by •the senses at all, but only by •the intellect; so all there is to

•having a sensory perception of one thing apart from another

is merely

•having an idea of one thing and understanding that it isn’t an idea of something else.

The only way you can come to understand this is by ·intellectually· perceiving one thing apart from another, ·i.e. conceiving one apart from the other·; and that isn’t a certain test unless ·in that act of conceiving· the idea of each thing is vivid and clear. ·But that’s just what I said!· Thus, if that proposed criterion for a real distinction is to be reliable, it must come down to the one that I put forward.

To anyone who claims not to have distinct ideas of mind and body, I can only say: ‘Attend carefully to the contents of the second Meditation.’ If anyone thinks—as some well may—that parts of the brain co-operate to produce thoughts, ·I say that· there are no positive grounds for this view, which has arisen from two facts ·about the experience of those who hold it·: •they have never had the experience of being without a body, and •they have frequently been obstructed by the body in their ·mental· operations. Similarly, if someone had his legs permanently shackled from infancy, he would think the shackles were part of his body and that he needed them for walking.

The cause of our idea of God

Objection
(2) From the idea of a supreme being that you find in your mind, and that you say couldn’t possibly have been produced by you, you bravely infer that there must exist a supreme being who alone can be the origin of this idea. However, we can find simply within ourselves a sufficient basis for our ability to form the idea in question, even if the supreme being didn’t exist or we didn’t know that he exists and never thought about his existing. For surely ·each of us can think as follows·:

I can see that just because I think I have some degree of perfection, and hence that others also have a similar

20

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

degree of perfection. This gives me the basis for thinking of any number of degrees, and piling up higher and higher degrees of perfection up to infinity. Even if there were only one degree of heat or light, I could always have the thought of further degrees, continuing the process of addition up to infinity. Using the same line of thought, surely I can take a given degree of being—the one I perceive myself to have—and add to that any degree you like, thus constructing the idea of perfect being from all the degrees that can be added on.

But (you say) an effect can’t have a degree of perfection or reality that wasn’t previously had by the cause. Yet we see that flies and other animals, and also plants, are produced from sun and rain and earth, which don’t have life. Now life (·which animals etc. have·) is nobler than any merely bodily level of existence (·which is all that the sun etc. have·); so it does happen that an effect gets from its cause some reality which nevertheless isn’t present in the cause. Anyway, the idea of a perfect being is merely a thought-entity, which is not nobler than your own mind which is thinking—·because no state of a substance, or event in the life of a substance, is nobler than the substance itself·. And how do you know that the idea would have come to you if instead of growing up among educated people you had spent your entire life alone in a desert? You derived this idea from thoughts you had in earlier meditations, from books, or from discussion with friends and so on, and not simply from your mind or from an existing supreme being. So you need to provide a clearer proof that you couldn’t have this idea if a supreme being didn’t exist; and when you have provided that, we’ll all surrender! But there’s good evidence that the idea does come from previously held notions, for example the fact that the natives of Canada—the Hurons and other primitive peoples—have no awareness of any idea of this sort, ·presumably because their intellectual past doesn’t provide the materials for such an idea·. Now, you could have formed your idea of a supreme being on the basis of your work in physics; the idea you could get from that would refer only to this corporeal world, which includes every kind of perfection that you can conceive. In that case, the most you could infer is the existence of an utterly perfect corporeal being—unless you add something further that lifts us up to an incorporeal or spiritual plane. We may add that you can form the idea of an angel by the same method as the idea of a supremely perfect being; but this idea isn’t produced in you by an angel, although the angel is more perfect than you. The fact is that you don’t have the idea of God, just as you don’t have the idea of an infinite number or an infinite line (and even if you can have the •idea, the •number is still impossible). Furthermore, the idea of a single simple perfection that includes all others arises merely from an operation of the reasoning intellect....

Reply
(2) When you say that we can find simply within ourselves a sufficient basis for forming the idea of God, you don’t depart at all from my own view. I said explicitly at the end of the third Meditation that ‘this idea ·of God· is innate in me’—in other words, it comes to me from no other source than myself. I concede also that we could form this idea ‘even if we didn’t know that the supreme being exists’, but not that we could form it ‘even if the supreme being didn’t exist’. On the contrary, I pointed out that the whole thrust of my argument lies in the fact that it is only because I was created by God that I have the power of forming this idea.

‘Your remarks about flies, plants etc. don’t show that an effect can have a degree of perfection that wasn’t previously

21

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

present in the cause. Animals don’t have reason, so it’s certain that any perfection they have is also possessed by inanimate bodies. [This •reflects Descartes’s view that an animal is merely a complex machine, and that its life is just the machine’s special kind of complexity of structure and operation. We immediately see, though, that he doesn’t •rely on this view here.] And if animals do have some perfection not shared by inanimate things, they must certainly have received it from elsewhere, in which case the sun, the rain and the earth are not adequate causes of animals. If you •don’t find any cause of a fly’s existence that has all the degrees of perfection possessed by the fly, and if also you •aren’t sure whether the causes of the fly’s existence include anything that you haven’t yet found, still it would be quite irrational to be led by this to doubt ·the thesis about perfections of effects and of causes·—something that the very light of nature makes obvious, as I’ll explain at length below.

Anyway, your point about flies is a point about material things; so it couldn’t occur to those who •follow my Meditations and, wanting to philosophize in an orderly manner, •direct their thought away from the things that are perceivable by the senses.

As for your calling our idea of God a ‘thought-entity’, this hasn’t any force against me. If you take a ‘thought-entity’ to be something that doesn’t exist, then it isn’t true that our idea of God is a thought-entity. Or it’s true only in the sense in which every operation of the intellect is a ‘thought-entity’, i.e. an entity that originates in thought; and indeed this entire universe can be said to be an entity originating in God’s thought, i.e. an entity created by a single act of the divine mind. Moreover I have already emphasized several times that I’m dealing merely with the representative perfection or reality of an idea; and this, just as much as the representative intricacy in the idea of a very ingenious machine, requires a cause that contains in reality whatever is contained merely representatively in the idea.

I don’t see how I can make it any clearer that this idea couldn’t be present to my mind unless a supreme being existed. I can only say that it depends on you: if you attend carefully to what I have written you should be able to free yourself from preconceived opinions that are eclipsing your natural light, and to accustom yourself to believing in the basic principles [primis notionibus, literally = ‘in the primary notions’], which are as evident and true as anything can be, in preference to •opinions that are obscure and false, though fixed in the mind by long habit.

(a) There is nothing in an effect that wasn’t previously present in the cause, either straightforwardly or in a higher form [see note on page 5]—that basic principle is as clear as any that we have. It is just the same as the plain man’s (b) Nothing comes from nothing; for if we allow something in the effect that wasn’t previously present in the cause, we’ll also have to admit that this something was produced by nothing. ·That is, if we deny (a) we’ll be denying (b). So you might say that our acceptance of (b) compels us to accept (a). But the real, basic order is the reverse of that: (a) is what compels us to accept (b)·. The reason why nothing can’t be the cause of a thing is simply that such a cause wouldn’t contain the same features as are found in the effect. All the reality or perfection that is present in an idea merely •representatively must—either straightforwardly or in a higher form—be •intrinsically present in its cause; that is a basic principle too. It’s the only basis for everything we have ever believed about the existence of things located outside our mind. The only thing that could have led us to suspect that such things exist was the simple fact that ideas of them reach our mind by means of the senses; ·and our beliefs about •what things outside the mind are like must have been

22

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

inferred somehow from •what our ideas of them are like·.

If you give the matter your careful attention, and spend time meditating with me, you’ll clearly see that we have an idea of a supremely powerful and perfect being, and that the reality represented in this idea isn’t one that we ourselves have, whether straightforwardly or in a higher form. I can’t force this truth on someone who is bored and inattentive; to get it you have to exercise your own powers of thought.

From all this it follows very clearly that God exists. But for the benefit of those in whom the natural light is so dim that they don’t see that it is a basic principle that every perfection that is •representatively present in an idea must •really—·i.e. intrinsically·—exist in some cause of the idea, I provided an even more straightforward demonstration of God’s existence, based on the fact that the mind that has this idea of God can’t have caused itself to exist. I don’t see what more is required to get you to ‘surrender’ ·as you promised·!

There’s no force in your suggestion that my idea of God might have come not from God but from thoughts I had in earlier meditations, from books, or from discussion with friends and so on. Suppose I did get the idea from someone else, then let me ask him where he got it from—‘from yourself or from some other source?’—and then the argument carries on as before, applied this time to him rather than to me. The conclusion will always be the same, namely that the original source of the idea is God.

As for your suggestion that my idea of God could have come from my work in physics: that strikes me as being as implausible as saying ‘We can’t hear anything, but we can learn about sounds by seeing colours’! Indeed, it would be easier to come up with a story about how colours resemble sounds than one about how bodies resemble God! As for your request that I ‘add something further that lifts us up to an incorporeal or spiritual plane’, the best I can do is to refer you back to my second Meditation, hoping that you’ll see that it is at least good for something. I don’t think I have ever put more effort into anything than I did into the long account that give there—one designed precisely for this purpose ·of ‘lifting us up to a spiritual plane·’. If that failed to achieve its purpose, it would be futile for me to try to achieve it here in a sentence or two.

It doesn’t matter that in the second Meditation I dealt only with the human mind; for I don’t mind telling you that our idea of •the divine intellect—to take just one of God’s attributes—differs from our idea of •our own intellect only in the way that the idea of an infinite number differs from the idea of the number 2 or 4. And the same holds for each individual attribute of God of which we recognize some trace in ourselves.

But there is something else: we understand God as having an absolute immensity = simplicity = unity, ·a single great attribute· which includes all his other attributes. There are no analogues of that in us or anything else; ·it is God’s alone; and so any evidence of· this uniquely divine attribute is, as I once said, ‘like the mark of the craftsman stamped on his work’. We have certain attributes which (because of our limited intellects) we attribute to God separately, one by one, because that is how we perceive them in ourselves; but our grasp of God’s simplicity = unity enables us to see that no one of those attributes belongs unambiguously to us and to God. [Descartes probably doesn’t mean that (say) the truths ‘A man has intellect’ and ‘God has intellect’ mean different things by ‘intellect’ or by ‘has’; he seems to mean just that those two sentences express truths that are radically different in kind.] Moreover, there are many indefinite [see page 12] particulars of which we have an idea, such as unlimited (or infinite) knowledge and power, and infinite number and length and so on; and we recognize that

23

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

some of these (such as knowledge and power) are contained straightforwardly in the idea of God, whereas others (such as number and length) are contained in that idea only in a higher form ·and not straightforwardly·. We surely wouldn’t see things in that way if our idea of God were merely a figment of our minds.

If the idea were a mere figment, it wouldn’t always be conceived by everyone in the same manner. It is very striking that metaphysicians unanimously agree in their descriptions of the attributes of God (at least the ones that can be known by unaided human reason). You’ll find that philosophers [here = ‘philosophers and scientists’] disagree much more about the nature of physical or sense-perceptible things....

If you’ll just attend to the nature of •supremely perfect being, you can’t possibly go wrong when trying to conceive correctly the idea of God. Some people mix other attributes in with •that one, which leads them into contradictions: they construct a chimerical idea of God, and then go on to say—reasonably enough!—that the God represented by that idea doesn’t exist. So when you talk of an ‘utterly perfect corporeal being’, if you mean absolutely perfect, so that you are talking about a being in which all perfections are found, you are uttering a contradiction. The very nature of a body implies many imperfections, such as its being divisible into parts—with this part being a different thing from that one; for it is self-evident that being undivided is a greater perfection than being divided. And if you mean ‘as perfect as a body can be’, ·you aren’t contradicting yourself but· you aren’t talking about God.

As for your further point that, although we are less perfect than angels, our idea of an angel doesn’t have to be produced in us by an angel: I entirely agree. As I said in the third Meditation, that idea can be assembled out of our ideas of God and of man. So that point does no harm to my position.

Some people deny that they have an idea of God, but ·in this denial· they are substituting some idol or the like. [This is a pun. Descartes’s point, as you’ll see in a moment, concerns the replacing of the idea of God by some kind of mental image of God. But his choice of words hints at a background thought of replacing God as an object of worship by a physical image such as the golden calf of Moses’ Israelites.] So, although they reject the name, they concede the reality—·or at any rate they aren’t saying anything that denies the reality. When they say ‘I don’t have an idea of God’, all they mean is that their imaginations don’t contain an image of God; their having a genuine idea of God is a topic on which they are silent·. I don’t regard the idea of God as the same kind of thing as the images of material things that we depict in our imagination; rather, it is what we perceive with our conceiving or judging or reasoning intellect. [Descartes is echoing an old tradition, which divided intellectual activities into three kinds, exemplified by these: •conceiving man (or having the thought of what it is to be a man), •judging that all men are mortal, and •reasoning that Because all men are mortal it follows that Socrates is mortal.] Now, in my thought—in my intellect—I can come upon some perfection or other that is above me. For example, I take in that when I count I can’t reach a largest number, and so I recognize that the process of counting involves something that exceeds my powers. What follows from this? Not that an infinite number exists (but not that it is a contradictory notion, as you say!). Rather, it follows that

this power I have of conceiving that there is a thinkable number which is larger than any number that I can ever think of

is something that I have received not from myself but from some other more perfect being.

....Now, what is this more-perfect-than-myself being? Is it a really existing number, the infinite number that I couldn’t get to the end of? Or is it something else? To answer

24

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

this, we have to take into account not merely •the power to give me the idea in question but also •all the other attributes that could be possessed by a being that gave me that idea. And when we do take that into account, we shall find that it can only be God. Finally, when they say that God ‘cannot be thought of’, they mean that we can’t have a thought in which we adequately grasp God; they aren’t denying that we can have the sort of thought we do have—it’s inadequate but is quite enough to give us the knowledge that God exists....

Two challenges concerning basic certainty

Objection
(3) You aren’t yet certain that God exists, and you say that you can’t be certain of anything—can’t know anything ‘vividly and clearly’—without first getting clear and certain knowledge of God’s existence. It follows that you don’t yet vividly and clearly know that you are a thinking thing. At the point ·in your argument· where you conclude that you clearly know what you are, ·namely a thinking thing·, you haven’t yet proved that God exists; but you admit that having clear knowledge ·of anything· requires having clear knowledge of an existing God.

Furthermore, ·this admission of yours seems to be obviously wrong·. An atheist is vividly and clearly aware that the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles; but he is so far from supposing the existence of God that he completely denies it. His view goes like this:

If God existed, there would be a supreme being and a supreme good; which means that the infinite would exist. But in each category of perfection •the infinite excludes •everything else whatsoever—every ·other· kind of being and goodness, as well as every kind of non-being and evil. But there are many kinds of being and goodness, and many kinds of non-being and evil; ·so the notion of something that excludes them all is incoherent, which implies that God couldn’t possibly exist·.

We think you should deal with this objection, so that irreligious people are left with nowhere to hide

Reply
(3) When I said that we can’t know anything for certain until we are aware that God exists, I said explicitly that I was speaking only of knowledge of conclusions that we remember without having in mind the reasoning that led us to them. Now, the dialecticians [= ‘specialists in applied logic’] don’t usually call awareness of first principles ‘knowledge’. And when we take in •that we are thinking things, •this is a basic principle that isn’t arrived at through any syllogism. When someone says ‘I am thinking, therefore I am, or I exist’, he isn’t inferring •existence from •thought by means of a syllogism; rather, a simple intuition of his mind shows it to him as self-evident. If he had been inferring it through a syllogism, ·it would have been this:

Everything that thinks is, or exists;
I think; therefore
I am, or exist.

And for this· he would need already to have known the first premise ‘Everything that thinks is, or exists’; but what actually happens is that he learns it by experiencing in his own case that it isn’t possible to think without existing. Constructing general propositions on the basis of our knowledge of particular ones is something that we just naturally do.
[In the next paragraph Descartes distinguishes cognitio from scientia. The right English word for scientia is ‘knowledge’, with this understood in a full-strength way; often enough cognitio can be translated the same

25

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

way, but not of course where they are being contrasted. No English word works exactly like cognitio (or its French equivalent connaissance). A cognitio might be called ‘an item of knowledge’ (we can’t say ‘a knowledge’), but when cognitio is being contrasted with scientia, ‘item of knowledge’ is too strong. This note is meant to explain the use of the clumsy phrase ‘cognitive possession’—something one has that is in the general area of knowledge/information/belief/etc.]

I don’t deny that an atheist can be ‘clearly aware that the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles’. But this cognitive possession of his isn’t true knowledge, I maintain, because no cognitive possession that can be rendered doubtful seems fit to be called ‘knowledge’; and this applies to our atheist, because—as I have shown well enough—he can’t be certain that he isn’t being deceived about things that seem to him very evident. This ·ground for· doubt may not occur to him, but it can crop up if he thinks about it or someone else raises the point. So he will never be free of this doubt—·and thus won’t have true knowledge·—until he accepts that God exists.

The atheist may think he has demonstrations to prove that there is no God, but that doesn’t matter. His proofs will be quite unsound; we’ll always be able to show him flaws in them; and when this happens he’ll have to abandon his view.

It won’t be hard for us to do this if his only ‘demonstration’ is the one that you offer him, with the premise that ‘in each category of perfection the infinite excludes everything else whatsoever’. ·This is vulnerable at three points·. (a) We can ask him: ‘How do you know that this exclusion of all other entities belongs to the nature of the infinite?’ He will have no reasonable reply to make to this. He can’t try to answer in terms of the nature of the infinite, because he regards the infinite as a nonentity, and therefore as not having a nature. So he will have to answer in terms of the meaning of the word ‘infinite’, a meaning that he has learned from others. ·And if he does in that way argue from the meaning of ‘infinite’, he is lost, because· the term ‘infinite’ is not generally taken to mean something that excludes the existence of finite things. (b) We can ask him: ‘What would the infinite power of this imaginary infinite amount to, if it could never create anything? ·And he will be stuck for an answer·. (c) And we can point out that his premise is false: Our awareness of having some power of thought in ourselves makes it easy for us to conceive that some other being may also have a power of thought, and a power greater than ours; and we can carry this thought right up to conceiving of this other being’s power as infinite, without that making us fear that this would involve some lessening of our own power. The same holds good for everything that we ascribe to God, including the power to create other things; so we can think of God as in every way infinite while still leaving room for the existence of created things. (In all this we must bear in mind that any power of ours is subject to the will of God.)

Can God lie?

Objection
(4) You say that God cannot lie or deceive. Yet some schoolmen say he can.... They think that in the strict sense God does lie, i.e. communicate to men things that are opposed to his intentions and decrees. For example, he unconditionally said to the people of Nineveh, through the prophet, ‘Forty more days and Nineveh will be destroyed’. And he said many other things that certainly didn’t turn out as he had said, because he didn’t want his words to correspond to his intentions or decrees. Now if God hardened Pharaoh’s heart and blinded his eyes, and if he sent upon his prophets the

26

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

spirit of untruthfulness, how do you conclude that we can’t be deceived by him? Can’t God treat men as a doctor treats the sick, or a father his children? In both these cases there is often deception, though it is always employed wisely and beneficially. ·Indeed, doesn’t God have to do this?· If God showed us the pure truth, what eye, what mental vision, could endure it?

In any case, to explain your being deceived about matters that you think you vividly and clearly know it wouldn’t be necessary to suppose that God is a deceiver, because the cause of the deception could lie in you, without your having the least knowledge of it. Why couldn’t it be in your nature to be very often and perhaps always deceived? How can you establish with certainty that you •can’t be, or even that you •aren’t, deceived in matters that you think you know vividly and clearly? Haven’t we often seen people turn out to be wrong in matters where they thought their knowledge was as bright as sunlight? Your principle of vivid and clear knowledge thus requires a vivid and clear explanation! One that will rule out the possibility that anyone of sound mind might be deceived on matters that he thinks he knows vividly and clearly. Otherwise we can’t see that any degree of certainty can possibly be within your reach or that of mankind in general.

Reply
(4) In saying that God doesn’t lie and isn’t a deceiver, I think I have all metaphysicians and theologians—past and future—on my side. What you say against this is on a par with •attacking the thesis that God is not given to anger or other emotions by •offering as counter-examples passages from Scripture where human feelings are attributed to God. ·I’m surprised at your trying this·. Everyone knows that there are two distinct ways of speaking about God. One of them

•is generally employed in the Bible; it fits how the plain man feels about things, and does contain some truth, though only truth relative to human beings.

For example, one might say ‘God was angry’ meaning that God’s conduct might strike the average not very thoughtful human being as an expression of anger. And the other way of speaking

•comes closer to expressing the naked truth—truth that isn’t relative to human beings.

The second of these ways of speaking is the one we should all use when philosophizing. In my Meditations I had a special obligation to speak in that way, because in that context I wasn’t entitled to bring in anything that was ‘relative to human beings’: I was supposing that no other human beings were yet known to me, and was considering myself only as a mind rather than a mind and body. This shows clearly that what I said in the Meditations ·about God’s not being a deceiver· was concerned not with the verbal expression of lies but rather with....the internal malice that deception involves.

And anyway the words of the prophet that you cite—‘Forty more days and Nineveh will be destroyed’—weren’t even a verbal •lie, but simply a •threat, the outcome of which depended on a certain condition. And when we are told that God ‘hardened the heart of Pharaoh’, or some such, this shouldn’t be taken to mean that he •positively brought this about; rather, he contributed •negatively to the hardening of Pharaoh’s heart by not conferring on him the grace that would have brought about a change of heart in him. Still, I have no quarrel with those who say that God can ·and does·, through the mouths of the prophets, produce verbal untruths; these untruths are free of any malicious intent to deceive—like the lies of physicians who deceive their patients

27

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

in order to cure them.

Nevertheless—and this is a more important point—sometimes we do seem to be really deceived by a natural instinct that God gave us. Someone suffering from dropsy has a positive impulse to drink, caused by the nature God has given to the body; the nature was designed to preserve the body, yet on this occasion the drink will harm it. But in my sixth Meditation I have explained why this is not inconsistent with the goodness or truthfulness of God.

But this kind of explanation wouldn’t work with our •clearest and most careful judgments; for if any of them were false, we would have no way of correcting them—no •clearer judgments, and no other natural faculty ·that could do the job·. I deal with this by flatly denying that any such judgments could be false. Here is the reasoning that leads me to this conclusion: The fact that we have ideas of truth and falsehood shows that

(a) we have a real faculty for recognizing truth and distinguishing it from falsehood.

(I emphasize ‘real’ because it’s important that this faculty is a positive property that we have, not a mere negation.) Now, when I proved God’s existence I proved that

(b) anything real in us must have been given to us by God.

And since he is the supreme being,

(c) God must be supremely good and true,

from which it follows that

(d) the notion of his creating anything that positively tends towards falsehood is self-contradictory.

From (a) and (b) it follows that

(e) our faculty for distinguishing truth from falsehood was given to us by God.

And from (d) and (e) it follows that this faculty of ours must tend towards the truth, at least when we use it correctly; for if it didn’t, then God (who gave it to us) would be a deceiver. By using it ‘correctly’ I mean ‘assenting only to things that we vividly and clearly perceive’; we can’t even invent a story about any other correct use of this faculty. So you see that once we are aware that God exists, we have to tell ourselves that he is a deceiver if we want to cast doubt on what we vividly and clearly perceive. And we can’t tell ourselves this; so it follows that whatever we vividly and clearly perceive must be completely accepted as true and certain.

As for doubts that I advanced in the first Meditation, I thought I had rather precisely removed them in the later Meditations; but I see that you are still stuck fast in them, so I shall now expound again the basis on which it seems to me that all human certainty can be founded. First of all, as soon as we think we correctly perceive something, we’re spontaneously convinced that it is true. Now if this conviction is so firm that it is impossible for us ever to have any reason for doubting what we are convinced of, then there are no further questions for us to ask: we have everything that we could reasonably want. What is it to us that someone may make out that the perception whose truth we are so firmly convinced of may appear false to God or an angel, i.e. that it is, absolutely speaking, false? What do we care about this ‘absolute falsity’, since we don’t believe in it or have even the smallest suspicion of it? For the sort of case that is in question here is one involving a conviction so firm that it is quite incapable of being destroyed; and such a conviction is clearly the same as the most perfect certainty.

But can we have any such certainty, any such firm and unshakable conviction?

Well, we clearly don’t have this kind of certainty when our perception is even slightly obscure or confused; for any obscurity is quite sufficient to cause doubts in us. And we don’t have such certainty about anything—however clear

28

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

·and distinct·—that is based on our use of our senses. For we have often observed that the senses are subject to error, as when someone with dropsy feels thirsty and when someone with jaundice sees snow as yellow—which he does just as •vividly and clearly as we do when we see it as white. Accordingly, if there is any certainty to be had—and it can’t be from anything •obscure or anything depending on the •senses—the only remaining alternative is that it occurs in the •brightly lit perceptions of the •intellect, and nowhere else. [Here and below, ’bright" etc. translates a reference to something’s being clare perceived by the intellect. See note on page 9.]

Some of these perceptions are so transparently open to our gaze and so simple that we can’t ever think of them without believing them to be true. Regarding these:

•While I think I exist,

•What has been done can’t be undone,

and their like, we manifestly have this kind of certainty. For we can’t doubt them unless we think of them; and we can’t think of them without believing they are true (as I have just said); from which it follows that we can’t doubt them without at the same time believing them to be true; which is to say that we can never doubt them.

You say that we have often seen people ‘turn out to be wrong in matters where they thought their knowledge was as bright as sunlight’, but that is no good as an objection to what I am saying. We have not often seen—indeed, we have never seen and couldn’t possibly see—this happening to those who have sought brightness in their perceptions solely in the intellect. It happens only to those who have tried to get it from the senses or from some false preconceived opinion.

It is also no objection for someone to make out that such as these might appear false to God or to an angel. For the evidentness of our perceptions won’t let us listen to anyone who makes up this kind of story.

There are other things that •our intellect perceives very clearly while we are attending to the reasons on which our knowledge of them depends—things that •we therefore can’t doubt while we are attending etc. But we may come to forget those reasons while still holding onto the conclusions that we derived from them; and then the question arises:

When we simply recollect that P was previously inferred from quite evident principles, ·but have forgotten how the inference went or what the principles were·, do we still have the same firm and unshakable conviction concerning P ·that we had while we were attending to the inference and its premises·?

My answer is ‘·Yes for some people, No for others·’. The certainty in question is indeed possessed by people whose knowledge of God enables them to grasp that the intellectual faculty that God gave them tends towards the truth; but it isn’t possessed by anyone else. I explained this so clearly at the end of the fifth Meditation that I don’t think I need to say any more about it here.

Objection
(5) If the will •never strays or sins as long as it is guided by the mind’s vivid and clear knowledge, and if it •exposes itself to danger by following a conception of the intellect that is not at all vivid or clear, then note what follows from this. A Turk or other unbeliever doesn’t sin in refusing to accept the Christian religion, and would sin if he did accept it, because he doesn’t have vivid and clear knowledge of its truth. Indeed, if your rule is true, then the will is going to be allowed to accept almost nothing, because there’s almost nothing that we know with the vividness and clarity you demand for the kind of certainty that is beyond any doubt. So you see how, in your desire to champion the truth, you may have proved

29

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

too much and wrecked rather than building.

Reply
(5) You deny that the will exposes itself to danger when it follows a conception of the intellect that isn’t at all vivid or clear. That surprises me. What can give the will certainty if it follows a perception that isn’t clear? Every philosopher and theologian—indeed everyone who thinks—agrees that the more clearly we understand something before assenting to it, the smaller is our risk of going wrong; and that those who do go astray are the ones who make a judgment while they are ignorant of the grounds on which it is based. ·Why have I brought ignorance into the story? Because· whenever we call a conception ‘obscure’ or ‘confused’, that’s because it contains some element of which we are ignorant. [As a follow-up to the long note on page 9, note that ‘obscure and confused’ (in that order) are a perfect contrast to ‘vivid and clear’ (in that order).]

So your objection concerning the faith that should be embraced has no more force against me than against anyone who has ever developed the power of human reason—really it has no force against anyone. Our faith is said to concern obscure matters, but there’s nothing obscure about the reasons for embracing the faith; on the contrary they are brighter than any natural light. We must distinguish •the subject-matter, i.e. what we assent to, from •the formal reason that moves the will to give its assent: all that we have to be shiningly clear about is the reason. No-one has ever denied that the subject-matter—the content of our faith—can be obscure, indeed can be obscurity itself! In my judgment that

Obscurity must be removed from our conceptions, so that we can assent to them without any danger of going wrong,

I’m forming a vivid judgment about this obscurity. There are two kinds of brightness or transparency that can move our will to assent to something: one comes from •the natural light, the other •from divine grace. Although our faith is commonly said to concern obscure matters, this refers only to the content or subject-matter of our faith; it doesn’t imply that there’s any obscurity in the formal reason for our assenting to matters of faith. Quite the contrary: this formal reason consists in a certain inner light that God supernaturally beams into us, making us confident that what we are asked to believe has been revealed by God himself. And it’s quite impossible that he should lie; so this is •more certain than any natural light, and is often even •more evident because of the light of grace.

When Turks and other infidels refuse to embrace the Christian religion, their sinfulness doesn’t come from their unwillingness to accept obscure doctrines (and they certainly are obscure!), but from •their resisting the impulses of divine grace within them, or from •their having by their other sins made themselves unworthy of grace in the first place. Consider an infidel who is untouched by supernatural grace and knows nothing of the things that we Christians think God has revealed to us: if he is induced by fallacious arguments to accept them—obscure as they are to him—I’m willing to say boldly that this doesn’t make him a true believer; it only means that he is committing a sin by not using his reason correctly. I don’t think that any orthodox theologian would have disagreed with me on this. No-one who reads what I write can think that I didn’t recognize this supernatural light, because in the fourth Meditation, where I was looking into the cause of falsity, I said explicitly that the supernatural light produces in our innermost thought a disposition to will, without lessening our freedom.

But please remember that in the context of questions about how one can legitimately use the will, I distinguished

30

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

very carefully the •conduct of life from the •contemplation of the truth. When it’s a matter of getting on with our lives, I am very far from thinking that we should assent only to what is clearly perceived. In fact I don’t think that we should always wait even for probability; sometimes we have to choose one alternatives out of many, knowing nothing about them; and once we have made our choice, so long as no reasons can be brought against it, we must stick to it as firmly as if it had been chosen for brilliantly clear reasons. I explained this in Discourse on the Method [early in Part 3]. But when our concern is solely with the contemplation of the truth, surely no-one has ever denied that we should withhold our assent from anything that we don’t perceive clearly enough. Now in the Meditations my sole topic was the contemplation of the truth. You can see this in my way of going about the whole thing, and also in my explicit declaration, at the end of the first Meditation, that I couldn’t possibly go too far in my distrustful attitude, since what was at stake was not action but only the acquisition of knowledge.

Two more objections

Objection
(6) In your reply to the First Objections [page 13], you seem to go astray in one of your inferences, namely this:

•What we vividly and clearly understand to belong to the true and unchanging nature of a thing can truly be asserted of it. •Once we have investigated carefully enough what God is, we vividly and clearly understand that existence belongs to his nature. Therefore,...

And the conclusion you reached was

Therefore, •we can truly assert of God that he does exist,

but it ought to have been:

Therefore, •we can truly assert that existence belongs to the nature of God.

It doesn’t follow from this that God in fact exists, but merely that if his nature is possible, or non-contradictory, he must exist. In other words, the nature or essence of God can’t be conceived apart from existence; hence, if the essence exists then God exists. This comes down to an argument that others have put like this:

•If there is no contradiction in God’s existing, it is certain that he exists;

•There is no contradiction in his existing;

•·Therefore... etc.·

The second premise brings trouble: opponents of the argument either •claim to doubt the truth of this premise or •deny it outright. Moreover, the clause in your argument ‘Once we have investigated carefully enough what God is...’ presupposes as true something that not everyone accepts; indeed you admit that you apprehend infinite being only in an inadequate way; and obviously you would have to say the same regarding every single attribute of God. Whatever is in God is utterly infinite; so who can for a moment apprehend any aspect of God except in an extremely ‘inadequate’ manner? So how can you have investigated vividly and clearly enough what God is?

Reply
(6) In criticising the conclusion of a syllogism of mine, you made a mistake in the argument. To get the conclusion you want, you should have stated the first premise as follows:

•What we clearly understand to belong to the nature of something can be truly asserted to belong to its nature;

and that premise is nothing but a useless tautology. But my

31

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

first premise was this:

•What we clearly understand to belong to the nature of something can truly be affirmed of that thing.

Thus if being an animal belongs to the nature of man, it can be affirmed that man is an animal; and if having three angles equal to two right angles belongs to the nature of a triangle, it can be affirmed that a triangle has three angles equal to two right angles; and if existence belongs to the nature of God, it can be affirmed that God exists, and so on. Now the second premise of my argument was:

•It belongs to the nature of God that he exists.

And from these two premises the evident conclusion to be drawn is the one I drew:

Therefore •it can truly be affirmed of God that he exists.

The correct conclusion is not, as you maintain, ‘Therefore we can truly assert that existence belongs to the nature of God’. As a basis for the objection that you go on to make, you should have replaced the first premise by

•What we clearly understand to belong to the nature of a thing cannot for that reason be affirmed of that thing unless its nature is possible, or non-contradictory.

Notice how weak this qualification is. •If ‘possible’ is taken to mean what everyone commonly does mean by it—namely ‘whatever doesn’t conflict with our human concepts’—then obviously the nature of God as I have described it is possible, because I supposed it to contain only things that according to our vivid and clear perceptions must belong to it; so it can’t conflict with our concepts! Alternatively, you may be inventing some other kind of possibility that relates to •the object itself ·rather than to •our concepts·; but this can never be known by the human intellect unless it matches the first sort of possibility, ·in which case God’s nature has this invented kind of possibility as well as the normal kind. If you try to avoid this result by supposing that the in-the-object kind of possibility that you have invented can part company with the normal relative-to-our-concepts kind·, that won’t so much support a denial of the possibility of God’s nature and existence as serve to undermine every other item of human knowledge. As far as our concepts are concerned, there is no impossibility in the nature of God; on the contrary, all the attributes that we include in the concept of God’s nature are so interconnected that it seems to us to be self-contradictory that any one of them should not belong to God. So if we deny that the nature of God is possible—·meaning that it is impossible according to your in-the-object kind of possibility·—we may just as well deny that the angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles, or that he who is actually thinking exists; and if we do this, we’ll be even better placed to deny that anything we acquire through the senses is true. The upshot will be that all human knowledge will be destroyed, though for no good reason.

As for the argument that you compare with mine—namely

(1) If there is no contradiction in God’s existing, it is certain that he exists;
(2) There is no contradiction in his existing; Therefore... etc.

—although this is materially true, it is formally invalid. For (1) has to mean:

(1*) If there is no contradiction in the concept of the cause on which the possibility of God’s existence depends, it is certain that he exists,

whereas (2) says that

(2*) There is no contradiction in the concept of the nature and existence of God.

....These are very different. For it may be, with respect to a given thing, that we understand there to be nothing in the thing itself that makes it impossible for it to exist, we

32

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

also understand, from the causal point of view, that there is something that prevents its being brought into existence.

·As for your next point·: even if we conceive of God only in an inadequate—or, if you like, ‘utterly inadequate’—way, this doesn’t rule out its being certain that his nature is possible or not self-contradictory. And it doesn’t prevent us from examining his nature with sufficient clarity (i.e. enough clarity to know that •his nature is possible and that •necessary existence belongs to this divine nature). Self-contradictoriness or impossibility resides solely in our thought, when we wrongly join together mutually inconsistent ideas; it can’t occur in anything outside the intellect. If something exists outside the intellect, then obviously it is possible and not self-contradictory. Self-contradictoriness in our concepts arises merely from their obscurity and confusion; it can’t occur in vivid and clear concepts. Thus, in the case of the few attributes of God that we do perceive, it is enough that we understand them vividly and clearly, even if not adequately. And when we take in that our admittedly inadequate concept of God contains necessary existence, we are entitled to say both that •we have examined his nature with sufficient clarity, and that •his nature is not self-contradictory.

Objection
(7) You don’t say a word about the immortality of the human mind. You should have taken special care to prove and demonstrate this, to counter the people (who aren’t themselves worthy of immortality!) who utterly deny and dislike it. You can’t infer that the mind cannot collapse or die from the premise that it is distinct from the body. (Not that you have given a good proof of that premise, as we pointed out in (1) above; ·but let that pass·.) What if its nature gave it the same life-span as the body, God having endowed it with just enough strength and existence to ensure that it came to an end with the death of the body?

These, Sir, are the points we wanted you to clarify, so as to enable everyone to derive the utmost benefit from reading your Meditations, which are argued with great subtlety and are also, in our opinion, true. For just that reason it would be worthwhile if you, after resolving our difficulties, were to set out the entire argument in geometrical fashion, starting from a set of definitions, postulates and axioms. You are highly experienced in employing this method, and it would enable you to fill the mind of each reader so that he could see everything at a single glance, as it were, and be permeated with awareness of God.

Reply
(7) I explained in the Synopsis of my Meditations why I wrote nothing about the immortality of the soul. And I have adequately proved that the soul is distinct from every body. But there remains your point that the soul’s distinctness from the body doesn’t imply that it is immortal, because God may have given it a nature such that it goes out of existence at just the moment when the body dies. I admit that I can’t refute this. I don’t undertake to use the power of human reason to settle matters that depend on the free will of God. Our natural knowledge tells us that the mind is distinct from the body, and that it is a substance. But....the final death of a human body depends solely on things’ coming apart or changing their shape; and we have no arguments, and no experience, suggesting that the death or annihilation of a substance like the mind results from such a trivial cause as a change in shape; for shape is simply a mode [= ‘non-essential property’], and what’s more it is a mode not of the mind but of the body, which is a different thing from the mind. Indeed, we don’t have arguments or experience suggesting that any

33

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

substance can go out of existence. And this entitles us to conclude that the mind, so far as it can be known by natural philosophy, is immortal.

But if it’s a question about the absolute power of God—‘Might God have decreed that human souls are to cease to exist precisely when the bodies he has joined to them are destroyed?’—then only God can answer that. And since he has revealed to us that this won’t occur, there is no room left for even the slightest room for doubt on this point.

It remains for me to thank you for the helpful and frank way in which you have brought to my notice not only points that have struck you, but also ones that might be raised by atheists and other hostile critics. In the objections that you raise I can’t see anything that I haven’t already answered, or ruled out in advance, in the Meditations. As to the points about the flies generated by the sun, the natives of Canada, the inhabitants of Nineveh, the Turks and so on, the objections you raise can’t occur to anyone who •follows the road I have pointed out and •lays aside for a time whatever he has acquired from the senses, so as to attend to dictates of pure and uncorrupted reason. Hence I thought that I had already adequately ruled out such objections in advance. But despite this, I think that these objections of yours will be a big help to me in my enterprise. For I expect that hardly any of my readers will be prepared to give such careful attention to everything I have written that they’ll remember all the contents by the time they reach the end. Those who don’t remember everything may easily fall prey to certain doubts; and they will subsequently see that their doubts have been dealt with in these replies of mine, or failing that, these replies will at least give them the opportunity to examine the truth more deeply.

Methods of presenting results

I now turn to your suggestion that I set out my arguments in geometrical fashion, so that readers could perceive them ‘at a single glance, as it were’. It is worth explaining here how far I have already followed this method, and how far I think it should be followed in future. I distinguish two things that are involved in the geometrical manner of writing—the •order of demonstration and the •method of presentation. [Descartes speaks of the order and method of demonstratio—the same word for each. But that word sometimes did mean ‘presentation’, and it seems clear that that’s what it means when Descartes writes about ‘method’.]

The order consists simply in this: what is put forward at any stage in the demonstration must be known without any help from anything that comes later. I tried to follow this order very precisely in my Meditations, which is why I dealt with the mind’s distinctness from the body only at the end, in the sixth Meditation, rather than in the second. It is also the reason why I deliberately omitted many things that would have required me to explain an even larger number of things.

The method of presentation divides into two varieties: the first proceeds by •analysis and the second by •synthesis. [The next two paragraphs use ‘analysis’ and ‘synthesis’ in senses that were current in Descartes’s time but have since died. They don’t stand for methods of discovery, but for methods of presenting something that has been discovered. A procedure that is ‘analytic’ in Descartes’s sense starts with what the investigator started with, and then follows his route from that first discovery through to others; whereas a ‘synthetic’ procedure starts with the most basic truths about the matter in hand, and then deductively arrives at others on the basis of them.]

Analysis shows how the thing was methodically arrived at...., so that if the reader is willing to follow it and attend sufficiently to everything in it, he will make the thing his own

34

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

and will understand it as completely as if he had discovered it for himself. ·That is an obvious advantage of the analytic procedure, but it also has a drawback, namely that· it has no way of compelling belief in an argumentative or inattentive reader; for if he fails to attend to the smallest points, even, he won’t see the necessity of the conclusion. And there are many such small points—important truths that are often scarcely mentioned in analytic presentations because they are transparently clear to anyone who does attend to them.

Synthesis, on the other hand, moves in the opposite direction.... It demonstrates [= ‘rigorously proves’] the conclusion clearly, using a long series of definitions, postulates, axioms, theorems and problems, so that if anyone denies a conclusion reached at any step in the argument, it can be immediately shown to be contained in what has gone before, so that even the stubbornest or most quarrelsome reader is compelled to give his assent. Still, this method is less satisfying than the method of analysis, and it doesn’t engage the minds of those who are eager to learn, since it doesn’t show how the thing in question was discovered.

The ancient geometers usually followed the synthetic procedure in their writings—·think for example of the axioms and postulates that kick off Euclid’s Elements·. This wasn’t because they were ignorant of analysis, I think, but because they valued it so highly that they kept it to themselves like a sacred mystery.

Analysis is the true method—the best method—of instruction, and it’s the one I followed in my Meditations. As for synthesis, which is of course what you’re asking me to use here, it can be very suitable to use in geometry as a follow-up to analysis, but it can’t so conveniently be applied to these metaphysical subjects. •On the one hand: the basic principles from which geometrical demonstrations start are readily accepted by anyone, because they agree with what our senses tell us. Hence there is no difficulty there, except in the proper deduction of the consequences; and even less attentive people can do that, provided they remember what has gone before; and that isn’t much of a proviso, because the analytic procedure breaks propositions down into their smallest elements, to enable them to be easily recited so that the student recalls them whether he wants to or not.

•On the other hand, nothing in metaphysics causes as much effort as getting vivid and clear perceptions of the basic principles. In themselves they are as evident as, or even more evident than, the basic principles that geometers study; but they conflict with many sense-based opinions that have become ingrained in us down through the years, so that they—the basic principles of metaphysics—won’t be fully known except by people who really concentrate and meditate and withdraw their minds from corporeal things as far as they can. Indeed, if the basic principles of metaphysics were put forward out of any context, they could easily be denied by those who like to contradict just for the sake of it.

That’s why I wrote ‘meditations’ rather than ‘disputations’ (a favourite with philosophers) or ‘theorems and problems’ (which the geometers like). I wanted to make it clear that I would have no dealings with anyone who wasn’t willing to join me in meditating and attending closely. Someone who is all set to attack the truth will, for just that reason, be less suited to perceive it: when confronted with convincing arguments that support the truth, he won’t attend to them properly because he’ll be busy looking for counter-arguments.

At this point you may want to object:

When we know that a given proposition is true, we certainly shouldn’t look for arguments against it; but while we are still in doubt about its truth, it is right for us evaluate all the arguments for and against, so as to find out which are the stronger. It isn’t reasonable

35

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

for you •to expect your arguments to be accepted as correct before they have been looked at hard, and •to prohibit consideration of any counter-arguments.

That would be a valid objection if the arguments that I ask my readers to attend to without fighting back were of a kind that might divert the reader’s attention from other arguments that had at least some chance of containing more truth than mine do. But ·that isn’t how things stand·. My exposition includes the highest level of doubt about everything: I am strongly recommending that each item should be scrutinized with the utmost care, so that absolutely nothing is accepted until it has been so vividly and clearly perceived that we can’t help assenting to it. The only opinions I want to steer my readers’ minds away from are ones that they have never properly examined—ones they have acquired not through firm reasoning but only from the senses. I don’t think that anyone who focuses his attention on my propositions can possibly think he is running a greater risk of error than he would have if he attended instead to other propositions that are somehow opposed to mine and that reveal only darkness (i.e. the preconceived opinions of the senses).

So I am entitled to require careful attention from my readers. Of the possible ways of presenting my results, I chose the one—·namely •analysis·—that would do the best job of getting readers to attend. I’m sure they will get more benefit from this than they will realize. When the •synthetic method of presentation is used, many people think that they have learned more than they really have. I would add that I think I can fairly give the back of my hand to the worthless verdict given on my work by those who stick to their preconceived opinions and refuse to meditate with me. But even those who do concentrate, and earnestly pursue the truth, will find it hard to take in my Meditations •as a whole, while also taking in the •individual parts that make it up. But both the •overall and the •detailed scrutiny are needed if the reader is to get the full benefit from my work. So I’ll tack on a short exposition in the synthetic style, which I hope will help my readers a little. But I ask them to bear in mind that I’m not aiming to include in this as much material as I put in the Meditations. If I did, I would have to go on much longer than I did there. Also, even the items that I do include won’t be explained precisely—because I want it to be brief, and also because I don’t want anyone to think that what follows is adequate on its own. Anyone who thinks this may give less careful attention to the Meditations themselves; yet I’m convinced that the Meditations will yield by far the greater benefit.

A ‘geometrical’ argument for God’s existence and the soul’s distinctness from the body

Definitions:
D1. Thought. I use this term to cover everything that is within us in such a way that we are immediately aware of it. Thus all the operations of the will, the intellect, the imagination and the senses are thoughts. I say ‘immediately aware’ so as to exclude the consequences of thoughts; my voluntarily snapping my fingers originates in a thought, but isn’t itself a thought.

D2. Idea. I use this term to refer to the form of any given thought, immediate perception of which makes me aware of the thought. When I express something in words and understand what I am saying, there must be within me an idea of what is signified by the words in question. So ‘ideas’ aren’t restricted to images depicted in the imagination. Indeed, in so far as these images are in the corporeal imagination [= ‘the imagination that is a part of the body’], i.e. are depicted in some

36

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

part of the brain, I don’t call them ‘ideas’ at all. I call them ‘ideas’ only in so far as they make a difference to the mind itself when it is directed towards that part of the brain.

D3. Representative reality of an idea. By this I mean the being of the thing that the idea represents, in so far as this exists in the idea. In the same way we can talk of ‘representative perfection’, ‘representative intricacy’ and so on. For whatever we perceive as being in •the objects of our ideas exists representatively in •the ideas themselves.

D4. Whatever exists in an object of one of our ideas in a way that exactly matches our perception of it is said to exist intrinsically in the object. And an object is said to contain something in a higher form [Latin eminenter, see note on page 5 above] when, although it doesn’t exactly match our perception of it, its greatness is such that it can fill the role of something that does match our perception.

D5. Substance. When we perceive—have a real idea of—some property, quality or attribute, any thing that this perceived item is immediately in (as in a subject), any thing by means of which this item exists, is a substance. Our only idea of substance itself, strictly understood, is the idea of

that in which x exists, either straightforwardly or in a higher form,

where x is anything that we perceive, anything that has representative being in one of our ideas. ·We are entitled to be sure that any such item that we perceive is in something, in some thing, in some subject·, because we know by the natural light that nothing can’t have a real attribute.

D6. The substance in which thought immediately resides is called mind. I use that term rather than ‘soul’ because the word ‘soul’ is ambiguous and is often applied to something corporeal.

D7. The substance that is the immediate subject of spatial extendedness, and of the qualities that presuppose extendedness (shape, position, movement, and so on), is called body. Whether what we call ‘mind’ and ‘body’ are one substance or two is a question to be dealt with later on.

D8. The substance that we understand as supremely perfect, and in which we conceive nothing that implies any defect or limitation in that perfection, is called God.

D9. When we say that something is contained in the nature or concept of a thing, that’s the same as saying that it is true of—or can be asserted of—that thing.

D10. Two substances are said to be really distinct when each can exist apart from the other.
[A ‘synthetic’ presentation might at this point set down some postulates—unargued propositions with something like the status of axioms. Descartes is about to present seven postulata, which is Latin for ‘postulates’, but he means it in a different sense—in fact its dominant sense—namely as meaning ‘requests’. In his demonstration of Proposition 4, he treats something in Request 2 as a premise in the argument, as though it were a ‘postulate’ in our sense. That’s one of several bits of evidence that Descartes is not very serious about this supposedly ‘geometrical’ presentation.]

Requests ·to the reader·

1. Please realize how feeble the reasons are that have led you to trust your senses until now, and how uncertain the judgments are that you have built up on the basis of the senses. Reflect long and often on this point, until at last you get the habit of no longer placing too much trust in the senses. You will need to do this, I think, if you are to perceive the certainty of metaphysical things—·i.e. of metaphysical truths·.

37

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

2. Please reflect on your own mind and all its attributes. You’ll find that you can’t be in doubt about these, even if you are supposing that everything you have ever acquired through your senses is false. Continue with this reflection until you get the habit of •perceiving the mind clearly and of •believing that it can be known more easily than any corporeal thing.

3. Ponder on the self-evident propositions that you’ll find within yourself—ones like ‘The same thing can’t both exist and not exist at the same time’, and ‘Nothingness can’t be the efficient cause of anything’, and so on. This will have you exercising the intellectual vision that nature gave you, in the pure form that it takes on when freed from the senses; for sensory appearances generally interfere with it and greatly darken it. This will enable you to see easily the truth of the axioms that are to follow.

4. Examine the ideas of the natures that contain a combination of many attributes, such as the nature of a triangle or a square or any other figure, as well as the nature of mind, the nature of body, and above all the nature of God = the supremely perfect being. Keep in mind that whatever you perceive to be contained in these natures can be truly affirmed of them. For example, the nature of a triangle includes its having three angles that are equal to two right angles; the nature of a body or an extended thing contains divisibility (for we can’t conceive of any extended thing that is so small that we can’t divide it, at least in our thought). That is why it can be truly asserted that the three angles of every triangle are equal to two right angles, and that every body is divisible.

5. Please put a lot of time and effort into contemplating the nature of the supremely perfect being. Above all, reflect on the fact that the ideas of all other natures contain •possible existence, whereas the idea of God contains not only possible but wholly •necessary existence. This alone, without a formal argument, will tell you that God exists; and this will come to be just as self-evident to you as the fact that 2 is even and 3 is odd. There are truths that some people find self-evident while others come to understand them only through argument.

6. Ponder all the examples that I went through in my Meditations, both of vivid and clear perception and of obscure and confused perception. That will enable you to distinguish ·for yourself· what is clearly known from what is obscure. It is easier to learn this through examples than to learn it by rules, and I think that in the Meditations I explained, or at least touched on, all the relevant examples.

7. When you notice that you have never detected any falsity in your clear perceptions, and have never—except by accident—found any truth in what is obscure to you, please conclude that it is quite irrational to cast doubt on the vivid and clear perceptions of the pure intellect merely because of •preconceived opinions based on the senses or •mere hypotheses that are partly leaps in the dark. That will get you to readily accept the following axioms as true and unquestionable. Some of these axioms could have been better explained, and indeed should have been introduced as theorems rather than as axioms, if I had wanted to be more precise.

Axioms or common notions
A1. Nothing exists concerning which one can’t ask ‘Because of what cause does it exist?’ This question can even be asked about God, not because he needs any cause in order to exist, but because the immensity of his nature is the cause or reason why he doesn’t need any cause in order to exist.

38

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

A2. The present doesn’t depend on the immediate past, and therefore a thing’s staying in existence needs a cause just as much as does its starting to exist in the first place.

A3. No thing, and no actual perfection in any thing, can possibly be caused by nothing, ·which is· a non-existing thing.

A4. Whatever reality or perfection there is in a thing is present, either straightforwardly or in a higher form, in its first and adequate cause.

A5. It follows from axiom 4 that the representative reality of our ideas needs a cause that contains this reality, not merely representatively but intrinsically—whether straightforwardly or in a higher form. If you aren’t sure that this is true, bear in mind that we must accept this axiom because our knowledge of all things—sense-perceptible and otherwise—depends on it. How do we know that the sky exists? Because we see it? But this ‘seeing’ doesn’t affect the mind except by giving it an idea—I mean a sheerly mental idea, not an image depicted in the corporeal imagination. Well, why can we use this idea as a basis for judging that the sky exists? It is because every idea must have a really existing cause of its representative reality; and in this case we judge that the cause is the sky itself. And we make similar judgments in other cases.

A6. There are various degrees of reality or being: a substance has more reality than a quality; an infinite substance has more reality than a finite one. So there is more representative reality in the idea of a substance than in the idea of a quality, and more representative reality in the idea of an infinite substance than in the idea of a finite substance.

A7. The will of a thinking thing is drawn voluntarily and freely (for this is the essence of will), but still inevitably, towards a clearly known good. Hence, if it knows of perfections that it lacks, it will proceed at once to give itself these perfections if it can.

A8. Whatever can bring about a greater or more difficult thing can also bring about a lesser thing.

A9. It is a greater thing to create or preserve a substance than to create or preserve the attributes or properties of that substance. But it isn’t a greater thing to create something than to preserve it, as I have already said ·in Axiom 2·.

A10. Existence is contained in the idea or concept of each thing, because we can’t conceive of anything except as existing. Possible or contingent existence is contained in the concept of a limited thing, whereas necessary and perfect existence is contained in the concept of a supremely perfect being.

Proposition 1: The existence of God can be known just by considering his nature.
Demonstration: Saying that something is contained in the nature or concept of a thing is the same as saying that it is true of that thing (D9). And necessary existence is contained in the concept of God (A10). Therefore it can be truly affirmed of God that necessary existence belongs to him, or that he exists.

This is the syllogism that I employed [on page 31 above] in replying to your Objection (6). Its conclusion can be seen to be self-evident by anyone who is free of preconceived opinions, as I said in my Request 5 above. But since it isn’t easy to arrive at such clarity of mind, I’ll now try to establish the same result in ·two· other ways.

Proposition 2: The existence of God can be demonstrated a posteriori from the mere fact that we have within us an idea of him.
Demonstration: The representative reality of any of our ideas has to have a cause that contains the very same reality, not merely representatively but ·intrinsically·, whether straightforwardly or in a higher form (A5). But we have an idea of God

39

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

(D2 and D7), and its representative reality isn’t contained in us either straightforwardly or in a higher form (A6); and indeed it can’t be contained in any being except God himself (D8). Therefore this idea of God, which is in us, must have God as its cause; and hence God exists (A3).

Proposition 3: God’s existence can also be demonstrated from the fact that we, who have the idea of him, exist.
Demonstration: If I had the power to keep myself in existence, I would have even more power to give myself the perfections that I lack (A8 and A9); for these perfections are merely attributes of a substance, whereas I am a substance. But if I had the power to give myself those perfections, I would already have them (A7); so I don’t have the power to keep myself in existence.

Now, I couldn’t exist unless I was kept in existence either by myself (if I have that power) or by some other being who has it (A1 and A2). But I do exist, and (as has just been proved) I don’t have the power to keep myself in existence. Therefore I am preserved by some other being.

Moreover, he who keeps me in existence has within himself, either straightforwardly or in a higher form, everything that is in me (A4). But I have within me the perception of many of the perfections I lack, as well as an idea of God (D2 and D8). Therefore he who keeps me in existence has a perception of those same perfections.

Finally, this being can’t have a perception of any perfections that he lacks, i.e. that he doesn’t have within himself either straightforwardly or in a higher form (A7). For since he has the power to keep me in existence (as I have already said), he has even more power to give himself those perfections if he lacked them (A8 and A9). And he has a perception of all the perfections that I know I lack and that I conceive to be capable of existing only in God, as has just been proved. Therefore he has those perfections within himself, either straightforwardly or in a higher form; and hence he is God.

Corollary: God created the heavens and the earth and everything in them. And he can bring about everything that we clearly perceive, in a way exactly corresponding to our perception of it.
Demonstration: All this clearly follows from the preceding proposition. For in that proposition I proved that God exists from the premise that there must exist someone who possesses, either straightforwardly or in a higher form, all the perfections of which we have any idea. Well, we have the idea of a power so great that he who has it—and he alone—created the heavens and the earth and can produce everything that I understand to be possible. Therefore in proving God’s existence I have also proved these other propositions about him.
[To call x and y ‘really distinct’ is to say that they are distinct things; realiter = ‘really’ comes from res = ‘thing’.]

Proposition 4: Mind and body are really distinct.
Demonstration: God can bring about everything that we clearly perceive, in a way exactly corresponding to our perception of it (Corollary to P4). We clearly perceive the mind, i.e. a thinking substance, apart from the body, i.e. apart from an extended substance (Postulate [or Request!] 2). And conversely no-one denies that we can clearly perceive the body apart from the mind. Therefore the mind can, at least through the power of God, exist without the body; and similarly the body can exist apart from the mind.

Now if substance x can exist apart from substance y, then x is really distinct from y (D10) But the mind and the body are substances (D5–7) which can exist apart from each other (as has just been proved). Therefore mind and body are really distinct.

40

Objections and Replies René Descartes Second Objections (mainly Mersenne)

Why do I speak of mind and body being separated through the power of God? Not because any such extraordinary power is needed to separate them, but because the preceding arguments have dealt solely with God, so there was nothing else I could use to make the separation. ·Bringing in God doesn’t weaken the result·: our knowledge that x is really distinct from y isn’t affected by the nature of the power that separates them.

41

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

Third Objections (Hobbes), and Descartes’s Replies

First Meditation: ‘On what can be called into doubt’

Objection
(1) The things that are said in this Meditation make it clear enough that there is no criterion by which we can distinguish our dreams from the waking state and from truthful sensations. So the images we have when we’re awake and having sensations aren’t properties that inhere in external objects, and don’t prove that any such external object exists at all. Therefore, if we follow our senses and leave our reason out of it, we’ll be justified in doubting whether anything exists. Thus, I acknowledge the correctness of this Meditation. But since Plato and other ancient philosophers discussed this uncertainty relating to the objects of the senses, and since the difficulty of distinguishing the waking state from dreams is common knowledge, I am sorry that Descartes, who is an outstanding original thinker, should be publishing this old stuff.

Reply
(1) •The arguments for doubting that Hobbes here accepts as valid are ones that I was presenting as merely plausible. I wasn’t hawking them as novelties! ·In offering them, I had three purposes in mind·. (a) I wanted to prepare my readers’ minds for the study of things related to the intellect, and help them to distinguish those from corporeal things; and •such arguments seem to be wholly necessary for this purpose. (b) I introduced the arguments partly so that I could reply to them in the subsequent Meditations. (c) And I wanted to show the firmness of the truths that I advance later on, in the light of the fact that they can’t be shaken by these metaphysical doubts. I wasn’t looking for praise when I presented these arguments; but I don’t think I could have left them out, any more than a medical writer can leave out the description of a disease when he wants to explain how it can be cured.

Second Meditation, ‘The nature of the human mind’

Objection
(2) [In this next paragraph, ‘I think’ translates cogito, and ‘I am thinking’ translates sum cogitans. The latter is deliberately clumsy Latin, which Hobbes uses in order to get sum = ‘I am’ = ‘I exist’ into the picture.] ‘I am a thinking thing.’ Right! For from the fact that I think, or have an image (whether I’m awake or dreaming), it follows that I am thinking; for ‘I think’ and ‘I am thinking’ mean the same thing. And from the fact that I am thinking it follows that I am, because something that thinks isn’t nothing. But when Descartes adds ‘that is, I am a mind or intelligence or intellect or reason’, a doubt arises.

‘I am thinking, therefore I am thought.’
‘I am using my intellect, hence I am intellect.’

Neither of those seems to be valid. Compare

‘I am walking, therefore I am a walk.’

Descartes is identifying •the thing that understands with •thinking, which is something that the thing does. Or at least he is identifying •the thing that understands with •intellect, which is a power ·or faculty· that the thing has. Yet all philosophers distinguish a subject from its acts and faculties, i.e. distinguish a subject from its properties and its essences: an entity is one thing, its essence is another; ·the entity has the essence·. Hence it may be that the thing that thinks—the subject that has mind, reason or intellect—is

42

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

something corporeal. Descartes assumes that it isn’t, but he doesn’t prove this. Yet the conclusion that he seems to want to establish is based on this inference.

In the same passage we find the following:

I know that I exist, and am now asking: what is this I that I know? If the I is understood strictly, as I have been doing, it can’t depend on things of whose existence I am still unaware.

It is quite certain that the knowledge of the proposition ‘I exist’ depends on the proposition ‘I think’, as Descartes himself has explained to us. But where do we get our knowledge of the proposition ‘I think’ from? It can only be from ·our immediate awareness of some thinking, together with· our inability to conceive an act without its subject—of jumping without a jumper, of knowing without a knower, or of thinking without a thinker.

It seems to follow from this that a thinking thing is something corporeal. For it seems that the subject of any act—the thing that performs the act—can be understood only in terms of a body or in terms of matter. Descartes himself shows this later on, with his example of the wax—which despite its changes in colour, hardness, shape and other acts is still understood to be the same thing, i.e. the same matter that is the subject of all these changes. Also, I don’t arrive at ‘I think’ through another thought. Someone can think that he did think (for that is simply an act of remembering), but it is impossible to think that one thinks, or to know that one knows. For then an infinite chain of questions would arise: ‘How do you know that you know that you know...?’ Knowing the proposition ‘I exist’ thus depends on knowing the proposition ‘I think’; and knowing ‘I think’ depends on our inability to separate •thought from •the matter that is thinking. So the right conclusion seems to be that the thinking thing is material rather than immaterial.

Reply
(2) When I said ‘that is, I am a •mind, or •intelligence, or •intellect or •reason’, I meant those terms to stand not for mere faculties ·or abilities·, but for things that have the faculty of thought. Nearly everyone understands the •first two terms in that way, and the •third and fourth are also often understood like that. I said this so explicitly and so often that it seems to me there was no room for doubt. There is no comparison here between ‘a walk’ and ‘thought’. ‘A walk’ is usually taken to refer simply to the act of walking, whereas ‘thought’ is sometimes taken to refer to the •act, sometimes to the •faculty ·or ability to perform the act·, and sometimes to the •thing that has the faculty ·and performs the act·. [Latin doesn’t distinguish ‘walk’ from ‘a walk’, or ‘thought’ from ‘a thought’. This version follows Cottingham in selecting ‘a walk’ and ‘thought’, these being what best fit the context.]

I don’t say that the thing that understands is the same as the •act of understanding. And I don’t identify the thing that understands with the intellect, if ‘the intellect’ is taken to refer to a •faculty ·or capacity·; they are identical only if ‘the intellect’ is taken to refer to the thing that understands. I admit that I referred to this thing or substance using absolutely •abstract words, because I wanted to strip away from it everything that didn’t belong to it; whereas Hobbes uses absolutely •concrete words—‘subject’, ‘matter’ and ‘body’—to refer to this thinking thing, so as to make it something that couldn’t be separated from the body.

I have no fear that anyone will think Hobbes’s procedure—running together many different things—is better suited to the discovery of the truth than my procedure of distinguishing each individual item as far as I can. But let’s stop discussing words, and come to the subject-matter.

‘It may be’, Hobbes says, ‘that the thing that thinks is something corporeal. Descartes assumes that it isn’t, but he

43

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

doesn’t prove this.’ But I didn’t assume it, nor did I ‘base’ my argument on it. I left it quite undecided until the sixth Meditation, where it is proved.

Hobbes is quite right in saying that ‘we can’t conceive an act without its subject’. We can’t conceive of thought without a thinking thing, because something that thinks isn’t nothing. But he then goes on to say, quite without any reason, and in violation of all usage and all logic: ‘So the right conclusion seems to be that the thinking thing is something corporeal, ·i.e. something in the nature of a body·.’ The subject of any act has to be understood as a •substance, but it doesn’t follow that it must be understood as a •body. Hobbes likes to say that it must be understood as ‘matter’; that is all right, as long as it’s understood to mean metaphysical matter, ·but Hobbes means physical matter, which is on a par with ‘body’·. [Descartes means ‘metaphysical matter’ to refer to an Aristotelian tradition in which each thing is seen as a combination of form with matter, where ‘form’ includes all the qualities/properties/attributes/accidents and ‘matter’ stands for whatever it is that has the form. In those terms, a mind could be seen as involving •mentalistic acts and properties and of •the ‘matter’ that has them; which doesn’t imply that the mind in question is a ‘material’ thing in the physical sense, something that takes up space etc.]

Logicians and plain folk usually say that some substances are spiritual and some corporeal. All that I proved with the example of the wax was that colour, hardness and shape don’t belong to the concept of wax. I wasn’t dealing there with the concept of mind or even with that of body.

I’ll explain the point briefly. It is certain that a thought can’t exist without a thing that is thinking; and quite generally no act or property can exist without a substance for it to belong to. But we don’t ·ever· come to know a substance •immediately, knowing it in itself, but only •through its being the subject of certain acts. This makes it perfectly reasonable and normal for us to use different names for substances that we recognize as being the subjects of radically different acts or properties, and then later on to consider whether these different names signify different things or one and the same thing. Now there are certain acts ·and properties· that we call ‘corporeal’, such as size, shape, motion and all others that can be thought only in terms of spatial extension; and we label as ‘body’ the substance that they are in—·i.e. the thing that performs the acts and has the properties·. We can’t intelligibly supposed that one substance •has shape, and another substance •moves, and so on, because all these acts fall under the common concept of extension. There are other acts that we call ‘acts of thought’, such as understanding, willing, imagining, having sensory perceptions, and so on; these all fall under the common concept of thought or perception or consciousness, and we call the substance that has them a ‘thinking thing’ or a ‘mind’ or any name you like as long as you don’t confuse this substance with corporeal substance. ·That confusion would be very bad·, because •acts of thought have nothing in common with •corporeal acts, and thought (the common concept of the •former) is radically different from extension (the common concept of the •latter). Once we have formed two distinct concepts of these two substances, it is easy, on the basis of what I have said in the sixth Meditation, to establish whether they are one and the same or different.
[A passing remark of Descartes’s—‘One thought can’t be the subject of another thought, says Hobbes; but who ever thought that it could?’—occurs at the start of this paragraph, a position suggesting that it connects with the rest of the paragraph, which it doesn’t.]

Objection
(3) ‘Which of all these activities is •distinct from my thinking? Which of them can be said to be •separate from myself?’

44

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

One might answer this question as follows: I who am thinking am •distinct from my thought; but I am not •separate from my thought—I’m •distinct from it ·only· in the way that (to repeat my earlier example) a jumper is distinct from his jump. If Descartes means to suggest that •he who understands is the same as •the understanding, we’ll be going back to the scholastic way of talking: the understanding understands, the sight sees, the will wills, and, by a very close analogy, the walking (or at least the faculty of walking) walks. All these expressions are obscure, improper, and quite unworthy of Descartes’s usual clarity.

Reply
(3) I don’t deny that I, who am thinking, am distinct from my thought, in the way a thing is distinct from a mode ·or property· that it has. But when I ask ‘Which of all these activities is distinct from my thinking?’, I’m referring to the various ways of thinking that I have just listed, not to myself as a substance. And when I add, ‘Which of them can be said to be separate from myself?’, I simply mean that all these ways of thinking inhere in me. I don’t see how one can pretend that there is any doubt or obscurity here.

Objection
(4) ‘I’m forced to admit that the nature of this piece of wax isn’t revealed by my imagination, but is conceived [Descartes wrote ‘perceived’] by the mind alone.’

•Imagining (i.e. having an idea) is very different from •mentally conceiving (i.e. reasoning one’s way to the conclusion that something is, or exists). But Descartes hasn’t explained what the difference is. Even the Aristotelians in ancient times taught clearly enough that a substance is not perceived by the senses but is inferred by reasoning.

Now, suppose it turned out that reasoning is nothing but the joining together and linking of names or labels by means of the verb ‘is’—what should we say then? It would follow that the inferences in our reasoning tell us nothing about the nature of things, but merely tell us about the labels applied to them—specifically, tell us whether we are combining the names of things in compliance with the arbitrary conventions that we have laid down for what they are to signify. If this is so, as it may well be, it will follow that reasoning depends on names, that names depend on the imagination, and that imagination depends (as I believe it actually does) on the motions of parts of our bodies. So the bottom line will be this: the mind is nothing more than the movements of various parts of an organic body.

Reply
(4) I did explain the difference between •imagination and a •purely mental conception in this very example, where I listed the features of the wax that we imagine and those that we conceive by using the mind alone. And in another place I also explained how one and the same thing, say a pentagon, is •understood in one way and •imagined in another. As for the joining that occurs in reasoning, what we join are not •names but •things signified by them, and I’m surprised that anyone should think otherwise. Who doubts that a Frenchman and a German can reason about the same things, although the words they think of are completely different? And surely Hobbes refutes his own position when he talks of ‘the arbitrary conventions that we have laid down for what words are to signify’. For if he grants that the words signify something, why won’t he allow that our reasoning deals with this signified something rather than merely with the words? As for his conclusion that the mind is a movement, if he is entitled to say that then he is entitled to say that the earth is the sky, or anything else he likes!

45

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

Third Meditation, ‘The existence of God’

Objection
(5) ‘Some of my thoughts are, so to speak, images or pictures of things—as when I think of a man, or a chimera, or the sky, or an angel, or God—and strictly speaking these are the only thoughts that should be called “ideas”.’

When I think of a •man, I am aware of an idea or image with a certain shape and colour; and I can wonder whether this image portrays a man. Similarly when I think of the sky. When I think of a •chimera, I am aware of an idea or image, and I can wonder whether it portrays a non-existent animal that could exist, or one that may but may not have existed at some previous time.

But when I think of an •angel, what appears before my mind is an image, now of a flame, now of a beautiful child with wings, but nothing that accurately portrays an angel—so it isn’t an idea of an angel. But I believe that there are invisible and immaterial creatures who serve God; and we give the name ‘angels’ to these things that we believe in or suppose to exist. But the idea I use in order to imagine an angel is composed of the ideas of visible things.

In the same way, we have no idea or image corresponding to the sacred name ‘God’. That’s why we are forbidden to worship God in the form of an image; for if we did, we might think that we were conceiving of him who is incapable of being conceived.

It seems, then, that there is no idea of God in us. A man born blind, who has often approached fire and felt hot, knows that there is something that makes him hot; and when he hears this being called ‘fire’ he concludes that fire exists. But he doesn’t know what shape or colour fire has, and absolutely no idea or image of fire appears before his mind. The same applies to a man who recognizes that his images or ideas must have a cause, which must have a prior cause... and so on until eventually he arrives at the supposition of some eternal cause that can’t have a prior cause because it never began to exist. And so he concludes that something eternal must necessarily exist. But he has no idea that he could call the ‘idea of’ that eternal being; he merely gives the name or label ‘God’ to the thing that he admits or believes in.

Now, from the ·very suspect· premise that we have an idea of God in our soul, Descartes proceeds to derive the theorem that God (i.e. the supremely wise and powerful creator of the world) exists. But he ought to have •given a better account of this ‘idea’ of God, and to have •inferred—·showing how the inference works·—not only the existence of God but also the creation of the world.

Reply
(5) Hobbes wants the term ‘idea’ to be used to refer only to the images of material things that are portrayed in the corporeal imagination; and with this on board he can easily ‘prove’ that there can’t be any proper idea of an angel or of God. But I make it quite clear in several places throughout the Meditations, and especially in this very place, that I take ‘idea’ to refer to whatever is immediately perceived by the mind. For example, when I want (or fear) something, I simultaneously perceive that I want (or am afraid); and that’s why I count wanting and fearing among my ideas. I used the word ‘idea’ because it was the term that philosophers standardly used to refer to the kinds of perception belonging to the divine mind, although we recognize that God doesn’t have any corporeal imagination. And I had no more appropriate term at my disposal. I think I explained the idea of God fully enough to satisfy anyone who is prepared to attend to my meaning; I cannot possibly satisfy those who prefer to give

46

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

my words a different sense from the one I intended. As for the final comment about the creation of the world—that is quite irrelevant.

Objection
(6) ‘Other thoughts have more to them than that: thus when I will, or am afraid, or affirm, or deny, my thought represents some particular thing but it also includes •something more than merely the likeness of that thing. Some thoughts in this category are called volitions or emotions, while others are called judgments.’

When someone wills, or is afraid, he has an image of the thing that he fears or the action that he wills; but what is the •‘something more’ that his thought includes? This isn’t explained. Even if fear were a thought, I don’t see how it could be anything but the thought of the thing we are afraid of. For fear of a charging lion is nothing but the idea of a charging lion together with the effect that this idea has on the heart, which in turn causes in the frightened man the animal motion that we call ‘flight’. And this motion of fleeing is not a thought; so we are left with the conclusion that fear doesn’t involve any thought except the thought that portrays the thing feared. And the same applies to willing.

As for affirmation and denial, these don’t exist apart from language and names; which is why brute beasts can’t affirm or deny, even in thought; and therefore can’t make judgments. But thought may be similar in man and beast. For when we say ‘That man is running’ our thought is just like that of a dog when it sees its master running. So affirmation and denial don’t add anything to simple thoughts, except perhaps the thought that the names involved in the assertion stand for what the asserter means them to stand for. And that isn’t a case of a thought’s including more than a portrayal of a thing; it’s a case of portraying the thing twice.

Reply
(6) It is self-evident that •seeing a lion while being afraid of it is different from simply •seeing it; and that •seeing a man run is different from •silently affirming to oneself that one sees him. I don’t see anything here that needs answering.

Objection
(7) ‘It remains for me only to ask how I received this idea from God. I didn’t get it from the senses: it has never come to me unexpectedly, as do most of the ideas that occur when I seem to see and touch and hear things. And it’s not something that I invented, either; for clearly I can’t take anything away from it or to add anything to it. The only remaining alternative is that my idea of God is innate in me, just as the idea of myself is innate in me.’

If there isn’t any idea of God (it hasn’t been proved that there is, and there seems not to be), then this entire argument collapses. As for ‘the idea of myself’: if ‘myself’ refers to •my body then this idea arises from eyesight; and if it refers to my soul, then there isn’t any idea of it. We infer by reason that there is •something in the human body that causes in it the animal movements by which it has sensations and moves; and we call this •something a ‘soul’, without having an idea of it.

Reply
(7) If there is an idea of God (and obviously there is), then this entire objection collapses. As for the further claim that (a) we don’t have an idea of the soul but (b) infer its existence by reason, this amounts to saying that (a) we don’t have an image ·or likeness· of the soul in the corporeal imagination, but (b) we nevertheless do have what I call an ‘idea’ of it.

47

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

Objection
(8) ‘The other idea of the sun is based on astronomical reasoning, i.e. is derived from certain notions that are innate in me.’

Whether we are •looking at the sun with our eyes, or •learning through reasoning that it is much bigger than it looks, it seems that there is only one idea of the sun at any one time. The ‘other idea’ isn’t an idea of the sun; it is a reasoned inference that the idea of the sun would be many times larger if one looked at the sun from a much closer distance.

There can of course be different ideas of the sun at different times, e.g. if one looks at the sun with the naked eye and then later looks at it with a telescope. But astronomical arguments don’t make the idea of the sun larger or smaller; what they do is to show that the idea acquired from the senses is deceptive.

Reply
(8) Here again, what Hobbes says is not an idea of the sun, but which he nevertheless describes, is the very thing that I call an ‘idea’.

Objection
(9) ‘Undoubtedly, the ideas that represent substances amount to something more—they contain within themselves more representative reality—than do the ideas that merely represent modes [= ‘qualities’]. Again, the idea that gives me my understanding of a supreme God—eternal, infinite, omniscient, omnipotent and the creator of everything that exists except for himself—certainly has in it more representative reality than the ideas that represent merely finite substances.’

I have already remarked, often, that we don’t have any idea of God or of the soul. I now add that we don’t have any idea of substance. For substance, considered as the ·metaphysical· matter [see note on page 44] that is the subject of accidental properties and of changes, is something that is brought out purely by reasoning; it isn’t something that is conceived, or that presents any idea to us. If this is true, how can it be said that ideas that represent substances to me have more to them, contain more representative reality, than those that represent qualities? And Descartes should re-think what ‘more reality’ means. Does reality admit of more and less? Does he think that one thing can be more of a thing than another? [Reminder: in Latin ‘reality’ and ‘thing’—realitas and res—are cognate terms.] If so, he should think about how to explain this to us with the degree of clarity that every demonstration demands, and that he himself has employed elsewhere.

Reply
(9) I have pointed out, often, that I use the term ‘idea’ to apply to •what is brought out by reasoning as well as •anything else that is perceived in any way whatsoever. And I have adequately made clear how reality admits of more and less. A substance is more of a thing than a mode; if there are real qualities or incomplete substances, they are things to a greater extent than modes but to a lesser extent than complete substances; and, finally, if there is an infinite and self-sufficient substance, it is more of a thing than a finite and dependent substance. All this is completely self-evident. [For an explanation of ‘real qualities’, see the note on page 78.]

Objection
(10) ‘So there remains only the idea of God: is there anything in that which couldn’t have originated in myself? By the word “God” I understand

a •substance that is

•infinite,

48

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

•independent,

•supremely intelligent,

•supremely powerful,

•the creator of myself and of anything else that may exist.

The more carefully I concentrate on these attributes, the less possible it seems that any of them could have originated from me alone. So this whole discussion implies that God necessarily exists.’ When I consider the attributes of God in order to get an idea of God and to see whether that idea contains anything that couldn’t have been derived from myself, what I think I find is this: What I think of in connection with the name ‘God’ doesn’t originate in myself but needn’t be derived from any source other than external ·material· objects. By the term ‘God’ I understand

a •substance,

i.e. I understand that God exists, though I get this not from an idea but from reasoning.

•Infinite,

i.e. I can’t conceive or imagine any supposed limits or outermost parts of it without being able to imagine further parts beyond them; so that what the term ‘infinite’ presents me with is not an idea of the infinity of God but an idea of my own boundaries or limits.

•Independent,

that is, I don’t conceive of a cause that produced God; which makes it clear that the ·only· idea I have linked to the term ‘independent’ is the memory of my own ideas, which began at different times and hence are dependent ·on the causes that started them up·. Hence ‘God is independent’ simply means that God is one of the things for which I can’t imagine an origin. And ‘God is infinite’ means that God is one of the things that we don’t conceive of as having bounds. This rules out any idea of God—for what sort of idea is it that has no origin and no limits?

•Supremely intelligent.

What, may I ask, is the idea through which Descartes understands the operation of God’s understanding?

•Supremely powerful.

Again, through what idea is power understood—power that relates to future things, i.e. things that don’t yet exist? My own understanding of power comes from an image or memory of past events, and I arrive at it as follows: ‘It did that, so it was able to do that, so if it continues to exist it will be able to do that again—which is to say that it has the power to do that.’ And these are all ideas that could have arisen from external objects.

•The creator of all that exists.

I can construct a sort of image of creation from what I have seen, e.g. a man being born or growing from a single point (as it were) to the size and shape that he now has. That’s the only sort of idea anyone has to go with the term ‘creator’. But our ability to imagine the world to have been created isn’t an adequate proof of the creation! Even if it had been demonstrated that there exists something infinite, independent, supremely powerful etc., it still wouldn’t follow that a creator exists. Unless anyone thinks that the following inference is correct: ‘There exists a being whom we believe to have created all things; therefore, the world was in fact created by him at some stage’!

Also, when Descartes says that the ideas of God and of our souls are innate in us, I want to know: when people are in a deep, dreamless sleep, are their souls thinking? If they aren’t, they don’t have any ideas at that time. It follows that no idea is innate, because what is innate is always present.

Reply
(10) Nothing that we attribute to God can have been derived

49

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

from external objects by copying them, because nothing in God resembles anything in external things, i.e. bodies. And elements in our thought that don’t •resemble external objects clearly can’t have •come from external objects, and must have come from ·another· cause that produced this diversity in our thought.

What, may I ask, is the method Hobbes uses to derive his notion of God’s understanding from external things? I can easily explain the idea I have of God’s understanding; for by ‘idea’ I mean ‘anything that is the form of some perception’. [Descartes thinks of a perception as a fully detailed mental event, and the ideas that it involves are aspects of it, properties of it, its ‘form’.] Now everyone perceives that he understands some things. So everyone has the form—or idea—of understanding; and by indefinitely extending this he can form the idea of God’s understanding; and similarly with God’s other attributes.

I proved the existence of God by using the idea of God that is within me. This idea contains ·a representation of· such immense power that I understand that if God exists it is a contradiction that anything else should exist that he didn’t create. The upshot, clearly, is that in demonstrating the existence of God I also demonstrated that God created the entire world, i.e. everything that exists apart from him. Lastly, when we say that an idea is innate in us, we don’t mean that it is always on view; that would mean that no idea was innate. All we mean is that we have within ourselves the faculty ·or ability· to summon up the idea.

Objection
(11) ‘The core of the argument is this: I couldn’t exist with the nature that I have—that is, containing within me the idea of God—if God didn’t really exist. By “God” I mean the very being the idea of whom is within me.’ Well, •it hasn’t been demonstrated that we have the idea of God; and •the Christian religion obliges us to believe that God cannot be conceived of (which I think implies that we have no idea of him); so it follows that no demonstration has been given of the existence of God, let alone of the creation ·of the world·.

Reply
(11) When they say that God ‘cannot be conceived of’, this means ‘conceived of in such a way as to have a fully adequate grasp of him’. As for how we can have an idea of God, I have gone over this till I’m sick of it! There’s absolutely nothing in this objection to invalidate my demonstrations.

Fourth Meditation, ‘Truth and Falsity’

Objection
(12) ‘So error is not something real, but is merely a defect. So there is nothing positively error-producing in the faculty of judgment that God gave me.’

Certainly ignorance is merely a defect, and we don’t need any positive faculty ·or power· in order to be ignorant; but it’s not obvious that the same thing holds for error. Why can’t sticks and stones be guilty of errors? It seems to be because they don’t have the power of reasoning and imagining. If that is right, then it follows that one can’t err unless one has the •power of reasoning, or at least the •power of imagining; and these are positive faculties that have been given to everyone who ·sometimes· errs, and not to anyone else.

What is more, ·a page later· Descartes writes: ‘It comes to my attention that my errors have two co-operating causes—my faculty of knowledge and my faculty of choice or freedom of the will.’ This seems to contradict the earlier passage. It should also be noted that Descartes assumes freedom of the will, opposing the view of the Calvinists but giving no argument for his view

50

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

Reply
(12) It’s true that in order to go wrong we need the faculty of reasoning, or rather of judging (i.e. affirming and denying), because error is a defect in this faculty. But it doesn’t follow that this defect is something real, any more than blindness is something real. ·I am sure Hobbes would agree about blindness, but then he should consider· the fact that sticks and stones cannot see and yet we don’t call them ‘blind’. I am surprised that so far I haven’t found a single valid argument in these objections.

I don’t see why the passage ·about ‘two co-operating causes· is said to contradict the earlier one. On the question of our freedom, all I ‘assumed’ was something that we all experience within ourselves. Our freedom is very evident by the natural light. There may indeed be many people who worry about how •God’s pre-ordaining everything is consistent with our being free. But anyone who simply thinks about •us will realize from his own experience that voluntariness and freedom are one and the same thing; ·and of course it is beyond dispute that many of our actions are voluntary·. This is no place for examining the opinion of other people on this subject.

Objection
(13) ‘For example, a while ago I asked whether anything in the world exists, and I came to realize that the fact of my raising this question shows quite clearly that I exist. I understood this so vividly that I couldn’t help judging that it was true. This wasn’t the “couldn’t help” that comes from being compelled by some external force. What happened was just this: a great light in the intellect was followed by a great inclination in the will. I wasn’t in a state of indifference, but this lack of indifference was a measure of how spontaneous and free my belief was.’ [‘Indifference’ is the state of being evenly balanced between two alternatives—not forced or even slightly pushed towards one of them.]

The phrase ‘a great light in the intellect’ is metaphorical, and so has no argumentative force. And in any case, anyone who •has no doubt ·concerning some opinion of his· claims to •have this sort of ‘great light’ and is just as strongly drawn to affirm his opinion as someone would be who •had real knowledge ·of it·. So this ‘light’ can explain why someone stubbornly defends or holds on to a given opinion, but not why he knows it to be true.

Further, it’s not only •knowing something to be true that lies outside the scope of the will, but also •believing it or •assenting to it. If something is supported by valid arguments, or reported as credible, we are forced to believe it. It is true that affirming and denying propositions, defending and refuting them, are acts of will; but it doesn’t follow that our inner assent depends on the will.

Thus, no valid demonstration is given for the conclusion that ‘The privation that constitutes the essence of error lies in the incorrect use of free will’. [A privation—Latin privatio—is an absence, or lack, of something that ought to be present; Descartes holds that being in error is merely not having some knowledge that one ought to have. He and some of his critics often use privatio just to mean lack or absence, with no implication about what ought to be present; for example on pages 64-66 the question of whether cold is just a ‘privation’ of heat, translated there by ‘absence’.]

Reply
(13) It is quite irrelevant whether the phrase ‘a great light’ has •argumentative force; what matters is whether it has •explanatory force—and it does! Everyone knows that ‘light in the intellect’ is taken to mean knowledge that one can see right into. Perhaps not everyone who thinks he has this does in fact have it, but that doesn’t stop it from being quite

51

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

different from a stubborn opinion that is arrived at without any evident perception.

As for the claim that we assent to things that we clearly perceive, ‘even if we don’t want to’, that’s like saying that we seek a clearly known good even if we don’t want to! The qualification ‘even if we don’t want to’ is inappropriate in such contexts, because it implies that we both will and don’t will the same thing. [The clause ‘even if we don’t want to’ replaces the Latin volentes nolentes = ‘wanting-to not-wanting-to’. It’s like the English ‘willy-nilly’, but it would hardly do to have Descartes saying ‘the qualification “nilly” is inappropriate’!]

Fifth Meditation, ‘The Essence of Material Things’

Objection
(14) ‘Even if there are not and never were any triangles anywhere outside my thought, still, when I imagine a triangle there is a determinate nature or essence or form of triangle that is eternal, unchanging, and independent of my mind. This is shown by the fact that the triangle can be demonstrated to have various properties.’ If triangles don’t exist anywhere, I don’t understand how triangle can have a nature. For what isn’t anywhere doesn’t exist, and so doesn’t have any essence or nature. A triangle in the mind comes from a triangle we have seen, or else it is made up out of things we have seen. But once we give the name ‘triangle’ to the thing from which, we think, the idea of a triangle came, then the •name remains even if the triangle itself is destroyed. Similarly, when our thought leads us to conceive that the angles of a triangle add up to two right angles, and we give the triangle this second name ‘having its angles equal to two right angles’, then the •name would remain even if no angles existed in the world; and so this will be the case:

The proposition ‘a triangle is that which has its angles equal to two right angles’ is forever true.

But this will not be the case:

The nature of a triangle exists for ever;

for it may be that every single triangle will cease to exist.

Similarly, the proposition ‘Man is an animal’ is eternally true because the names are eternal; but when the human race ceases to be, there will be no human nature any more.

This shows clearly that essence, considered as distinct from existence, is merely a linking of names by the verb ‘is’. And hence essence without existence is a human artifact. It seems that •essence is to •existence as •the mental image of a man is to •the man. Or ·we could say that· •the essence of Socrates is to the •existence of Socrates as •the proposition ‘Socrates is a man’ is to •the proposition ‘Socrates exists’. At a time when Socrates doesn’t exist, the proposition ‘Socrates is a man’ signifies merely a linking of terms; and ‘is’ or ‘to be’ carries the image of the unity of a thing to which two terms are applied. [Hobbes has said that so-called ‘essences’ are merely pairs of ‘names’ linked by ‘is’ (Latin est). In that last sentence he throws in ‘or “to be”’ (Latin vel esse), Why? Because esse—‘to be’—is the root of essentia = ‘essence’. This little subtlety is lost when we move out of Latin.]
Reply

(14) The distinction between essence and existence is known to everyone. And this talk about eternal names, as opposed to concepts or ideas of eternal truths, has already been amply refuted.

52

Objections and Replies René Descartes Third Objections (Hobbes)

Sixth Meditation, ‘The existence of material things’

Objection
(15) ‘God has given me no faculty for finding out whether ideas are emitted by bodies or not; but he has strongly inclined me to believe that bodies produce them. So if the ideas were transmitted from a source other than corporeal things, God would be a deceiver; and he is not. So bodies exist.’

It is generally thought that doctors aren’t at fault if they deceive their patients for their health’s sake, and that fathers aren’t at fault if they deceive their children for their own good. The wrongness of deception consists not in the falsity of what is said but in the harm done by the deceiver. Descartes should thus consider whether the proposition ‘God can never deceive us’ is universally true. For if it isn’t universally true, the conclusion ‘So bodies exist’ doesn’t follow.

Reply
(15) My conclusion doesn’t require that we can never be deceived (indeed, I have readily admitted that we are often deceived). All it requires is that we aren’t deceived in cases where our going wrong would be evidence that God intended to deceive us—which would be inconsistent with his essence. Yet again, bad argument!

Objection
(16) ‘For I now notice that the waking state is vastly different from dreams, in that dreams are never linked by memory with all the other actions of life as waking experiences are.’

Consider someone who dreams that he isn’t sure whether or not he is dreaming; couldn’t he dream that his dream fits in with his ideas of a long series of past events? If this is possible, then the dreamer will judge certain items that appear to be events from his past life to be true occurrences, just as he might if he were awake. Moreover, as Descartes himself asserts, the certainty and truth of all knowledge depends solely on our knowledge of the true God. But in that case an atheist can’t infer that he is awake on the basis of memory of his past life. The alternative is that someone can know he is awake without knowledge of the true God.

Reply
(16) A dreamer cannot really connect his dreams with the ideas of past events, though he may dream that he does. Everyone knows that a man may be deceived in his sleep. But afterwards, when he wakes up, he will easily recognize his mistake.

An atheist can infer that he is awake on the basis of memory of his past life. But if he doesn’t know that he was created by a non-deceiving God, he can’t know for sure that this criterion is sufficient to make it certain that he isn’t mistaken.

53

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

Fourth Objections (Arnauld) and Descartes’s Replies

Introduction to the Objections
[Arnauld, born in 1612, wrote these Objections in 1640; his important exchange of letters with Leibniz began in 1686! Here he addresses his comments to Mersenne, who had solicited them.] You have done me a kindness, but are making me pay a high price for it! You have allowed me to see this brilliant work only on condition that I make public my opinion of it. This is a hard condition, which I have been driven to accept by my eagerness to see this superb piece of work.... You know how highly I rate the power of Descartes’s mind and his exceptional learning.

The work you are giving me to scrutinize requires an uncommon intellect; and if you over-rate my powers, that doesn’t make me any less aware of my own inadequacy. The work also requires a mind that is calm, free from the hurly-burly of all external things, and attentive to itself—which can happen only if the mind meditates attentively and focuses on itself. You know this, and you also know about all the tiresome duties that are keeping me busy; but still you command, and I must obey! If I go astray it will be your fault, since it’s you who are making me write.

This work could be claimed to belong entirely to philosophy; but Descartes has very properly submitted himself to the judgment of the theologians, so I am going to play a dual role here. I shall first present what seem to me to be the possible philosophical objections concerning the major issues of the nature of our mind and [starting at page 64] of God; and then [starting at page 75] I shall present problems that a theologian might come up against in the work as a whole.

Introduction to the Replies
[Descartes addresses his replies to Mersenne.] I couldn’t possibly wish for a more perceptive or more courteous critic of my book than ·Antoine Arnauld·, whose comments you have sent me. He has dealt with me so gently that I can easily see his good will towards myself and the cause I am defending. ·He does attack various things in the Meditations, but two aspects of his attacks keep me cheerful·. •When he does attack me, he has looked into the issues so deeply, and examined all the related topics so carefully, that I am sure there aren’t any other difficulties that he has overlooked. •And where he thinks my views are not acceptable, he presses his criticisms so acutely that I’m not afraid of anyone’s thinking that he has kept back any objections for the sake of the cause. So I am not so much •disturbed by his criticisms as •happy that he hasn’t found more to attack.

Objections concerning the human mind

The first thing that I find remarkable is that Descartes has based his whole philosophy on a principle that was laid down by St Augustine—a man of amazing abilities in theology and also in philosophy. In his book On Free Will a participant in a dialogue [Arnauld gives the details] prepares the way for a proof of the existence of God, thus:

First, if we start from what is most evident, I ask you: Do you yourself exist? Or are you perhaps afraid of making a mistake in your answer? ·You shouldn’t be, because· if you didn’t exist it would be quite impossible for you to make a mistake.

Compare that with what Descartes says:

54

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

·Perhaps· there is a supremely powerful and cunning deceiver who deliberately deceives me all the time. Even then, if he is deceiving me I undoubtedly exist.

But let us move on from this to the more central matter of Descartes’s way of getting from this principle to the result that our mind is separate from our body [Arnauld here fairly represents Descartes’s argument, but this isn’t an exact quotation from the Meditations]:

•I can doubt whether I have a body, and even whether there are any bodies at all in the world; but I can’t doubt that I am, or that I exist, so long as I am doubting or thinking.

•So I who am doubting and thinking am not a body. For if I were, my doubts about my body’s existence would be doubts about my existence, ·and we have just seen that the latter doubt is ruled out·.

•Indeed, even if I stubbornly maintain that there are no bodies whatsoever, the conclusion I have reached still stands: I am something, and therefore I am not a body.

This is certainly very acute. But someone will bring up the objection that Descartes raises against himself: the fact that I have doubts about bodies, or even deny that there are any, doesn’t make it the case that no body exists. He writes [this is quoted from the Meditations]:

These things that I suppose to be nothing because they are unknown to me—mightn’t they in fact be identical with the I of which I am aware? I don’t know; and just now I shan’t discuss the matter, because I can form opinions only about things that I know. I know that I exist, and I am asking: what is this I that I know? My knowledge of it can’t depend on things of whose existence I am still unaware.

But Descartes admits ·in his Preface to the Meditations· that in the ·version of the· argument set out in his Discourse on the Method, the proof excluding anything corporeal from the nature of the mind was put forward not ‘in an order corresponding to the actual truth of the matter’ but in an order corresponding to his ‘own perception’—so that the sense of the passage was that he wasn’t aware of anything that he knew belonged to his essence except that he was a thinking thing. That makes it clear that the objection still stands, exactly as before, and that he still owes us an answer to the question ‘How does he get from the premise that •he isn’t aware of anything else belonging to his essence to the conclusion that •nothing else does in fact belong to it?’ I admit that I’m a bit slow about such things, but I haven’t been able to find an answer to this question anywhere in the second Meditation. It seems, though, that Descartes does attempt a proof of this conclusion in the sixth Meditation, ·presumably postponing it because· he takes it to depend on his having clear knowledge of God, which he hadn’t yet achieved in the second Meditation. Here is the proof:

I know that (1) if I have a vivid and clear thought of something, God could have created it in a way that exactly corresponds to my thought. So the fact that (2) I can vividly and clearly think of one thing apart from another assures me that the two things are distinct from one another—·that is, that they really are two·—since they can be separated by God. Never mind how they could be separated; that doesn’t affect the judgment that they are distinct.... On the one hand I have a vivid and clear idea of myself as something that thinks and isn’t extended, and one of body as something that is extended and doesn’t think. So it is certain that I am really distinct from my body and can exist without it.

55

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

We must pause a little here, for it seems to me that in these few words lies the crux of the whole difficulty.

First of all, if premise (1) of this argument is to be true, its topic must be not •any kind of knowledge of a thing, or even •vivid and clear knowledge, but rather •knowledge that is adequate. For Descartes admits in his reply to Caterus [page 16] that for one thing to be conceived distinctly and separately from another they don’t have to be really distinct—·i.e. to be two things rather than one·—and that all that is needed is for them to be ‘formally distinct’, which can be achieved ‘by an abstraction of the intellect that conceives the thing inadequately’. And in that same passage he draws the following conclusion:

In contrast with that, when I think of a body as merely something having extension, shape and motion, and deny that it has anything belonging to the nature of mind, this involves me in a complete understanding of what a body is. Conversely, (2) I understand the mind to be a complete thing that doubts, understands, wills, and so on, while denying that it has any of the attributes contained in the idea of a body. This would be quite impossible if the mind weren’t really distinct from the body.

But someone may question whether (2) is true, and maintain that the conception you have of yourself (·your mind·) when you conceive of yourself as a thinking, non-extended thing is an inadequate one; and the same may be true of your conception of yourself (·your body·) as an extended, non-thinking thing. So we must look at how this is proved in the earlier part of the argument. For I don’t think that this matter is so clear that it should be assumed without proof as a first principle that can’t ·and therefore needn’t· be demonstrated.

Let us start with the first part of your claim, namely that

when you think that a body is merely something having extension, shape, motion etc., and deny that it has anything in the nature of a mind, you have a complete understanding of what a body is.

This ·is evidently true, but it· doesn’t do much for you. Those who maintain that our mind is a body don’t infer from this that every body is a mind. On their view, •body relates to •mind as •genus to •species. A complete thought of a genus can leave out a species, and can even include a denial of properties that are special to that species—which is why logicians say ‘The negation of the species doesn’t negate the genus’, for example, ‘x is not a marmoset’ doesn’t entail ‘x is not a mammal’. Thus I can understand the genus figure without bringing in my understanding of any of the properties that are special to a circle. So it remains to be proved that the mind can be completely and adequately understood apart from the body.

I can’t see anywhere in the entire work an argument that could serve to prove this claim, apart from what is laid down at the start [this isn’t an exact quotation from the Meditations]:

I can deny that any body exists, or that anything is extended, but while I am thus denying, or thinking, it goes on being certain to me that I exist. Thus, I am a thinking thing, not a body, and body doesn’t come into the knowledge I have of myself.

But so far as I can see, all that follows from this is that I can obtain some knowledge of myself without knowledge of the body. But it isn’t transparently clear to me that this knowledge is complete and adequate, enabling me to be certain that I’m not mistaken in excluding body from my essence. I’ll explain through an example.

Suppose someone knows for certain that the angle in a semi-circle is a right angle, and thus that this angle and the

56

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

diameter of the circle form a right-angled triangle. In spite of knowing this, he may •doubt, or •not yet have grasped for certain, that the square on the hypotenuse equals the sum of the squares on the other two sides; indeed he may even •deny this if he has been misled by some fallacy. (·For brevity’s sake, I’ll express this as ‘the triangle’s having the property P’·.) But now, if he argues in the same way that Descartes does, he may appear to have confirmation of his false belief, as follows: ‘I vividly and clearly perceive that the triangle is right-angled; but I doubt that it has the property P; therefore it doesn’t belong to the essence of the triangle that it has the property P.’

Again, even if I deny that the square on the hypotenuse equals the sum of the squares on the other two sides, I still remain sure that the triangle is right-angled—my mind retains the vivid and clear knowledge that one of its angles is a right angle. And given that this is so, not even God could bring it about that the triangle is not right-angled.

Therefore, ·I might argue·, the property P that I can doubt—or indeed that I can remove—while leaving my idea ·of the triangle· intact doesn’t belong to the essence of the triangle. Now look again at what Descartes says:

I know that if I have a vivid and clear thought of something, God could have created it in a way that exactly corresponds to my thought. So the fact that I can vividly and clearly think of one thing apart from another assures me that the two things are distinct from one another—·i.e. that they are two·—since they can be separated by God.

Well, I vividly and clearly understand •that this triangle is right-angled, without understanding •that the triangle has the property P. It follows, on Descartes’s pattern of reasoning, that God at least could create a right-angled triangle with the square on its hypotenuse not equal to the sum of the squares on the other sides!

The only possible reply to this that I can see is to say that the man in this example doesn’t vividly and clearly perceive that the triangle is right-angled. But how is my perception of the nature of my mind any better lit than his perception of the nature of the triangle? He is just as certain •that the triangle in the semi-circle has one right angle (which is the criterion of a right-angled triangle) as I am that •I exist because I am thinking.

Now although the man in the example vividly and clearly knows that the triangle is right-angled, he is wrong in thinking that property P doesn’t belong to the nature ·or essence· of the triangle. Similarly, although I vividly and clearly know my nature to be something that thinks, mightn’t I also be wrong in thinking that nothing else belongs to my nature apart from my being a thinking thing? Perhaps my being an extended thing also belongs to my nature. Someone might also point out that since I infer my •existence from my •thinking, it’s not surprising if the •idea that I form by thinking of myself in this way represents me to myself purely as a thinking thing; for the •idea was derived entirely from my thought. So •this idea can’t provide any evidence that only what is contained in •it belongs to my essence.

One might add that the argument seems to prove too much, and takes us back to the Platonic view (though Descartes rejects it) that nothing corporeal belongs to our essence, so that man is only a mind, with the body being merely its vehicle—giving rise to the definition of man as ‘a mind that makes use of a body’.

You might reply, ·in an attempt not to be pushed to the Platonic extreme of denying that I am any way corporeal·, that body is

•excluded from my essence only in so far as I am a thinking thing,

57

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

and not

•excluded from my essence period.

But that could raise the suspicion that in my knowledge of myself as a thinking thing I don’t, ·after all·, have a complete and adequate conception of myself, but only an inadequate conception reached through intellectual abstraction.

Geometers conceive of a line as a length without breadth, and they conceive of a surface as length and breadth without depth, despite the fact that no length exists without breadth and no breadth without depth. Well, in the same way someone might suspect that every thinking thing is also an extended thing, having •the attributes that all extended things have—shape, motion, etc.—and also •the special power of thought. Given that it had that power, it could by an intellectual abstraction be thought of as just a thinking thing, though really it had bodily attributes as well. In the same way, although quantity can be conceived in terms of length alone, in reality breadth and depth belong to every quantity, along with length.

The difficulty is increased by the fact that the •power of thought seems to be tied to bodily organs, since •it can be thought to be dormant in infants and extinguished in madmen. Impious soul-destroyers—·i.e. those who deny there is such a thing as the soul·—make a great deal of this fact; ·but it can also be appealed to by those who think that there are indeed souls, which are bodies·.

Up to here I have been discussing the real distinction between our mind and the body. But since Descartes has undertaken to demonstrate •the immortality of the soul, we ought to ask whether •this obviously follows from soul’s being distinct from the body. No it doesn’t, according to the philosophical principles of the man in the street; for people ordinarily take it that the souls of brute animals are distinct from their bodies, but nevertheless perish along with them.

I reached this point in my comments, and was planning to show how Descartes’s own principles, which I thought I had gathered from his way of doing philosophy, would make it easy to infer •the immortality of the soul from •the mind’s real distinctness from the body. But then a little study composed by our illustrious author—·namely, his ‘Synopsis of the Meditations’·—was sent to me. It sheds much light on the Meditations as a whole, and offers the treatment of the immortality issue that I had been about to propose. As for the souls of the brutes, Descartes elsewhere indicates that they don’t have souls; all they have is a body whose structure of parts is such that all the movements we see ·the animal make· can be produced in it and by means of it.

I’m afraid this view won’t be widely accepted unless it is supported by very solid arguments. Consider just one example:

The light reflected from the body of a wolf onto the eyes of a sheep moves the tiny fibres of the optic nerves, and when this motion reaches the brain it spreads the animal spirits throughout the nerves in the manner required for the sheep to start running away.

At first sight it seems incredible that this should happen without the assistance of any soul. [Cartesians and others believed in ‘animal spirits’, which have been described as the animal body’s ‘hydraulic system’—a fluid or gas that was so superfine that it could move around the body very fast and get in anywhere.]

I want to add here that I wholly agree with Descartes’s views about •how imagination differs from intellect or thought, and about •how much more certain we can be of things we have grasped through reason than of what we observe through the bodily senses. I long ago learned from Augustine....that we must completely dismiss those who think that what we see with the intellect is less certain than what we see with these bodily eyes.... He wrote....that

58

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

when doing geometry he found •the senses to be like a ship, because...

... when •they had brought me to the place I was aiming for, I sent them away; and now that I was standing on dry land I started to examine these ·geometrical· matters using only my thought, ·with no appeal to my senses·, though for a long time my footsteps were unsteady. Thus, I think that a man has a better chance of •sailing on dry land than of •perceiving geometrical truths through the senses, although the senses do seem to help a little when we begin to learn.

Replies concerning the nature of the human mind
I shan’t waste time here by thanking my distinguished critic for bringing in Augustine’s authority to support me, and for setting out my arguments so vigorously that his ·main· fear seems to be that others won’t see how strong they are. But I will begin by pointing out where it was that I set out to prove that from

•the fact that all I am aware of as belonging to my essence (that is, the essence of the mind alone) is my being a thinking thing

it follows that

•nothing else does in fact belong to my essence,

—namely, in the place where I proved that God exists, a God who can bring about everything that I vividly and clearly recognize as possible. Now there may be much within me that I’m not yet aware of. For example, in the passage in question I was supposing that I wasn’t yet aware—·as I would come to be in the sixth Meditation·—that the mind had the power of moving the body, or that the mind was substantially united to the body.
[That later awareness was expressed in a memorable passage in the sixth Meditation:

Nature teaches me, through these sensations of pain, hunger, thirst and so on, that I (a thinking thing) am not merely in my body as a sailor is in a ship. Rather, I am closely joined to it—intermingled with it, so to speak—so that it and I form a unit. If this weren’t so, I wouldn’t feel pain when the body was hurt but would perceive the damage in an intellectual way, like a sailor seeing that his ship needs repairs.

Descartes uses ‘substantial unity’ and its cognates in various places, though not in the Meditations, to refer to the ‘not-like-a-sailor-in-a-ship’ idea. He never provides an account of what this substantial unity is, as distinct from what it is not.]
But what I am aware of ·in the second Meditation· is sufficient for me to be able to exist with it and it alone; so I am certain that •I could have been created by God without having other attributes of which I am unaware, and hence that •these other attributes don’t belong to the essence of the mind. For it seems to me that if something can exist without attribute A, then A isn’t included in its essence. And although •mind is part of the essence of •man, •being united to a human body is not part of the essence of •mind.

I must also explain what I meant by this:

A real distinction between x and y can’t be inferred from the fact that x is conceived apart from y by an abstraction of the intellect that conceives x inadequately. It can be inferred only if we have a •complete understanding of x as apart from y, an understanding of x as a complete thing.

Arnauld assumes my view to be that •adequate knowledge of a thing is required here; but that’s not what I was saying. Complete knowledge is different from adequate knowledge. If a piece of knowledge about x is to be adequate, it must contain absolutely all the properties of x. God has adequate knowledge of •everything, and knows that he has; but that is his special privilege. A created intellect, though it may have adequate knowledge of many things, can never know

59

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

for sure that it has such knowledge of •anything unless God tells it through a special revelation.

It isn’t hard to have adequate knowledge of x: all you need is an intellect whose power of knowing is adequate for x. But for the intellect to know for sure •that it has such knowledge, i.e. •that God put nothing into x beyond what the intellect is aware of, its power of knowing would have to equal the infinite power of God, and for this to happen would be flatly self-contradictory.

For us to recognize that x and y are distinct things ·through the ‘conceiving-separately’ test·, it can’t be required that we have adequate knowledge of them, because—as I have just explained—we can never know that we have such knowledge, ·so that the test would never be usable·. So when I said that

For x to be really distinct from y, it isn’t enough that x is understood apart from y by an abstraction of the intellect that conceives x inadequately,

I didn’t think that anyone could take this to imply that what is needed for ·the ‘conceiving-separately’ way of· establishing a real distinction is adequate knowledge. All I meant to be requiring was knowledge that we haven’t ourselves made inadequate by an abstraction of the intellect. There is a great difference between

‘My knowledge of x is wholly adequate’,

which we can never know for sure unless God reveals it to us, and

‘My knowledge of x hasn’t been made inadequate by an abstraction of the intellect.’

It’s not hard for our knowledge to be adequate enough for us to know that that is true.

Similarly, when I said that x must be understood completely, I didn’t mean that my understanding of x must be adequate, but only that I must understand x well enough to know that my understanding is complete.

I thought I had made this clear from what I had said just before and just after the passage in question. For a little earlier I had distinguished ‘incomplete’ from ‘complete’ entities, and had said that for there to be a real distinction between x and y each of them must be understood as ‘an entity in its own right that is different from everything else’.

And later on, after saying that I had ‘a complete understanding of what a body is’, I immediately added that I also ‘understood the mind to be a complete thing’. The meaning of these two phrases was identical; i.e. I took ‘a complete understanding of x’ and ‘understanding x to be a complete thing’ to mean exactly the same.

You could fairly enough ask at this point (1) ‘What do you mean by “complete thing”?’ and (2) ‘How do you prove that all it takes to establish that x is really distinct from y is •that x and y be understood as “complete” and that •each be capable of being understood apart from the other?’

My answer to (1) is that all I mean by a ‘complete thing’ is a substance endowed with forms or attributes that suffice for me to recognize that it is a substance.

We don’t have immediate knowledge of substances, as I have pointed out elsewhere. We know them only by perceiving certain forms or attributes that can’t exist except as inhering in something; and we call the thing they inhere in a ‘substance’. If we then tried ·in thought· to strip the substance of the attributes through which we know it, we would be destroying our entire knowledge of it. We might still be able to apply various words to it, but we couldn’t have a vivid and clear perception of what we meant by these words.

I realize that certain substances are commonly called ‘incomplete’. But if the reason for that is that they can’t exist on their own, then this involves something that I see as self-contradictory:

60

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

•they are substances, i.e. things that exist on their own;

•they are incomplete, i.e. not fit to exist on their own.

We can also call a substance ‘incomplete’ in a different sense: x is itself a complete substance, but it has a kind of incompleteness because •it combines with some other substance y to form something that has a unity in its own right, and so •considered in the light of that combination x is ‘incomplete’ because it is only a part of the larger thing. For example, a hand is a complete substance when it is considered on its own, but it is an incomplete substance when it is thought of in relation to the whole body of which it is a part. In just that way, a mind and a body are incomplete substances when thought of in relation to the human being which they together make up. But considered on their own they are complete.

For just as being extended and divisible and having shape etc. are forms or attributes by which I recognize the substance called ‘body’, so understanding, willing, doubting etc. are forms by which I recognize the substance called ‘mind’. And I don’t have any less grasp of a thinking substance as a complete thing than I have of an extended substance as a complete thing.

Arnauld suggests that ‘body relates to mind as genus relates to species’, but there is no way that can be right. For although a •genus can be understood without this or that specific differentia—·i.e. without thinking of this or that •species falling under the genus·—there is no way for a •species to be thought of without its •genus.

For example, we can easily understand the genus ‘figure’ without thinking of a circle (though our understanding won’t be distinct unless it does involve a specific figure, and it won’t involve a complete thing unless it also brings in the nature of body). But we can’t understand the specific differentia that marks off circle without at the same time thinking of the genus figure—·because to be a circle is, precisely, to be a figure that is characterised by that specific differentia·.

Now, I think I showed well enough in the second Meditation that the mind can be perceived distinctly and completely (i.e. sufficiently for it to be considered as a complete thing) without any of the forms or attributes by which we recognize that body is a substance. And similarly a body can be understood distinctly and as a complete thing without any of the attributes belonging to mind.

Arnauld comes in at this point, arguing that although I can have some knowledge of myself without knowledge of the body, it doesn’t follow that this knowledge is complete and adequate, so as to enable me to be certain that I’m right to exclude body from my essence. He uses the example of a triangle inscribed in a semi-circle, which we can vividly and clearly understand to be right-angled although we don’t know, or may even deny, that ·it has property P, i.e.· the square on the hypotenuse equals the sum of the squares on the other sides. But we can’t infer from this that there could be a right-angled triangle that lacked the property P.

But this example differs in many (·at least three·) respects from the case under discussion.

First: a triangle may be taken concretely as a substance with a triangular shape, but there is certainly no way of understanding the property P as a substance! So neither the triangle nor the property can be understood as a complete thing, as mind and body are. And neither of them can be called a ‘thing’ in the sense I was using when I said in the sixth Meditation ‘it is enough that I can understand one thing apart from another’ and so on, meaning ‘thing’ as ‘complete thing’. This is clear from what ·I said at the start of the paragraph that· came after that: ‘Besides I find in myself faculties’ and so on. I didn’t say that these faculties

61

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

were things, but carefully distinguished them from things or substances.

Second: although we can vividly and clearly understand that a triangle in a semi-circle is right-angled without being aware of its having property P, we cannot have a clear understanding of a triangle’s having property P without at the same time taking in that it is right-angled. In contrast with that, we can vividly and clearly perceive the mind without the body and the body without the mind.

Third: although it is possible to have a concept of triangle inscribed in a semi-circle that doesn’t include

•the triangle’s having property P, i.e. equality between the square on the hypotenuse and the sum of the squares on the other sides,

it is not possible to have a concept of triangle inscribed in a semi-circle that does include

•there being no ratio at all between the square on the hypotenuse and the squares on the other sides.

Hence, though we may be unaware of what the ratio is, we can’t rule out any candidate unless we clearly understand that it is wrong for the triangle; and we can’t clearly understand this for the ratio equality, ·because it is right for the triangle. So the concept in question must, in an indirect and oblique way, involve the property P: it must involve a thought of ‘some ratio or other’ which could take the value equality·. In contrast with this, the concept of body doesn’t include—·or even indirectly and obliquely involve·—anything at all that belongs to the mind, and the concept of mind doesn’t include—·or even indirectly and obliquely involve·—anything at all that belongs to the body.

·Summing up·: Although I said ‘it is enough that I can vividly and clearly understand one thing apart from another’ and so on, I can’t go on to argue ‘yet I vividly and clearly understand that this triangle is right-angled without understanding that the square on the hypotenuse’ and so on: •because the ratio between the square on the hypotenuse and the sum of the squares on the other sides isn’t a complete thing; •because we don’t clearly understand the ratio to be equality except in the case of a right-angled triangle; and •because there is no way of understanding the triangle distinctly while denying that it has property P.

But now I must ·move towards question (2) [on page 60] and· explain how the mere fact that I can vividly and clearly understand one substance apart from another is enough to make me certain that one excludes the other.

The answer is that the notion of a substance is just this: a substance is something that can exist by itself, i.e. without the help of any other substance. And no-one has ever perceived two substances by means of two different concepts without judging them to be really distinct—·i.e. judging that they are two substances and not one·.

Thus, if I hadn’t been looking for greater than ordinary certainty, I’d have settled for showing in the second Meditation that the mind can be understood as a subsisting thing without anything belonging to the body being attributed to it, and conversely that the body can be understood as a subsisting thing without anything belonging to the mind being attributed to it. I wouldn’t have added anything more to my demonstration that the mind is really distinct from the body, because it is generally accepted that the way things are according to our perception of them is the way they are in reality. But one of the extravagant doubts that I put forward in the first Meditation deprived me of certainty about this very point (namely whether things are in reality as we perceive them to be), as long as I was supposing myself to be ignorant of ·God·, the author of my being. That’s why everything I wrote about God and truth in the third, fourth and fifth Meditations contributes to the conclusion—finally

62

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

established in the sixth Meditation—that the mind is really distinct from the body.

Arnauld says: ‘I have a clear understanding of a triangle inscribed in a semi-circle without knowing that the triangle has the property P.’ It is true that one can understand the triangle without thinking of the ratio of •the square on its hypotenuse to •the sum of the squares on the other sides; but one can’t understand it as not having this ratio. Whereas we can understand the mind to exist •without bringing in any thought of the body, and indeed •while denying of it all the attributes of a body. For it is of the nature of substances that they should mutually exclude one another.

Arnauld continues: ‘Since I infer my existence from my thinking, it’s not surprising if the idea that I form in this way represents me purely as a thinking thing.’ But this is no objection to my argument. For in the same way when I examine the nature of the body, I don’t find the least trace of thought in it. And there can’t be a stronger argument for a distinction between two things than the fact that when we examine them separately everything we find in one is different from what we find in the other.

And I don’t see why this argument ‘proves too much’. The least thing one can say to establish that x really is distinct from y is that x can be separated from y by the power of God. Also, I thought I was being very careful to ward off the false inference that man is simply ‘a mind that makes use of a body’. In the sixth Meditation, where I dealt with the mind’s distinctness from the body, I showed along with this that the mind is substantially united with the body [see note on page 59]. And the arguments I used to prove this are as strong as any I can remember ever having read. Saying that •a man’s arm is a substance that is really distinct from the rest of his body isn’t denying •that the arm belongs to the nature of the whole man. And saying that •the arm belongs to the nature of the whole man doesn’t create the suspicion that •it can’t subsist apart from the rest of the man’s body. I don’t think I proved too much in showing that the mind can exist apart from the body, or that I proved too little in saying that the mind is substantially united with the body, for that substantial union doesn’t prevent us from having a vivid and clear concept of the mind on its own, as a complete thing. This is quite different from the concept of a surface or a line, which can’t be understood as complete things unless we attribute to them not just length and breadth but also depth.

Finally the fact that •the power of thought is dormant in infants and disturbed—not ‘extinguished’, ·as Arnauld said·—in madmen doesn’t show that we should regard •it as attached to bodily organs in such a way that it can’t exist without them. We have plenty of experience of thought being •impeded by bodily organs, but it doesn’t follow from this that thought is •produced by those organs—a view that there’s not the slightest reason to accept.

Admittedly, the closeness of the mind’s union with the body—a union that we experience constantly through our senses—makes us unaware of the real distinctness of mind from body unless we attentively meditate on the subject. But I think that those who repeatedly ponder on what I wrote in the second Meditation will be easily convinced that the mind is distinct from the body—not merely thought of as distinct by a fiction or abstraction of the intellect, but known to be a distinct thing because that’s what it really is.

I shan’t respond to Arnauld’s observations about the immortality of the soul, because they don’t conflict with my own views. As for the souls of brute animals: this isn’t the place to go into that subject. I make some explanatory remarks about it in Part 5 of my Discourse on the Method, and I couldn’t add to them without giving an account of the

63

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

whole of physics. Still, so as not to pass over the topic in complete silence, I’ll say the thing that it is most important to say, namely: in our bodies and those of the brutes, no movements can occur without the presence of all the organs or instruments that would enable the same movements to be produced in a machine. So even in our own case the mind doesn’t directly move the physical limbs, but simply controls the animal spirits [see note on page 58] that flow from the heart via the brain into the muscles, and sets up certain motions in them; for the spirits are naturally adapted to moving in all sorts of ways without difficulty. Many of the motions occurring inside us don’t depend in any way on the mind: heartbeat, digestion, nutrition, breathing when we are asleep, and also such waking actions as walking, singing and the like when we do them without thinking about them. When someone falls, and holds out his hands so as to protect his head, he isn’t instructed by reason to do this. Rather, the sight of the impending fall reaches the brain and sends the animal spirits into the nerves in the manner needed to produce this movement of the man’s hands, without any mental volition, just as it would be produced in a machine. And since our own experience reliably informs us that this is so, why should we be so amazed that the ‘light reflected from the body of a wolf onto the eyes of a sheep’ should equally be capable of arousing the movements of flight in the sheep?

Are any of the movements of the brutes similar to ones that occur in us with the help of the mind, or do they all resemble only those that depend merely on the flow of the animal spirits and the disposition of the organs? If we want to think our way through to an answer to this, we should consider the differences between men and beasts—I mean the differences set out in Part 5 of my Discourse on the Method, for I don’t think there are any others. If we do this, we’ll easily see that •all the actions of the brutes resemble only •human actions that occur without help from the mind. This will force us to conclude that we don’t know of any source of movement in animals other than the layout of their physical parts and the continual flow of the spirits that are produced by the heat of the heart as it rarefies the blood. We shall also see that what led us to imagine that the brutes have some other source of motion was merely our failure to distinguish the two sources of motion just described: seeing that the source depending solely on the animal spirits and physical organs exists in the brutes just as it does in us, we jumped to the conclusion that the other source—mind or thought—also exists in them. Beliefs that we have had since our earliest years, even though we have since had solid evidence against them, can’t easily be eradicated unless we think long and hard about that evidence.

Objections concerning God

(1) The first proof of the existence of God, which Descartes sets out in the third Meditation, falls into two parts: (a) God exists if there is an idea of God in me; (b) Given that I possess such an idea, the only possible source of my existence is God. I have only one criticism of (a). Descartes first asserts that ‘falsity in the strict sense can occur only in judgments’, but a little later he admits that ideas can be false—not ‘formally false’ but ‘materially false’, and this strikes me as inconsistent with his own principles. I am anxious to be clear about this dark matter, so I’ll discuss an example, which may help to clarify things. Descartes says that ‘if cold is merely the absence of heat, the idea of cold that represents it to me as a positive thing will be materially false’.

But if cold is merely an absence, there can’t be an idea of cold that represents it to me as a positive thing; so Descartes is here confusing a •judgment with an •idea. What is the

64

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

idea of cold? It is coldness itself existing representatively in the intellect. But if cold is an absence, it can’t exist representatively in the intellect by means of an idea whose representative existence is something positive. So if cold is merely an absence, there can’t ever be a positive idea of it, so there can’t be an idea ·of it· that is materially false.

This is confirmed by an argument of Descartes’s own—the argument to prove that the idea of an infinite being has to be a true idea because, although I can tell a story according to which no such being exists, I can’t tell one according to which the idea of such a being doesn’t represent anything real to me.

This obviously holds for any positive idea. For although I can tell a story according to which cold is represented ·to me· by a positive idea, but is actually not something positive, I can’t tell one according to which the positive idea doesn’t represent anything real and positive to me. For what makes an idea count as ‘positive’ isn’t •any fact about it considered as a psychological event (for if that were the test all ideas would be positive), but rather •the facts about its representative nature, what it represents to our mind. Thus, the idea we have been discussing may perhaps not be the idea of cold, but it can’t be a false idea.

You may reply: ‘What makes it false is precisely its not being the idea of cold.’ No: what is false is your judgment that it’s the idea of cold; the idea that you have is, in itself, perfectly true. Just as the idea of God should never be called ‘false’—not even ‘materially false’, though someone might transfer it to something that isn’t God, as idolaters have done. Summing up ·this part of my discussion·: what does the idea of cold—the one you say is materially false—represent to your mind? An absence? Then it is true. A positive entity? Then it isn’t the idea of cold.

Also: what is the cause of the positive representative being—·the content of the idea·—which you say makes the idea materially false? ‘The cause is myself’, you may answer, ‘in so far as I come from nothing.’ But in that case the positive representative being of an idea can come from nothing, and that shakes the foundations of Descartes’s theoretical structure.

Start of replies to objections concerning God
(1) Up to here I have tried confront Arnauld’s arguments and refute them. But now I am going to do what people do when fighting stronger opponents: instead of meeting him head on I will dodge his blows.

He presents only three criticisms in this section, and each can be accepted if what I wrote is understood in his way, But I meant each in a different sense from his, one that seems to me to be equally correct.

The first point concerns my statement that certain ideas are materially false—by which I mean that those ideas provide subject-matter for error. But Arnauld concentrates on ideas considered formally, and maintains that there is no falsity in them. [Descartes then sketches the other two points; these sketches will be presented at the starts of his (2) and (3) respectively. He continues:] But let us deal with the points more carefully one at a time.

When Arnauld says ‘if cold is merely an absence, there can’t be an idea of cold that represents it to me as a positive thing’, it’s clear that he is dealing solely with an idea taken formally. Since ideas are forms of a kind, and aren’t composed of any matter, when we think of them as representing something we are taking them not materially but formally. But if we consider ideas not as •representing this or that but simply as •intellectual events, then we can be said to be taking them materially; but in that case no question arises about whether they are true or false of their objects.

65

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

The only remaining sense for ‘materially false’ as applied to an idea is the one I am presenting here, ·namely ‘providing subject-matter for error’·. Whether cold is something positive or merely an absence makes no difference to my idea of cold, which remains the same as it always was. It is this idea which, I claim, can provide subject-matter for error if cold is in fact an absence and doesn’t have as much reality as heat; for if I consider the ideas of cold and heat just as I received them from my senses, I can’t tell that one of them represents more reality to me than the other.

I certainly didn’t ‘confuse a judgment with an idea’. For I said that the falsity to be found in an idea is material falsity, while the falsity involved in a judgment can only be formal.

When Arnauld says that the idea of cold ‘is coldness itself existing representatively in the intellect’, I think we need to make a distinction. It often happens with obscure and confused ideas—such as the ideas of heat and cold—that an idea of something is wrongly taken to be the idea of something else. Thus if cold is merely an absence, the idea of cold is not •‘coldness itself existing representatively in the intellect’ but something else that I wrongly mistake for this absence, namely •a sensation that in fact doesn’t exist outside the intellect.

This doesn’t apply to the idea of God, because that can’t be taken to be the idea of something that it doesn’t fit, ·i.e. of something other than God·. I’m saying that about the vivid and clear idea of God; as for the confused ideas of gods that idolaters concoct, I see no reason why they can’t be called ‘materially false’ because they provide the idolaters with subject-matter for false judgments. But ·material falsity is a matter of degree·: ideas that give the judgment little or no scope for error don’t seem as much entitled to be called ‘materially false’ as those that give great scope for error. It’s easy to show by examples that some ideas provide much more scope for error than others. Confused ideas that •are made up at will by the mind, such as the ideas of false gods, don’t provide as much scope for error as the confused ideas that •come from the senses, such as the ideas of colour and cold (if I am right that these ideas don’t represent anything real). The greatest scope for error is provided by the ideas arising from the sensations of appetite. Thus the idea of thirst that the patient with dropsy has does indeed give him subject-matter for error, since it can lead him to judge that a drink will do him good, when in fact it will do him harm.

But Arnauld asks, concerning the idea of cold that I called ‘materially false’, what it represents to me. He says:

If it represents an absence, it is true. If it represents a positive entity, it isn’t the idea of cold.

That is correct; but my only reason for calling the idea ‘materially false’ is that its obscurity and confusedness made me unable to judge whether what it represents to me is something positive existing outside of my sensation; so that I may be led to judge that it is something positive when really it is a mere absence.

So when Arnauld asks ‘What is the cause of the positive representative being which you say makes the idea materially false?’, he is asking an improper question. I don’t claim that an idea’s material falsity results from some positive entity; it arises solely from the obscurity of the idea—although something positive underlies it, namely the actual sensation involved.

Now this positive entity, ·the sensation·, exists in something real, namely me; but the obscurity of the idea (which is the only cause of my judging that the idea of the sensation of cold represents some external item called ‘cold’) doesn’t have a real cause but arises simply from the fact that my nature is not perfect in all respects.

This doesn’t in any way ‘shake the foundations’ of my

66

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

philosophy. When I use the label ‘materially false’ for ideas that I think provide subject-matter for error, am I moving too far away from standard philosophical usage? I might have been worried about this (I have never spent very much time reading philosophical texts), but I found the word ‘materially’ used in exactly my sense in the first philosophical author I came across, namely Suarez, Metaphysical Disputations IX.ii.4.

Objection
(2) I turn now to (b) the second half of the proof [given on page 64], where Descartes asks ‘whether I who have the idea of an infinite being could derive my existence from any source other than an infinite being, and in particular whether I could derive it from myself’. He maintains that I couldn’t derive my existence from myself, because ‘if I had given existence to myself I would also have given myself all the perfections of which I find I have an idea’. But Caterus ·in the first set of Objections· has an acute reply to this: ‘derived from oneself’ should be taken not •positively but •negatively, so that it simply means ‘not derived from anything else’. He continues:

But now, if something gets its existence ‘from itself’ in the sense of not getting it from anything else, how can we prove that this being takes in everything and is infinite? Don’t tell me: ‘If it derived its existence from itself, it could easily have given itself everything.’ For the thing we are now talking about didn’t get its existence from itself as a cause; it didn’t exist prior to itself so as to be able to choose in advance what it would come to be. [page 4]

To refute this argument, Descartes maintains that the phrase ‘deriving one’s existence from oneself’ should be taken not •negatively but •positively, even when it refers to God, so that ‘in a certain way God relates to himself as an efficient cause relates to its effect’ [page 8]. This seems to me to be a hard saying, and indeed to be false.

Thus I partly agree with Descartes and partly disagree with him. I agree that I couldn’t derive my existence from myself in any way but positively; but I don’t agree that the same holds for God. On the contrary, I think it is obviously self-contradictory to maintain that anything derived its existence positively—as it were causally—from itself. So I propose to establish Descartes’s conclusion but by a completely different route, as follows [this slightly expands Arnauld’s formulation]:

(i) To derive my existence from myself, I would have to derive it positively—as it were, causally.

(ii) Nothing can positively—as it were, causally—derive its existence from itself.

Therefore (iii) it is impossible that I should derive my existence from myself.

Premise (i) is proved by Descartes’s own arguments based on the fact that, since the moments of time are separable from each other—·meaning that the existence of one stretch of time doesn’t logically necessitate the existence of any others·—my existing now doesn’t imply that I’ll still exist in a minute from now, unless there is some cause which as it were creates me anew at each moment’ [page 7].

As for premise (ii), I think this is so clearly shown to be true by the natural light that it can hardly be given any proof except for the piffling kind of ‘proof’ that establishes a well-known result by means of premises that are less well-known. And Descartes seems to have recognized its truth, since he hasn’t ventured to deny it openly. Consider this reply that he makes to Caterus:

I didn’t say that nothing could possibly be its own efficient cause. This is obviously true when the term ‘efficient’ [see note on page 6] is taken to apply only to

67

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

causes that are •temporally prior to or •different from their effects. But in the present context that seems not to be the best way of interpreting ‘efficient’....because the natural light doesn’t demand that we think of an efficient cause as having to be •temporally prior to its effect. [page 6 above]

The •temporal-priority part of this is quite true, but why did Descartes drop the •having-to-be-different part? Why didn’t he add that the natural light doesn’t demand that an efficient cause of x be different from x? Was it because the light of nature wouldn’t let him say this ·because it does make that demand·?

Since every effect depends on its cause, gets its existence from its cause, isn’t it clear that no thing can depend on itself, receive its existence from itself?

Again, every cause is the cause of an effect, and every effect is the effect of a cause. So there is a two-way relation between cause and effect, and a relation must involve two terms.

Also, it’s absurd to conceive of a thing as having existence and then at a later time receiving existence. But that’s what we would be thinking if we applied the notion of cause and effect to a thing in respect of itself, ·thinking that there are cases of cause-effect that instead of the form x-y have the form x-x·. The notion of cause is the concept of •giver of existence. The notion of effect is the concept of •receiver of existence. The notion of a cause is essentially prior to the notion of an effect.

We can’t use our notion of cause to conceive of something as giving existence unless we conceive of it as having existence; for no-one gives what he doesn’t have. So ·in our attempted thought of something as cause of itself· we would be putting our conception of the thing as having existence before our conception of it as receiving existence; but in the case of any receiver, it first receives x and then has x.

Another way of putting the argument: No-one gives what he doesn’t have. So no-one can give himself existence unless he already has it. But if he already has it, why should he give it to himself? Finally, Descartes asserts that ‘there is no real distinction between preservation and creation—only a conceptual one—this being one of the things that the natural light makes evident’. But the same natural light makes it evident that nothing can create itself. Therefore nothing can preserve itself, ·i.e. keep itself in existence·.

If we come down from the general thesis to the application of it to God in particular, I think it is even more clearly true: God cannot get his existence from himself positively, but only negatively, i.e. not getting his existence from anything else.

This is clear first of all from Descartes’s own argument to prove that if a body gets existence from itself it must do so in the positive way. He says:

The parts of time don’t depend on one another; so the supposed fact that this body has existed until now ‘from itself’, i.e. without a cause, isn’t sufficient to make it the case that this body will continue to exist in future, unless the body has some power which (as it were) re-creates it continuously. [page 8]

But so far from this argument being applicable to a supremely perfect or infinite being, we can actually infer the opposite result, and for opposite reasons. It goes like this:

Built into the idea of an infinite being is the being’s having a duration that is infinite, i.e. not restricted by any limits; and it follows from this that it is indivisible, permanent, and existing all at once, so that the concepts of ‘before’ and ‘after’ can’t be applied ·to it·, except through an error and imperfection of

68

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

our intellect.

It obviously follows from this we can’t conceive of an infinite thing as existing, even for a moment, without conceiving of it as something that has always existed and will always exist, for eternity (Descartes himself establishes this elsewhere). So there’s no point in asking why this being continues to exist.

Augustine, whose remarks on the subject of God are as noble and sublime as any that have appeared since the time of the sacred authors, frequently teaches that in God there is no past or future but only eternally present existence. This makes it even clearer that the question of why God should continue in existence cannot be asked without absurdity, since the question manifestly involves the notions of ‘before’ and ‘after’, past and future, which should be excluded from the concept of an infinite being.

And God can’t be thought of as positively getting his existence ‘from himself’, as if he had created himself in the beginning. For that would require him to exist (·so as to give existence·) before he existed (·as a result of receiving it·). As Descartes often says, his sole basis for holding that God gets existence ‘from himself’ is his view that God really does keep himself in existence.

But an infinite being can’t be thought of as •keeping itself in existence, any more than it can be thought of •being brought into existence. For what is keeping-in-existence except continual re-creation, ·i.e. continual being-brought-into-existence·? Thus all keeping-in-existence presupposes being-brought-into-existence....

So we should conclude that God cannot be conceived of as positively getting existence from himself, except through an imperfection of our intellect, which conceives of God after the fashion of created things. Another argument will make this even clearer.

When we look for the efficient cause of something, we are looking for the cause of its •existing, not the cause of its •essence. When I see a triangle, I may look for the efficient cause of this triangle’s existing; but it would be absurd to inquire into the efficient cause of this triangle’s having three angles equal to two right angles. If anyone asks what causes the triangle to have that property, the right response is not to give an efficient cause but rather to explain that this is the nature ·or essence· of a triangle. That’s why mathematicians, who aren’t concerned with the existence of the objects they study, never give demonstrations involving efficient or final causes [see note on page 6]. But it belongs to the essence of an infinite being that it exists—or stays in existence, if you wish—just as it belongs to the essence of a triangle to have its three angles equal to two right angles.

•Why does a triangle have three angles equal to two right angles? •Because this is the eternal and unchangeable nature of a triangle.

•Why does God exist, or continue in existence?

•Because this is the nature of a supremely perfect being.

That is the answer we should give. We shouldn’t try to find any efficient cause either in God or outside him. (Nor any ‘quasi-efficient’ cause! My concern is with realities, not labels.)

Descartes says that the light of nature lays it down that for any existing thing we may ask why it exists—that is, we may ask •what its efficient cause is or, if it doesn’t have one, •why it doesn’t. I reply to this that if someone asks

Why does God exist?

we oughtn’t to answer in terms of an efficient cause, but should explain that he exists simply •because he is God, or •because he is an infinite being. And if someone asks

What is the efficient cause of God’s existing?

69

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

we ought to reply that he doesn’t need an efficient cause. And if the questioner goes on to ask

Why doesn’t he need an efficient cause?

we ought to answer that it’s because he is an infinite being whose existence is his essence. For the only things that need an efficient cause are those in which actual existence can be distinguished from essence.

This disposes of the argument that follows the passage just quoted:

So if I thought that nothing could possibly relate to itself in the way an efficient cause relates to its effect, I certainly would not conclude that there was a first cause! On the contrary, if someone postulated a ‘first cause’ I would ask what its cause was, so I would never arrive at a genuine first cause of everything.

Not at all! If I thought we ought to look for the efficient cause....of any given thing, then what I would be looking for was a cause distinct from the thing in question, because it seems perfectly obvious that nothing can possibly relate to itself in the way that an efficient cause stands to its effect. Descartes should be advised to re-think this matter very carefully, because I know for sure that almost every theologian will be upset by the proposition that God derives his existence from himself positively, as it were causally.

Reply
(2) Arnauld’s second point concerns my claim that God derives his existence from himself ‘positively and as it were causally’. All that I meant by this was that the reason why God doesn’t need any efficient cause in order to exist is based on something positive—namely the very immensity of God, which is as positive as anything can be! Arnauld, however, shows that God is not self-created or self-preserved by the positive influence of any efficient cause; and this I quite agree with. [That is the sketch mentioned in a note on page 65. Then we come to what Descartes says when ‘dealing with the points more carefully one at a time’:]

The complaint that Arnauld emphasizes •most—though it seems to me to be the •least deserving of emphasis—concerns the passage where I said that ‘in a certain way God relates to himself as an efficient cause relates to its effect’. Arnauld says that it is ‘a hard saying, and indeed false’ to suggest that God is his own efficient cause; but I actually denied that suggestion in the passage just quoted. For in saying that God ‘in a certain way’ stands in the same relation ·to himself· as an efficient cause ·does to its effect·, I made it clear that I did not suppose he was the same as an efficient cause; and in using the phrase ‘we are quite entitled to think’, I meant that I was explaining the matter in these terms merely because of the imperfection of the human intellect. Indeed, throughout the rest of the passage I confirmed this. Right at the beginning, having said ‘we may always ask, of any existing thing what its efficient cause was’, I added ‘and if it didn’t have one, why didn’t it need one?’ These words show clearly that I did believe that there is something that doesn’t need an efficient cause. And what could that be but God? A little further on I said that there is in God ‘such great and inexhaustible power that he needed no help from anything else in order to exist, or in order to stay in existence’ so that he is, ‘in a way, his own cause’. Here the phrase ‘his own cause’ can’t possibly be taken to mean an efficient cause; it simply means that God’s inexhaustible power is the cause or reason why he doesn’t need a cause. And since that inexhaustible power—that immensity of essence—is utterly positive, I said that the reason or cause why God needs no cause is a positive one. Now this can’t be said of any finite thing, even one that is perfect of its kind. When a finite thing is said to get its existence ‘from itself’, this has to taken in a

70

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

negative sense, meaning that its positive nature provides no basis for thinking that it doesn’t need an efficient cause.

Similarly, in every passage where I compared

•the formal cause—the reason provided by God’s essence, in virtue of which he needs no cause in order to exist or to stay in existence—

with

•the efficient cause—without which finite things can’t exist—

I always chose my wording so as to make it clear that the two kinds of cause are different. [See the note on them on page 6.] And I never said that God preserves himself by some positive force, in the way created things are preserved—·kept in existence·—by him; what I described as a ‘positive’ thing was the immensity of his power or essence, in virtue of which he doesn’t need a preserver.

So I can freely accept everything Arnauld puts forward to prove (and this is the only upshot of his arguments) that God isn’t the efficient cause of himself and doesn’t keep himself in existence himself by any positive power or by continuously re-creating himself. But I hope Arnauld won’t deny that •the immensity of God’s power in virtue of which he doesn’t need a cause in order to exist is a positive thing in God, and that •nothing else contains anything positive that frees it from needing an efficient cause in order to exist. That is all I meant when I said that the •only sense in which anything other than God can be said to get its existence ‘from itself’ is a •negative one....

But since Arnauld has given me such a sombre warning that ‘almost every theologian will be upset by the proposition that God derives his existence from himself positively, as it were causally’, I’ll explain a little more carefully why this way of talking is very useful—even necessary—when dealing with these matters, and explain why there is absolutely nothing in it to be upset about. [Then a paragraph about the Latin and Greek terminology used by theologians when writing about relations (‘producing’, ‘begetting’ etc.) amongst the members of Christianity’s Holy Trinity. In that tricky area, Descartes says, there are reasons to be wary of the word ‘cause’, but:] where there is no such risk of error, and we are dealing with God not as a trinity but simply as a unity, I don’t see why the word ‘cause’ must be avoided at all costs, especially in a context where it seems to be

•very useful, because it serves to demonstrate the existence of God,

and also

•indispensable, because it is needed if that demonstration is to be completely clear.

I think it is clear to everyone that the concept of efficient causes comes into our primary and principal way, if not our only way, of demonstrating that God exists. We can’t make the demonstration precise unless we set our minds free to ask about the efficient causes of everything, even of God—for we can’t legitimately make an exception of God at a stage where we haven’t yet proved that he exists! So we should ask about everything ‘Does it get its existence from itself or from something else?’; and this question leads to the inference that God exists, even though we have not given an explicit account of what it means to say that something gets its existence ‘from itself’. Those who are guided purely by the natural light will in this context, unprompted, form a concept of cause that is common to •efficient causes and to •formal causes: they will take

•‘x gets its existence from something else’

to mean that x gets its existence from that thing as an efficient cause, and

•’x gets its existence from itself’

to mean that x gets its existence from itself as a formal

71

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

cause, meaning that x’s essence entails that x doesn’t need an efficient cause. Accordingly, I didn’t explain this point in my Meditations, but left it out, assuming it was self-evident.

Some people are in the habit of assuming that nothing can be the efficient cause of itself, and they carefully distinguish efficient causes from formal ones. So when they confront the question

Does anything get its existence from itself?

they find it natural to think of this only in terms of efficient causes, strictly so-called. And that leads them to suppose that the phrase ‘from itself’ must be taken not as meaning ·positively· •‘from a cause’ but only negatively •‘without a cause’—implying that for some reason we mustn’t ask why the thing exists. Caterus showed in the first set of Objections that if we read the phrase ‘from itself’ in this way, we won’t be able to produce any argument for the existence of God based on his effects; so this interpretation must be totally rejected. To deal with this matter properly, I think, we have to show that between •‘efficient cause’ in the strict ·and narrow· sense and •‘no cause at all’ there is a third possibility, namely •‘the positive essence of a thing’, to which the concept of an efficient cause can be extended. (·This kind of concept-stretching is perfectly legitimate·. In geometry the concept of •the arc of a circle is standardly extended, for the case of an indefinitely large circle, to cover •straight lines; and the concept of a •straight-sided polygon is extended, for the case of a polygon with indefinitely many sides, to cover •circles.) I thought I explained this in the best way available to me when I said that when we are exploring this question we shouldn’t restrict the meaning of ‘efficient cause’ to causes that are •prior in time to their effects or •different from them.

·We need to leave •priority and •otherness out of the meaning of ‘efficient cause’· because if we don’t, the question would be trivial, since everyone knows that nothing can be •prior to itself or •distinct from itself. ·And omitting •priority is legitimate·, because the restriction ‘prior in time’ can be deleted from the concept while leaving the notion of efficient cause intact. That a cause needn’t be prior in time ·to its effect· is clear from the fact that something counts as a cause only while it is producing its effect, as I have said.

The second condition—·otherness·—can’t also be deleted; but this shows only that a cause that isn’t distinct from its effects is not an ‘efficient cause’ in the strict ·and narrow· sense; and this I admit. But it doesn’t follow that such a cause is in no way a positive cause that can be regarded as analogous to an efficient cause; and that’s all that my argument requires. The natural light that enables me to perceive that

if I had given myself existence, I would have given myself all the perfections of which I have an idea,

also enables me to perceive that

nothing can give itself existence in the restricted sense usually implied by the proper meaning of the term ‘efficient cause’.

For in that sense, ‘x gives existence to x’ would mean that x as giver was different from x as recipient, so that we would have ‘x is different from x and x is x’—which is self-contradictory. So the question ‘Can anything give itself existence?’ must be taken to mean ‘Does anything have a nature or essence such that it doesn’t need an efficient cause in order to exist?’

The further proposition that

•if there is something that doesn’t need an efficient cause in order to exist, it will give itself all the perfections of which it has an idea, if it doesn’t already have them,

means that this being must actually have all the perfections it is aware of. This is because we perceive by the natural

72

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

light that a being whose essence is so immense that it

•doesn’t need an efficient cause in order to exist

is also a being that

•doesn’t need an efficient cause in order to have all the perfections it is aware of.

The being’s own essence is the higher-form source from which it gets everything that we can think of as gettable from an efficient cause.

The point of saying that it will give itself all the perfections ‘if it doesn’t already have them’ is just to help you get your mind around this, ·and not to imply that such a being might for a while be aware of perfections that it didn’t yet have·. For the natural light enables us to perceive that it is impossible for such a being to have the power and will to give itself something that it doesn’t yet have; rather, its essence is such that it possesses from eternity everything that we can now suppose it would give to itself if it didn’t yet have it. [In all this, ‘it’ could be replaced by ‘he’; there is no difference in the Latin.]

All the above ways of talking, derived from an analogy with the notion of efficient causation, are utterly necessary for guiding the natural light so that we get a clear awareness of these matters. It was exactly that sort of analogy, between a curved-line figure and a straight-line one, that enabled Archimedes to demonstrate various properties of the sphere that could hardly have been grasped in any other way. No-one criticizes these proofs for likening a sphere to a polyhedron, and in the same way—so it seems to me—I shouldn’t be criticized for using the analogy of an •efficient cause to explain features that in fact belong to a •formal cause, i.e. to the essence of God.

There’s no possible risk of error in using this analogy, because the one feature of an efficient cause that can’t be transferred to a formal cause ·is in no danger of being carried across to the ‘cause of itself’ context, because that transfer· involves an obvious contradiction that no-one would be seduced into accepting: specifically, it involves saying that something could be different from itself....

[Descartes then points out that although he calls God the cause of himself, he doesn’t call him the effect of himself, because the status of effect involves a certain indignity. He sees a precedent for this in what theologians say about the Christian Trinity—the Father is the ‘originating source’ of the Son, they say, but they don’t say that the Son is ‘originated’.—He then spends a short paragraph contending that in equating God’s essence with his formal cause he is following Aristotle. Then:]

It was, however, scarcely possible for me to handle this topic without applying the term ‘cause’ to God. See what happened when Arnauld tried to reach the same conclusion as I did, but by another route. He completely failed in this, or so it seems to me. •First, he explains at length that God isn’t his own efficient cause, since ‘x is the efficient cause of y’ entails that x is distinct from y. •Then he shows that God doesn’t positively get his existence from himself, where ‘positively’ is taken to imply the positive power of a cause. •And then he shows that God doesn’t really preserve himself ·or keep himself in existence·, if ‘preservation’ is taken to mean the continuous creation of a thing. I am happy to accept all this. But then Arnauld again tries to show that God can’t be called his own efficient cause, on the grounds that ‘when we look for the efficient cause of something, we are looking for the cause of its •existence, not the cause of its •essence’. He continues:

But it belongs to the essence of an infinite being that it exists, no less than it belongs to the essence of a triangle to have its three angles equal to two right angles. And hence if someone asks whether God exists, it wouldn’t be right to answer that in terms of

73

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

an efficient cause, any more than it would be to do that if someone asks why the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles.

This line of thought can easily be turned against Arnauld, as follows. Although we don’t ask for the efficient cause of something’s essence, we can ·properly· ask for the efficient cause of something’s existence; and in the case of God, essence is not distinct from existence; therefore we can ask for the efficient cause ·of an essence· in the case of God.

But to reconcile our two positions, the question ‘Why does God exist?’ should be answered not in terms of an efficient cause in the strict sense, but simply in terms of the essence or formal cause of the thing. And precisely because in the case of God there is no distinction between existence and essence, the formal cause will be strongly analogous to an efficient cause, and hence can be called something close to an efficient cause.

Finally, Arnauld adds:

If someone asks ‘What is the efficient cause of God’s existing?’, we should reply that he doesn’t need an efficient cause. And if the questioner goes on to ask ‘Why doesn’t he need an efficient cause?’ we should answer that it’s because he is an infinite being whose existence is his essence. For the only things that need an efficient cause are those in which actual existence may be distinguished from essence.

This, he says, disposes of my argument that ‘if I thought that nothing could possibly relate to itself in the way an efficient cause relates to its effect, then in the course of my inquiry into the causes of things I would never arrive at a first cause of everything’. But it seems to me that this point ·of Arnauld’s· neither disposes of my argument nor in any way shakes or weakens it. In fact the principal force of my proof depends on it, as do all the proofs that can be constructed to demonstrate the existence of God from his effects. And most theologians maintain that an argument based on God’s effects is the only kind that can be adduced to prove his existence.

Thus, in denying that God relates to himself in a manner analogous to that of an efficient cause ·to its effect·, Arnauld not only fails to clarify the proof of God’s existence, but actually prevents the reader from understanding it. This is especially true at the end when he concludes that ‘if we thought we ought to look for the efficient cause....of any given thing, then what we would be looking for would be a cause distinct from the thing in question’. ·Think about what this implies regarding arguments for God’s existence, arguments that aim to bring non-believers to believe that God exists·. Take someone who doesn’t yet know that God exists: how can he inquire into the efficient cause of other things (this being his route to the knowledge of God), unless he thinks he can inquire into the efficient cause of anything whatsoever? And how can he terminate his inquiries by arriving at God as the first cause, if he thinks that for any given thing we must look for a cause that is distinct from it?

[Descartes then argues that Arnauld’s resistance to concept-stretching, if applied to mathematics, would undercut the good work that Archimedes did on the basis of treating a circle as a polygon with infinitely many sides. Then:] I have pursued this issue at somewhat greater length than the subject required, in order to show that I am extremely anxious to prevent anything at all being found in my writings which could justifiably give offence to the theologians.

Objection
(3) Let me add something that I missed earlier. Descartes lays it down as certain that there can be nothing in him,

74

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

considered as a thinking thing, of which he isn’t aware, but it seems to me that this is false. For by ‘himself, considered as a thinking thing’ he means simply his mind, considered as distinct from the body. But surely we can all see that there may be many things in our mind of which the mind isn’t aware. To give one example out of ever so many: the mind of an infant in its mother’s womb has the power of thought, but isn’t aware of it.

Reply
(3) Arnauld’s third and last point concerns my saying that ‘there is nothing in the mind of which we aren’t aware’. I meant this to refer to the operations of the mind, but Arnauld takes it to apply to the mind’s powers, and so denies it. [That is the sketch mentioned in the note on page 65. Then we come to what Descartes says when ‘dealing with the points more carefully one at a time’:]

It seems to me self-evident that the mind, considered as a thinking thing, can’t contain anything of which it isn’t aware. We can’t make sense of the proposition that the mind, seen as a thinking thing, contains something that isn’t a thought or something dependent on a thought....and we can’t have any thought that we aren’t aware of at the very moment when it is in us. Which is why I am sure that the mind begins to think as soon as it is implanted in the body of an infant, and that it is immediately aware of its thoughts, even though it doesn’t remember this afterwards because the impressions of these thoughts don’t remain in the memory.

But although we are always •actually aware of the acts or operations of our minds, we aren’t always aware of the mind’s faculties or powers, except •potentially. By this I mean that when we concentrate on employing one of our faculties, then we immediately become actually aware of it, if the faculty in question resides in our mind. So we can say: it’s not in the mind if we aren’t capable of becoming aware of it.

Objection
(4) I have one further worry, namely how Descartes avoids reasoning in a circle when he says that it’s only because ·we know that· God exists that we are sure that whatever we vividly and clearly perceive is true.

But we can be sure that God exists only because we vividly and clearly perceive this; so before we can be sure that God exists we need to be able to be sure that whatever we perceive clearly and evidently is true.

Reply
(4) Lastly, as to my not being guilty of circularity when I said that •our only reason for being sure that what we vividly and clearly perceive is true is the fact that ·we know for sure that· God exists, and that •we are sure that God exists only because we perceive this clearly: I have already given an adequate explanation of this point in items (3) and (4) in my reply to the second Objections [starting on page 25], where I distinguished •perceiving something clearly from •remembering having perceived it clearly at an earlier time. At first we are sure that God exists because we are attending to the arguments that prove this; but afterwards all we need to be certain that God exists is our memory that we did earlier perceive this clearly. This ·memory· wouldn’t be sufficient if we didn’t know that God exists and isn’t a deceiver.

Points that may give difficulty to theologians

(1) In order to bring to an end a discussion that is growing tiresomely long, I’ll now aim for brevity, and simply indicate the issues rather than argue them out in detail.

75

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

First, I am afraid that Descartes’s somewhat free style of philosophizing, which calls everything into doubt, may cause offence to some people. He himself admits in his Discourse on the Method that this approach is dangerous for those of only moderate intelligence; but I agree that the risk of offence is somewhat reduced in the Synopsis.

Still, I think the first Meditation should be furnished with a brief preface explaining that there is no •serious doubt cast on these matters, and that all he wants to do is to set aside temporarily anything about which there is even the •‘slightest’ and most •‘exaggerated’ doubt (as Descartes himself puts it elsewhere); this being done as an aid to discovering something so firm and stable that not even the most perverse sceptic will have any scope for doubt about it. And a related point: I suggest that the clause ‘since I didn’t know the author of my being’ should be replaced by ‘since I was pretending that I didn’t know...’ etc.

In the case of the fourth Meditation (‘Truth and Falsity’), I strongly urge—for reasons that it would take too long to list—that Descartes should make two things clear, either in the Meditation itself or in the Synopsis.

The first is that when he is inquiring into the cause of error, Descartes is dealing above all with how we go wrong in •distinguishing true from false, not with how we go wrong in •pursuing good and ·avoiding· evil.

All Descartes needs for his purposes is the discussion of the •first kind of error; what he says there about the cause of error would give rise to serious objections if it were stretched to cover •the second. So ·errors having to do with good and evil should be explicitly declared off-limits·: it seems to me that prudence requires, and the expository order that Descartes values so much demands, that anything that isn’t relevant and could generate controversy should be omitted. Otherwise the reader may be drawn into pointless quarrels over irrelevancies, and be blocked from taking in the essentials.

The second point I would like Descartes to stress is this: Where he says that we should assent only to what we vividly and clearly know, he is talking only about scientific and theoretical matters, and not with matters having to do with faith and the conduct of life; so that he is condemning only •rashly adopted views of the opinionated, not •prudent beliefs of the faithful. As St Augustine wisely points out:

Three things in the soul of man need to be distinguished, even though they are closely related: understanding, belief and opinion.

A person •understands if he grasps something through a reliable reason. He •believes if he is influenced by weighty authority to accept a truth even though he doesn’t grasp it through a reliable reason. And he is •opinionated if he thinks he knows something that he actually doesn’t know.

Being opinionated is a very grave fault, because: (a) If someone is convinced that he knows the answer already, he won’t be able to learn, even when there is something to be learnt; and (b) rashness ·in rushing to judgment· is in itself a mark of a disordered soul.

Understanding comes from reason; belief from authority; opinionatedness from error. This distinction will help us to understand that we aren’t guilty of being hasty and opinionated when we hold on to our faith in matters that we don’t yet grasp.

Those who say that we shouldn’t believe anything that we don’t know for sure are scared of being thought to be •opinionated. Admittedly •that is a disgraceful and wretched fault; but we should carefully reflect on the fact that

•reckoning one knows something

76

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

is very different from

•understanding that one is ignorant about something, while believing it under the influence of some authority.

If we reflect on this we will surely avoid the charges of error on the one hand, and inhumanity and arrogance on the other. (The Usefulness of Belief, ch. 15)

A little later, in Chapter 12 [sic], Augustine adds: ‘I could produce many arguments to show that absolutely nothing in human society will be safe if we set ourselves to believe only what we can regard as having been clearly perceived.’ These, then, are the views of Augustine.

Descartes, sensible man that he is, will readily judge how important it is to make those distinctions. Otherwise, people who are prone to impiety (and these days there are plenty of them) may distort his words in order to subvert the faith.

Reply
(1) I countered Arnauld’s first group of arguments and dodged the second group. The arguments in his final section I completely agree with—except for the last one, and don’t think it will be hard to bring him around to my view on that.

I completely concede, then, that the contents of the first Meditation, and indeed the others, aren’t suitable for every mind. I said this whenever the occasion arose, and I’ll go on doing so. That is the only reason why I didn’t deal with these matters in the Discourse on the Method, which was written in French ·and therefore aimed at a wider audience·, reserving them for the Meditations, which I warned should be studied only by very intelligent and well-educated readers. Someone might object: ‘If there are things that very many people ought not to read about, you’d have done better to avoid writing about them!’ I don’t accept that, because I regard these matters as so crucial that without them no firm or stable results can ever be established in philosophy. Fire and knives are dangerous in the hands of careless people or children, but they are so useful for human life that no-one thinks we should do without them altogether.

The next point concerns the fact that in the fourth Meditation I dealt only ‘with how we go wrong in distinguishing true from false, not how we go wrong in pursuing good and ·avoiding· evil’, and that when I asserted that ‘we should assent only to what we clearly know’ this was always subject to the exception of ‘matters having to do with faith and the conduct of life’. This is shown by the structure and texture of my book, and I also said it explicitly in (5) in my reply to the second Objections [page 31], and I also gave advance warning of it in the Synopsis. I say this in order to show how much I respect Arnauld’s judgment and how much I welcome his advice. [What comes next is Arnauld’s ‘last one’.]

Objection
(2) What I see as most likely to offend theologians is the fact that Descartes’s doctrines do damage to the Church’s teaching concerning the sacred mysteries of the Eucharist.

We believe on faith that the substance of the bread is taken away from the bread of the Eucharist and only the accidents—·the properties·—remain. These are extension, shape, colour, smell, taste and other qualities perceived by the senses.

But Descartes thinks there aren’t any sensible qualities—merely motions in the bodies that surround us, enabling us to perceive the various impressions that we then call ‘colour’, ‘taste’ and ‘smell’. Thus, only shape, extension and mobility remain; and these, Descartes maintains, are not intelligible apart from some substance for them to inhere in, and therefore can’t exist without such a substance. He repeats this in his reply to Caterus.

77

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

Also, the only distinctness that he allows between a substance and its states is a formal one; and that doesn’t seem to be enough distinctness to allow for the states to be separated from the substance even by God.

Descartes’s great piety will lead him, I’m sure, to ponder on this matter attentively and diligently, regarding himself as obliged to put his most strenuous efforts into the problem. Otherwise, even though he was aiming to defend the cause of God against the impious, he may seem to have endangered the very faith, founded by divine authority, that he hopes will lead him to the eternal life of which he has undertaken to convince mankind.

Reply
(2) There remains the sacrament of the Eucharist, with which Arnauld believes my views are in conflict. He says: ‘We believe on faith that the substance of the bread is taken away from the bread of the Eucharist and only the accidents remain’; and he thinks that I don’t admit that there are any real accidents, but recognize only modes that are unintelligible apart from some substance for them to inhere in and therefore can’t exist without such a substance.
[‘Accident’ means ‘property’. A ‘real accident’—where ‘real’ comes from res = ‘thing’—is a thing-like property, which can move across from one substance to another: x becomes cool while y becomes warm because (so the theory goes) the individual instance of warmth that x had moves across to y.

As well as this kettle (a particular thing), and warmness (a universal property), there is the warmness of this kettle (a particular property).

Some philosophers thought that real accidents—also called ‘real qualities’ by Descartes—can also exist apart from any substance; hence the contrast with ‘modes that are unintelligible apart from some substance’. Descartes’s writings show him as sceptical about real accidents, even if he doesn’t explicitly deny that there are any. How do ‘real accidents’ connect with the Eucharist? Descartes is about to tell us.]
I can easily escape this objection by saying that I have never denied that there are real accidents. It is true that in the Optics and the Meteorology I didn’t use them to explain the matters which I was dealing with, but in the Meteorology I said explicitly expressly that I wasn’t denying their existence. And in the Meditations, although I was supposing that I didn’t yet have any knowledge of them, that didn’t commit me to there not being any. The analytic style of writing [see note on page 34] that I adopted there allows us sometimes to assume things that haven’t yet been thoroughly examined; and this is what happened in the first Meditation, where I made many assumptions which I then refuted in the subsequent Meditations. And I certainly didn’t intend at that point to reach definite conclusions about the nature of accidents; I simply set down what appeared to be true of them on a preliminary survey. And when I said that modes are not intelligible apart from some substance for them to inhere in, I didn’t mean to be denying that they can be separated from a substance by the power of God; for I firmly insist and believe that God can bring about many things that we can’t understand.

But I now openly acknowledge that I am convinced that when we perceive a body by our senses, what affects our senses is simply the surface—the outer boundary—of the body in question. That is because (a) nothing can affect our senses except through contact (as all philosophers agree, even Aristotle); and (b) contact with an object takes place only at the surface. So bread or wine, for example, are perceived by the senses only to the extent that the surface of the bread or wine comes into contact with our sense organs, either immediately or via the air or other bodies (as I maintain) or via ‘intentional species’ (as many philosophers hold). [This use of ‘species’ has nothing to do with classification, species/genus etc. Its meaning has to do with resemblance. Some medievals thought they

78

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

found in Aristotle a theory of sense-perception according to which when you see (for example) the full moon, the moon is sending to your eyes ‘species’, i.e. items that resemble the moon. As you might expect, some philosophers interpreted these ‘species’ as real accidents (see note early in this Reply). A few lines down the next page Descartes will kidnap ‘species’ and make it mean something that fits with his utterly different views about sense-perception. All occurrences of ‘species’ other than in the discussion of the Eucharist will be replaced by ‘image’.]

·WHAT IS A SURFACE?·

Our conception of a body’s surface shouldn’t be based merely on what we could learn through our fingers; it should also cover all the tiny gaps between the particles of flour that make up the bread, the tiny gaps between the particles of alcohol, water, vinegar etc. that are mixed together to make wine, and similarly for the particles of other bodies. ·Don’t think of· these particles ·as static, uniform cubes; they· have various shapes and motions, so that when they are packed together, however tightly, there are bound to be many spaces between them—spaces that are not empty but full of air or other matter. Bread, for example, has gaps that we can see with the naked eye; they are big enough to contain not just air but water or wine or other liquids. And since bread doesn’t lose its identity when the air or other matter in its pores is replaced, it is clear that this matter doesn’t belong to the substance of the bread. So the surface of the bread isn’t

•the smallest area that completely surrounds the entire piece of bread,

but rather

•the area that immediately surrounds the bread’s individual particles.

·That is, the surface isn’t smooth; it is extremely bumpy, because it tightly wraps over the outside of each tiny particle at the edge of the bread·.

This surface moves •in its entirety, of course, when a whole piece of bread is moved from one place to another, and there is also •partial movement when some particles of the bread are agitated by air or other bodies that enter its pores. Thus, if a body has some or all of its parts in continual motion (as I think that most of the particles of bread do, and all those of wine), then its surface must be understood to be in some sort of continual motion.

Don’t think of the surface of a body—bread, wine or whatever—as •a part of the substance or the quantity of the body in question, or as •a part of the surrounding bodies. It should be thought of as the boundary that •the individual particles share with •the bodies that surround them. This boundary isn’t a thing out there in the world; it is a way of conceptualising a part of the world.

·THE EUCHARIST, SURFACES, REAL ACCIDENTS·

Contact occurs only at this boundary, and we have sensory awareness of things only through contact. With those two results on board, consider the statement that ·in the Eucharist·

the substances of the bread and wine are changed into the substance of something else in such a way that this new substance •is contained within the boundaries that the bread and wine formerly had

—meaning that the new substance •exists in the same place that the bread and wine formerly occupied (or, ·to be really accurate about it·, the place that the bread and wine would occupy now if they were still present; this differs from the other formulation because the boundaries of the bread and wine are continually in motion). Clearly, this ·indented· statement entails that the new substance must affect all our senses in exactly the way that the bread and wine would be affecting them if no transubstantiation had occurred.

Now, the teaching of the Church in the Council of

79

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

Trent....is that ‘the whole substance of the bread is changed into the substance of the body of our lord Christ, while the species of the bread remains unaltered’. The only sense that can possibly be made of ‘the •species of the bread’ is as referring to the •surface between the individual particles of the bread and the bodies surrounding them.

I repeat that contact occurs only at this surface. Aristotle himself acknowledges (De Anima III.13) that all the senses—not just the sense of touch—operate through contact. [Descartes quotes this in Greek.]

No-one thinks that ‘species’ here means anything other than ‘whatever it is that is needed in order to act on the senses’. And no-one who believes that the bread is changed into the body of Christ would deny that this body of Christ is precisely contained within the same surface that would contain the bread if it were present. [The Latin means that no believer would say this; evidently the word non was dropped out.] Christ’s body, however, isn’t supposed to be spatially present, but to be (·and here again I quote the Council of Trent·) present ‘sacramentally, with a kind of existence which •we cannot express in words but which •we nevertheless can, when our thought is enlightened by faith, understand to be possible with God, and in which •we should most steadfastly believe’. All this is so smoothly and correctly explained by my principles that I have no reason to fear that anything here will give the slightest offence to orthodox theologians. On the contrary, I confidently look to them for hearty thanks to me for putting forward opinions in physics that fit with theology much better than those commonly accepted. For as far as I know the Church has never taught that the ‘species’ of the bread and wine that remain in the sacrament of the Eucharist are real accidents that miraculously subsist on their own when the substance in which they used to inhere has been removed.

[The remaining part of the Replies to Arnauld were added in the second edition of the work.] ·Still, ‘real accidents’ loom large in much of what theologians say about the Eucharist, so that they might be thought to be essential to it. I’ll explain why they aren’t·. Perhaps what happened was that the theologians who first tried to give a philosophical account of the Eucharist were so firmly convinced that there are ‘real accidents’ that stimulate our senses and are distinct from any substance that it didn’t enter their heads that there could ever be any doubt about this. They found so many difficulties in the way of doing this that they should have come to think what travellers think when they find themselves confronted by rough territory that they can’t get through—namely they had strayed from the true path! ·I now present three reasons why it was a bad move to interpret the Eucharist in terms of ‘real accidents’·.

(a) Anyone who makes this move, and who agrees that all sense-perception occurs through contact, seems to contradict himself in supposing that for objects to stimulate the senses they need ·real accidents, i.e.· something more than the various configurations of their surfaces. ·Don’t say ‘The real accidents are not something over and above contact; they are needed for there to be contact·; for it is self-evident that a surface is on its own sufficient to produce contact. As for those who deny that sense-perception occurs through contact, nothing they can contribute to the topic will have any semblance of truth!

(b) We can’t have the thought of the accidents of the bread as real [= ‘thing-like’] and yet existing apart from the bread’s substance, without thinking of them as substances. So it seems to be a contradiction to say that

•the whole substance of the bread changes,

as the Church believes, and that

•something real that was in the bread remains.

80

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

For the ‘something real’ that is thought of as remaining must be thought of as something that subsists and is therefore a substance, even if the word ‘accident’ is applied to it. [Something ‘subsists; if it exists on its own, not supported or possessed by something else.] So the ‘real accidents’ interpretation of the Eucharist maintains that

•the whole substance of the bread changes,

and that

•a part of the bread’s substance (the part called a ‘real accident’) remains.

If this is expressed in terms of ‘real accident’ without explicitly equating this with ‘substance’, it isn’t verbally selfcontradictory; but it is still conceptually self-contradictory.

That seems to be the main reason why some people have taken issue with the church of Rome on this matter; ·but their quarrel should have been not with •the doctrine of the Eucharist as such but only with •the interpretation of it in terms of ‘real accidents’.· Surely everyone agrees that we ought to prefer opinions that can’t give others any opportunity or pretext for turning away from the true faith—as long as •they aren’t in conflict with any theological or philosophical considerations, and •we are at liberty to make up our own minds. And the supposition of real accidents is inconsistent with theological arguments, as I think I have just shown clearly enough; and it is also completely opposed to philosophical principles, as I hope to demonstrate in the comprehensive philosophical treatise [the Principles of Philosophy] on which I am now working. I’ll show there how colour, taste, heaviness, and all other qualities that stimulate the senses, depend simply on the exterior surface of bodies.

(c) The words of consecration [= ‘the words with which the officiating priest blesses the sacramental bread and wine’] imply, all on their own, that a miracle of transubstantiation is occurring. To bring ‘real accidents’ into the story is to add to that miracle something new and incomprehensible—namely real accidents existing apart from the substance of the bread without themselves becoming substances. As well as being contrary to human reason, this violates the theologians’ •axiom that the words of consecration bring about nothing more than what they signify, and their •preference for not explaining in terms of miracles anything that can be explained by natural reason. All these difficulties disappear when my explanation is adopted; for it removes the need to posit a miracle to explain how accidents can remain once the substance has been removed....

And there is nothing incomprehensible or difficult about supposing that God, the creator of all things, can change one substance into another substance that remains within the surface that contained the former one. Nor can anything be more in accordance with reason or more widely accepted among philosophers than the general statement that

not just all •sense-perception but all •action between bodies occurs through contact, and this contact can take place only at the surface.

This clearly implies that any given surface must always act and react in the same way, even though the substance beneath it is changed.

So if I can speak the truth here without giving offence, I venture to hope that the theory of ‘real accidents’ will some day be •rejected by theologians as irrational, incomprehensible and hazardous for the faith, and be •replaced by my theory which will be regarded as certain and indubitable. I thought I should come right out with this here, so as to do what I could to forestall slanders—I mean the slanders of people who want to seem more learned than others, and are thus never more annoyed than when someone comes up with a new scientific proposal that they can’t pretend they knew about already. It is often the case with these

81

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fourth Objections (Arnauld)

people that the truer and more important they think a ·new· thesis is, the more fiercely they will attack it; and when they can’t refute it by rational argument, they’ll claim without any justification that it is inconsistent with holy scripture and revealed truth. ·Actually·, it is the height of impiety to try to use the Church’s authority in this way to subvert the truth. But I appeal against the verdict of such people to the higher court of pious and orthodox theologians, to whose judgment and correction I most willingly submit myself.

82

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

Fifth Objections (Gassendi) and Descartes’s Replies

Introduction to objections
Sir, Mersenne gave me great pleasure in letting me see your splendid book, the Meditations on First Philosophy. I’m most impressed by your excellent arguments, your sharpness of intellect, and your brilliant style. And I’m happy to congratulate you on the intelligent and successful way in which you have tried to push back the boundaries of the sciences and lay bare things that have been hidden in darkness all through the centuries. Mersenne asked me, as a friend of his, to send you any unresolved doubts about your book, but it has been hard for me to do this. I was afraid that if I didn’t accept your arguments I would simply be showing my lack of intelligence.... Still, I have yielded to my friend, thinking that you will accept and approve of a plan that is more his than mine; and I’m sure that your good nature will make you see that my intention was simply to uncover the reasons for my doubts ·about some of the things you have written·. I’ll be more than satisfied if you have the patience to read through my comments. If they lead you to •have any doubts about your arguments, or •to spend time answering them instead of doing more important things, that won’t be my fault! I’m almost embarrassed to present you with my doubts; I’m sure that each of them has often occurred to you in the course of your meditations, only to be dismissed as negligible or else ignored for some other reason. The comments that I shall make, then, I intend merely as suggestions, not about your conclusions but about your ways of arguing for them. I acknowledge, of course, the existence of almighty God and the immortality of our souls; my reservations are only about the force of the arguments that you employ to prove these and other related metaphysical matters.

Introduction to replies
Distinguished Sir, In criticizing my Meditations you have produced an elegant and careful essay that I think will be of great benefit in shedding light on their truth. I am greatly indebted to you for writing down your objections and to Mersenne for encouraging you to do so. He wants to inquire into everything, and tirelessly supports everything that furthers the glory of God; he knows that the best way to discover whether my arguments deserve to be regarded as valid is to have them examined and vigorously attacked by critics of outstanding learning and intelligence, and to see whether I can reply satisfactorily to all their objections.... What you offer, in fact, are not so much •philosophical arguments to refute my opinions as •oratorical devices for getting around them; but I like that! You have read the arguments contained in the objections of my other critics, and it now seems that there may be no other arguments that could be brought against me; because if there were, your diligence and sharpness of intelligence would have found them. What you are up to, I think, is •to call to my attention the argument-dodging devices that might be used by people whose minds are so immersed in the senses that they shrink from all metaphysical thoughts, and thus •to give me the opportunity to deal with them. In replying to you, therefore, I’ll address you not as the discerning philosopher that you really are, but as one of those men of the flesh whose ideas you have presented. [The significance of ‘men of the flesh’ will emerge on page 88.]

83

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

Objections to the first meditation

There’s very little for me to pause over in the first Meditation, for I approve of your project of freeing your mind from all preconceived opinions. There is just one thing that I don’t understand: why didn’t you didn’t say, simply and briefly, you were regarding your previous knowledge as •uncertain so that you could later single out what you found to be true? Why instead did you treat everything as •false, which seems more like acquiring a new prejudice than relinquishing an old one? ·Proceeding in terms of ‘uncertainty’ rather than ‘falsehood’ would have spared you the need for two dubious moves. Specifically·, it would have spared you the need to imagine a deceiving God or some evil Spirit who tricks us, and enabled you instead simply to point to the darkness of the human mind or the weakness of our nature. And that might have led you away from •pretending that you are asleep and •taking everything that you are confronted with to be an illusion. Can you make yourself believe that you aren’t awake, and make yourself regard as false and uncertain whatever is going on around you? ·One trouble with these two moves of yours is that they won’t convince anybody·. Say what you will, no-one will believe that you have really convinced yourself •that nothing you formerly knew is true, and •that your senses, or sleep, or God, or an evil Spirit, have been deceiving you all along. Wouldn’t it have been more in accord with philosophical openness and the love of truth simply to state the facts candidly and straightforwardly, rather than (as some critics may say) to resort to artifice, sleight of hand and circumlocution? However, this is the route you have chosen, so I’ll let the point drop.

Replies regarding the first meditation
You say that you approve of my project of freeing my mind from preconceived opinions—and indeed no-one could find fault with it. But you would have preferred me to carry it out by saying something ‘simply and briefly’—i.e. in a perfunctory fashion. Is it really so easy to free ourselves from all the errors we have soaked up since our infancy? Is it possible to be too careful in carrying out a project that everyone agrees should be pursued? Presumably you meant only to point out that most people, although verbally admitting that we should escape from preconceived opinions, never actually do so because they don’t •put any effort into it and don’t •count as a preconceived opinion anything that they have once accepted as true. You make a fine job of acting the part of such people here, omitting none of the points that they might raise, and saying nothing that sounds like philosophy. For when you say that there’s no need to imagine that God is a deceiver or that we are dreaming and so on, a philosopher would have thought he should supply a reason why these matters shouldn’t be called into doubt; and if he had no such reason—and in fact none exists—he wouldn’t have made the remark in the first place. Nor would a philosopher have added that in this context it would be sufficient to ‘point to the darkness of the human mind or the weakness of our nature’. We aren’t helped to correct our errors when we are told that we make mistakes because our mind is in darkness or our nature is weak—this is like saying that we make mistakes because we are apt to go wrong! It is obviously more helpful to focus as I did on all the circumstances where we may go wrong, to prevent our rashly giving assent in such cases. Again, a philosopher wouldn’t have said that ‘treating everything as false seems more like acquiring a new prejudice than relinquishing an old one’; or at least he would have first tried to prove that regarding everything as false might create a risk of some deception—·because if it doesn’t do that it shouldn’t count as a ‘prejudice’·. You don’t do that.... A philosopher wouldn’t

84

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

be surprised at such suppositions of falsity, any more than he would be surprised if we tried to straighten out a curved stick by bending it in the opposite direction. ·Of course the proposition that everything I have hitherto believed is false is itself false; but· a philosopher would know that such assumptions of falsehoods often contribute to bringing the truth to light, for example when astronomers imagine the equator, the zodiac, or other circles in the sky, or when geometers add new lines to given figures. Philosophers frequently do the same. Someone who calls this ‘resorting to artifice, sleight of hand and circumlocution’ and says it is unworthy of ‘philosophical openness and the love of truth’ merely reveals himself as wanting to indulge in rhetorical display rather than being philosophically open and wanting to give reasons.
[Gassendi published a book containing his Objections to the Meditations and his answers to Descartes’s Replies. Descartes didn’t think the new material was worth answering; but his friend Clerselier asked some of his friends to read Gassendi’s book and select points that they thought Descartes should attend to. Descartes replied to those in a letter to Clerselier, doing this ‘more in recognition of the work your friends have put in than through any need to defend myself’. These replies concern the first three Meditations; the points Clerselier’s friends raise about Meditations 4–6 have already been answered, Descartes says. Here is what he wrote in answer to the points concerning the first Meditation:]

Your friends note three criticisms made against the first Meditation.

(a) In wanting us to give up every kind of preconceived opinion, they say, I am asking for something impossible. This reflects Gassendi’s failure to understand that the term ‘preconceived opinion’ applies not to all the notions in our mind (I admit we can’t get rid of all those) but only to all the present opinions that are residues of previous judgments that we have made. And because, as I have explained in the appropriate place, it is a voluntary matter whether we judge or not, this is obviously something that is in our power. For, after all, all that’s needed to rid ourselves of every kind of preconceived opinion is a policy of not affirming or denying anything that we have previously affirmed or denied until we have examined it afresh, though still retaining all the same notions in our memory. I did say that there was some difficulty in expelling from our belief system everything we have previously accepted; partly because •we can’t decide to doubt until we have some reason for doubting (which is why in my first Meditation I presented the principal reasons for doubt), and partly because •no matter how strongly we have resolved not to assert or deny anything, we easily forget this unless we have strongly impressed it on our memory (which is why I suggested that we should think about it very carefully).

(b) In thinking we have given up our preconceived opinions, they say, we are in fact adopting other even more harmful preconceptions. This rests on an obviously false assumption. I did say that we should push ourselves to the point of denying the things we had previously affirmed too confidently, but I explicitly stipulated that we should do this only at times when our attention was occupied in looking for something more certain than anything that we could deny in this way. And obviously during those times one couldn’t possibly adopt any preconceptions that might be harmful.

(c) They say that the method of universal doubt that I have proposed can’t help us to discover any truths.This is mere carping. It’s true that doubt doesn’t on its own suffice to establish any truth, but doubt is nevertheless useful in preparing the mind for the establishing of truths later on; and that is all I used it for.

85

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

Objections to the second meditation

(1) Turning to the second Meditation, I see that you still pretend ·to have been deceived about everything·, but you go on to recognize at least that you, the pretender, exist. And you conclude that the proposition I am or I exist is true whenever it comes before you, i.e. is conceived by your mind. But I can’t see that you needed all this apparatus, when you were already rightly certain, on other grounds, that you existed. You could have made the same inference from any one of your other actions, since it is known by the natural light that whatever acts exists.

You add that you don’t yet have much understanding of what you are. Here I seriously agree with you; I accept this, which is the starting-point for the hard work. But it seems to me that you could have raised this question—‘·What am I?·’—without all the circumlocutions and elaborate suppositions.

Next, you set yourself to meditate on what you formerly believed yourself to be, so as to remove the doubtful elements and be left with only what is ‘certain and unshakable’. Everyone will be with you in this: you are now getting to grips with the problem. You used to believe you were a man; and now you ask ‘What is a man?’ You carefully dismiss the common definitions and concentrate on ‘the first thought that came to mind’, namely that you had a face and hands and the other limbs making up what you called the body; followed by the thought that you were nourished, that you moved about, and that you engaged in sense-perception and thinking—actions that you attributed to the soul. Fair enough—provided we don’t forget your distinction between the soul and the body. You say that you didn’t know what the soul was, but imagined it to be merely ‘something like a wind or fire or ether’ permeating the more solid parts of your body. That is worth remembering. As for the body, you had no doubt that its nature consists in its being ‘capable of taking on shape and having boundaries and filling a space so as to exclude any other body from it, and in its being perceived by touch, sight, hearing, smell and taste and being moved in various ways’. But you can still attribute these things to bodies even now, though not attributing all of them to every body: wind isn’t perceived by sight, but it is a body. And some of the other attributes that you mention as seemingly not possessed by bodies are possessed by some of them: wind and fire can move many things. When you go on to say that you used to deny that bodies have the ‘power of self-movement’, it’s not clear how you can still maintain this. For it would imply that every body must by its nature be immobile, that all its movements have some non-bodily source, and that we can’t suppose that water flows or an animal moves unless it has some non-bodily power of movement.

Reply
(1) You are still •using rhetorical tricks instead of •reasoning. You make up fictions about me:

•that I am pretending, when in fact I am serious, and •that I am asserting things, when in fact I am merely raising questions or putting forward commonly held views in order to inquire into them further.

When I said that the entire testimony of the senses should be regarded as uncertain and even as false, I was entirely serious. This point is essential for a grasp of my Meditations—so much so that anyone who won’t or can’t accept it won’t be able to come up with any objections that deserve a reply. Don’t forget, though, the distinction that I insisted on in several of my passages, between •getting on with everyday life and •investigating the truth. For when we are making

86

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

practical plans it would of course be foolish not to trust the senses; the sceptics who paid so little heed to human affairs that their friends had to stop them falling off precipices deserved to be laughed at. That’s why I pointed out in one place that no sane person ever seriously doubts such things. But when we are investigating what can be known with complete certainty by the human intellect, if we are to be reasonable we must seriously reject these things as doubtful and even as false; the purpose here is to come to recognize that certain other things are in reality better known to us because they can’t be rejected in this way.

You don’t accept as having been made seriously and in good faith my statement that I didn’t yet properly grasp what this ‘I’ who thinks is, but I did provide a full explanation of the statement ·which showed that it was meant seriously·. You also question my statements that •I had no doubts about what the nature of the body consisted in, that •I didn’t credit it with any power of self-movement, and that •I imagined the soul to be like a wind or fire, and so on; but these were simply commonly held views that I was bringing forward so as to show in the appropriate place that they were false.

It’s hardly honest to say that I refer nutrition, motion, sensation, etc. to the soul, and then immediately to add ‘Fair enough, provided we don’t forget your distinction between the soul and the body’. For just after that I explicitly assigned nutrition to the body alone; and as for movement and sensation, I assign them mostly to the body, attributing to the soul only the element of thought ·involved in my being conscious that I walk, or that I sense·.

What is your reason for saying that I ‘didn’t need all this apparatus’ to prove that I existed? This remark of yours gives me a strong reason to think that I haven’t used enough ‘apparatus’, since I haven’t yet managed to make you understand the matter correctly. You say that I could have made the same inference from any one of my other actions, but that is far from the truth, because my thought is the only one of my actions of which I am completely certain—I’m talking here about metaphysical certainty, because that’s what this is all about. For example, I can’t say ’I am walking, therefore I exist’, except by adding to •my walking •my awareness of walking, which is a thought. The inference is certain—·meaning that it makes the conclusion certain·—only if its premise concerns this awareness, and not the movement of my body; because it can happen, e.g. in dreams, that I seem to myself to be walking but am really not doing so. And so from the fact that I think I am walking I can very well infer the existence of a mind that •thinks but not the existence of a body that •walks. And the same holds for all the other cases.

Objection
(2) You go on to ask whether, given that you are being deceived, you can still attribute to •yourself any of the properties that you believed to belong to the nature of •body; and after a careful examination you say that you can’t find in yourself any such attributes. But at that stage you’re already regarding yourself not as a whole man but as an inner or hidden part of one—the kind of component you previously thought the soul to be. So I ask you, Soul (or whatever name you want to go by!), have you at this stage corrected your earlier thought that you were like a wind diffused through the parts of the body? Certainly not! So why isn’t it possible that you are a wind, or rather a very thin vapour....diffused through the parts of the body and giving them life? Mightn’t it be this vapour that sees with the eyes, hears with the ears, thinks with the brain, and does all the other things that would ordinarily be said to be done by you? And if that is so, why shouldn’t you have the same shape as your whole body

87

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

has, just as the air has the same shape as the vessel that contains it? Why shouldn’t you think that you are enclosed within •whatever it is that encloses your body, or within •your body’s skin? Why shouldn’t you occupy space—the parts of space that the solid body or its parts don’t fill? I mean that you may be diffused through pores in the solid body, so that no region that is entirely filled by a part of you contains also a part of your body; just as in a mixture of wine and water the ·very small· parts of the wine aren’t to be found where parts of the water are, although we can’t see them as separated from one another. Again, why should you not be able to exclude any other body from the space which you occupy, given that the spaces you occupy can’t be occupied at the same time by the parts of the more solid body? Why shouldn’t you be in motion in many different ways? You move many parts of your body, and you couldn’t do that without being in motion yourself, could you?.... If all this is so, why do you say that you have within you ‘none of the attributes that belong to the nature of body’?

Reply
(2) You adopt an amusing figure of speech in which you address me not as a whole man but as an unembodied soul. I think you mean to tell me that these objections came not from the mind of a subtle philosopher but from flesh alone. I ask you then, Flesh (or whatever name you want to go by!), are you so out of touch with the mind that you couldn’t take it in when I corrected the common view that what thinks is like a wind or similar body? I certainly corrected this view when I showed that I can •suppose that there are no bodies—and thus no wind—while still •retaining everything that lets me recognize myself as a thinking thing. So your questions about whether I might be a wind, or occupy space, or move, are so fatuous as to need no reply.

Objection
(3) Moving on, you say that of the attributes ascribed to the soul, neither nutrition nor movement are to be found in you. But ·that doesn’t prove that you aren’t a body, because· something can be a body without receiving nutrition. Also, if you are a body of the ·extremely rarefied· kind we call ‘spirit’ [see note on page 58], then given that your limbs ·and large organs·, being more solid, are nourished by a more solid substance, why shouldn’t you, being more rarefied, be nourished by a more rarefied substance? [‘Rarefied’ means ‘extremely finely divided’; a rarefied body is a gas. The kind that constitutes the ‘animal spirits’ in our bodies was thought to be even more rarefied—even more gaseous—than any of the gases we are familiar with, such as the air of our atmosphere.] Moreover, when the body that these limbs are part of is growing, aren’t you growing too? And when the body is weak, aren’t you weak too? As for movement: what causes your limbs to move is you; they never adopt any posture unless you make them do so; and how can this happen unless you also move? You say ‘Since I don’t have a body, these are mere inventions’, ·but what is the status of ‘Since I don’t have a body’?· If you are fooling us, or are yourself befooled, there’s nothing more to say. But if you are speaking seriously, you ought to prove that •you don’t have a body that you inform, and that •you aren’t the kind of thing that is nourished and that moves. [In this occurrence, ‘a body that you inform’ means ‘a body of which you are the soul or mind’. This use of ‘inform’ comes from the scholastics, who were partly following Aristotle’s doctrine that the soul is ‘the form of’ the body’.]

You go on to say that you don’t have sense-perception. But surely it is you who see colours, hear sounds, and so on. ‘This’, you say, ‘doesn’t happen unless there is a body ·at work·.’ I agree. But ·what right have you to assume that there isn’t a body at work?· For one thing, you have a body, and you yourself are present within the eye, which obviously

88

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

doesn’t see unless you are at work. Also, you could be a rarefied body operating by means of the sense organs. You say: ‘In my dreams I have appeared to perceive through the senses many things that I realized later I hadn’t perceived through the senses at all.’ Admittedly, it can happen that you are deceived in this way: seeming, at a time when your eyes are not in use, to have sense-perception of something that couldn’t be really perceived without using eyes. But this kind of falsity isn’t a common occurrence in your life; you have normally used your eyes to see and to take in images—ones that you can now have without the eyes being at work.

Finally you reach the conclusion that you think. No question about that; but it remains for you to prove that the power of thought is so far beyond the nature of a body that neither a spirit nor any other mobile, pure and rarefied body can be organized in such a way as to be capable of thought. Along with that you’ll have to prove that the souls of the brutes are incorporeal, because they think too—i.e. they’re aware of something internal, over and above the doings of the external senses, not only when they are awake but also when dreaming. You’ll also have to prove that this solid body of yours contributes nothing whatever to your thought (·which may be hard to prove·, given that you have never not had this body, and ·therefore· have never had any thoughts when separated from it). You will thus have to prove that you think independently of the body, so that you can never be hampered by it or disturbed by the nasty thick fumes that occasionally have a bad effect on the brain.

Reply
(3) If I’m a rarefied body, why can’t I be nourished etc.? This question doesn’t put me under pressure any more than the preceding ones did, because I deny that I am a body. I’ll say this just once:

You nearly always use the same style, not attacking my arguments but ignoring them as if they didn’t exist, or quoting them inaccurately or in a truncated form; and you round up various ‘difficulties’ of the sort philosophical novices raise against my conclusions or against others like them—or even unlike them! Each of these ‘difficulties’ either •is irrelevant or •has been discussed and resolved by me in the appropriate place. So it’s simply not worth my while to answer all your questions individually; doing so would involve me in repeating myself a hundred times.

I’ll just deal briefly with the points that might possibly cause difficulty to readers who aren’t utterly stupid. Perhaps some readers are impressed more by •how many words are used than by •the force of the arguments; but I don’t care so much about their approval that I am prepared to become more verbose in order to earn it!

First point: I don’t accept your statement that the mind grows and becomes weak along with the body. You don’t support this by any argument. It’s true that the mind works less perfectly in the body of an infant than in an adult’s body, and that its actions can often be slowed down by wine and other corporeal things. But all that follows from this is that the mind, so long as it is joined to the body, uses it like an instrument to perform the operations that take up most of its time. It doesn’t follow that the mind is made more or less perfect by the body. That inference of yours is on a par with this: •A craftsman works badly whenever he uses a faulty tool; therefore •The source of a craftsman’s knowledge of his craft is the good condition of his tools.

I have to say, Flesh, that you seem to have no idea of what is involved in arguing rationally. You say that although it •has sometimes happened that when my eyes were not

89

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

in use I seemed to have sense-perception of things that actually can’t be perceived without the eye, this kind of falsity hasn’t happened to me •all the time, and therefore I shouldn’t suspect the trustworthiness of the senses. As though discovering error on some occasions isn’t a sufficient reason for doubt! You also imply that whenever we make a mistake we can discover that we have done so; whereas really the error consists precisely in our not recognizing it as a case of error.

Finally, Flesh—you who often demand arguments from me when you don’t have any and the onus of proof is on you—you should realize that good philosophical method doesn’t make this requirement of us:

•When you refuse to admit something because you don’t know whether it is true, you should prove it to be false.

What is required is this:

•When you admit something as true, you should prove it to be true.

Thus, when I recognize that I am a thinking substance, and form a vivid and clear thinking-substance concept that doesn’t contain any of the things relating to the concept of bodily substance, that’s all I need to be entitled to assert that so far as I know myself I am nothing but a thinking thing. And that is all that I asserted in the second Meditation, which is our present concern. I didn’t have to admit that this thinking substance was some mobile, pure and rarefied body, because I had no convincing reason for thinking it was. If you have such a reason, teach it to us! and don’t require me to prove the falsity of something that I refused to accept precisely because I didn’t know whether it was true or false.... When you add that I’ll also have to prove that ‘the souls of the brutes are incorporeal’ and that ‘this solid body contributes nothing to my thought’, you show that you don’t know where the onus of proof lies, i.e. what must be proved by each party ·to the dispute·. I don’t think that the souls of the brutes are incorporeal, or that this solid body contributes nothing to our thought; but this isn’t the place to go into all that.

Objection
(4) You conclude: ‘Strictly speaking, then, I am simply a thing that thinks—a mind, or soul, or intellect, or reason.’ Oh, I now learn that I have been dreaming! I thought I was addressing a human soul, the internal generator by which a man lives, has sensations, moves around and understands; and now I find that I have been addressing nothing but a mind, which has divested itself not just of the body but also of the very soul.
[In the early modern period, the

Latin anima = French âme = English ‘soul’

was often used to mean about the same as the

Latin mens = French esprit = English ‘mind’.

But Gassendi is here using anima = ‘soul’ differently, harking back to the scholastics and to Aristotle. They understood the anima to be the animater, the life-giver, the source of an organism’s vital processes, so that it made sense for them to speak of the anima of a plant—its ‘vegetative soul’, as the English translators put it.]
Are you going along with the ancients who believed that the soul is diffused through the whole body, but thought that its principal part—its ‘controlling element’ [he gives it in Greek]—was located in a particular part of the body, such as the brain or the heart? Of course they thought that the •soul was also to be found in this part, but they held that the •mind was, as it were, added to and united with the soul that existed there, and joined with the soul in informing [see note on page 88] this part of the body. I ought to have remembered this from the discussion in your Discourse on the Method, where you seemed to hold that all the functions that are ·customarily· assigned to the vegetative and sensitive soul

90

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

don’t depend on the rational soul but can be exercised before the rational soul arrives in the body, as is the case with the brutes who according to you don’t have reason. I don’t know how I came to forget this, unless it was because I still wasn’t sure that you preferred not to apply the word ‘soul’ to the source of the vegetative and sensory functions in both us and the brutes, and wanted instead to say that the ‘soul’ in the strict sense is our mind. But it’s the vegetative and sensitive source—·the anima = ‘soul’ in my sense·—that is properly speaking said to ‘animate’ us; so all that is left for the mind to do is to enable us to think—which is what you do in fact assert. So ·I’ll set ‘soul’ aside, and· proceed with the term ‘mind’, understood to be strictly a thinking thing.

You add that thought is the only thing that can’t be separated from you. There is certainly no reason to disagree, especially if you are only a mind, and don’t allow that your substance is distinct from the substance of the soul in any way except conceptually. But I want to stop here, ·not to disagree, but· to ask whether in saying that thought can’t be separated from you, you mean that you will think continuously for as long as you exist. This squares with the claims of the famous philosophers who, in arguing that we are immortal, help themselves to the premise that we are perpetually thinking (which I interpret as meaning that we are perpetually in motion!). But it will hardly convince those who don’t see how anyone could think during deep sleep—or in the womb, for that matter. And here I pause with another question: Do you think that you were infused into the body, or into one of its parts, while still in the womb? or at birth? But I shan’t press this point too insistently, asking whether you remember what you thought about in the womb or in the first few days or months or even years after you were born. If you ·do address that question, and· answer that you have forgotten, I shan’t ask why. But I suggest that you bear in mind how obscure, meagre and virtually non-existent your thought must have been during those early periods of your life.

You go on to say that you are not ‘that structure of limbs and organs that is called a human body’. No question about that, because you are considering yourself solely as a thinking thing and as a part of the whole composite that is a human being—a part that is distinct from the external and more solid part. You go on: ‘Nor am I a thin vapour that permeates the limbs—a wind, fire, air, breath, or whatever I imagine; for I have supposed all these things to be nothing. But even if I go on supposing these to be nothing...’—stop right there, Mind! Don’t go on making those ‘suppositions’ (really, those fictions); rather, get rid of them. You say: ‘I’m not a vapour or anything of that kind.’ But if the entire soul is something of this kind, why shouldn’t you....be regarded as the most refined and pure and active part of the soul, ·and thus as being ‘of that kind’, after all?· You say: ‘These things that I am supposing to be nothing—mightn’t they in fact be identical with the I of which I am aware? I don’t know; and just now I shan’t discuss the matter.’ But if you ‘don’t know’, if you aren’t discussing the matter, why do you assume that you are none of these things? You say: ‘I know I exist; this knowledge can’t depend on things of whose existence I am still unaware.’ Fair enough; but remember that you haven’t yet made certain that you are not air or a vapour or something else of this sort.

Reply
(4) This next question of yours calls attention to the troubling ambiguity of the word ‘soul’. But I dealt with this ambiguity in the proper place, doing it so precisely that I just can’t face saying it all over again here. I’ll just say this: because words are usually given their meanings by ignorant people,

91

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

•words don’t always have a good fit with •things. It’s not for us to change meanings that have become current in ordinary usage; but it is all right for us to emend a meaning when we see it creating misunderstandings. Thus, those who first gave ‘soul’ its meaning probably didn’t distinguish between two sources ·of energy or activity· that are in us:

•the one by which we are nourished and grow and unthinkingly perform all the other actions that we have in common with the brutes,

and

•the one by virtue of which we think.

So they used the one word ‘soul’ to name both; and when it came into their minds that thought is distinct from nutrition, they called the thinking element ‘mind’, and took it to be the principal part of the soul. Whereas I, realizing that what leads to our being nourished is radically different from what leads to our thinking, have said that when the word ‘soul’ is used to name to both of these sources it is ambiguous. If we want to take ‘soul’ in its special sense, as meaning—·to put it in scholastic terms·—the ‘first actuality’ or ‘principal form of man’, then it must be understood to apply only to the source in us of our thinking; and to avoid ambiguity I have generally used the term ‘mind’ for this. For the mind, as I understand it, isn’t a part of the soul; it is the whole thinking soul.

You say you want to stop and ask whether I’m wedded to the view that the soul always thinks. Why shouldn’t it always think, given that is a thinking substance? It’s not surprising that we don’t remember the thoughts the soul had when in the womb or in a deep sleep, because there are many other thoughts that we also don’t remember, although we know we had them as healthy, wide-awake adults. While the mind is joined to the body, its only way of remembering its past thoughts is by applying itself to traces of those thoughts imprinted on the brain. So wouldn’t we expect that the brain of an infant, or of a man fast asleep, is not in a good state for receiving these traces?

Lastly, there is the passage where I said that perhaps that of which I don’t yet have knowledge (namely my body) is not distinct from the ‘I’ of which I do have knowledge (namely my mind). ‘I don’t know; and just now I shan’t discuss the matter.’ Here you object: ‘If you don’t know, if you aren’t discussing the matter, why do you assume that you are none of these things?’ But it’s not true that I ‘assumed’ something that I didn’t know. Quite the contrary: because I didn’t know whether the body was identical with the mind, I made no assumptions about this, and attended only to the mind; then later on, in the sixth Meditation, I demonstrated—I didn’t assume!—that the mind is really distinct from the body. In this area it is you, Flesh, who are seriously at fault, because you assume that the mind is not distinct from the body, while having little or no rational basis for saying so.

Objection
(5) You next describe the thing you call the ‘imagination’. You say that ‘imagining is simply contemplating the shape or image of a bodily thing’; and you want to infer from this that what enables you to know your own nature is something other than your imagination. But since you are allowed to define ‘imagination’ as you like, then if you are a body—and you haven’t yet proved that you aren’t—why can’t your contemplation of yourself involve some bodily form or image? And when you contemplate yourself, do you find that anything comes to mind except some pure, transparent, rarefied substance like a wind, pervading the whole body or at least the brain or some part of it, and from that location animating you and performing all your functions. ‘I realize’, you say, ‘that none of the things that the imagination enables

92

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

me to grasp has any relevance to this knowledge I have of myself.’ But you don’t say how you ‘realize’ this. A little way back you decided that you didn’t yet know whether these things belonged to you; so how do you now arrive at the conclusion just quoted?

Reply
(5) What I wrote about the imagination will be clear enough to those who study it closely, but it isn’t surprising if those who don’t meditate on it find it very obscure. But I should point out to such people that my assertion that •certain things don’t belong to my knowledge of myself is consistent with my previous statement that •I didn’t know whether certain things belong to me or not. For ‘belonging to me’ is clearly quite different from ‘belonging to my knowledge of myself’.

Objection
(6) You say next that ‘the mind must be carefully diverted from such things if it is to perceive its own nature as distinctly as possible’. Good advice. But after you have carefully diverted yourself from these things, how distinctly have you managed to perceive your nature? In saying that you are simply ‘a thing that thinks’, you mention an •activity that we were all already aware of; but you tell us nothing about the •substance that performs this activity—what sort of substance it is, how it holds together, how it organizes itself to perform so many functions of such different kinds, and other matters of this sort that we haven’t known until now.

You say that we can perceive by the intellect what we can’t perceive by the imagination (and you identify the imagination with the ‘common sense’). [The ‘common sense’ was a supposed faculty, postulated by Aristotle, whose role was to integrate the data from the five specialized senses.] But, my good Mind, can you show that there are several internal faculties and not one simple all-purpose one that enables us to know whatever we know? When I •see the sun with open eyes, •sense-perception occurs, obviously. And when later on I •think about the sun with my eyes closed, •internal cognition occurs also, obviously. But how can I tell that I am perceiving the sun with my •‘common sense’ or faculty of imagination, rather than with my •mind or intellect that can choose sometimes to take in the sun imaginatively (which is different from taking it in intellectually) and sometimes to take it in intellectually (which isn’t the same as taking it in imaginatively)? If brain damage or some injury to the imaginative faculty left the intellect untouched, still properly performing its particular functions, then we could say that the intellect was as distinct from the imagination as the imagination is from the external senses. But because that isn’t what happens, there is surely no easy way of establishing the distinction.

You say that imagination occurs when we contemplate the image of some bodily thing, which surely implies that our knowledge of bodies must come from the imagination alone—or at any rate that no other way of knowing them can be recognized. That’s because all our knowledge of bodies comes from contemplating images of them.

You say that you can’t help thinking that the bodily things that you form images of in your thought, and that the senses investigate, are known with much more distinctness than ‘this puzzling “I” that can’t be pictured in the imagination’; which yields the surprising result that you have a more distinct knowledge and grasp of things that are doubtful and foreign to you! First comment: You are quite right in using the phrase ‘this puzzling “I”’. For you really don’t know what you are, or what your nature is, so you can’t be any more confident that your nature is such that you can’t be grasped through the imagination. Second comment: All our knowledge appears to have its source in our senses. The

93

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

maxim

•Whatever is in the intellect must previously have existed in the senses

seems to be true, although you deny it. For unless our knowledge enters in a single swoop, it is slowly established by analogy, composition, division, extrapolation and restriction, and in other similar ways that I needn’t list here. So it is no surprise if the things that rush in of their own accord and strike the senses should make a more vivid impression on the soul than things that the soul constructs and compounds for itself (when the occasion arises) out of the material that impinges on the senses. Another point: you call bodily things ‘doubtful’, but—own up!—you are just as certain of the existence of the body you inhabit and of all the objects in your environment as you are of your own existence. Also: if what makes you manifest to yourself is the activity called ‘thought’ and nothing else, what about how other things are manifested? They are made manifest not just by various activities but also by various qualities—size, shape, solidity, colour, taste, etc.—so that although they exist outside you, it’s to be expected that your knowledge and grasp of them should be more distinct than your knowledge and grasp of yourself. How could you understand something outside you better than you understand yourself? Well, the same thing happens in the case of the eye, which sees other things but doesn’t see itself.

Reply
(6) The things you say here, my dear Flesh, seem to me to amount to grumblings more than objections. There’s nothing here that needs an answer.

Objection
(7) ‘Well, then, what am I?’ you ask. ‘A thing that thinks. What is that? A thing that doubts, understands, affirms, denies, wants, refuses, and also imagines and senses.’ That’s a long list, but I won’t query each individual item. My only question concerns your statement that you are a thing that senses. This is surprising, because you earlier maintained the opposite. Or ·when you wrote ‘I am a thing that senses’· did you perhaps mean this?–

In addition to •yourself there is a •bodily faculty lodged in the eyes, ears and other organs—a faculty that receives the images of sensible things and thus •starts the act of sense-perception which you then •complete, so that it’s you who really sees and hears and has the other sensory perceptions.

I think that’s what leads you to class both sense-perception and imagination as kinds of thought. Fair enough; but then you should consider whether sense-perception in the brutes shouldn’t also be called ‘thought’, since it is quite like your own. If it does count as ‘thought’, that means that the brutes have minds quite like yours.

·I can think of nine things you might say to distinguish yourself from the brutes; I’ll go through them—labelled (a) through (i)—one by one·. (a) You may say that you occupy the citadel in the brain and receive there whatever messages are transmitted by the animal spirits that move through the nerves; so that sense-perception occurs there where you are, though it is said to occur throughout the body. So be it, ·but that doesn’t distinguish you from the brutes, because· they too have nerves, animal spirits and a brain, and their brain contains a cognition-generator that receives messages from the spirits (just as yours does) and thus completes the act of sense-perception.

(b) You may say that this generator in the brains of animals is merely the corporeal imagination or faculty for forming images. But in that case you must show that you, who reside in the brain, are something different from the

94

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

corporeal imagination or the human faculty for forming images. I asked you a little while ago for a criterion proving that you are something different, but I don’t think you’ll provide one.

(c) You may cite ·human· operations that far surpass what the animals do; but that shows only that man is the finest animal, not that he isn’t an animal. Similarly, though you show yourself to be the finest of imaginative faculties, you still count as one of them. Give yourself the special label ‘mind’ if you like, but your having this grander name doesn’t mean that your nature is different, ·i.e. that you are radically different·. To prove that—i.e. to prove that you are not a body—you need to do something quite different in kind from anything the brutes do—something that takes place outside the brain or at least independently of it. That’s what you need to do, and you don’t do it, ·apparently because no such thing exists in the human behavioural repertoire·. On the contrary, •when the brain is disturbed you are disturbed, •when the brain is overwhelmed you are overwhelmed, and •when images of things are erased from the brain you don’t retain any trace of them.

(d) You may say that whatever occurs in animals happens through blind impulses of the animal spirits and the other organs, just as motion is produced in a clock. This may be true for ·animal· functions like nutrition and the pulsing of blood, which occur in just the same way in the case of man. But can you cite any sensory events—any so-called ‘passions of the soul’—that are produced by a blind impulse in brutes but not in us? ·Here is how it goes in brutes·:

•A scrap of food transmits its image into the eye of a dog; •the image is carried to the brain, where •it hooks onto the soul (so to speak), with the result that •the soul and the entire body joined to it is drawn towards the food as if by tiny, delicate chains.

Similarly if you throw a stone at a dog: the stone transmits its image and, like a lever, pushes the soul away and thereby drives off the body, i.e. makes it flee. But doesn’t all this occur in the case of man? Perhaps you have in mind some quite different process in a man ·who ducks away from a missile·; if you have, I would be so grateful if you would explain it.

(e) You may say that ·you are radically different from the brutes in that· you are free, and have the power to prevent yourself from running away and ·the power to prevent yourself· from charging forward. But the cognition-generator in an animal does just the same: a dog, despite its fear of threats and blows may rush forward to snap up a bit of food it has seen—just like a man! You may say that a dog barks simply •from impulse, whereas a man speaks •from choice. But there are causes at work in the man too—ones that we might describe by saying that he ·also· speaks from some impulse. What you attribute to choice occurs as a result of a stronger impulse, and indeed the brute also chooses, when one impulse is greater than another. [He gives an anecdotal example. Then:]

(f) You say that the brutes don’t have reason. Well, of course they don’t have •human reason, but they do have •their own kind of reason. So it doesn’t seem right to call them ‘non-rational’ except in contrast with us or with our kind of reason; and anyway reason seems to be something general that can be attributed to animals just as well as can the cognitive faculty or internal sense.

(g) You may say that animals don’t engage in reasoning. But although they don’t reason as perfectly or about as many subjects as man does, they do still reason, and the difference ·between their reasoning and ours· seems to be merely one of degree.

(h) You may say they don’t speak. Well, of course, not

95

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

being human beings they don’t produce human speech, but they still produce their own form of speech, which serves them just as our speech serves us.

(i) You may say that even a delirious man can still string words together to express his meaning, which even the wisest of the brutes cannot do. But it’s not fair •to expect the brutes to use human language and •turn one’s back on the kind of language that they do have. But to go into this would need a much longer discussion.

Reply
(7) Here again you produce a lot of grumblings, which don’t need a reply any more than the previous lot did. Your questions about the brutes are out of place in this context because the mind, when engaged in private meditation, can experience its own thinking but can’t have any experience to settle whether or not the brutes think. It must tackle that question later on, by an empirical investigation of their behaviour. I won’t take time off to disown the ·nine· foolish claims that you put into my mouth; I’ll settle for merely pointing out that you don’t accurately report everything I say. ·Despite what you allege·, I did provide—indeed I often provided!—a criterion to establish that the mind is different from the body, namely that the whole nature of the mind consists in its thinking, while the whole nature of the body consists in its being an extended thing; and there is absolutely nothing in common between thought and extension. I also showed clearly—and often!—that the mind can operate independently of the brain; for the brain can’t have any role in pure understanding, but only in imagining or perceiving by the senses. Admittedly, when imagination or sensation is strongly active (as happens when the brain is in a disturbed state), it’s hard for the mind to have leisure for understanding other things. But when the imagination is less intense, we often have thoughts that have nothing to do with it. For example, when we are asleep and are aware that we are dreaming: we need imagination in order to dream, but only the intellect will tell us that that’s what we are doing.

Objection
(8) Next you introduce the example of the wax, and you explain at length that the so-called •accidents of the wax [= ‘qualities of the wax’] are one thing, and the wax itself—the •substance of the wax—is another. You say that only the mind or intellect can give us a distinct perception of the wax itself or its substance, and that sensation and imagination don’t come into it. First comment: This is just what everyone commonly asserts, namely that we can abstract the concept of the wax or its substance from the concepts of its accidents. But does that imply that the substance or nature of the wax is itself distinctly conceived? We conceive that besides the colour, shape, meltability etc. of the wax there’s something that is the subject of the accidents and changes we observe; but we don’t know what this subject is, what its nature is. This always eludes us; and our view that there is something underneath the accidents is only a sort of guess. So I’m surprised at your saying that when the forms ·or accidents· have been stripped off like clothes, you perceive more perfectly and evidently what the wax is. Admittedly, you perceive •that the wax or its substance must be something over and above such forms; but if we are to believe you, you don’t perceive •what this something is. For what is happening here is nothing like seeing the clothes that a man is wearing and then stripping them off so as to see who and what he is! Second comment: When you think you somehow perceive this underlying ‘something’, I’d like to know what you perceive it as. Don’t you perceive it as spread out and extended? (·Presumably you do, because· you don’t

96

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

conceive of it as a point, yet it is the kind of thing that expands and contracts.) And since its extension isn’t infinite, but has limits, don’t you conceive of it as having some kind of shape? And when you seem to as-it-were-see it, don’t you attach to it some confused sort of colour? You certainly take it to be something more solid, and so more visible, than a mere vacuum. Thus, even your ‘understanding’ turns out to be some sort of imagining. And if you say that you conceive of the wax apart from any extension, shape or colour, then tell us openly what sort of conception you do have of it.

What you have to say about ‘men whom we see, or perceive with the mind, when we make out only their hats or cloaks’ doesn’t show that judgments are made by the mind rather than by the imagination. You deny that a dog has a mind like yours, but it certainly makes a similar kind of judgment when it sees not its master but simply the hat or clothes ·that he is wearing·. [Gassendi develops this point in more detail and with another example. Then:] When you go on to say that the perception of colour and hardness and so on is ‘not vision or touch but is purely a scrutiny by the mind alone’, I agree, as long as •the mind is not something different from •the imaginative faculty. You add that this scrutiny can be imperfect and confused or vivid and clear, depending on how carefully we concentrate on what the wax consists in. But that doesn’t show that the scrutiny made by the mind, when it examines this mysterious ‘something or other’ that exists over and above all the forms ·or qualities·, constitutes vivid and clear knowledge of the wax. What it really consists in is a scrutiny by the senses of all the possible accidents and changes that the wax can undergo. From these we can certainly arrive at a conception and explanation of what we mean by the term ‘wax’; but the alleged naked substance—better, hidden substance—is something we can’t conceive for ourselves or explain to others.

Reply
(8) Here, as often elsewhere, all you show is that you don’t have a proper grasp of what you are trying to criticize. I didn’t abstract the concept of the wax from the concept of its accidents. Rather, I wanted to show how the substance of the wax is revealed by means of its accidents, and how a reflective and distinct perception of it (the sort of perception, Flesh, that you seem never to have had!) differs from the ordinary confused perception. I don’t see what argument you are relying on when you so confidently say that a dog makes discriminating judgments in the same way that we do, unless it is this: A dog is made of flesh, so everything that is in you also exists in the dog. But I observe no mind at all in the dog, so I don’t think there is anything to be found in a dog that resembles the things I recognize in a mind.

Objection
(9) You now go on as follows:

But what am I to say about this mind, or about myself? (So far, remember, I don’t admit that there is anything to me except a mind.) What, I ask, is this ‘I’ that seems to perceive the wax so clearly? Surely, I am aware of my own self in a truer and more certain way than I am of the wax, and also in a much more distinct and evident way. What leads me to think that the wax exists—namely, that I see it—leads much more obviously to the conclusion that I exist. What I see might not really be the wax; perhaps I don’t even have eyes with which to see anything. But when I see or think I see (I am not here distinguishing the two), it is simply not possible that I who am now thinking am not something. Similarly, that I exist follows from the other bases for judging that the wax exists—that I touch it, that I imagine it, or any other basis, and

97

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

similarly for my bases for judging that anything else exists outside me.

I quote all this so that you’ll realize that it demonstrates that you do indeed distinctly know that you exist because you distinctly see and know that the wax and its accidents exist, but not that you know (distinctly or indistinctly!) what you are, what kind of thing you are. That would have been worth proving, whereas your existence ·wasn’t worth proving because it· was never in doubt. But I shan’t press this point, any more than I did my earlier point that although you aren’t at this stage admitting that you have anything except a mind—and therefore are excluding eyes, hands and other bodily organs—you nevertheless speak of the wax and its accidents that you see and touch etc. But to see or touch these things (or, as you put it, to think that you see and touch them) without eyes or hands is obviously impossible.

You proceed as follows:

As I came to perceive the wax more distinctly by applying not just sight and touch but other considerations, all this too contributed to my knowing myself even more distinctly, because whatever goes into my perception of the wax or of any other body must do even more to establish the nature of my own mind.

No. All that you establish through your conclusions about the wax is that you perceive •the existence of your mind and not its •nature, and your other considerations won’t take you any further than that. If you want to infer anything more from your perception of the substance of the wax, you’ll have to settle for this:

Our conception of this substance is merely a confused perception of something unknown; therefore our conception of the mind is also a confused perception of something unknown.

You may well repeat your earlier phrase ‘this puzzling “I”’.

Now for your conclusion:

See! With no effort I have reached the place where I wanted to be! I now know that even bodies are perceived not by the senses or by imagination but by the intellect alone, not through their being touched or seen but through their being understood; and this helps me to know plainly that I can perceive my own mind more easily and clearly than I can anything else.

That’s what you claim; but I don’t see how you can deduce or ‘know plainly’ that anything can be perceived regarding your mind except that it exists. I can’t see that you have done what you promised in the heading of this Meditation, namely to establish that ‘the human mind is better known than the body’. You weren’t aiming to prove •that the human mind exists, or •that its existence is better known than the body’s existence, because the existence of the human mind is something that no-one questions. What you were setting out to do, surely, was to establish that the mind’s nature is better known than the body’s; and you haven’t succeeded in that. As regards the nature of the body, you have listed all the things we know: extension, shape, occupying space, and so on. But after all your efforts, Mind, what have you told us about yourself? You aren’t a bodily structure, you aren’t air, or a wind, or a thing that walks or senses, you aren’t this and you aren’t that! Even if we grant all these (though you yourself rejected some of them), they aren’t what we were led to expect. They are simply negative results; but the question is not what you aren’t but what you are. And so you refer us to your principal result, that you are a thing that thinks—i.e. a thing that doubts, affirms etc. First point about this: Saying that you are a ‘thing’ isn’t giving us any information. ‘Thing’ is a general, imprecise and vague word that doesn’t apply to you any more than it does to anything in the world that isn’t a mere nothing. You are a ‘thing’—i.e.

98

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

you aren’t nothing, i.e. you are something. But a stone is something and not nothing, and so is a fly, and so is everything else! Next point: When you go on to say that you are a thinking thing, then we know something—·what you say has real content·—but we knew it already! We weren’t looking to you for that. Who doubts that you are thinking? What we didn’t have, and were looking to you for, was knowledge about that inner substance of yours whose defining property is to think,....about what sort of thing this ‘you’ who thinks really is. If we ask about wine, wanting to know more about it than what is common knowledge, we won’t settle for your telling us that ‘wine is a liquid thing, squeezed from grapes, white or red, sweet, intoxicating’ and so on. You will have to launch an investigation of the internal substance of wine, letting us see how it is manufactured from spirits, tartar, the distillate, and other ingredients mixed together in such and such quantities and proportions. Well, similarly, if you want to give us knowledge of yourself that goes beyond common knowledge (i.e. the kind of knowledge we have had until now), you must see that it won’t do for you to announce that you are a thing that thinks and doubts and understands etc. If you are to succeed in uncovering your internal substance and explaining it to us, you’ll have to dig into yourself, subjecting yourself to a kind of as-it-were-chemical [labore quodam quasi chymico] investigation. If you provide us with that, we’ll be able to investigate for ourselves whether you are better known than the bodies whose nature we know so much about through anatomy, chemistry, so many other sciences, so many senses and so many experiments.

Reply
(9) You say that all my points about the wax demonstrate that •I distinctly know that I exist, but not that •I distinctly know what I am, what sort of thing I am. This surprises me, because •the former can’t be demonstrated without •the latter. And I don’t see what more you expect here, unless you want to be told what colour or smell or taste the human mind has, or the proportions of salt, sulphur and mercury from which it is compounded. You want us, you say, to conduct ‘a kind of chemical investigation’ [labore quodam chymico] of the mind, as we would of wine. This is indeed worthy of you, Flesh, and of anyone who has only a confused conception of everything and so doesn’t know the right questions to ask about each thing. Speaking for myself, I have never thought that anything more is required to reveal a substance than its various attributes, so that the more attributes of a given substance we know, the more completely we understand its nature. Now we can pick out many different attributes in the wax:

it is white,
it is hard,
it can be melted,

and so on. And there are correspondingly many attributes in the mind:

it has the power of knowing that the wax is white,

it has the power of knowing that it is hard,

it has the power of knowing that it can lose its hardness (i.e. melt),

and so on. ·These are genuinely distinct powers, because· someone can know about the hardness without thereby knowing about the whiteness, e.g. a man born blind; and so on in other cases. This clearly shows that we know more attributes of our mind than we do of anything else. For no matter how many attributes we recognize in a thing, we can list the same number of attributes in the mind—attributes that enable it to know the attributes of the thing. So the nature of the mind is the one we know best of all. Finally, you criticise me for this: although I haven’t admitted that

99

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

I have anything apart from a mind, I nevertheless speak of the wax that I see and touch, which is impossible without eyes and hands. You should have noticed that I carefully pointed out that I was here dealing not with •actual sight and touch, which need bodily organs, but with •the thought of seeing and touching, which doesn’t need those organs (our dreams teach us that). Of course you can’t really have failed to notice this—your purpose must have been just to show me what absurd and unfair quibbles can be thought up by people who are more anxious to attack a position than to understand it.

[Now follows material that Descartes wrote to Clerselier in answer to Gassendi’s book; see note on page 85.]
Your friends note six objections against the second Meditation.

(a) Gassendi claims that when I say ‘I am thinking, therefore I exist’ I presuppose the premise ‘Whatever thinks exists’, and thus I have already adopted a preconceived opinion. Here he once more misuses the term ‘preconceived opinion’. For although we can call that proposition a preconceived opinion when it is carelessly believed to be true only because we remember having judged it to be true previously, we can’t say that it is always a preconceived opinion. For when we examine it, it appears so evident to the understanding that we can’t help believing it, even if this is the first time in our life that we have thought of it—which would clear it from the charge of being a preconceived opinion! But the most important mistake Gassendi makes here is to suppose that knowledge of particular propositions (·for example about my thinking·) must always be deduced from universal ones (·for example, about everyone’s thinking·), following the same order as that of a syllogism in applied logic. This shows how little he knows about how truth should be sought; for it is certain that to discover the truth we need always to start with •particular notions en route to •general ones that we come to later on; though then we may also reverse the order, take a general truth that we have discovered ·on the basis of •some particular truths·, and deduce •other particular truths from it. If you are teaching a child the elements of geometry, you won’t get him to understand the general proposition ‘When equal quantities are taken from equal amounts the remaining amounts will be equal’, or ‘The whole is greater than its parts’, unless you show him particular examples. It is by failing to take heed of this that Gassendi has gone astray and produced so many invalid arguments that pad out his book. He has simply made up false ·allegedly suppressed· premises whenever the mood takes him, as though I had used them to deduce the truths that I expounded.

(b) Your friends note that in order to know that I am thinking I must know what thought is; and yet, they say, I don’t know this, because I have denied everything. But I have denied only preconceived opinions—not notions like these, that are known without any affirmation or negation. [Descartes’s main point here seems to be that in the second Meditation he was denying propositions, whereas his notion of thought—his knowledge of ‘what thought is’—isn’t propositional; in making room for it in his mind he isn’t assenting to any proposition.]

(c) It is objected that thought can’t exist without an object (·i.e. with something that is thought about·), for example some body. Let’s beware of the ambiguity in the word ‘thought’: it is used to refer to •the thing that thinks and also to •what that thing does. Now, I deny that the thing that thinks needs any object apart from itself in order to do what it does (though it may also extend the scope of its activity to material things when it examines them).

(d) It is objected that although I have a thought of myself, I don’t know if this thought is a •bodily event or a self-moving atom, rather than an •immaterial substance. This involves

100

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

the ambiguity of ‘thought’—again! Apart from that, I can see only a challenge that has no basis, rather like this:

‘You judge that you are a man because you perceive in yourself all the things that lead you to give the name “men” to those who possess them; but how do you know that you aren’t an elephant rather than a man, for various other reasons that you don’t perceive?’

·Why is that a fair comparison?· Because the present objection amounts to this, addressed to the substance that thinks:

‘You judge that you are an intellect because you have observed in yourself all the properties of intellectual substances, and can’t detect any of the properties of bodies; but how do you know that you aren’t a body rather than an immaterial substance?’

(e) It is objected that even if I find no extension in my thought, it doesn’t follow that my thought is not extended, because my thought isn’t the standard that determines the truth of things.

(f) And that although my thought finds a distinction between thought and body, this distinction may be false. These two stand or fall together. Now, we must be very careful to notice the ambiguity in the words ‘my thought isn’t the standard that determines the truth of things’. If it means that my thought mustn’t be the standard for others, obliging them to believe something just because I think it is true, then I entirely agree. But that is quite irrelevant in the present context, because I never wanted to force anyone else to follow my authority. On the contrary, I said repeatedly one shouldn’t allow oneself to be convinced by anything except the evidentness of reasons. Again, if we take ‘thought’ to apply to any kind of activity of the soul, we can indeed have many thoughts that don’t imply anything about things that are outside us. But this too is irrelevant in the present context, where the topic is •thoughts that are vivid and clear perceptions and •judgments that each of us must make, for himself, as a result of these perceptions. That’s why I say that, in the sense in which the words should be understood here, the thought of each person—i.e. his perception or knowledge of something—should be for him the ‘standard that determines the truth of’ the thing; in other words, his judgments about this thing are correct only if they conform to his perception. This holds even for the truths of faith: we shouldn’t decide to believe them until we have perceived some convincing reason for thinking that they have indeed been revealed by God. What about ignorant people? Wouldn’t it be as well for them, on difficult topics, to follow the judgment of those who know more? Yes, but they must be guided by their own perception which tells them that •they are ignorant, and that •those whose judgment they propose to follow may be less ignorant than they are. Without that, they ought not to follow those others; and if they did, they would be behaving more like automatons or beasts than like men. Thus the most absurd—the most wild—mistake that a philosopher can make is to be willing to make judgments that don’t correspond to his perception of things; and I don’t see how Gassendi could be cleared of having committed this blunder in most of his objections. For he doesn’t want each person to abide by his own perception, and claims that we should instead believe the opinions or fantasies that he chooses to set before us, although we haven’t the least perception of them.

Objections to the third meditation

(1) In the third Meditation you recognize that •your vivid and clear knowledge of the proposition ‘I am a thing that thinks’ is the cause of •your certainty regarding it; and from this

101

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

you infer that you can lay down the general rule ‘Everything that I perceive very vividly and clearly is true’. Perhaps this was the best rule to be found in the darkness that prevailed there; but when we see that many great thinkers, who must have perceived very many things vividly and clearly, have judged that the truth of things is hidden either in God or at the bottom of a well, isn’t it reasonable to suspect that this rule ·of yours· may be •deceptive? Or perhaps it is •empty! According to the arguments of the sceptics, which you know, it seems that the only thing we can regard as true because vividly and clearly perceived is this: for anyone, what appears to be so is what appears to be so! ·We might give your ‘general rule’ a little content:

propositions about what appears to x at time t are themselves vividly and clearly perceived by x at t, and so—in accordance with your ‘general rule’—can be accepted as true by x at t;

but this is not enough content for your purposes or anyone else’s·. I vividly and clearly perceive the pleasant taste of a melon, so it’s true that that’s how the taste of a melon appears to me; but how can I convince myself that it is therefore true that such a flavour really exists in the melon? When I was a boy and in good health I vividly and clearly perceived a quite different taste in the melon; and I see that many people also perceive it differently.... Do we then have truth conflicting with truth? Isn’t it rather that something’s being vividly and clearly perceived doesn’t mean •that it is true in itself, but only •that that is how it is vividly and clearly perceived? And what holds for tastes also holds for intellectual matters. I used to be utterly certain of these:

•we can’t go from a quantity less than Q to one greater than Q without passing through Q; and

•if two lines are extended to infinity they must eventually meet.

I thought I perceived these things so vividly and clearly that I counted them as utterly true and unquestionable axioms; and yet I have since come across arguments that convinced me that each of them is false and that I perceived this even more vividly and clearly. But when I now consider the nature of mathematical propositions I am back in doubt again. I recognize that such and such propositions about quantities, lines and so on are indeed just as I conceive or suppose them to be; that is true, but it doesn’t imply that those propositions are true in themselves. Anyway, setting aside mathematical matters and returning to our present topics: why do people have so many different opinions about them? Everyone thinks that he vividly and clearly perceives the truth that he champions. Don’t reply that most of them are either tentative in their beliefs or insincere ·in what they say about what they believe·; there are those who face death for their opinions, even though they see others dying for the opposite cause. You can hardly think that their dying words are less than utterly sincere. Admittedly you do mention the difficulty that ‘I previously accepted as perfectly certain and evident many things that I afterwards realized were doubtful’. But in that passage you don’t •remove the difficulty or •confirm your rule; you merely snatch the opportunity to •discuss ideas that can deceive you into thinking that they represent things external to yourself, when in fact they may never have existed outside you. You return to the theme of a deceiving God who can mislead you about the propositions ‘Two and three are five’ and ‘A square has no more than four sides’, implying that we mustn’t expect confirmation of your rule until you have shown that there is a God who cannot be a deceiver. May I make a suggestion? What you ought to be working on is not •establishing this rule, which makes it so easy for us to accept falsehoods as true, but rather •proposing a method to guide us and show us, on those occasions when we think

102

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

we vividly and clearly perceive something, whether we are mistaken or not.

Reply
(1) Well done! Here at last you produce—for the first time, as far as I can see—an argument against me. You want to prove that the rule ‘Whatever we vividly and clearly perceive is true’ isn’t reliable, and you say that great thinkers, who must surely have perceived many things vividly and clearly, have nevertheless judged that the truth of things is hidden in God or at the bottom of a well. Your argument from authority is sound enough, Flesh; but you shouldn’t have presented it to a mind—·like mine at the start of the third Meditation·—that can’t be influenced by the authority of past people because it is so withdrawn from bodily things that it doesn’t even know whether there have been any such people! Your next point, taken from the sceptics, is a standard move, and not a bad one, but it doesn’t prove anything. Nor does the fact that some people face death to defend opinions that are in fact false; for it can never be proved that they vividly and clearly perceive what they so stubbornly affirm. You conclude this section by saying that what I should work on is not •a rule to establish the truth but •a method for determining whether or not we are deceived when we think we perceive something clearly. I don’t dispute this; but I maintain that I carefully provided such a method in the appropriate place, where I first eliminated all preconceived opinions and afterwards listed all my principal ideas, distinguishing the clear ones from those that are obscure or confused.

Objection
(2) You next distinguish ideas (by which you mean image-like thoughts) into three classes:

(a) innate, (b) caused from outside, and (c) invented.

In (a) you put your ‘understanding of what a thing is, what truth is and what thought is’. In (b) you put your ‘hearing a noise or seeing the sun or feeling the fire’. And in (c) you put your ‘invented ideas of sirens and hippogriffs’. You add that it may be that all your ideas belong in (a), or all in (b), or all in (c), because you haven’t yet clearly perceived their origin. Well, to guard you against slipping into error at this stage, before you have managed to perceive the origin of your ideas, I point out to you that all ideas seem to be (b) caused by things that exist outside the mind and are within range of one of our senses. The mind has the faculty—actually it is the faculty—of perceiving ideas that things send to it through the senses; these ideas are clear and uncluttered, and they are presented to us exactly as they are. But the mind also has the faculty of assembling these ideas into larger structures, pulling them apart into smaller ones, comparing them, and so on.

So class (c) isn’t distinct from (b), because we invent ideas by assembling them out of ideas that come to us from things outside us. [Gassendi goes on to present examples. Then:]

What about class (a)—the images that you say are innate? There don’t seem to be any: all the ideas that are said to belong in (a) appear to have an external origin. You say ‘I derive from my own nature my •understanding of what a thing is’, by which you presumably....mean that you derive your •idea of thing. Now, all individual items are things, but you don’t say that our ideas of them—e.g. our idea of the sun, or of this pebble—are innate. So you must be talking about the idea of thing considered in general.... But how can the mind contain this idea unless it also contains.... ·the ideas of· all the kinds of things from which the mind abstracts so as to form this all-purpose concept of thing? Surely if the idea of thing is innate, the ideas of animal, plant, stone, and of any other universal will also be innate....

103

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

You also say ‘I derive from my nature my •understanding of what truth is’, presumably meaning your •idea of truth. But if a judgment’s truth is simply its •conformity with the thing that it is about, then truth is a •relation, which implies that there is nothing to it over and above the thing and the idea ·or judgment· that are so related.... And since this applies to any particular truth, it can also apply to truth in general, the notion or idea of which is derived from the notions or ideas of particular things (in the way I have said that the idea of thing is).

Again, you say that ‘I derive from my own nature my •understanding of what thought is’ (presumably meaning, again, your •idea of thought). But just as the mind can construct the idea of one town from the idea of another [this had been one of his examples], so from the idea of one action such as seeing or tasting, it can construct the idea of another action such as thinking. For the various cognitive faculties are known to be analogous, so that a grasp of one easily leads to a grasp of another. Anyway, what needs work here is not the idea of thought, but rather the idea of the mind itself, the soul. If we grant that this idea is innate, we won’t jib at admitting that the idea of thought is also innate. So we must wait for you to prove the innateness of ·our idea of· the mind or soul.

Reply
(2) I’m amazed at the line of argument by which you try to prove that all our ideas are caused from outside us, and that we don’t make any of them, because (you say) the mind is capable not merely of perceiving ideas that are caused from outside it but also ‘of assembling these ideas into larger structures, pulling them apart into smaller ones, comparing them, and so on’. From which you infer that the ideas of chimeras that the mind makes up by assembling and pulling apart etc. aren’t made by the mind but are caused from outside. By this argument you could prove •that Praxiteles never made any statues, because he didn’t get the marble he used in them from within himself; or •that you didn’t produce these objections, because you put them together using words that you acquired from others rather than inventing them yourself. Actually, the form of a •chimera doesn’t consist in parts of the goat and the lion, and the form of your •objections doesn’t consist in the individual words you have used; each of them consists in the elements’ being put together in a certain way.

I am also surprised by your contention that the idea of thing can’t be in the mind unless the ideas of animal, plant, stone, and all the ·other· universals are there. As if I can’t grasp my own status as a thinking thing unless I also grasp ·ideas of· animals and plants, these being needed for me to have the idea of thing. Your remarks about the idea of truth are equally false. And the remarks with which you close the section are about things that I didn’t discuss at all, so in them you are simply beating the air.

Objection
(3) What you seem to question next is not just whether any ideas come from external things, but whether there are any external things. Apparently you argue like this:

I have within me ideas of things that are called ‘external’; but the ideas don’t establish that the things exist, because the ideas don’t necessarily arise from •such things rather than from •myself or •some other source—I don’t know what.

I think this is why you said earlier that you hadn’t previously perceived the earth, the sky and the stars, but only the ideas of the earth, the sky and the stars, which might be illusory. But if you still don’t believe that the earth, sky, stars and so

104

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

on exist, why do you walk on the earth and move your body to look at the sun?.... You can certainly say that you have these doubts, and you can develop them with great subtlety, but they don’t push things on for you. Anyway, you don’t really doubt that the things outside you exist, so let’s ·stop this game, and· discuss things as they are, doing this in an honest adult fashion. If, granting the existence of external objects, you think it can’t be properly shown that our ideas are derived from them, you’ll have to dispose not only of the objections that you raise against yourself, but also of other difficulties that can be raised.

You admit that we accept that our ideas come from external things because •nature has apparently taught us to think that they do, and also because •we know by experience that the ideas in question don’t depend on us or on our will. I set aside those arguments and their solution, and present something else that you ought also to have raised and answered, namely: Why does a man born blind have no idea of colour? a man born deaf no idea of sound? Surely it’s because external objects have never been able to transmit any images of themselves to the minds of such unfortunate people, because ever since their birth the doors have been closed against the entry into their minds of these images.

Later on you push the example of your two ideas of the sun: one of them, deriving from the senses, makes the sun appear small and isn’t accurate; the other, based on astronomical reasoning, gives us a truer conception of the sun as huge. The latter idea, you say, isn’t drawn from the senses but derived from innate notions or produced in some other way. Actually, both these ideas of the sun resemble it, and are true (i.e. conform to the sun), though one more than the other....

Although the second, vast idea of the sun is perceived by the mind alone, it doesn’t follow that the idea is derived from some innate notion. Experience establishes that objects appear smaller from a distance than they do from close up, and reasoning based on experience confirms this. ·And because we know this·, our mind’s power amplifies the idea of the sun that comes to us through sense-perception so that it corresponds exactly with the agreed distance of the sun from us.... Do you want to know how it can be that no part of this idea has been implanted in us by nature? Go to the congenitally blind man to find out! You will find that the idea ·of the sun· in his mind

•has no colour or luminosity, •is not even round

(unless someone has told him the sun is round and he has previously held a round object in his hands), and

•isn’t nearly as large ·as yours and mine·,

(unless he has amplified his previously accepted idea as a result of reasoning or the influence of some authority). Here is a question for you, concerning you and me—we who have so often looked at the sun, seen its apparent diameter, and reasoned about its true diameter. Do we have any image of the sun other than the ordinary one? Reasoning tells us that it is more than 160 times bigger than the earth, but does that give us an idea of such a vast body? We certainly amplify the idea derived from the senses as much as possible, and exert our mind as much as possible; but all that we succeed in creating for ourselves is pitch-black darkness. If we want to have a distinct idea of the sun, then our mind must always return to the image that it has received through the eye. It is enough if we accept that the sun is bigger ·than it looks to us·, and that we would have a larger idea of it if our eyes could move closer to it....

Reply
(3) Here, aiming to destroy the arguments that led me to judge that the existence of material things should be doubted,

105

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

you ask why in that case I walk on the earth etc. This obviously •assumes the very thing that had to be •proved, namely that my walking on the earth is so certain that there can be no doubt of it.

In addition to the arguments that I put forward against myself, and refuted, you raise the challenge ‘Why is there no idea of colour in a man born blind? or of sound in a man born deaf?’ This shows plainly that you have no significant arguments to produce. How do you know that there is no idea of colour in a man born blind? We know that we sometimes have sensations of light and colour while our eyes are closed, ·so why shouldn’t the man born blind have them too?· [The next sentence expands what Descartes wrote, in ways that can’t easily be indicated by the ·small dots· convention.] And even if we grant that the man born blind has no ideas of colour, that doesn’t have to be explained in your way, by supposing that his lack of eyesight prevents such ideas from being passed on from material things into his mind; those who deny the existence of material things can offer a quite different explanation, namely that the blind man’s isn’t capable of making such ideas.

Your next point about the two ideas of the sun proves nothing. You take the two ideas to be one because they are ideas of only one sun, which is like saying that a true statement doesn’t differ from a false one that is asserted about the same thing. In saying that the idea we reach through astronomical reasoning is not in fact an idea, you are restricting the term ‘idea’ to images depicted in the corporeal imagination; but this goes against my explicit assumption.

Objection
(4) Next, you recognize the inequality and diversity to be found among our ideas. You say:

Undoubtedly, the ideas that represent substances amount to something more—they contain within themselves more representative reality—than do the ideas that merely represent qualities. Again, the idea that gives me my understanding of a supreme God—eternal, infinite, omnipotent and the creator of everything that exists except for himself—certainly has in it more representative reality than the ideas that represent merely finite substances.

[Gassendi comments at some length on the distinction between ‘intrinsic reality’ of x and the ‘representative reality’ in an idea of x. Then:] You and I agree that the representative reality in an idea of x is to be measured not •by the total intrinsic reality of x (the reality that x has in itself) but •by....how much knowledge of x is possessed by the mind that has the idea. Thus you count as having a complete idea of a man if you have looked at him •carefully and •often •from all sides; but your idea will be incomplete if you have merely seen him •in passing •once •from one side. If you haven’t seen the man himself, but only a mask over his face and clothes covering the rest of him, then you count as not having any idea of him, or anyway of having one that is very incomplete and utterly confused.

In the light of this I claim that we do have a distinct and genuine idea of qualities, but that our idea of the unseen substance that underlies them is confused—and is indeed a pure fiction. So when you say that the idea of a substance has more representative reality than does the idea of its qualities, ·I have two objections·. (a) We don’t have any genuine idea or representation of a substance, so we don’t have one with representative reality. (b) Even if we grant that there is such an idea, and that it has some representative reality, we must still deny that this reality is greater than what there is in the idea of the qualities. Why? Because the

106

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

idea of the substance gets its representative reality from the ideas of the •qualities under which—in the guise of which—we conceive of the •substance....

Now for what you say about the idea of God: since ·at this stage in the third Meditation· you aren’t yet sure whether God exists, how do you know that he is represented by your idea of him as ‘supreme, eternal, infinite, omnipotent and the creator of all things’? Don’t you get this from your previously conceived knowledge of God, that is, from having heard these attributes ascribed to him? Would you describe him like that if you hadn’t previously heard anything of the sort? You’ll say ‘I introduced this just as an example, without meaning to lay down any definition ·of God· at this stage’. All right; but watch out that you don’t later take it as an established result!

The idea of an infinite God, you say, has more representative reality than does the idea of a finite thing. ·I have three points to make about this·. (a) The human intellect is not capable of conceiving of infinity, so it can’t contemplate—and indeed can’t even have—any idea representing an infinite thing. When someone calls something ‘infinite’, he is attributing to

•a thing that he doesn’t grasp

(because it extends beyond any grasp of it he can have)

•a label for which he doesn’t have a meaning that he can grasp!

(because his intelligence is always confined within some limit, so that he can’t understand the limitlessness that the label attributes to the thing). (b) Although commonly every supreme perfection is attributed to God, it seems that such perfections are all taken from things that we admire in ourselves, such as

longevity, power, knowledge, goodness, blessedness

and so on. We amplify these as much as we can, and say that God is

eternal, omnipotent, omniscient, supremely good, supremely blessed

and so on. So the idea representing all these things—·these divine attributes·—doesn’t contain more representative reality than do ·the ideas of· the finite things taken together; it is compounded and augmented from the ideas of these finite things in the way I have just described. When someone calls something ‘eternal’, he isn’t getting his mind around the entire extent of its duration—a duration that never started and will never end. Similarly....with the other ·divine· attributes.

(c) Can anyone claim that he has an authentic idea of God—one that represents God as he is? If there were nothing to God except what is contained in our little idea of him, what an insignificant thing he would be! Surely we must believe that God’s perfections are less like man’s than an elephant is like a tick on its skin. We can no more form a genuine idea of God on the basis of what we observe of men’s perfections than we can form a genuine idea of an elephant by observing the tick. Can we really congratulate ourselves if, after seeing the perfections of a man, we form an idea which we maintain is the idea of God and is genuinely representative of him? How could we detect in God the presence of those puny perfections that we find in ourselves?.... God is infinitely beyond anything we can grasp, and when our mind sets itself to contemplate him, it is in the dark—indeed, it is nothing. So we have no grounds for claiming that we have any authentic idea that represents God. ·And we don’t need such an idea·. What we can do—namely to

construct, on the analogy of our human attributes, an idea of some sort for our own use, an idea that doesn’t

107

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

•go beyond what we humans can grasp and doesn’t

•contain any ·representative· reality except what we perceive in our encounters with other things

—is more than enough ·for our purposes·.

Reply
(4) ·At the end of my preceding comment I pointed out your mistake of equating ideas with images in the corporeal imagination·. And now you are doing it again! You deny that we have a true idea of substance on the grounds that substance is perceived not by the imagination but by the intellect alone. But I have already made it clear, Flesh, that I don’t want any conversation with someone who is prepared to use only his imagination and not his intellect.

You next say: ‘The idea of a substance gets its ·representative· reality from the ideas of the qualities under which—in the guise of which—we conceive of the substance.’ Here you prove that in fact you have no distinct idea of substance. For a substance can never be conceived ‘in the guise of’ its qualities, and can’t derive its reality from them. (On the contrary, philosophers commonly conceive of qualities in the guise of substances, since they often say that they are ‘real’ [= ‘thing-like’, i.e. substances in disguise; see note on page 78].) In fact, any reality that can be attributed to a quality....is taken from the idea of a substance.

You go on to say that we have the idea of God merely through of having heard others ascribing certain attributes to him. What about the first men—the first who were ‘heard’ speaking of these attributes? Where did they get their idea of God from? If they got them from themselves, why can’t we also get it from ourselves? If by divine revelation, then God exists.

You add: ‘When someone calls something “infinite”, he is attributing to a thing that he doesn’t grasp a label for which he doesn’t have a meaning that he can grasp.’ Here you fail to distinguish

•an understanding that is suited to the scale of our intellect,

(and each of us knows by his own experience that he has this sort of understanding of the infinite) from

•a fully adequate conception of things

(and no-one has this sort of conception of the infinite or of anything else, however small). Also, it is false that the infinite is understood through the negation of a boundary or limit [this refers to Gassendi’s speaking of ‘the limitlessness that the label “infinite” attributes to a thing’]; on the contrary, all limitation implies a negation of the infinite; ·so that ‘finite’ is a negative term and ‘infinite’ a positive one·.

It is also false that the idea representing all the perfections that we attribute to God ‘doesn’t contain any more representative reality than do ·the ideas of· the finite things taken together’. •You yourself admit that in order to attribute these perfections to God we must use our intellects to ‘amplify’ them. In amplifying them don’t we make them greater than they would have been if they weren’t amplified? •And another point: how could we be able to amplify ·our ideas of· all created perfections (i.e. to conceive of something greater or more ample than they are) if we didn’t ·already· have an idea of something greater, namely God? •Finally, it is again false that ‘God would be an insignificant thing if there were nothing to him except what is contained in our understanding of him’. For we understand God to be infinite, and nothing can be greater than that! You are still mixing up •understanding with •imagination, and supposing that we imagine God to be like some enormous man—likening us to someone who has never seen an elephant and makes a fool of himself by imagining it to be like some enormous tick.

108

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

Objection
(5) You next assume that ‘it is obvious by the natural light that the total cause of something must contain at least as much ·reality· as does the effect’. From this you infer that there must be at least as much intrinsic reality in the cause of an idea as there is representative reality in the idea. Stop for a moment, while we examine this huge step that you have just taken.

First, it is indeed commonly said that ‘There is nothing in the effect that isn’t in the cause’, but this seems to refer to •material causes rather than •efficient causes [see explanatory note page 6]. clearly an efficient cause is something external to the effect, and is often of a quite different nature. An effect is indeed said to ‘get its reality from’ its efficient cause, but it doesn’t follow that the efficient cause must have had this reality in itself; it may have borrowed it from elsewhere. To see this clearly, consider effects produced by some skill. A house gets all its reality from the builder, but the builder doesn’t have this reality in himself—he simply takes it from some other source and passes it on to the house. [He gives other examples; and then attacks Descartes’s use of the concept of containing something ‘in a higher form’ [see note on page 5]: to say that the efficient cause of my being F ‘possessed Fness in a higher form’ is just to say that my efficient cause wasn’t F but was able to cause me to be F. Then:] In short, an efficient cause doesn’t contain ·the reality of· its effect except in the sense that it can shape it and produce the effect out of a given material.

To discuss what you say about representative reality, I take the example of my own image, which I can look at either in a mirror or in a painting. •The image in the mirror has •me for its cause because I transmit my image onto the mirror, whereas •the image on the canvas is caused by •the painter. Now consider the idea or image of me that is in (for example) you: do I cause this idea by transmitting my image onto your eye and on through to your intellect? or does some other cause trace the image out in the intellect as if with a pen or pencil? It seems that there doesn’t have to be any cause other than myself; for although your intellect may subsequently modify its idea of me—amplify or reduce it, combine it with something else, or whatever—I myself am the primary cause of all the reality that the idea contains within itself. And if this holds for ·ideas of· me it must also hold for ·ideas of· any external object.

Now, you divide the reality belonging to this idea into two kinds. [Gassendi’s account of the idea’s •intrinsic reality is obscure, and seems not to contribute to what follows. Then:] The •representative reality of an idea of me has to be

•the representation or likeness of me that the idea carries,

or at any rate

•the way the parts of the idea are fitted together to make a pattern that represents me.

Either way, it seems to be nothing real, but merely a relation amongst the various parts and between the parts and myself; in other words, it is merely a feature of the idea’s intrinsic reality.... But never mind; let’s call it ‘representative reality’, since this is what you want.

Against that background, it seems that you ought to compare

•the intrinsic reality of the idea of me with the

•intrinsic reality of me

(i.e. with my substance), or to compare

the •representative reality of the idea of me with •the proportion obtaining between my various parts or my external form and outline.

But what you want to do is to compare the •representative reality of the idea with my •intrinsic reality.

109

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

Returning now to the ‘as-much-reality’ axiom: clearly there is in me as much intrinsic reality as there is representative reality in the idea of me; and indeed that the representative* reality of the idea is virtually nothing by comparison with my intrinsic reality, i.e. my entire substance. [*Gassendi wrote formalem = ‘intrinsic’—evidently a slip.] So we must grant you that ‘there must be at least as much intrinsic reality in the cause of an idea as there is representative reality in the idea’, for the whole of what is in the idea is virtually nothing in comparison with its cause. [Perhaps Gassendi meant to write here that ‘the whole representative reality in the idea is virtually nothing’ etc. That would fit his down-playing account of what representative reality is.]

Reply
(5) You say a great deal here to give the appearance of contradicting me, but in fact you don’t contradict me at all, because you reach exactly the same conclusion as I do. But your discussion includes many assertions that I strongly disagree with. You say that the axiom ‘There is nothing in the effect that didn’t previously exist in the cause’ should be taken to refer to material rather than efficient causes; but it’s obviously unintelligible that perfection of form should ever pre-exist in a material cause; it can do so only in an efficient cause. [There is a note on page 6 about these different kinds of cause. An example of what Descartes is getting at here: If we want to explain the inscription on a coin (its ‘form’), we must look at the die that stamped the coin out of the silver plate (the coin’s ‘efficient cause’); we couldn’t explain it by investigating the nature of silver (the coin’s ‘material cause’).] Nor do I agree that the intrinsic reality of an idea is a substance, and so on.

Objection
(6) Your next step is as follows. If the representative reality of any one of your ideas turns out to be so great that you don’t contain it within you either in a higher form or straightforwardly, so that you can’t yourself be its cause, it follows that something besides you exists in the world. For if this weren’t so, you would have no argument to convince yourself that anything else exists. Certainly, what you have already said shows that you aren’t the cause of the ·representative· reality of your ideas; the cause is, rather, the things that the ideas represent—things that send images of themselves to you as though to a mirror.... But does •the question of what causes your ideas affect •the confidence of your belief that there exist things besides yourself in the world? Please give a straight answer; for whatever the ‘idea’ situation turns out to be, we hardly need to look for arguments to prove that other things exist.

Then you list the ideas that are in you, namely ideas of

yourself,
God,
inanimate bodily things,
angels,
animals, and
men.

You find no problem in the idea of •yourself, and you think that your ideas of •bodily things could have come from yourself; and you go on to say that starting with those two ideas and your idea of •God you can assemble your ideas of •angels, •animals and •men. Your idea of yourself is—·in your hands·—so fertile that you can derive many other ideas from it; I am puzzled by your claim that there is no problem about it. In fact you have no idea of yourself, or at most you have a very confused and incomplete one, as I noted when commenting on the second Meditation. In the latter you concluded that

•there is nothing that you could perceive more easily or evidently than yourself.

110

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

But since you don’t and can’t have any idea of yourself, what you ought to have said was that

•you can perceive anything at all more easily and more evidently than yourself!

Thinking about why •sight doesn’t see itself and •intellect doesn’t understand itself, I realize that ·these are just special cases of the more general truth that· •nothing acts on itself. (Other special cases: the finger-tip doesn’t tap on itself, the foot doesn’t kick itself.) For us to become aware of something, that thing has to act on our cognitive faculty by sending its image to the faculty....and of course a faculty can’t send an image of itself to itself.... [He applies this to the case of seeing yourself in a mirror: you act on the mirror, which then acts back on you.] Show me a mirror that you yourself—you considered as the mind that you say you are—can act on in this way, and I promise that when it bounces your image back to you you’ll finally succeed in perceiving yourself. Not otherwise. [Gassendi mentions difficulties that he could point out regarding Descartes’s claim to have ideas of God and angels, but he doesn’t press them. Then:]

But let us consider your ideas of bodily things. There’s a big difficulty about how you can derive these from your idea of yourself at a time when you claim that you aren’t a body and don’t consider yourself as one. If all you know is a non-bodily substance, how can you get a grasp of bodily substance? [He suggests an answer that Descartes might give, and criticises it; then develops the original criticism further.]

Reply
(6) If you had any argument to prove the existence of material things, you would surely have produced it here. But all you do is to ask whether my mind is uncertain about whether anything exists in the world apart from itself; and you say that there’s no need to look for arguments to decide this—thus appealing to our preconceived opinions. Here you show that you can’t produce any argument to support your assertion—it wouldn’t be more obvious if you hadn’t said anything at all!

What you then say about ideas doesn’t need to be answered, because in it you restrict the term ‘idea’ to images depicted in the imagination, whereas I extend it to cover every object of thought.

But I have a question about the argument you use to show that ‘nothing acts on itself’. You don’t usually give arguments; but here you do—supporting your case with the example of the finger that doesn’t tap itself and the eye that doesn’t see itself directly but only in a mirror. It is easy to answer this. It isn’t the case that the eye sees itself not directly but in a mirror. Rather, it is the mind—and only the mind—that recognizes the mirror, the eye, and itself. The realm of bodies provides other counter-examples: when a top spins, isn’t its turning a case of the top’s acting on itself?

Finally, I did not say that the ideas of material things are derived from the mind, as you (not very honestly) say I did. Later on I explicitly showed that these ideas often come to us from bodies, which is what enables us to show that bodies exist. All that I said about this in the passage we are now discussing was that we never find so much reality in these ideas that we have to conclude (given that there is nothing in the effect that didn’t not previously exist in the cause, either straightforwardly or in a higher form) that they couldn’t have originated in the mind alone. And this claim you don’t attack at all.

Objection
(7) You then draw the following conclusion:

So there remains only the idea of God: is there any-

111

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

thing in that which couldn’t have originated in myself? By the word ‘God’ I understand a substance that is indefinite [Descartes had written ‘infinite’], independent, supremely intelligent, and supremely powerful, which created myself and anything else that may exist. The more carefully I concentrate on these attributes, the less possible it seems that any of them could have originated from me alone. So this whole discussion implies that God necessarily exists.

This is the result you were aiming for. I accept the conclusion, but I don’t see how it follows from your premises. The attributes that you understand God to have are of such a kind, you say, that •they couldn’t have originated from you alone, and you want to infer from this that •they must have originated from God. Well, it’s absolutely true that they didn’t originate from you alone,....but that’s because they were derived from things in your environment—parents, teachers, professors, and human society generally. ‘But I am merely a mind’, you may say; ‘I am not admitting anything outside of me—not even ears to hear with or men to talk to me.’ You may say this, but would you be saying it if there were no men to talk to you or you had no ears to hear them with? Let’s be serious: can you honestly deny that all the words you use in describing God come from the human society in which you live? And if this is true of the words, isn’t it also true of the underlying notions that these words express?.... Granted, if you really understood the nature of God, whatever it is, that would give us reason to think that you had learnt this from God; but ·you don’t have such an understanding, because· all the characteristics you attribute to God are merely perfections that you have observed in people and other things, and that the human mind can understand, build with, and amplify, as I have already explained several times.

You say that the idea of a substance could come from yourself because you are a substance, but that the idea of an infinite substance couldn’t come from you because you are not infinite, ·and so must have come from God·. But you don’t have the idea of an infinite substance except verbally—·i.e. except in being able to manage the phrase ‘infinite substance’·.... So there isn’t an idea here that must originate from an infinite substance: ·whatever substitute you have for a genuine idea of infinite substance·, it can be constructed by building and amplifying in the way I have explained. The philosophers of ancient times took in •this visible space and •this single world and •these few sources of energy, and acquired their ideas of these things; then they amplified these ideas to form ideas of an •infinite universe, •infinitely many worlds and •infinitely many sources of energy. Do you want to say that they didn’t form those ideas by their own mental powers, and that the ideas were put into their minds by an infinite universe, an infinity of worlds, and an infinity of sources of energy? You insist that your thought of the infinite involves ‘a true idea’; but if it were a true idea it would represent the infinite as it is, and you would hence perceive its principal feature, namely its infinity. But in fact your thought never gets beyond the finite, and you call it ‘infinite’ only because you don’t perceive what is out of reach of your thought; so it is quite right to say that you perceive the infinite by a negation of the finite. [Gassendi elaborates on this at some length.]

You say that it doesn’t matter that you don’t grasp [Latin comprehendas = understand, with a suggestion of getting one’s mind around something] the infinite or everything that is in it, and that all you need for •a true and completely vivid and clear idea of it is •an understanding of a few of its attributes. But if you don’t grasp the infinite but merely the finite, then you don’t have a true idea of the infinite but merely of the finite.

112

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

You can perhaps claim to know part of the infinite, but not to know the infinite. A man who has never left an underground cave knows a part of the world, but....he would make a fool of himself if he took his idea of this tiny portion of the world to be a true and authentic idea of the entire world. You say that

•it is in the nature of the infinite not to be grasped by a finite creature like yourself.

I agree, but ·I also insist that·

•it is not in the nature of a true idea of an infinite thing to represent such a tiny part of it!

Actually, not even a part of it, because it is not a fraction of the whole.... Do you hold that there would be a fine likeness of me if a painter merely painted one of my hairs, or only its tip? Yet the gap between •the tip of one of my hairs and •the whole of me is not just smaller, not just enormously much smaller, but infinitely smaller than the gap between •everything we know of the infinite, or God, and •God himself in his entirety....

Reply
(7) You have said all this before, and I have disposed of it. I’ll make one •point about the idea of the infinite. You say that this can’t be a true idea unless I grasp the infinite; and that the most I can be said to know is a part of the infinite, and a very small part at that, which doesn’t match the infinite any better than a picture of one tiny hair represents the whole man. My •point is that, on the contrary, the proposition ‘I grasp something that is infinite’ is a flat-out contradiction, because a true idea of the infinite can’t be grasped at all, that being a consequence of the essence of infinity. [Descartes’s thought here is that (a) having no limits is an essential feature of the infinite, and that (b) to grasp something is to have a mental hold on it all, to get your mind around it, to ride around its boundaries, so to speak; and you can’t do this if the thing has no boundaries. As noted earlier, ‘grasp’ translates comprehendere; and the phrase ‘not bounded by any limits’ at the end of this paragraph uses the same word—nullis limitibus comprehensam.] And yet it is obvious that our idea of the infinite represents not merely one part of it but the whole of it—representing it in a manner that is appropriate to a human idea. No doubt God, or some other intelligent nature more perfect than a human mind, could have a much more perfect idea, i.e. one that is more exact and distinct. Similarly when a beginner in geometry understands that a triangle is a figure bounded by three lines, we don’t doubt that he has an idea of the whole triangle, even though he is unaware of many properties of that idea that geometers can pick out. Well, just as it suffices for •having an idea of the whole triangle to •understand that it is a figure contained within three lines, so it suffices for •having a true and complete idea of the infinite in its entirety to •understand that it is a thing that isn’t bounded by any limits.

Objection
(8) In another passage you argue as follows:

Whenever I know that I doubt something or want something, I understand that I lack something and am therefore not wholly perfect. How could I grasp this unless I had an idea of a more perfect being—an idea that enabled me to recognize my own defects by comparison?

Well, it is hardly surprising that you should •be in doubt about something, or •want something, or recognize that you •lack something, given that you don’t •know everything, don’t •possess everything, and •aren’t everything!.... It’s true that you aren’t wholly perfect (and it isn’t rude of me to say this), but does that lead you to understand that there is something more perfect than you? Surely things that you want are not

113

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

always in some sense more perfect than you. [In this paragraph and elsewhere, it may be worthwhile to remember that ‘perfect’ translates perfectus, which can easily mean ‘complete’.] When you want some bread, the bread isn’t in any way more perfect than you or your body; it is merely more perfect than the emptiness of your stomach. [Gassendi offers a mildly complex explanation of why Descartes came to hold his wrong view about this. Then:]

A little later you raise a possible objection to your argument:

Perhaps I am greater than I myself understand: perhaps all the perfections that I attribute to God are ones that I do have in some potential form, and they merely haven’t yet shown themselves in actuality, as they would if my knowledge gradually increased to infinity.

You respond to that:

Though it is true that my knowledge is increasing, and that I have many potentialities that aren’t yet actual, this is all quite irrelevant to the idea of God, which contains nothing that is potential. Indeed, this gradual increase in knowledge is itself the surest sign of imperfection.

But although the features that you perceive in the idea actually exist in •the idea, it doesn’t follow that they actually exist in •the thing that it is an idea of.... Some ancient philosophers had an idea that actually contained an infinity of worlds, but you won’t infer from this that this infinity of worlds actually exists! [He develops this point in terms of an architect’s •actual plans for a •potential building, and then returns to the impossibility of having ‘a true and genuine idea of God’, because there is always so much more to be discovered about God...]—infinitely more than remains to be discovered about a man when you have seen only the tip of one of his hairs. Indeed, even if you haven’t seen the whole man, you have seen other men, and this will give you a basis—by comparison—for making some conjectures about him. But we have never been in a position to know anything that resembles God and his immensity.

You say that you ‘take God to be actually infinite, so that nothing can be added to his perfection’. But you are here making a judgment about something of which you are ignorant. Your judgment is based simply on a presumption, like that of the philosophers who thought there are •infinitely many worlds, •infinitely many sources of energy, and an •infinite universe. Your further comment that ‘the representative being of an idea cannot come from potential being but only from actual being’ can hardly be true, given my point about the ideas of the architect and of the ancient philosophers, especially when you remember that ideas of this sort are constructed from other ideas, which the intellect originally derived from actually existing causes.

Reply
(8) When you (a) deny that we have a •true idea of God, you repeat the mistake you made in (7). For although we don’t know everything that is in God, all the attributes that we recognize in him are •truly there. You also (b) say that if someone wants some bread, the bread is not more perfect than him; and (c) that although a feature that I perceive in an idea actually exists in the idea, ‘it doesn’t follow that it actually exists in the thing that the idea is an idea of’. And finally you (d) say that I am making a judgment about something of which I am ignorant. But these comments and their like merely show that you, Flesh, are anxious to rush in and attack many statements without understanding them. (b) The fact that someone wants bread doesn’t imply that •bread is more perfect than •he is, but merely that •his state

114

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

when he doesn’t need bread is more perfect state than •his state when he does need it. (c) From something’s existing in an idea I don’t infer that it exists in reality, except when we can’t come up with any cause for the idea except the actual existence of the thing it represents. And I have demonstrated that that’s how things stand with the idea of God, and not with the idea of many worlds or of anything else. (d) I am not making a judgment about something of which I am ignorant: I gave reasons to back up my judgment—reasons that are so solid that you haven’t been able to mount the slightest attack against any of them.

Objection
(9) You next ask whether, given that you have an idea of a being more perfect than you, you could exist if no such being existed. And you say in reply: ‘Well, if God didn’t exist, from what would I derive my existence? It would have to come from myself, or from my parents, or from some other beings less perfect than God.’ And you go on to prove—quite unnecessarily!—that you don’t derive your existence from yourself, followed by a reason why you haven’t always existed. There was no point in that either, except that it leads into your view that you have a cause that not only •created you but •keeps you in existence. ·I have some comments to offer on that view·. From the premises

•the time through which you live has many parts, and

•each part is independent of the others,

you infer that

•you must be created anew in each individual part.

But look at this another way: There are indeed some effects that can’t keep going unless the efficient cause that produced them in the first place continues to act. The light of the sun is an example of this (though in cases like that, it isn’t really the •same effect that keeps going but rather ‘an •equivalent effect’, as they say about the water in a river). But we see some other effects continuing when their acknowledged cause has stopped acting and perhaps has even stopped existing. Manufactured things and organisms are cases of this; I shan’t bore us with a list; it’s enough to cite you as an example, whatever your cause eventually turns out to be! You say that the parts of your time are ‘independent of each other’. This is open to challenge: can we think of anything whose parts are less ‘independent of each other’, more inseparably linked together? Is there anything whose later parts are more inevitable, more closely tied to the earlier parts and more dependent on them, ·than a period of time·? But I’ll set that aside, and put this to you:

The parts of time •are external, they •are successive [meaning that none of them sticks around for long enough to achieve anything], they •do not act. So how can their being dependent or independent make any difference to your coming into existence or staying in existence?

They have no more effect on that than the flow of waterparticles in a river has on the creation and preservation of some rock over which it flows. From the fact that you existed a little while ago, you say, it doesn’t follow that you must exist now. I agree; but ·you are wrong about why this is so·. It isn’t because

•a cause is needed to create you anew,

but rather because

•there may be some cause present that could destroy you, or you may have some weakness within you that will lead to your destruction.

You say: ‘There is no real distinction between preservation and creation—only a conceptual one—and this is one of the things that the natural light makes evident’. But how is this ‘evident’ if not in the case of light and similar effects? [Gassendi presumably means: light and its like are the nearest things

115

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

you’ll get to examples of something’s being kept in existence by the cause that brought it into existence, yet even with them it isn’t ‘evident’ that bringing-into-existence is the same process as keeping-in-existence.] You go on to argue like this:

•You are not aware of having any power that will keep you in existence for the next few minutes. •You are a thinking thing ·and thus would be aware of such a power if you had it·.

Therefore

•You don’t have any such power.

But you do have a power in virtue of which you can think you’ll exist a few minutes hence (though not necessarily or indubitably, because this power—this natural constitution—of yours, whatever it is, doesn’t guard against every external or internal cause that might destroy you). So you will indeed continue to exist because of a power that you have—not •to create yourself anew ·at every moment·, but •to ensure that you will continue unless some destructive cause intervenes. [Gassendi criticises Descartes’s reasons for denying that he owes his existence to his parents. Then:] You say:

But if your parents were the cause of your existence, then that cause may have derived its existence not from itself but from another cause; and the same may be true of that prior cause, and so on ad infinitum. The only way you could rule out such an infinite regress would be to prove that the world began at some time, so that there must have been a first parent who had no parent. An infinite regress seems to be absurd only for causes that are linked in a hierarchical way so that a cause that is lower in the chain can’t act without the motive power of one that is higher. For example, when something is pushed by a stone, the stone by a stick, and the stick by a hand; or when a weight is lifted by the first link of a chain, which is pulled by the second link, and so on. In such cases we must eventually reach one link in the chain that is the first to move; ·it would be absurd to think of a weight as lifted by an infinitely long chain·. But there seems to be no absurdity when we have causes that are inter-related in such a way that if an earlier cause is destroyed the subsequent cause depending on it can survive and continue to act. So when you say that it’s clear that an infinite regress is impossible in the case we are discussing, you must ask whether this was just as clear to Aristotle, who was strongly convinced that there was never any first parent!

You go on as follows:

It might be thought that several partial causes contributed to my creation—that I received the idea of one of the perfections that I attribute to God from one cause, and the idea of another from another. But this can’t be right, because God is the only thing that has all these perfections, and his simplicity—that is, the unity or inseparability of all his attributes—is one of the most important of the perfections that I understand him to have.

·Two points about this·: (a) For you to have an idea of a certain perfection, you don’t have to have been acted on by something that has that perfection. (b) Even if I am wrong about that, your idea of something that has all the perfections could be something that you put together out of your ideas of the individual perfections....You know how the poets describe Pandora! [They say that she was made out of clay by a master sculptor, and that in being made she received all perfections, as gifts from all the gods of Olympus, presumably one gift per god.] You might have acquired that idea in the following way:

You admired various people’s outstanding knowledge, wisdom, justice, steadfastness, power, health, beauty,

116

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

happiness, longevity and so on; then you put all these things together and thought how admirable it would be if one person had all these perfections at once. You then heightened all these perfections, by large steps and small, leading you to the thought that this person would be all the more admirable if his knowledge, power, duration and so on were unlimited, so that he was omniscient, omnipotent, eternal and so on. And when you saw that human nature would not admit of such perfections, you supposed that if they were all combined in one nature, that would be a blessed nature indeed. Then you thought it worth investigating whether such a being existed, and came up with certain arguments to make it seem more reasonable than not that he should exist. And that led you to exclude all bodily attributes and other limitations that imply some imperfection.

Why couldn’t your idea of God have come about in that way?.... As for the perfection of unity, there is certainly no contradiction in conceiving of all the perfections that we attribute to God as being intimately connected and inseparable; even if your ideas of them were not •placed in you by God but •derived by you from things you have seen, and then amplified etc. Pandora....is not the only example. People have also conceived of the perfect republic, the perfect orator and so on.... Although your conclusion that God exists is true, it doesn’t seem to me that you have provided a very compelling demonstration of it.

Reply
(9) When you say that we can stay in existence without the continual action of our cause, you are disputing something that all metaphysicians affirm as an obvious truth—though uneducated folk often miss it because they attend only to the causes of •coming into existence and not the causes of existence itself—·i.e. the causes of •staying in existence·. Thus

•the architect is a cause of the house, and a father is a cause of his child,

only in being the causes of their coming into being; so that once the work is completed (·the house built, the child born·) it can remain in existence with no input from this kind of cause. But

•the sun is the cause of the light it emits, and God is the cause of created things,

not just as causes of the coming-into-existence of these things, but also as causes of their existence (·i.e. their staying in existence·); so in these cases the cause must continue to act in the same way on the effect in order to keep it in existence.

This can be clearly demonstrated from what I have said about the independence of the parts of time. You try to dodge this by talking about how the parts of time, considered in the abstract, are necessarily inter-connected. But what is in question here is not that, but rather the time or duration of a thing that lasts through time; and you wouldn’t deny that each individual moment of that can be separated from its immediate predecessor and successor, which implies that the thing that lasts through time may go out of existence at any given moment. You say that we have a power that ensures that we shall continue to exist unless some destructive cause intervenes. You don’t realize that in •implying that a created thing can stay in existence independently of anything else, you are •attributing to it a perfection that only a creator can have. Similarly, in implying that •the creator could bring the existence of something to an end only by performing some positive act (thus tending towards non-being), you are •attributing to him the imperfection of a created thing.

117

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

It isn’t absurd to suppose an infinite regress, you say, but this is undermined by what you say later on. For you admit that an infinite regress is absurd in the case of ‘causes that are linked in a hierarchical way so that a cause that is lower in the chain can’t act without one that is higher’. But those are just precisely the causes that are at issue here, since we are dealing with causes of existence, not causes of coming into existence (such as parents). So you can’t set the authority of Aristotle against me here, or the stories about Pandora. You agree that I can augment—a little or a lot—all the perfections that I observe in people, until I see that ·through my augmentations· each has become a kind of perfection that can’t possibly belong to human nature; and this is all I need to demonstrate the existence of God. For I maintain and insist that if we hadn’t been created by God we wouldn’t have had this amplifying power. But I’m not surprised that you can’t see that I have given an utterly evident demonstration of this, because I can’t see that you have managed to get a correct understanding of any one of my arguments..

Objection
(10) You say this:

It remains for me only to ask how I received this idea from God. I didn’t get it from the senses; and it’s not something that I invented, either; for clearly I can’t take anything away from it or to add anything to it. The only remaining alternative is that my idea of •God is innate in me, just as the idea of •myself is innate in me.

But, I repeat, you could have partly derived it from the senses and partly made it up. When you say that you can’t add anything to it or take anything away, remember that when you first acquired it, it wasn’t as complete as it is now. Bear in mind

•that there may be men or angels or other natures more learned than you from which you may learn things about God that you don’t know now;

•that God (at least) could give you such information and instruct you so clearly, in this life or the next, that you would have to regard your present knowledge of him as worthless; and

•that we can ascend from the perfection of created things to knowledge of the perfections of God in such a way as to uncover more perfections every day.

So we can’t at any one moment possess a complete idea of God, but only one that becomes more and more complete each day. You go on as follows:

It is no surprise that God in creating me should have placed this idea in me, to serve as a mark of the craftsman stamped on his work. The mark need not be anything distinct from the work itself. But the mere fact that God created me makes it believable that I am somehow made in his image and likeness, and that I perceive this likeness in the same way that I perceive myself. That is, when I turn my mind’s eye on myself, I understand that I am a thing that is incomplete and dependent on something else, and that aspires without limit to ever greater and better things; but I also understand at the same time that he on whom I depend has within him all those greater things—not just indefinitely but infinitely, not just potentially but actually—and hence that he is God.

All your assertions here are plausible, and I don’t deny their truth; but how do you prove them? Setting aside my previous points, ·I’ll present four main difficulties about this·. (a) If the idea of God is in you like the mark of a craftsman stamped on his work, what kind of stamping is this? What is this

118

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

‘mark’ like? How do you recognize it? If it isn’t ‘distinct from the work’ or the thing itself, does that mean that you are an idea? Are you nothing but a way of thinking? Are you both •the mark that is stamped and •the subject on which it is stamped? (b) It is believable, you say, that you are made in the image and likeness of God. This is certainly believable, given religious faith; but how are we to understand it through natural reason, unless you are making God to be like a man? What could that likeness consist in? Since you are dust and ashes, can you presume that you resemble that eternal, incorporeal, immense, most perfect, most glorious and above all most invisible and incomprehensible nature? Have you known that nature face to face? Is that what enables you to compare yourself with it and say that you resemble it? (c) The fact that he created you, you say, makes it believable that you resemble him. On the contrary, this fact makes such a resemblance wholly unbelievable, because ·in general· a product is not similar to the workman who made it except when he engenders it by communicating his nature to it—·for example, when the ‘workman’ is a father and the ‘product’ is his son·. But you aren’t begotten by God in this way: you aren’t his offspring; you don’t share his nature; you are merely created by him, i.e. produced by him in accordance with an idea. You can’t resemble him, any more than a house resembles a bricklayer! This objection stands even if we grant you—though you haven’t yet proved it—that you were indeed created by God. (d) You say that you perceive the likeness when you take in that you are a thing that is incomplete and dependent, and that aspires to greater and better things. But why isn’t this rather an argument for a dissimilarity between you and God, since he is utterly complete and independent and self-sufficient, being the greatest and best of all things? ·Two further points, that I’ll mention but not discuss·. (e) When you understand yourself to be dependent, you shouldn’t immediately infer that the thing on which you depend is something other than your parents; and if you do think it is something other than them, that doesn’t explain why you should think you resemble it. (f) There is no reason why God shouldn’t be thought to have imprinted the idea of himself on everyone else as well as on you; which makes it surprising that other people •don’t have your understanding of these matters. The fact that they •don’t shows that there is no idea imprinted on us by God.... But I have already spent too much time on this topic.

Reply
(10) You attack my statement that nothing can be added to or taken away from the idea of God—so you are ignoring the common philosophical maxim that the essences of things are indivisible. An idea represents the essence of a thing, and if anything is added to or taken away from an idea then it automatically becomes the idea of something else. This is how the ideas of Pandora and of all false gods are formed by those who don’t have a correct conception of the true God. But once the idea of the true God has been conceived, although we may detect additional perfections in him that we hadn’t previously noticed, this doesn’t mean that we have added anything to the idea of God; we have simply made it more distinct and explicit. This presupposes that our original idea did contain all these perfections ·though we didn’t notice them in it·, and this presupposition must be right if the original idea was a true one. Similarly, when we become aware of various properties in the triangle of which we were previously ignorant, we aren’t adding to our idea of a triangle. Also [harking back to a part of Gassendi’s (9), on page 116]: the idea of God isn’t something that we form step by step, amplifying the perfections of his creatures; it

119

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

is formed—snap!—all at once and in its entirety as soon as our mind reaches an infinite that can’t be amplified.

(a) You ask how I prove that the idea of God is present in us like the mark of a craftsman stamped on his work. ‘What kind of stamping is this? What is this “mark” like?’ Well, suppose there is a painting in which I observe such skill that I judge that it could only have been painted by Apelles, and the following interchange occurs:

Descartes: That unmatchable technique is like a kind of mark that Apelles stamped on all his pictures to distinguish them from others. Gassendi: What kind of stamping is this? What is this ‘mark’ like?

If you did ask such a question, everyone would see you as deserving to be laughed at rather than answered.

(b) You go on as follows: ‘If it isn’t “distinct from the work” or the thing itself, does that mean that you are an idea? Are you nothing but a way of thinking? Are you both the mark that is stamped and the subject on which it is stamped?’ This doesn’t deserve an answer either. Here’s another fragment of conversation:

Descartes: The technique by which we can distinguish Apelles’s paintings from others isn’t anything distinct from the paintings themselves. Gassendi: So you are saying that the paintings are nothing but the technique; they don’t consist of any material, and are simply a way of painting.

·That would obviously be absurd, and so is the ‘distinct from the work’ jibe that you launched at me·.

(c) You deny that we are made in the image of God, and say that this would make God like a man; and you list ways in which human nature differs from the divine nature. That is about as clever as saying ‘That picture isn’t a portrait of Alexander, because it isn’t like Alexander: it is made of wood and paint, while he is composed of flesh and bones.’ An image doesn’t have to be in all respects exactly like the thing of which it is an image, but merely to resemble it in some respects; and it is clear that the wholly perfect power of thought that we understand to be in God is represented by our less perfect faculty of thought.

You compare God’s creation to •the labour of a workman rather than to •parental procreation, but you have no reason for this. Even if the three ways of acting—·divine creation, parental procreation, and manufacture·—are completely different in kind, divine creation is nevertheless more closely analogous to natural procreation than to artificial production or manufacture. But I didn’t say that we resemble God as closely as children do their parents. Also, even in manufacture there is sometimes a resemblance between the craftsman and his product, for example when a sculptor makes a statue resembling himself.

(d) You report me as saying that I perceive my likeness to God in the fact that I am an incomplete and dependent thing. That is false and quite unfair. I brought my incompleteness etc. into the discussion as evidence of a dissimilarity, so as to show that I wasn’t trying to make men equal to God. What I did say was this: •God has very great qualities; •I am inferior to him in this respect because I only aspire to have them; and •my venturing to aspire to them shows that there is in me something resembling them.

(e) Finally, you say that it is surprising that not everyone shares my understanding of God, since he imprinted the idea of himself on them just as he did on me. This is like being surprised that although everyone is aware of the idea of a triangle, people differ in what properties of it they notice, and some people may draw false conclusions about it.

[Now follows material that Descartes wrote to Clerselier in answer to Gassendi’s book; see note on page 85.]

120

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

Your friends have noted four objections against the third Meditation.

(a) ‘Not everyone is aware of the idea of God within himself.’ But if we take the word ‘idea’ in the way I explicitly announced that I was taking it (not taking refuge in ambiguity, like those who restrict ‘idea’ to images of material things formed in the imagination), then we can’t deny that we have some idea of God, unless we’re willing to say that we don’t understand the meaning of the phrase ‘the most perfect thing we can conceive of’; for that is what everyone calls ‘God’. The wish to disagree is being taken to extraordinary lengths when someone says that he doesn’t understand the meaning of one of the most ordinary expressions in common use! Also, someone who denies having any idea of God, in my sense of ‘idea’, is making the most impious confession he could make. He is saying not only that he doesn’t know God by natural reason, but also that he couldn’t get knowledge of God through faith or in any other way. The point is that someone who has no perception ·or idea· corresponding to the meaning of the word ‘God’ can’t meaningfully say ‘I believe that God exists’. One might as well say that one believes that nothing exists, thus remaining in the depths of impiety and the extremes of ignorance.

(b) Their next point is the claim that if I did have this idea, I would grasp it. [They use the verb comprendre, and this is like the Latin comprehendere—see page 113—-in involving the thought of getting one’s mind around something.] This has no basis. Since the word ‘grasp’ implies some limitation, a finite mind can’t •grasp God, who is infinite. But that doesn’t prevent it from •having a perception of God. Similarly, one can’t hug a mountain, but one can •touch it.

(c) Your friends make a point about my arguments, namely that many people have read them without being convinced by them. Well, I push back with the fact that other people have understood them and found them acceptable. We should give more credence •to one person who honestly says that he has seen or understood something than •to a thousand others who deny what he says because they haven’t been able to see or understand it. Think of the discovery of the antipodes: the report of a few sailors who had circled the earth was believed in preference to the views of those thousands of philosophers who didn’t believe the earth was round. My critics cite Euclid’s Elements, claiming that they are easy for everyone to understand, ·presumably implying that the truth needn’t be difficult·. They should remember this: among those who are regarded as the most learned experts in scholastic philosophy, not one in a hundred understands the Elements; and not one in ten thousand understands all the demonstrations of Apollonius or Archimedes, although these demonstrations are just as evident and certain as Euclid’s.

(d) Lastly, your friends say that from the fact that I recognize some imperfection in myself it doesn’t follow that God exists. So? I didn’t infer God’s existence directly from that premise alone, but brought in further considerations. Here they merely remind me of Gassendi’s habitual ploy: truncating my arguments and reporting only parts of them, so as to make them seem imperfect.

Objections to the fourth meditation

(1) You start the fourth Meditation by going over the results you think you have demonstrated in the previous Meditations—results that you expect to open the way to further progress. To speed things up, I shan’t keep insisting that you should have provided better demonstrations of these results; it will do if you remember what has been conceded and what hasn’t, so that the discussion doesn’t get dragged

121

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

into the realm of preconceived opinion.

Next you reason that it is impossible that God should deceive you; and to excuse the deceptive and error-prone faculty that God gave you, you suggest that the fault lies in nothingness. You have some idea of that, you say, and your nature involves it, because you take yourself to be something intermediate between nothingness and God. This is a splendid argument! I’ll pass over the impossibility of explaining how we have an idea of nothingness, and what kind of idea it is, and how our nature can involve it, and so on. I simply point out that this distinction ·between God and nothingness· doesn’t alter the fact that God could have given man a faculty of judgment that was immune from error. Without giving man a faculty of infinite scope—·which would clear him, according to you, of all involvement with nothingness·—God could have given him a kind of faculty that would never lead him to assent to falsehood. With that he would clearly perceive anything he did know, and would avoid taking sides in matters where he was ignorant.

When you discuss this objection, you say that it’s not surprising if you don’t understand the reason for some of God’s actions. That is right; but it is surprising that you should •have a true idea representing God as omniscient, omnipotent and wholly good, and yet •observe that some of his works are not wholly perfect. Given that he could have made things ·if not completely perfect then· at least more perfect than he did make them, this seems to show that he must have lacked either the knowledge or the power or the will to do so. He was (to put it mildly) somewhat imperfect if, having the knowledge and the power, he lacked the will and preferred imperfection to perfection.

Your •refusal to invoke final causes in physics might be right in a different context, but when you are dealing with God •it obviously creates a risk of losing touch with the principal argument that establishes by the natural light the wisdom, providence and power of God, and indeed his existence. Leaving aside the universe as a whole, the heavens and its other main parts, where can you find better evidence for the existence of such a God than in the function of the various parts in plants, animals, and man.... We have seen great thinkers being led by a study of anatomy not just to a knowledge of God but also to singing his praises for having organized all the parts and harmonized their functions in such an admirably providential way.

You will say that we should investigate the physical causes of this organization and arrangement, and that it is foolish to bring in •purposes rather than •agents or •materials. [Gassendi is here echoing the traditional notions of •final cause, •efficient cause, and •material cause. See explanatory note on page 6.] But no mere mortal can possibly understand—let alone explain—

•the agent that produces the form and arrangement we observe in the valves that serve as the openings to the vessels in the chambers of the heart.

Nor can we understand

•the source from which this agent gets the material from which the valves are fashioned, or

•how it makes them operate, or

•what organic structure it employs, or

•how it makes use of the valves, or

•what it requires to ensure that they are of the correct hardness, consistency, fit, flexibility, size, shape and position.

Since, I say, no physicist can discover and explain these and similar structures, why not at least admire their superb functioning and the indescribably great providence that has so neatly designed the valves for this function? Why not praise someone who comes to see that we have to acknowledge

122

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

some first cause that arranged these and all other things with such supreme wisdom and precise conformity with his purposes? [or ‘with its purposes’—Latin doesn’t distinguish these.]

It is rash to investigate God’s purposes, you say. This may be true of purposes that God wanted to remain hidden or ordered us not to investigate; but surely it doesn’t apply to the purposes that aren’t much trouble to discover because God has left them on display, so to speak, especially since these are purposes that will lead us to offer great praise to God whose purposes they are.

You may say that our idea of God gives us true and authentic knowledge of God and his purposes, without bringing in the purposes of things. But not everyone has your good fortune of having such a perfect idea from birth and seeing it before him with such clarity. Since there are people to whom God hasn’t granted such clear vision, you shouldn’t frown on their coming to know and glorify the craftsman through an inspection of his works. I need hardly stress that this—·I mean this attention to God’s works, and thus to the world as given through the senses·—doesn’t rule out our making use of the idea of God, since this too appears to be entirely derived from our knowledge of things in the world. Own up! Don’t you owe a great deal, if not everything, to empirical knowledge? Suppose that ever since being implanted in the body you had remained shut in with no external senses to enable you to perceive this universe of things or anything outside yourself, what progress do you think you would have made? Wouldn’t you have been absorbed in private meditation, eternally turning thoughts over and over? Answer in all honesty and tell me what idea of God and yourself you think you would have acquired under such circumstances.

Reply
(1)

I did explain quite adequately what sort of idea of nothingness we have, and how our nature involves non-being: the idea of nothingness I called a ‘•negative idea’, and I said that ‘being involved in •non-being’ simply means that we are •not the supreme being and that there are very many things that we do •not have. But you are always looking for flaws where none exist.

When you say that I ‘observe that some of God’s works are not wholly perfect’, you are plainly inventing something that I neither wrote nor thought. What I did say was that if certain things are considered as separate wholes rather than as playing a part in the world as a whole, they can appear to be imperfect.

The things you say in defence of final causes should be applied to efficient causation. The workings of the various parts of plants and animals etc. make it appropriate to admire God as their efficient cause—to recognize and glorify the craftsman through examining his works; but we can’t guess from this what purpose God had in creating any given thing. In •ethics, where it is often legitimate to employ conjectures, it may sometimes be pious to try to guess what purpose God had in mind in his direction of the universe; but in •natural science, where everything must be backed up by the strongest arguments, such conjectures are futile. Perhaps some of God’s purposes are more out in the open than others? No! They are all equally hidden in the impenetrable depths of his wisdom. And don’t tell stories about how none of us mortals can understand other kinds of cause. They are all much easier to discover than God’s purposes, and the ones that you offer as examples of the difficulties involved are in fact ones that many people consider they do know about. Finally you put to me a frank question:

123

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

What sort of idea would my mind have had of God and of itself if, ever since being implanted in the body, it had remained shut in with none of the senses functioning?

Here is my frank and honest reply:

If you mean this to be a case where my body doesn’t help and doesn’t interfere with my mind, I have no doubt that in that case my mind would have exactly the same ideas of God and itself that it actually has, the only difference being that they would have been much purer and clearer.

The senses often get in the way of the mind’s activities, and they never help in the perception of ideas. The only thing that prevents all of us being equally aware that we have these ideas is that we’re too busy perceiving the images of corporeal things.

Objection
(2) The solution that you offer is this: a created thing that appears imperfect should be considered not as a ·free-standing· whole, but as a part of the universe, and from this point of view it will be perfect. That’s an excellent distinction! But our present topic is not

•something’s functioning imperfectly as a part, or being imperfect as compared with the whole,

but rather:

•something that has a special function just in itself, and performs that function imperfectly.

And even if you bring in the thing’s relation to the universe, we can still ask: Wouldn’t the universe be more perfect than it is now if all its parts were more perfect than they are now? Thus, a republic whose citizens are all good will be more perfect than one in which most or some of them are bad.

So when you go on to say later on that the universe would be worse than it actually is if all its parts were exactly alike in being immune from error, this is like saying that a republic has somewhat more perfection if some of its citizens are bad than it would have if they were all good....

You say that you have no right to complain that the role God wanted you to play in the world isn’t the most elevated or most perfect of all. But still we have a question: why wasn’t God satisfied with assigning to you a role that was •the least elevated of the perfect roles, rather than giving you an •imperfect role? A ruler can’t be blamed for not appointing all the citizens to the highest offices, keeping some in middling or low positions; but he would be open to criticism if he not only assigned some to the lowest positions but also assigned some to jobs that were downright bad.

You say that •you can’t find any reason to prove that God ought to have given you a greater faculty of knowledge than he did; and that •you wouldn’t expect a craftsman—even a very skillful one—to put into each of his works all the perfections that he is able to put into some of them. But that doesn’t touch the objection that I have just raised. The problem doesn’t concern God’s reason for not giving you a greater faculty of knowledge, but his reason for giving you a faculty that is subject to error. I am not asking •‘Why didn’t the supreme craftsman bestow all the perfections on each of his works?’ but rather •‘Why did he bestow imperfections on some of them?’

You say that although you can’t avoid error by making yourself have a clear perception of things, you can avoid it by sticking to the rule of not assenting to anything that you don’t clearly perceive. Well, you can always keep this rule carefully in mind, but still isn’t it an imperfection that you don’t perceive clearly matters that you need to decide on, so that you are perpetually open to the risk of error?....

124

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

[Gassendi then criticises two of Descartes’s moves. (a) Saying that what is bad in my error comes from my misuse of the relevant faculty, not from the faculty itself, and thus not from God. (b) When I make a wrong judgment, there is nothing wrong with what is positive in what I do (and thus nothing wrong with anything that might involve God). My error is essentially negative—it consists in something missing—and negatives are not God’s doing. Gassendi says that each of these evades the real problem, for reasons which he eventually sums up thus:] A locksmith isn’t at fault for not making an enormous key to open a tiny box; but he is at fault if he makes a small key that won’t—or won’t easily—open the box. Similarly, God is not to be blamed for giving mere man a judging faculty that is too small to cope with everything, or even to cope with most things or with the most important things; but we can still wonder why he gave man a faculty that is uncertain, confused and inadequate even for the few matters that he did want us to decide on.

Reply
(2) All through this you assume, wrongly, that our being liable to error is a •positive imperfection, when really it is merely—in a God’s-eye view—the •privation of some greater creaturely perfection. [See note on ‘privation’ on page 51.] And your comparison between the citizens of a republic and the parts of the universe doesn’t work: the bad character of the citizens is indeed—in a republic’s-eye view—something positive; but this doesn’t carry over to man’s liability to error, or his lack of all perfections, when this is seen from the standpoint of the good of the universe. Here is a better comparison to make: •someone who thinks that there oughtn’t to have been any creatures in the world who were liable to error (i.e. who weren’t wholly perfect) can be compared with •someone who wanted the whole of the human body to be covered with eyes so as to look more beautiful (there being no part of the body more beautiful than the eye).

Your supposition that God has assigned bad roles to us, has given us imperfections, and so on, is flatly false. It is also just false that God ‘gave man a faculty that is uncertain, confused and inadequate even for the few matters that he did want us to decide on’.

Objection
(3) You next ask what is the cause of error or falsity in you. ·I accept your view that making a judgment, whether true or false, involves both the •intellect and the •will. That is·, I don’t question your thesis that

•the intellect is simply the faculty of being aware of ideas, or of apprehending things simply, without affirming or denying anything.

Nor do I dispute your view that

•the will (or freedom of choice) is a faculty whose function is to affirm or deny, to give or withhold assent.

My only question is this: why do you hold that our •will (or freedom of choice) is not restricted by any limits, while our •intellect is so restricted? It seems to me that these two faculties have an equally broad scope; certainly the scope of the intellect is at least as wide as that of the will, because the will never aims at anything that the intellect has not already perceived.

I said ‘•at least as wide’, but really the intellect’s scope seems to be •even wider than the will’s. For the will (or choice or judgment), and hence our picking on something x to be pursued or avoided, never occurs unless we have previously apprehended x, i.e. unless the idea of x has already been set before us by the intellect. ·That guarantees ‘at least as wide’; but we can strengthen it to ‘even wider’ because of two

125

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

kinds of case·. (a) We understand something only obscurely, so that we make no judgment about it, and don’t pursue or avoid it. (b) We understand something in such a way that there are reasons of equal weight on either side, or no reasons at all, so that no judgment follows.

You say that you can always understand the possibility that your faculties—including the intellect itself—could be increased more and more, so that you can form an infinite idea of intellect. But if the intellect can extend itself even to an infinite object, that alone shows that it is no more limited than the will. You say that you recognize your will to be equal to God’s—not in its extent, of course, but in its essential intrinsic nature; but surely this holds for your intellect too, since you have defined the essential notion of the intellect in the same way as you have defined that of the will. Tell us, please: can the will extend to anything that escapes the intellect? ·clearly the right answer is No·.

So it seems that error doesn’t arise in the way you say it does, from •the will’s having a greater scope than the intellect, and •its judging concerning matters that the intellect doesn’t perceive. The two faculties have equal scope; error arises from the will’s judging badly in matters that the intellect perceives badly.

You compare the question of your own existence with that of the existence of other things. You are quite right about your judgment that you exist, but you seem to have gone wrong concerning the existence of other things. For you claim—just joking, perhaps?—to doubt something that you are really in no doubt about, ·namely that there exist things other than yourself·. You already have a prior understanding of something apart from you and distinct from you, so you do judge that something apart from you and distinct from you exists. [Neither the Latin nor Clerselier’s French version yields any clue as to why Gassendi should make that inference.] What you suppose ·for purposes of argument·, namely that you haven’t yet found any convincing reason either way on this question, is indeed possible. But if it were actual, no judgment ·about the existence of other things· would follow; rather, your will would always be indifferent [= ‘evenly balanced’] and wouldn’t come down on either side until the intellect found some plausible argument that broke the tie.

You go on to say that this indifference extends to cases where you don’t have clear enough knowledge; for although probable conjectures may pull you one way, the mere knowledge that they are conjectures may push your assent the other way, ·so that there will be equilibrium and thus no judgment·. But this seems quite wrong. If your conjectures are pulling you towards judging that P, your knowledge that they are merely conjectures may, rather than inclining you to judge that not-P, merely introduce reluctance and hesitancy into your judgment that P.

You add that your point is confirmed by your experience of the last few days, when you supposed that opinions you believed to be absolutely true were false. But remember that I don’t accept that that’s what happened. You can’t really have felt or been convinced that you had never seen the sun or the earth or men and so on, or that you had never heard sounds or walked or eaten or written or spoken or performed similar activities involving the use of your body and its organs.

Finally, the essence of error seems to consist not in •the incorrect use of free will (as you maintain) but rather in •the disparity between our judgment and the thing that our judgment is about. And this seems to happen when our intellectual uptake of a thing doesn’t match how the thing really is. So the blame seems to lie not with the will for not judging correctly but with the intellect for not displaying the object correctly. The will seems to depend on the intellect

126

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

in the following way: when the intellect perceives something clearly, or seems to do so, the will makes a judgment that is approved and settled, irrespective of whether it really true or only thought to be true. But when the intellect’s perception is obscure, the will in this case will make a judgment that is doubtful and tentative, but is regarded for the time being as truer than its opposite, irrespective of whether it really accords with the truth of the matter or not. The upshot is that we have the power not so much to guard against •error as to guard against •persisting in error; and if we want to use our judgment correctly, we should not so much •restrain our will as •apply our intellect to develop clearer awareness, which our judgment will always then follow.

Reply
(3) You ask me to say briefly whether the will can extend to anything that escapes the intellect. Yes, this occurs whenever we happen to go wrong. Thus when you judge that the mind is a kind of rarefied body, you can understand •that the mind is the mind, i.e. a thinking thing, and •that a rarefied body is an extended thing; but you certainly don’t understand the proposition that it is one and the same thing that thinks and is extended. You simply want to believe it because you have believed it before and don’t want to change your view. It’s the same when you judge that an apple, which may in fact be poisoned, is nutritious: you understand that •its smell, colour and so on are pleasant, but this doesn’t mean that you understand that •it will be beneficial to eat; you judge that it will because you want to believe it. I do admit that when we direct our will towards something, we always have some sort of understanding of some aspect of it, but I deny that our understanding and our will are of equal scope. With any given object, we may have many desires but very little knowledge. And when we judge badly, it’s not that we exercise our will in a bad fashion, but that the object of our will is bad. There is no such thing as understanding in a bad fashion; when someone is said to ‘understand in a bad fashion’, what is really going on is that he wrongly judges that his understanding is more extensive than it in fact is.

[In this paragraph, Descartes writes as though defending a view of free will as involving an indifferent (= evenly balanced) will. But Gassendi hasn’t attacked any such general view.] You next deny certain propositions about the indifference of the will. But they are self-evidently true, and I’m not going to defend them by argument here. They are the sorts of things that each of us should to know by experience of his own case, rather than having to be convinced of them by rational argument. The trouble with you, Flesh, is that you apparently don’t attend to the what the mind does within itself. Enjoy your unfreedom, if that’s what you want. I am delighted with the freedom that I experience within myself. And you haven’t produced any arguments against it—merely bald denials. I affirm what I have experienced and what anyone else can experience for himself, whereas the only basis for your denial, it seems, is your not having the appropriate experience; so my own view is probably entitled to receive more widespread acceptance.

[Now Descartes comes to a thesis that Gassendi has attacked, namely that our will is free to judge that P or to judge that not-P, whatever our understanding says about it.] Anyway, your own words show that you have in fact had the experience of freedom. We can’t guard against •erring, you say, because the will can’t be directed to anything that isn’t determined by the intellect; but you admit that we can guard against •persisting in error, which we couldn’t do unless the will had the freedom to direct itself either way without the determination of the intellect—which you have just denied! ·To see the inconsistency in your position, think about what not-persisting-in-error

127

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

must involve·. Take a case where my intellect has already determined my will to make an error, i.e. to judge that P (where P is some false proposition). Now you want my will to ‘guard against persisting in error’, and I ask: what will determine my will to set up this guard?

•If the will is determined by itself ·to stand guard·, then it can after all be directed towards something without being sent that way by the intellect,

which is what you say that it can’t do, this being what we are arguing about. On the other hand,

•If the will is determined by the intellect ·to stand guard·, then it isn’t the will that is guarding against error; but the intellect.

The second case must be one where the intellect •first directs the will towards a falsehood and •then happens to undergo some change that results in its directing the will towards the truth. ·As between these two alternatives, I hold with the first: the will isn’t determined by the intellect to guard against error—and (I now add) wasn’t determined by the intellect to fall into error in the first place·. What do you think that falsity is? and how do you think it can be an object of the intellect? I understand falsity to be merely a privation of the truth, so I am sure that it is flat-out impossible for the intellect to apprehend falsity under the guise of truth; which is what would have to happen if the intellect were to determine the will to accept something false.

Objection
(4) You then conclude by exaggerating the good that this Meditation can do, and ·as a prime example of that ‘good’· you lay down a rule for arriving at the truth: you will reach the truth, you say, if you attend closely enough to all the things that you perfectly understand, and separate these from everything that you apprehend only in a more confused and obscure manner.

This is certainly true, but it could have been understood without any reference to the fourth Meditation, which seems to have been wholly superfluous. There is no problem about accepting the rule

•Don’t judge that P unless you vividly and clearly understand that P;

but there is a problem about applying that rule, i.e. about acquiring the skill or the method that will enable us to discover in a given case that our understanding is so vivid and clear as to be true and to make it impossible that we should be mistaken. As I objected at the beginning, we are often deceived even when we think we know something as vividly and clearly as anything can possibly be known. You also raised this objection against yourself, but we are still waiting for the skill or technique that I have asked for, and it is what you should be mainly working on.

Reply
(4) As for the good these Meditations can do: I did point out, in the short Preface that I think you have read, that those who don’t attend to the proper order of my arguments and the connection between them, but merely pick quarrels with individual passages, won’t get much benefit from the book. As for a method enabling us to distinguish the things that we really perceive clearly from those that we merely think we perceive clearly, I think I have provided a fairly precise one; but I expect it to be overlooked by readers who spend so little effort on shedding their preconceived opinions that they complain that I have not dealt with them in a ‘simple and brief statement’.

128

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

Objections to the fifth meditation

‘The essence of material things, and the existence of God considered a second time’ (1) You say that you distinctly imagine quantity (that is, extension in length, breadth and depth) and also number, shape, position, motion and duration. Out of all these ideas you claim to have, you select •shape, and out of all the shapes you select a •triangle, about which you say:

Even if there are not and never were any triangles outside my thought, still, when I imagine a triangle there is a determinate nature that isn’t invented by me or dependent on my mind. Consider the things that I can prove about the triangle—that its three angles equal two right angles, that its longest side is opposite its greatest angle, and so on. I am forced to agree that the triangle has these properties, even if I didn’t give them a thought when the triangle first came into my mind. So they can’t have been invented by me.

That’s all you have to say about the essence of material things; you add a few remarks, but they are part of the same argument. I shan’t raise objections here, except to murmur that the label ‘unchangeable and eternal nature’—·which you give to the nature of the triangle, just before the passage I have quoted·—doesn’t clearly fit anything except ·the nature of· almighty God.

You’ll say that what you are proposing is the standard scholastic view that the natures or essences of things—·not just of God·—are eternal, and that eternally true propositions can be asserted of them. But it is very hard to swallow: there’s no way to make sense of •there being human nature at a time when there are no human beings, or of •the rose’s being a flower (·that great ‘eternal truth’!·) at a time when not even one rose exists.

They distinguish talk about things’ •essences from talk about their •existence, and hold that although things don’t •exist from eternity their •essences are eternal. But the most important element in things is their •essence, but ·since those are eternal and therefore don’t begin·, all that God does is to produce their •existence; it isn’t a very impressive feat, is it? Isn’t it on a par with a tailor trying a suit of clothes on someone? How can people contend that the essence of man—which is in Plato, for example—is eternal and independent of God? ‘Because it is •universal’ will they say? But everything in Plato is •particular. ·Talk about ‘universals’ isn’t just nonsense·: after seeing the nature of Plato and of Socrates and similar natures of other men, the intellect abstracts from them some common concept in respect of which they all agree, and this can be regarded as a ‘universal’—the universal nature or essence of man—because it is understood to apply to every man. But it doesn’t make sense to suppose that there was a universal nature ·of man· before Plato and the others existed, and before the intellect did the abstraction.

You’ll say that the proposition ‘Man is an animal’ is eternally true, and thus true even when no man exists. But it seems not to be true, unless it is taken to mean that whenever a man exists he will be an animal. Admittedly the proposition

•Man is

does seem to be different from the proposition

•Man is an animal.

.... ·But despite the superficial difference, they come down to the same thing·. By the former we mean

•Man, the animal, is,

and by the latter we mean

•Man, while he exists, is an animal.

129

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

And another point: The proposition ‘Man is an animal’ is no more necessary than is the proposition ‘Plato is a man’, so—·on the scholastic view I am now discussing·—it follows that even ‘Plato is a man’ is eternally true, Plato’s individual essence being just as independent of God as the universal essence of man; and so on through boringly many other examples that could be given. [Gassendi further develops his view that natures/essences/universals are not free-standing components of the world, but only upshots of a certain way of thinking. ‘The ·universal· triangle’, he says, ‘is a kind of mental rule for us to use to find out whether something deserves the label ‘triangle’. Then:]

So we shouldn’t think that the properties demonstrated of material triangles—·i.e. triangular bits of matter·—are ones they have derived from the ideal ·or universal· triangle. ·The truth is the reverse of that·. The material triangles have these properties in their own right, and it’s the ideal triangle that has them only because the intellect gives them to it (after inspecting the material triangles); and they then hand them back to the material triangles again in the course of the demonstration. [And the same applies, Gassendi says, to universal human nature in relation to Plato and Socrates and you and me.]

According to you, Mind, you have the idea of triangle and would have had it even if you had never seen bodies with a triangular shape, just as you have the idea of many other shapes that have never impinged on your senses. But (I have said this before) if you had been deprived of all your sensory functions, and had never seen or touched the various surfaces and edges of bodies, you couldn’t have acquired or formed within yourself the idea of triangle or of any other shape. You do indeed have many ideas that never entered your mind via the senses; but it’s easy for you to have those, because you made them—in ways I have listed—out of other ideas that did come to you via the senses.

It would have been appropriate to say something here about the false nature of a triangle that is supposed to consist of lines that •have no breadth, •enclose an area with no depth, and •terminate in points that have no dimensions at all. But this would have taken me too far afield.

Reply
(1) You haven’t attended closely enough to how the parts of my work all fit together; I say this because you, after quoting one brief fragment, say that this is all I have to say on the topic under discussion! My own view is that the ‘fit’ of the parts is such that, for any given thesis P ·that I assert·, •everything I say before reaching that point and •most of what follows, contribute to the proof of P. So you can’t give a fair account of what I say on any topic unless you go into everything I wrote about all the other related issues.

It seems to you ‘very hard’ to accept that there is anything unchangeable and eternal apart from God. That is how it ought to seem if I was •talking about existing things, or was •proposing something as unchangeable in a way that made it independent of God. But....I do not think that the essences of things, and the mathematical truths we can know concerning them, are independent of God. Nevertheless I do think that they are unchangeable and eternal, because God willed and decreed that they should be so. Call this ‘hard’ or ‘easy’ to accept, as you will; all I need is that it is true.

The points you make against the universals of the dialecticians don’t touch me, because I don’t understand universals in the way they do. But as for the essences that we know vividly and clearly, such as the essence of a triangle or of any other geometrical figure, I can easily force you to admit that our ideas of them are not taken from particular instances, because you say here that they are false! (I suppose you

130

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

say that because they don’t square with what you’ve always thought about the nature of things!) ·Your commitment to their falsity comes up· later on [start of objections to sixth Meditation, page 135], when you say that ‘pure mathematics deals with items—including points, lines, surfaces....—that can’t exist in reality’. This implies that no triangle has ever existed, and nor has any property that we take to be essential to a triangle or to any other geometrical figure.... But unless you are maintaining that the whole of geometry is false, you can’t deny that many truths about these essences can be demonstrated; and the fact that they never change makes it right to call them ‘immutable and eternal’. Perhaps they don’t square with your suppositions about the nature of things, or with the atomic view of reality invented by Democritus and Epicurus, but that is a purely relational property of them—·on a par with having-been-forgotten-by-Pierre and being-spoken-of-by-Yvette-last-Tuesday·—which implies nothing about the essences themselves. All right, so they don’t fit •your views, but they undoubtedly conform to •the true nature of things established by God. I’m not saying that there exist substances with length but no breadth, or breadth but no depth; geometrical figures are being understood not as substances but as boundaries of substances.

Moving on now: I don’t accept the common view that the ideas of geometrical figures entered our minds via the senses. The world undoubtedly could contain figures like the ones the geometers study, but I contend that there aren’t any in our environment except perhaps ones that are too small to impinge on our senses. Most geometrical figures are composed of straight lines; but no really straight line ever affects our senses: when we examine the best candidates through a magnifying glass, we find they are irregular, with wavy curves the whole way along. Thus, when as children we first saw a triangular figure drawn on paper, that can’t have been what showed us how the true triangle studied by geometers should be conceived, because •the pencilled figure contains •the true triangle only in the way that •a rough unpolished carving contains •the finished statue of Mercury that it is going to become. Our seeing the pencilled triangle did give us the thought of a true triangle, but not in the way you think. What really happened was this: We already had the idea of the true triangle, which was easier for our mind to grasp than the more complex pencilled triangle; so when we saw the complex composite figure, what we took in was not •the figure we saw but rather •the true triangle. Compare what happens when we see a sheet of paper on which some lines have been drawn to represent a man’s face: what this produces in us is not so much the idea of •these lines as the idea of •a man. But this wouldn’t happen unless we already knew the human face from some other source, and we were more accustomed to thinking about the face than to thinking about the lines on paper.... Well, in the same way, we couldn’t recognize the geometrical triangle from the diagram on the paper unless our mind already had the idea of it from some other source.

Objection
(2) The next thing you tackle is demonstrating the existence of God. The thrust of your argument is in this passage:

On careful reflection it becomes quite evident that, just as having-internal-angles-equal-to-180° can’t be separated from the essence of a triangle, and as the idea of highlands can’t be separated from the idea of lowlands, so existence can’t be separated from the essence of God. Just as it is self-contradictory to think of highlands in a world where there are no lowlands [see note at page 10], so it is self-contradictory to think of God as not existing—that is, to think of

131

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

a supremely perfect being as lacking a perfection, namely the perfection of existence.

But the kind of comparison you are making isn’t wholly fair. It is quite all right for you to compare essence with essence, but instead of going on to compare existence with existence or a property with a property, you compare •existence with a •property. What you should have said, it seems, is that

•just as having-internal-angles-equal-to-180° can’t be separated from the essence of a triangle, so omnipotence can’t be separated from the essence of God.

Or that

•just as the existence of a triangle can’t be separated from its essence, so the existence of God can’t be separated from his essence.

If you had done this, both your comparisons would have been satisfactory, and I would have accepted both. But you wouldn’t have been showing that God necessarily exists; for a triangle doesn’t necessarily exist either, although its essence and existence can’t be actually separated. Real separation is impossible no matter how much the mind may separate them or think of them apart from each other—as indeed it can even in the case of God’s essence and existence.

I notice also you count existence as one of God’s perfections, but don’t treat it as one of the perfections of a triangle or a highland, though it could be said that in its own way it is just as much a perfection of each of these things. In fact, however, existence is not a perfection either in God or in anything else; it is that without which there are no perfections.

What doesn’t exist has no perfections or imperfections; what does exist may have various perfections, but existence won’t be one of them.... We don’t say that existence ‘exists in a thing’ as perfections do. And if a thing lacks existence, we don’t say that it is imperfect or lacks a perfection; rather, we say instead that it is nothing at all.

When you listed the triangle’s perfections you ·rightly· didn’t put existence on the list and infer from this that the triangle exists. Similarly, when you listed God’s perfections you shouldn’t have included existence among them so as to reach the conclusion that God exists, unless you wanted to beg the question [= ‘assume the thing you were trying to prove’].

You say that existence is •distinct from essence in the case of everything else but not in the case of God. But how can we •distinguish Plato’s essence from his existence, except merely in our thought? Suppose he no longer exists: where now is his essence? Surely in the case of God the distinction between essence and existence is also just like that: it is a distinction in our thought.

You then raise an objection against your argument: From the fact that you think of highlands with lowlands, or of a horse with wings, it doesn’t follow that those highlands or that horse exists; and similarly from the fact that you think of God as existing it doesn’t follow that he exists. You argue that this involves a logical mistake. It can’t have been hard to pinpoint the mistake, given that you constructed it ·to be a mistake·! But you pinpoint it by saying that it is a manifest contradiction that an existing God should not exist, while omitting to point out that the same applies in the case of a man or a horse!

But if you had taken the highlands and their lowlands, or the horse and its wings, as comparable to God and his knowledge (or his power or other attributes), then the objection would still have stood, and you’d have had to explain how it is possible for us to think of a sloping mountain or a winged horse without thinking of them as existing, yet impossible to think of a wise and powerful God without thinking of him as existing.

132

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

You say that you aren’t free to think of God without existence (that is, a supremely perfect being without a supreme perfection), in the way you are free to imagine a horse without wings. I have to add to this only the following comment. You are free

•to think of a wingless horse without thinking of the existence

that would, according to you, be a perfection in the horse if it were present; and you are also free

•to think of God as having knowledge and power and other perfections without thinking of the existence

that would complete his perfection, if he had it. Just as the horse that is thought of as having the perfection of wings isn’t therefore taken to have the existence that is (you say) a principal perfection, so thinking of God as having knowledge and other perfections doesn’t imply that he has existence. This—·i.e. the proposition that he exists·—remains to be proved. You say that existence and all the other perfections are included in the idea of a supremely perfect being, but saying that is simply asserting what should be proved, and assuming the conclusion as a premise. Otherwise—·i.e. unless you show what the relevant difference is between the idea or essence of the winged horse Pegasus and the idea or essence of God·—I can say that the idea of a perfect Pegasus contains not just the perfection of his having wings but also the perfection of existence.... Any point that you make about God in this area will be an equally good point about Pegasus, and vice versa.

You say that one can think of a triangle without thinking that it has three angles equal to two right angles, though it does, as appears afterwards when one attends to the matter; and similarly, one can think of the other perfections of God without thinking of his existence, though he does exist, as becomes clear when one attends to the fact that existence is a perfection. But look at the reply you have laid yourself open to: when we afterwards recognize that the triangle has that property, it is because it is proved by a demonstration; similarly, if we are to recognize that existence belongs to God, this too must be demonstrated. Otherwise it will be easy to ‘establish’ that anything has any property at all!

You say that the thought

(a) God has all perfections

is not on a par with the thought

(b) Within a circle all four-sided figures can be inscribed;

because (b) is false, and we can afterwards learn that a rhombus can’t be inscribed in a circle, whereas (a) is not wrong because we afterwards find that existence belongs to God. It seems to me that (a) and (b) are entirely on a par; or if they aren’t, you must show that existent God isn’t a self-contradictory concept in the way that rhombus inscribed in a circle is. I’ll pass over your other assertions, which are either •unexplained or •unproved or •disposed of by things I have already said. These include the statements that

•God is the only thinkable thing whose essence includes existence;

•It doesn’t make sense to suppose that there are two or more Gods of this kind;

•Such a God has existed from eternity and will last through eternity;

•You perceive many other attributes in God, none of which can be removed or altered.

These assertions should be looked at more closely and investigated more carefully if their truth is to be uncovered and they are to be regarded as certain, etc.

133

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

Reply
(2) I don’t see what sort of thing you want existence to be, or why it can’t be said to be a property just like omnipotence—provided we take ‘property’ to stand for any attribute, or anything that can be predicated of a thing, which is just how it should be taken in this context. (In the case of God, indeed, necessary existence really is a ‘property’ in the strictest sense of the term, since God is the only thing whose essence includes it. [The Latin and French words for ‘property’ could express the idea of what something exclusively has—a meaning that lingers on in English in the phrase ‘proper name’.]) So a triangle’s existence isn’t comparable with God’s, because existence relates differently to God’s essence from how it relates to the triangle’s.

In listing •existence among the properties belonging to the •essence of God I don’t ‘beg the question’ any more than I do when I list •having-angles-equal-to-two-right-angles among the properties belonging to the •essence of the triangle.

And it’s not true that with God as with the triangle, existence and essence can be thought of apart from one another; for God is his own existence, which isn’t so for the triangle. I don’t deny that, just as •necessary existence is a perfection in the idea of God, •possible existence is a perfection in the idea of a triangle; ·and in saying this I mean ‘perfection’ quite strictly·, for the triangle’s having this makes the idea of it superior to the ideas of chimeras, which can’t possibly be supposed to have existence. So you haven’t even slightly weakened the force of my argument at any point; you remain trapped by the logical mistake that you say I could have exposed so easily.

I have already dealt with the other points that you raise. And you are quite mistaken when you say that (a) the demonstration of God’s existence is not like (b) the demonstration that the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles. The reasoning is the same in both cases, except that the demonstration in (a) is much simpler and clearer than the corresponding demonstration (b). I pass over your remaining points: when you say that I explain nothing, you yourself are explaining and proving nothing—except that you are incapable of proving anything.

Objection
(3) Finally, you say that the certainty and truth of all knowledge depends uniquely on knowledge of the true God, without which there can be no true certainty or knowledge ·about anything·. You illustrate this point as follows:

When I think hard about triangles, it seems quite obvious to me—steeped as I am in the principles of geometry—that a triangle’s three angles are equal to 180°; and while I am attending to the proof of this I can’t help believing it. But as soon as I turn my mind’s eye away from the demonstration, then although I remember that I perceived it very clearly I can easily fall into doubt about its truth, if I am without knowledge of God. For I could convince myself that I am naturally disposed to go wrong from time to time concerning matters that I think I perceive as evidently as can be. This seems even more likely when I remember that I have often regarded as certainly true some propositions that other arguments have later led me to think false. But now I have seen that God exists, and have understood that everything else depends on him and that he isn’t a deceiver; from which I have inferred that everything that I vividly and clearly perceive must be true. So even when I am no longer attending to the arguments that led me to accept this—·i.e. to accept the proposition about triangles·—as long as I remember that I did vividly and clearly perceive it no counter-arguments can make

134

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

me doubt it. It is something that I know for certain to be true. That applies not only to this one proposition, but to anything that I remember ever having proved in geometry and the like.

Here, Sir, I accept that you are speaking seriously; and there’s nothing I can say except that I think you’ll find it hard to convince anyone that •before you had established the above conclusion about God you were less certain of these geometrical demonstrations than you were •afterwards. These proofs seem to be so evident and certain that they force us to assent to them, and once we have perceived them they don’t let the intellect remain in further doubt. So, indeed, when faced with these proofs, the mind may very well tell the evil demon to go hang himself, just as you yourself emphatically asserted that you couldn’t possibly be deceived about the proposition or inference ‘I am thinking, hence I exist’, even though you hadn’t yet arrived at knowledge of God. Of course it is quite true—as true as anything can be—that God exists, is the author of all things, and is not a deceiver; but these truths seem less evident than the geometrical proofs, as is shown by the fact that many people dispute the existence of God, the creation of the world, and so on, whereas no-one challenges the demonstrations of geometry. Will you, then, be able to convince anyone that the geometrical proofs depend for their evidence and certainty on the proofs concerning God? That would imply that such atheists as Diagoras or Theodorus can’t be made completely certain of these geometrical proofs—how are you going to convince anyone of that? And how often do you find a believer who, when asked why he is certain that the square on the hypotenuse of a right-angled triangle is equal to the squares on the other sides, will answer: ‘Because I know that God exists and cannot deceive, and that he is the source of this geometrical truth and of all other things’? Won’t such a person answer ‘Because I know and am convinced of it by an indubitable demonstration’? And how likely is it that Pythagoras, Plato, Archimedes and Euclid and the other mathematicians will answer in the God-invoking way? None of them seems to have thought about God as a way of becoming completely certain of his demonstrations! But since you are assuring us only of your own views (·so that your position doesn’t involve a large falsehood·), and since your position is in any case a pious one (·and so its falsity won’t do any harm·), there is really no reason why I should dispute what you say

Reply
(3) To set against the point you make here about Diagoras, Theodorus, Pythagoras and others, I cite the case of the sceptics who did have doubts about these very geometrical demonstrations. And I insist that they couldn’t have had such doubts if they had known the true nature of God. Moreover, you can’t show that P is better known than Q by pointing out that more people think P is true than think Q is true. What is needed to show that P is better known than Q is that people who know the true nature of both P and Q see that P is prior in the order of knowledge and more evident and more certain.

Objections to the sixth meditation

(1) I have no objection to what you say at the beginning of the sixth Meditation, namely that ‘material things, insofar as they are the subject-matter of pure mathematics, can exist’. In fact, however, material things are the topic of applied, not pure, mathematics, and pure mathematics deals with items—including points, lines, surfaces—....that can’t exist in reality. The only point that gave me pause is that here

135

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

again you distinguish between imagining and understanding. But surely, Mind, these two appear to be acts of one and the same faculty, as I have suggested above, and at most there is between them a difference of degree.

And now—take note of this!—that can be inferred from things that you yourself have said. You said earlier that ‘imagining is simply contemplating the shape or image of a bodily thing’. But in the present passage you don’t deny that understanding consists of contemplating triangles, pentagons, chiliagons, myriagons and so on; and these are shapes of corporeal things. Now comes your distinction:

Imagination involves •applying the cognitive faculty to a body.

Understanding doesn’t require this kind of •application or effort.

Thus, when you effortlessly perceive a triangle as a figure consisting of three angles, you say that you ‘understand’ it; but when you have to strain a bit to •make the figure become present to you, so to speak, to •contemplate and examine it and to •pick out the three angles distinctly and in detail, then you say you ‘imagine’ it. For example, you perceive without effort that a chiliagon is a figure with a thousand angles, but no amount of mental application or effort suffices for you to •pick its angles out or make them become present before you, so to speak, or to •see them all in detail. You are in a confused state, just as you are when dealing with a myriagon or any other shape of this sort; so you think that in the case of the chiliagon or myriagon you have understanding, not imagination.

But ·this isn’t a deep difference, as is shown by the fact that· there’s nothing to prevent you from extending your imagination to take in the chiliagon as it already takes in the triangle; and then both chiliagon and triangle would come within the scope of the understanding and of the imagination. For you do make an effort to get some sort of picture of the chiliagon with all its many angles, even though the number of angles is so large that you can’t grasp it distinctly. ·Don’t resist this line of thought by taking your understanding’s grasp of the chiliagon to be more of an achievement than it really is·. You do perceive ·or understand· that ‘chiliagon’ signifies a figure with a thousand angles, but that’s just the meaning of the word; it doesn’t follow that you •understand the thousand angles of the figure any better than you •imagine them.

·Nor is the difference between understanding and imagination a difference of kind·. As we move from triangle to quadrilateral to pentagon to hexagon... and so on through figures with more and more sides, our perception loses distinctness and gains confusedness gradually; ·which means that the difference we are considering is a difference of degree·.... When the number of sides is large enough, we can no longer clearly visualize the figure, and we don’t bother to make the mental effort to do so.

[Gassendi continues to hammer home the claim that the difference is a relatively shallow difference of degree, not a deep different of kind. In doing this, he faces Descartes with the difference between

(a) with great effort perceiving something distinctly

and

(b) easily perceiving something confusedly.

He says that Descartes has tied the understanding/imagination line to the easy/effortful distinction, so that he would have say that of the above two perceptions it is (b), the confused one, that counts as understanding. Gassendi goes on to say that Descartes’s account libels the understanding while praising the imagination; his reason for this is peculiar, and Descartes doesn’t reply to it.]

You say later on that the power of imagining, being

136

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

distinct from the power of understanding, is not a part of your essence. But how can that be, if they are one and the same power, functioning in ways that differ merely in degree?

You add that when the mind imagines, it turns towards the body, whereas when it understands, it turns towards itself and its own ideas. But what if it can’t turn onto itself or one of its ideas without at the same time turning to something corporeal or something represented by a corporeal idea? For triangles, pentagons, chiliagons, myriagons, and the other shapes or their ideas are wholly corporeal; and when the mind understands them it has to attend to them as corporeal or quasi-corporeal objects. As for the ideas of supposedly immaterial things—God, an angel, the human soul or mind—our ideas even of these are corporeal or quasi-corporeal, because (I repeat) those ideas are derived from the human form and from other things that are very rarefied and simple and hard to perceive with the senses, such as air or ether. There is no need to spend time on your statement that it is only probable that bodies exist, because you can’t have meant this seriously.

Reply
(1) I have already dealt with your denial of the statement that material things exist in so far as they are the subject-matter of pure mathematics.

It is false that our understanding of a •chiliagon is confused. Many properties can be very vividly and clearly demonstrated of it, and this couldn’t happen if we perceived •it only confusedly or (as you claim) only in a verbal way. We have in fact a clear •understanding of the whole figure, although we can’t •imagine all of it all at once. And this shows clearly that understanding doesn’t differ merely in degree from imagining; they are two quite different kinds of mental operation: in understanding the mind employs only itself, while in imagination it contemplates a bodily form. And although geometrical figures are wholly corporeal, this doesn’t entail that the ideas through which we understand them count as corporeal (unless they fall under the imagination).

Lastly you say that the ideas of God, an angel, and the human mind ‘are corporeal or quasi-corporeal, because they are derived from the human form and from other things that are very rarefied and simple and hard to perceive with the senses, such as air or ether’. Only you, Flesh, would say such a thing! In fact, if anyone represents God or the ·human· mind to himself in that way, he’s trying to imagine something unimaginable; all he will succeed in doing is to form a corporeal idea to which he falsely assigns the name ‘God’ or ‘the mind’. A true idea of the mind contains only thought and its attributes, none of which is corporeal.

Objection
(2) You next discuss the senses, starting with a fine survey of the things you had previously taken in through the senses and, with nature alone as your judge and guide, believed to be true. Then you report the experiences that so shook your faith in the senses that you backed off into the position we saw you take up in the first Meditation. I don’t want to start an argument here about the truthfulness of the senses. There is deception or falsity, but it’s not to be found in the senses: they are quite passive, and report only appearances that have to appear in the way their causes make them appear. Any error or falsity is in the judgment, in the mind, which •isn’t cautious enough and •doesn’t notice such facts as that things at a distance....appear smaller and more blurred than when they are nearby. Still, deception does occur, and we mustn’t deny it. The only tough question is this: Does deception occur all the time, making it impossible

137

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

for us ever to be sure of the truth of anything we perceive by the senses?

We don’t have to look far for obvious examples ·of deception·. With regard to the cases that you put forward as problematic, all I have to say is that it seems to be quite uncontroversial ·and unproblematic· that when we look at a tower from nearby, and touch it, we are sure that it is square, although when we were further off we judged it to be round or at least weren’t sure what its shape was.

Similarly the feeling of pain that seems to occur in the foot or hand after it has been amputated may sometimes give rise to deception, because the spirits responsible for sensation have been accustomed to pass into the limbs and produce a sensation in them. [Gassendi says that there is nothing deceptive about pain-location for people who are not amputees. He then turns to dreaming, and says that while we are awake we can’t wonder whether we are awake or asleep. He continues:] Thus, although we can see ourselves as naturally open to deception even when the truth seems utterly certain, we can nonetheless see ourselves as having a natural capacity for arriving at the truth. We are sometimes deceived—we don’t spot the logical fallacy, we don’t realize that the stick is partially immersed in water—but we also sometimes have an understanding of the truth: a geometrical demonstration comes clear, the stick is taken out of the water; and in these cases there can be no doubt about the truth. And even in cases where there is room for doubt, at least there is no room for doubt that things appear to us in such and such a way: it has to be wholly true that they appear as they do.

Reason may persuade us not to accept much of what nature pushes us into believing, but it can’t take away the truth of the appearances or of what the Greeks called ‘the phenomena’. Is •reason’s relation to sensory impulses analogous to •the right hand’s holding up the left when it is failing through fatigue? or is some other analogy more appropriate? We don’t have to go into that!

Reply
(2) This clearly shows that you are relying entirely on your view (long held and never cured) that we suspect falsity only in situations where we have previously found it, so that if a tower appears square when we look at it from close up and touch it, we are sure that it is square. You also maintain that when we are awake, we can’t wonder whether we are awake or asleep, and so on. But why should you think that you have already noticed all the circumstances in which error can occur? Anyway, it is easy to prove that you are sometimes mistaken about something that you accept as certain. But when you come round to saying that at least there is no room for doubt that things appear to us as they do, you are back on the right road: I said exactly this in the second Meditation. But our present topic is the truth about the things located outside us, and you haven’t said anything true about this.

Objection
(3) You next come to the task you have set yourself, though your approach to it looks like a light skirmish ·rather than a weighty intellectual battle·. You say: ‘But now, when I am beginning to know myself and my maker better, although I don’t think I should recklessly accept everything I seem to have acquired from the senses, neither do I think it should all be called into doubt.’ That’s quite right, but it’s not a new thought: you must have had it before ·starting to know yourself and your maker better·. You continue:

First, I know that if I have a vivid and clear thought of something, God could have created it in a way that exactly corresponds to my thought. So the fact that I

138

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

can vividly and clearly think of one thing apart from another assures me that the two things are distinct from one another, since they can be separated by God. Never mind how they could be separated; that doesn’t affect the judgment that they are distinct

One could complain that you should first have shown that •God exists and •how powerful he is, on the way to showing that he can bring about anything that you are capable of understanding; but I shan’t linger on that. The one thing that has to be said about the above passage is that in it you are using something •obscure to prove something •clear (I’m not suggesting that the inference itself contains any obscurity). Consider these two properties of the triangle:

•its longest side is opposite its biggest angle;

•its three angles are equal to two right angles.

Do you understand the first of those properties separately from ·your understanding of· the second? ·Presumably you do·. And do you infer from this that God could separate the two properties, enabling the triangle to have one of them not the other....?

But I shan’t press this point, because the separation ·of mind from body that you insist on· really doesn’t matter much.... Here is the conclusion you come to:

I know that I exist and that nothing else belongs to my nature or essence except that I am a thinking thing; from this it follows that my essence consists solely in my being a thinking thing, even though there may be—and we’ll see soon that there certainly is—a body that is very closely joined to me. I have a vivid and clear idea of •myself as something that thinks and isn’t extended, and one of •body as something that is extended and doesn’t think. So it is certain that •I am really distinct from •my body and can exist without it.

So this is the conclusion you were rushing towards? [In accusing Descartes of ‘rushing’, Gassendi may be joking at his own expense. His comments on the Meditations are 20% longer than the work itself; and he has recently pointed to three places (one in a passage omitted from this version) where he could, but chooses not to, make them longer still by raising further problems.] It is the source of our main difficulties here, so we should ·slow down a little and· try to see how you manage to establish it. The crucial thing is the distinction between •you and •body. What body are you talking about? Obviously, ·you are referring to· this solid body made up of limbs ·and bones and organs etc.·—the one you are no doubt referring to when you say ‘I have a body that is joined to me’ and ‘It is certain that I am distinct from my body’ and so on.

But, Mind, there’s no difficulty about this body. There would be a problem if... [and then he gives some details of views philosophers have held according to which the mind is somehow adjectival on the body, i.e. is a state or condition of the body. None of this is relevant to Descartes, he remarks. Then:] The difficulty that arises for you is not about whether you are separable from this body (which is why I have suggested that you didn’t need to appeal to God’s power to establish that things which you understand apart from each other are separate). Rather, the difficulty concerns the body that you are: ·for all you have said to the contrary, perhaps it isn’t the bones-and-organs body of which I have just spoken·; it may instead be a rarefied body [see note on page 88] that is spread all through this solid ·lumpy· one, or is segregated within some part of it. Anyway, you haven’t yet convinced us that you are something wholly incorporeal, ·something that has none of the features of a body·. When in the second Meditation you declared that you are not a wind, fire, air or breath, I warned you that you had asserted this without any proof.

139

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

You said there that you weren’t arguing about these things at that stage; but you never went on to discuss them, and you never gave any sort of proof that you aren’t a body of this ·rarefied· sort. I had hoped that you would now offer one; but what discussion and proof you do offer simply establishes that you are not this solid ·bones-and-organs· body, and I repeat that there is no difficulty about that.

Reply
(3) I shan’t stop to deal with your tedious and repetitious assertions, such as that I didn’t prove various truths that in fact I had demonstrated, that I discussed only this solid body when in fact I dealt with every kind—even the most rarefied kind of body. Faced with assertions like those, offered without supporting argument, all I can do is to offer a flat denial. But just in passing, I would like to know your basis for saying that I dealt with this solid ·bones-and-organs· body and not with rarefied ones. You seem to base it on my saying ‘I have a body that is joined to me’ and ‘It is certain that I am distinct from my body’; but I don’t see why these remarks shouldn’t apply to a rarefied body just as well as to a solid one. Your understanding of the remarks is one that no-one else will share. Anyway, in the second Meditation I did show that the mind can be •understood as an existing substance even on the •supposition that no body exists—including no wind or fire or vapour or breath or any other body, however thin and rarefied. But whether this substance (·the mind·) is actually distinct from any body whatsoever is something that I said I wasn’t arguing about at that point; I discussed and demonstrated this claim in the sixth Meditation. But evidently you have altogether failed to understand any of this, since you run together •the question of what we can understand this substance to be and •the question of what it really is.

Objection
(4) ‘But’, you say, ‘on the one hand I have a vivid and clear idea of myself as a thinking, non-extended thing; and on the other hand I have a distinct idea of body as an extended, non-thinking thing.’ I don’t think that the ‘body’ part of this need give us much trouble. If you are referring to the idea of ‘body’ in its broadest sense, then I say again that you haven’t yet proved that no body (·in that most general sense·) can be capable of thought....

But ·I don’t think that that is what you are saying·. I am pretty sure that what you are claiming to be distinct and separable from is only this solid ·bones-and-organs· body, ·so that you aren’t committed to the view that rarefied matter can’t think·. What I question in this is not whether you have an idea of this body so much as how you could have it if you really were an unextended thing. Tell me, how do you think that you, an unextended subject, could receive the image or idea of a body, which is something extended? Whether the image comes from a body or from some other source, it can’t represent a body unless it is itself extended, having parts located beside other parts. If it doesn’t have parts, how will it represent parts? [Gassendi repeats this challenge with ‘extension’, ‘shape’, ‘spatial orientation’, and ‘various colours and so on’. Then:] It seems, then, that your idea of body is in some way extended. But if that is so, how can you, if you are unextended, have become its subject? ·That is, how can an unextended substance have an idea that is extended· How will you adapt it to yourself? make use of it? gradually experience its fading and disappearing?

Regarding your idea of yourself, I have nothing to add to what I have already said, especially concerning the second Meditation. What came out of that was the point that you, far from having a vivid and clear idea of yourself, have no idea of yourself. Why? Because although you recognize that

140

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

you are thinking, you don’t know what kind of thing you, who are thinking, are. You are aware of this operation ·of thinking·, but the most important element is still hidden from you, namely the substance that does the thinking. This prompts the thought that you’re like a blind man who, on feeling heat and being told that it comes from the sun, thinks he has a vivid and clear idea of the sun because if he is asked what the sun is he can reply ‘It is a thing that heats’.

But I should add that you have something else to say about yourself. You say that

•you are a thinking thing

and also that

•you are not extended.

This is still open to question because you haven’t proved it, but I’ll let that pass. Just tell me: does this give you a vivid and clear idea of yourself? You say that you aren’t extended—that is, you say what you are not, not what you are. To have a vivid and clear idea (i.e. a true and authentic idea) of something, doesn’t one have to know the thing positively, to know something one could affirm concerning it? Or is it enough to know that it is not some other thing? Would someone have a vivid and clear idea of Bucephalus if all he knew about Bucephalus was that he wasn’t a fly? [Bucephalus was Alexander the Great’s horse.]

I’ll drop that point now, and ask you something else. You say you are an unextended thing, but aren’t you diffused all through the body? I don’t know how you will answer this. From the start I gathered that you were in the brain, but I •didn’t find you saying this explicitly, and •arrived at it by inference from something you did say, namely that you are ‘not affected by all parts of the body, but only by the brain—or only one small part of it’. But this didn’t really settle the question. You could have meant that you are present only in the brain (or a part of it), but you instead have meant that although present all through the body you are affected only in one part of it—just as we commonly say that the soul is diffused throughout the whole body but sees only in the eye.

A similar doubt was raised when I read ‘the whole mind seems to be united to the whole body’. In that remark you don’t outright say that you are united to the whole body, but you don’t deny it either. Whatever you meant to be saying, let’s see where we get if we take it that you are diffused all through the entire body. Now I ask: given that you •stretch from head to foot, •have the same extent as the body and •have parts corresponding to all its parts, are you really unextended? (This question doesn’t presuppose any view about what you are—i.e. whether you are a soul, or something else.) If you reply—·as a scholastic might·—that you are unextended because you are wholly in the whole body and wholly in every part of it, I ask What do you mean by that? Can one thing exist in its entirety in several places at the same time? Our faith tells us that this is true in the case of the sacred mystery of the Eucharist [see pages 74–7 above]. But ·we aren’t invoking •faith in discussing •a sacred mystery·; we are using •the natural light in discussing •a natural object, namely you. [Gassendi spells out somewhat the impossibility of a thing’s being wholly in one place and at the same time wholly in another. Then:]

So let us now explore instead the thesis that you are in the brain alone, or just in one small part of it. You’ll see that the same awkwardness arises. For any part, however small, is still extended, and since your extent is the same as its extent, you are extended too. Will you say that you take the ‘part’ in question to be a point? This is surely incredible, but never mind—let’s run with it. If it is a •physical point, the difficulty remains, because a physical point is extended and has parts. Then is it a •mathematical point? Well, as

141

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

you know, mathematical points ·aren’t real things; they· are purely imaginary. But I’ll go along with—and explore—the fiction that you are joined to and exist in a mathematical point in the brain. See what a useless fiction this turns out to be! [Gassendi easily finds problems for this ‘fiction’. (a) Information from nerves requires that different nerves intersect, and they intersect at difference places and never at a mathematical point. (b) A mind tied to mathematical point couldn’t get any sense of where a given signal comes from. And on the output side he mentions several problems that all rely on his assumption that only a body can make a body move, so that an unextended mind couldn’t initiate or even steer movements of the body, and nor could a non-part of the brain that was a mathematical point. Then:]

But why should I spend time on this when really it is up to you to prove that you are an unextended and hence incorporeal thing? Here is something you might say (though I think you won’t):

Man is commonly said to consist of ‘a body and a rational soul’, ·and thus to have two parts, of which· one is a body, so the other isn’t.

If you do say that, I’ll offer the following reply:

Man consists of two kinds of body, a solid ·bones-and-organs· one and a rarefied one. The common name ‘body’ is used for the former of these, while the latter is called the ‘soul’.

....So, you see, I agree with your confident conclusion that

•you are really distinct from •your body;

but I don’t infer from this that you are incorporeal, because I take it to mean that

you (•the rarefied body that is your mind) is really distinct from •your more solid ·bones-and-organs· body.

You add that therefore you ‘can exist apart from the body’. Well, yes of course you can—just as the vapour carrying the smell of an apple can exist outside the apple!—but what makes that interesting? Well, ·it isn’t entirely trivial, because· it gives you a position different from the philosophers who think that you will wholly perish when you die [what follows expands Gassendi’s wording in ways that small dots can’t easily convey]:

Your mind is ‘the form of’ your body; that is, it is adjectival upon your body; for you to have a mind of such and such a kind is for your body to be disposed to behave thus and so. So when your body dies, you—i.e. your mind—will go out of existence, becoming nothing. In the same way, when a spherical object is squashed flat its sphericalness goes right out of existence, becomes nothing.

But on your view (as I am supposing it to be) that you (your mind) is some rarefied matter, the death of your solid ·bones-and-organs· body doesn’t imply the immediate annihilation of your mind. Your bodily death might bring with it a dispersal of your mind—·like a gust of wind dispersing smoke·—but your mind will still exist in a scattered form, i.e. will still exist because all its parts would still exist. Because of its dispersal it couldn’t still count as being a thinking thing, a mind, or a soul, ·but wouldn’t be outright annihilated·.

In raising all these objections I am not casting doubt on your intended conclusion, merely expressing reservations about your argument for it.

Reply
(4) You ask how, in my view, an unextended subject like me could receive the image or idea of an extended body. I answer that the mind doesn’t receive any corporeal image; no such image is involved in the •pure understanding of corporeal or incorporeal things. It’s true that •imagination—which

142

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

can only have corporeal things as its object—does need an image that is a real body.The mind applies itself to this image—·turns its attention towards it·—but it ·into itself·.

I can easily answer your point about the idea of the sun that a congenitally blind man gets merely from the sun’s heat. The blind man can have a vivid and clear idea of the sun as •something that gives heat, without having any idea of it as •something that gives light. Your comparison between me and the blind man fails ·in two ways·.

(a) We know ever so much more about •a thinking thing than the blind man knows about a ‘heating thing’—indeed we know more about •that than we do about anything else whatsoever, as I showed in the appropriate place.

(b) The only people who can prove that the blind man’s idea of the sun doesn’t contain everything that can be perceived regarding the sun are those who have eyesight and can detect the sun’s light and shape as well as its heat. But you, far from knowing more of the mind than I do, know less; so in this respect you are more like the blind man, while the worst that can be said of me is that my vision is somewhat impaired—like that of the rest of the human race!

When I added that the mind is not extended, I didn’t mean to be explaining what the mind is, merely pointing out that those who think it is extended are wrong. [This next bit is peculiar. Cottingham is surely right: when Gassendi wrote that Bucephalus wasn’t a fly (musca), Descartes misread this as musica = ‘music’.] In the same way, if anyone said that Bucephalus was music, it would be perfectly worthwhile for someone else to say that this was false. You go on to argue that the mind makes use of an extended body and is therefore extended itself. That is no better than arguing that Bucephalus neighs and whinnies, thus producing sounds related to music, and is therefore himself music! The mind’s being united to the whole body doesn’t require it to be extended; it’s not in its nature to •be extended, only to •think. And the mind doesn’t understand extension by containing an extended image, though it does imagine extension (as I have explained) by turning its attention to a corporeal image. Finally, it just isn’t true that the mind couldn’t move a body without itself being a body.

Objection
(5) As your discussion continues, you make many points that are relevant ·to your main thesis·, and I won’t stop to deal with all of them. One passage that strikes me is this:

Nature also teaches me, through these sensations of pain, hunger, thirst and so on, that I am not merely in my body as a sailor is in a ship. Rather, I am closely joined to it—intermingled with it, so to speak—so that it and I form a unit. If this were not so, I—who am nothing but a thinking thing—wouldn’t feel pain when the body was hurt but would perceive the damage in an intellectual way, like a sailor seeing that his ship needs repairs. And when the body needed food or drink I would intellectually understand this fact instead of (as I do) having confused sensations of hunger and thirst. These sensations are confused mental events that arise from the union—the intermingling, as it were—of the mind with the body.

All this is quite right, but you still have to explain... [and Gassendi launches into a series of challenges, centring on these two: (a) an unextended mind couldn’t be ‘intermingled’ with an extended body; (b) an unextended mind and an extended body couldn’t combine to form a ‘unit’. Union requires contact, Gassendi says, and an unextended mind can’t be in contact with anything else. Then:]

You admit that you feel pain—how do you think it’s possible for you to have this sensation if you are incorporeal

143

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

and unextended? The only understanding we have of pain is this: pain comes from the action of something that pushes into the body and separates its components, breaking up their continuity. Pain is an unnatural state; but how can something that is by its nature homogeneous, simple, indivisible and unchangeable get into an unnatural state or be acted on unnaturally? And another point: pain either is an alteration or involves an alteration, but something can’t be altered if it has no more parts than a point, and hence can’t change Why not? Because if something that has no parts alters its nature, it is thereby reduced to nothing. [Gassendi then adds a final point: if the mind didn’t have parts, it couldn’t sense pains as coming from different parts of the body.]

Reply
(5) Your remarks about the union of the mind with the body are like some of your earlier ones. You don’t come up with any objections to my arguments; you merely air some doubts that you think arise from my conclusions, though their real source is your own desire to bring the imagination in on matters that aren’t within its proper province. An example is your attempt to compare the intermingling of mind and body with the intermingling of two bodies; I need only say that we oughtn’t to make such a comparison, because mind/body is quite different in kind from body/body. And we shouldn’t imagine that the mind •has parts on the grounds that it •understands parts in the body. Whatever the mind understands must be in the mind—where did you get that from? If it were right, a mind that understands the size of the earth must have that size—so far from being unextended!

Objection
(6) I’ll pass over the remainder of your long and elegant discussion, where you set about showing that something exists besides yourself and God. You deduce that your body and bodily faculties exist, and that there are other bodies that •pass their image along to your senses and to yourself, and •produce the feelings of pleasure and pain that give rise to your desires and aversions.

Here is the result you get from all this: ‘So far as bodily well-being is concerned, my senses usually tell the truth.’ And you infer from this that you ‘should have no more fears about the falsity of what my senses tell me every day’. And you go on to say that ‘dreams are never linked by memory with all the other actions of life as waking experiences are’; and you thus establish that you are encountering real objects and are not asleep but awake. You then say that ‘From the fact that God isn’t a deceiver it follows that in cases like this I am completely free from error’. This is a very pious statement, and your final conclusion that human life is subject to error and we must ‘acknowledge the weakness of our nature’ is certainly an excellent one.

These, sir, are the thoughts that came into my mind when studying your Meditations. As I said at the outset, you have no reason to worry about them, because my powers of judgment aren’t strong enough for my views to have any value for you. When some dish pleases my palate but I see others don’t like it, I don’t defend my taste as being more perfect than theirs; and similarly, when an opinion appeals to me but not to others, I don’t conclude that I have come closer to the truth than they have. I agree with the common saying that ‘Everyone regards his own opinions as more than adequate’! Wanting everyone to have the same opinion is no more reasonable than wanting everyone’s tastes to coincide. I say this to assure you that so far as I’m concerned you should feel free to brush off all my comments as worthless. I’ll be sufficiently rewarded if you recognize my strong affection for you, and accept that I have great respect

144

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

for your powers. When expressing disagreements one tends to say things too bluntly; if any of my comments are like that, I wholly retract them and ask you to blot them out. My chief aim has been to do you some service and to keep my friendship with you safe and in good repair.

Reply
(6) Here you don’t contradict me on any point, although you still have a great deal to say! This shows the reader that he shouldn’t judge how many •arguments you have from how many •words you produce.

In this long discussion between Mind and Flesh, Mind has disagreed with Flesh on many points, as was only to be expected. But now, as I come to an end, I recognize the true Gassendi, admire him as an outstanding philosopher, and embrace him as a man of intellectual honesty and moral integrity whose friendship I’ll always try to deserve by any acts of kindness I can perform. Please don’t take it hard that I have used a philosopher’s licence in refuting his objections, since everything he has said has given me great satisfaction. Among other things, I have been delighted that such a celebrated writer hasn’t been able, in the whole course of his long and careful essay, to produce a single reasoned objection to my arguments (or even my conclusions) that I haven’t been able to answer with great ease.

[Now follows material from Descartes’s letter to Clerselier, mainly answering Gassendi’s book; see note on page 85.] At the end my critics—·your friends·—add a thought that I don’t think Gassendi included in his book, though it is very similar to his objections. They say that many very able people think they clearly see that •mathematical extension, which I lay down as the fundamental principle of my physics, is merely •my thought—that it doesn’t and can’t exist outside my mind, being merely something I achieve by abstraction from physical bodies. From this they infer that the whole of •my physics ‘must be imaginary and fictitious, as indeed must be the whole of pure mathematics, whereas •real physics, dealing with things created by God, requires the kind of matter that is real, solid and not imaginary’. Here is the objection of objections! The doctrine of those ‘very able people’, in a nutshell! All the things that we can understand and conceive are, according to them, only imaginings and fictions of our mind that can’t really exist, which implies that nothing that we can in any way understand, conceive, or imagine should be accepted as true. So if we are to deserve a place among these great minds, we must slam the door on reason, and content ourselves with being •monkeys or •parrots rather than men. For if the things we can conceive must be rejected as false merely because we can conceive them, our only remaining option is to accept as true only things that we don’t conceive; so we’ll have to construct our doctrines out of those things,

•imitating others without knowing why, like monkeys, and

•uttering words whose sense we don’t in the least understand, like parrots.

But I have some consolation: my critics here link my physics with pure mathematics, which I desire above all that it should resemble. They add two further questions at the end:

•How can the soul move the body if it isn’t itself in any way material?

•How can the soul receive the image of corporeal objects?

These questions provide an occasion for me to point out that Gassendi was being quite unfair when, pretending to object to my views, he asked many such questions that don’t need to be answered in order to prove what I asserted in my

145

Objections and Replies René Descartes Fifth Objections (Gassendi)

writings. Ignorant people can in fifteen minutes ask more questions of this kind than a wise man could answer in a lifetime; and that’s why I am not answering either of them. To answer them would require, amongst other things, an account of how the soul is united with the body, which I haven’t yet dealt with at all. But I will say—just to you ·and without thinking of my critics·—that those two questions ·are pointers to a ‘problem’ that doesn’t exist because it· assumes something that is false and can’t in any way be defended, namely that two substances whose natures are different (like the soul and the body) can’t act on each other. ·To see how silly it is to assume this as something to be taken for granted, consider the fact that· those who admit the existence of real accidents such as ·individual instances of· heat, weight and so on [see note on page 78] have no doubt that these accidents can act on the body; yet there is much more of a difference between them and it, i.e. between accidents and a substance, than there is between two substances ·such as mind and body·.

146

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

Sixth Objections (Mersenne and others) and Descartes’s replies

[In the contemporary French translation of the work, done by Descartes’s friend Clerselier who was presumably well informed, the Sixth Objections are said to be by ‘various philosophers, theologians, and geometricians’.]
After a very careful reading of your Meditations and of your replies to the objections so far raised, we find there are still some difficulties remaining, which it is only fair to ask you to remove. (1) From the fact that •we are thinking it doesn’t seem to be entirely certain that •we exist. For you can’t be certain that you are thinking unless you know •what thinking is, and ·you can’t be certain that you exist unless you know· •what your existence is; and you don’t yet know either of these things, so how can you know that you are thinking or that you exist? You say ‘I am thinking’ and then you go on to say ‘therefore, I exist’, but in neither of these do you really know what you are saying. Indeed, you don’t even

know that you are saying or thinking anything,

since this seems to require that you should

know that you know what you are saying;

which in turn requires that you

be aware of knowing that you know what you are saying,

and so on ad infinitum. Hence it is clear that you cannot know whether you exist or even whether you are thinking.

Reply
(1) It is true that no-one can be certain that he is thinking or that he exists unless he knows what thought is and what existence is. But this doesn’t require •reflective knowledge—·i.e. knowledge gained by looking into one’s own mind·—or •knowledge through demonstrations; still less does it require •knowledge of reflective knowledge, i.e. knowing that we know, and knowing that we know that we know, and so on ad infinitum, this being a kind of knowledge that can’t possibly be had about anything. All that is required is to know it by the internal awareness that always precedes reflective knowledge. This inner awareness of one’s thought and existence is so innate in all men that we can’t help having it. Some people tell themselves (and us) the story that they don’t have it, but they are folk who are up to their ears in preconceived opinions and pay more attention to words than to their meanings. In fact, when anyone notices that he is thinking and that it follows from this that he exists, even though he may never before have asked what thought is or what existence is, he can’t not know enough of both to meet the requirements.

Distinctness of mind from body

Objection
(2) When you say that you •are thinking and that you •exist, it might be maintained that what you are doing is not •thinking, but merely moving; and that ·you don’t •exist, meaning that you aren’t a thing or substance that exists, because· you are nothing but corporeal motion. For no-one has managed to understand your ‘demonstration’ that what you call thought can’t be a kind of corporeal motion. Have you used your method of analysis to slice up the motions of that rarefied matter of yours so finely that you can be certain that it is self-contradictory that our thoughts should be reducible to these corporeal motions? Can you make us certain of this? We’ll attend closely ·to anything you say·,

147

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

and our powers of perception are, we think, reasonably keen.

Reply
(2) [This paragraph expands what Descartes wrote—not drastically, but in ways that can’t easily be indicated by small dots.] When someone who knows what motion is notices that he is thinking, it simply can’t happen that he believes that he is mistaken and is ‘not thinking but merely moving’. His idea or notion of •thought is quite different from his idea of •corporeal motion, so he must understand each as different from the other. Still, he often ascribes many different properties to a single subject, without being aware of any connection between them; so he may wonder whether—or even believe that—he is a single subject that •thinks and also •moves. To evaluate this question or belief of his, we have to attend to the fact that when we have an idea of x and a quite different idea of y, there are two different things we might mean when say that ‘x is y’: we may be speaking of

(a) the unity or identity of their nature,

or we may be speaking of

(b) their unity of composition.

(a) Our ideas of shape and of motion are not the same, nor are our ideas of understanding and volition, But we clearly perceive that a substance that is capable of having a shape is also capable of being moved; and so it can happen that spherical x and rotating y are one and the same in virtue of a unity of nature. Similarly with understanding and willing: thoughtful x and ambitious y are one and the same in virtue of a unity of nature. (b) Our ideas of bones and of flesh are not the same; but these differ in such a way that we can’t take bony x to be fleshy y in virtue of a unity of nature. If we are to say ‘x is y’ we should be asserting only a unity of composition, based on the fact that a single animal has those bones and has that flesh. Now I have looked at two different sorts of case:

(a) shape and motion
     understanding and willing

(b) flesh and bones.

Into which of these two categories should we put

thought and extension?

Can we rightly say that thinking x is extended y by virtue of a unity of nature? Do thought and extension (a) have the same kind of affinity or connection that we find between shape and motion, or understanding and volition? Or is it rather that (b) when we say ‘thinking x is walking y’ we ought to mean this to hold in virtue of unity of composition, simply because the thought and extension are found in the same man, just as bones and flesh are found in the same animal? I maintain that the right answer is (b), because I find an extended thing to be so utterly different from a thinking thing—at least as different as bones are from flesh.

You go on to say that no-one has been able to grasp this demonstration of mine. I can’t let that stand, because it may get in the way of the truth ·by persuading people not to take the argument seriously·. I reply: so far, only a few people have examined the demonstration, and several of them have said that they do understand it. ·Who should be relied on—they or you?· One witness who has sailed to America, and says that he has also seen the antipodes, is more entitled to be believed than a thousand others who have no knowledge of America or the antipodes and therefore deny that they exist! Similarly, those who put a proper value on reasoning will have more respect for the authority of •one person who says he has understood a proof correctly than for •a thousand others who claim—with no reasons—that it can’t be understood by anyone. Their failure to understand the argument doesn’t imply that others can’t understand it;

148

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

and their thinking that it does imply this—i.e. thinking that if they can’t understand it, it must be unintelligible—shows that they are sloppy in their thinking and don’t deserve to have their views accepted.

Lastly, my critics ask whether I have used my method of analysis to sort out all the motions of that rarefied matter of mine. Is this (they ask) what makes me certain ·that nothing extended can think·? If so, can I show my critics, who are most attentive and (they think) reasonably perceptive men, that it is self-contradictory that thought should be reduced to corporeal motions? By ‘reduced’ I take it that they mean that thought and corporeal motions are one and the same. I reply that I’m very certain about this, but I can’t guarantee that others can be convinced of it, however attentive they may be, and however sharp-minded they think they are! I can’t guarantee that they will be convinced, at least while they focus their attention not on objects of pure understanding but only on objects of the imagination ·and the senses·. You must have misdirected your attention in this way if you imagine that the way to distinguish thought from motion is by conceptually slicing up some kind of rarefied matter! The only way of understanding the distinction is by taking in that (a) the notions of •a thinking thing and of •an extended or mobile thing are completely different, and independent of each other; and (b) that it is self-contradictory to suppose that things that we clearly understand as different and independent couldn’t be separated, at least by God, ·and (c) if x could be separated from y, then x is distinct from y·. Thus, however often we find such a pair of properties in one and the same subject—e.g. finding thought and corporeal motion in the same man—we ought not to infer that they are one and the same in virtue of a unity of nature, but should regard them as the same only in respect of unity of composition.

Animal thought

Objection
(3) Several of the Church Fathers believed, as did the Platonists, that •angels are corporeal (from which the Lateran Council inferred that they can be depicted); and they took exactly the same view of the •rational soul, some of them maintaining that ·its corporeal nature can be seen from the fact that it· is passed on from parents to child in procreation. Yet they still maintained that •angels think, and that •the soul thinks. They seem to have thought that this could occur by means of corporeal motions, or even that angels are themselves corporeal motions—which they didn’t in any way distinguish from thought. There is confirmation for their view in the thoughts of apes, dogs and other animals. Dogs bark in their sleep as if they were chasing hares or robbers, and when they are awake they know that they are running, just as in their dreams they know that they are barking; yet we agree with you that there is nothing to these animals except their bodies. You may say that a dog doesn’t know that it is running or thinking, but you can’t prove this; and the dog might well think the same about us, namely that when we are running or thinking we don’t know that that’s what we are doing. You don’t see the dog’s internal mode of operation any more than the dog sees yours; and there have been plenty of distinguished men who have been prepared to allow that the beasts have reason. We don’t accept that all their operations can be satisfactorily explained in terms of mechanics, without invoking •sensation, •life or •soul—indeed we’ll bet you anything you like that this ridiculous claim is impossible. And if it is maintained that apes, dogs and elephants can perform all their operations by mechanical means, lots of people will say that man himself lacks sensation and intellect, and can do everything by

149

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

means of mechanical structures, without any mind. For the limited reasoning power to be found in animals differs from human reason only in degree; it doesn’t imply any essential difference.

Reply
(3) What you take here from the Platonists and their followers is something that has now been rejected by the entire Catholic Church and is commonly hooted off the stage by philosophers. The Lateran Council did conclude that angels could be depicted, but that didn’t mean they were granting that angels are corporeal. And even if they really were believed to be corporeal, it wouldn’t make sense to suppose their minds to be inseparable from their bodies (·and therefore not distinct from their bodies·), any more than it is in the case of men. Another point: even if the human soul were passed on ·from the parents· in procreation, it wouldn’t have to be corporeal; it could have been derived from the soul of the parents, just as the body grows from the parents’ body. As for dogs and apes: if I conceded that they have thought, that would imply that ·in this respect they resemble men·, not because

•in men as well as in animals there is no mind distinct from the body,

but rather because

•in animals as well as men there is a mind distinct from the body.

This was the view taken by the very Platonists whom my critics were taking as authorities a moment ago, as can be seen from their following the Pythagoreans in believing that a soul could move from one body to another. Actually, though, the brutes don’t have any thought. My critics imply that this is merely something that I said; but I didn’t just say it—I proved it by very strong arguments that so far no-one has refuted. As for the charge of ‘saying without proving’, the boot is on the other foot: my critics say, as if they were present in the animals’ hearts, that ‘dogs when awake know that they are running, and in their dreams know that they are barking’. They go on to say that they don’t believe that the behaviour of the beasts can all be ‘explained in terms of mechanics, without invoking sensation, life or soul’ (I take this to mean ‘without invoking thought’; for I accept that the brutes have what is commonly called ‘life’, and a corporeal soul and organic sensation); moreover, they are ready to bet any amount that this ‘ridiculous claim’ is impossible. But those remarks aren’t arguments; they are the sort of thing one can say about any thesis, however true it might be. Usually when someone resorts to bets in a debate, it is because he has run out of arguments! And ·the label ‘ridiculous’, which invites people to laugh at my views, doesn’t count for anything either·: there was a time when distinguished people used to laugh at those who claimed that the antipodes exist. I don’t think that a claim should be immediately dismissed as false just because some people laugh at it.

My critics add in conclusion: ‘If it is maintained that apes, dogs and elephants can perform all their operations by mechanical means, lots of people will say that man himself lacks sensation and intellect, and can do everything by means of mechanical structures, without any mind.’ This isn’t an argument that proves anything, except perhaps that some muddled people are so strongly wedded to their preconceived opinions (or their pre-adopted sentences) that rather than change them they will deny truths about themselves—truths that they must continually experience within themselves as true. We can’t fail to experience constantly within ourselves that we are thinking. When it is shown that animate brutes can do everything they do without any thought, no-one

150

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

should infer from this that he himself doesn’t think! Here is my diagnosis of someone who does make that inference:

He used to attribute thought to the brutes, which helped to convince him that he operates in exactly the same way as the brutes do. Then, when it is pointed out to him that the brutes don’t think, he has a choice between giving up ‘I think’ and giving up ‘Men and the brutes operate in the same way’; and he actually—·bizarrely·—prefers to deny that he thinks, because he is so wedded to the sentence ‘Men and the brutes operate in the same way’ that he won’t give it up.

But I can’t convince myself that there are many people of this sort. Most people who believe that thought is not distinct from corporeal motion are led by that to the conclusion ·not that men don’t think but· that brutes do think, and that their thought is similar in kind to ours (basing this on their observations of animal behaviour). And they will add that the difference between animal thought and human thought is merely one of degree; from which they will infer—a reasonable inference, ·although it is to a false conclusion·—that the beasts, although they have less reason than we do, have minds that are of exactly the same type as ours.

Objection
(4) Regarding the kind of knowledge that an atheist can have: When the atheist asserts ‘If equals are taken from equals the remainders will be equal’ or ‘The three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles’ or the like, he maintains that his knowledge ·of these truths· is very certain and indeed—on your own criterion—utterly evident. For he can’t think of these propositions without believing them to be wholly certain. He maintains that this is so true that even if God doesn’t exist—even if God isn’t even possible (which is what he believes)—he is just as certain of these truths as if God really existed. No reason for doubt can be produced (he thinks) that could shake his confidence. What reason can you produce? That God, if he exists, may deceive him? The atheist will reply that he can’t be deceived about these truths even by a God who exercises all his omnipotence to this end.

Reply
(4) It is easy to demonstrate that the atheist’s kind of knowledge is not rock-solid and certain. As I have already said, the less power the atheist attributes to his creator the more reason he will have to suspect that his nature may be so imperfect that he can be deceived even in matters which seem utterly evident to him. And he’ll never get free of this doubt until he recognizes that he has been created by a true God who doesn’t have it in him to be a deceiver.

God as a liar

Objection
(5) You say firmly that no deception is to be found in God. Now many theologians believe that the damned, both angels and men, are continually deceived by the idea of a tormenting fire that God implants in them; they firmly believe and think they perceive very clearly that they are really being tormented by the fire, although there is no such fire. So might not God deceive us with similar ideas, continually deluding us by sending such images or ideas into our souls? [The critics develop this point a little, adding that God could have good reasons for such deceptions. They then cite two biblical passages which mean, they say, that humans can’t really know anything:] ‘If anyone thinks he knows something, he doesn’t yet know anything as he ought to’ (1 Corinthians 8:2);

151

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

‘Then I understood that of all the works of God, a man can find no reason for the works that are performed under the sun; and the harder he works to find it the less success he will have; indeed, even if a wise man says that he knows it, he ·doesn’t know it and· won’t be able to find it out’ (Ecclesiastes 8:17). The whole book ·of Ecclesiastes· makes it clear that the ‘wise man’ speaks on the basis of carefully considered reasons, not hastily or thoughtlessly; this is exceptionally clear when the issue of the mind, which you maintain is immortal, is discussed. For Ecclesiastes 3:19 says that the death of a man ‘is as the death of a beast’. Don’t think that this refers only to ·the death of· body, because the text adds that ‘a man has no pre-eminence above a beast’. And it says regarding the spirit of man that no-who knows ‘whether it goes upward’ (i.e. is immortal), or whether it ‘goes downward’ (i.e. perishes) like the spirits of beasts. Don’t reply that these are words put into the mouth of an unbeliever; if they were, the writer would have said so, and then refuted these assertions, ·whereas in fact he does neither·. And don’t claim that you don’t have to reply to these points because Scripture is the theologian’s affair, not the philosopher’s. You as a Christian ought to be ready to reply as best you can to every objection that can be raised against the faith, especially when it also goes against a position you wish to establish.

Reply
(5) It is self-contradictory that men should be deceived by God; this is clearly demonstrated from the fact that the •supreme being can’t have anything to do with •non-being, and that’s what deception essentially is. All theologians are agreed about this. Also, the certainty of the Christian faith depends on it, for why would we believe what God has revealed to us if we thought that he sometimes deceived us? Theologians do indeed commonly say that the damned are tormented by the fires of hell; and what they mean is not that the damned are ‘deceived by •the idea of a tormenting fire that God implants in them’, but rather than they are tormented by •a real fire. As Peter Lombard writes in his ·authoritative· work Sentences (at IV:44), ‘just as the incorporeal spirit of a living man is naturally confined within the body, so after death it can easily be confined in corporeal fire, through the power of God’, and so on.

As for the passages cited from Scripture, I don’t think there is any onus on me to comment on them, except when they seem conflict with some opinion that is mine alone. For when the Scriptures are invoked against opinions of Christians generally, e.g. that something can be known, and that human souls are not like those of animals, it would look like arrogance on my part if I came up with replies of my own rather than resting content with replies already discovered by others. For I have never pursued theological studies much except as part of my private education, and I don’t feel within myself enough divine grace to give me a calling to such sacred studies. So I hereby declare that from now on I’ll refuse to respond to questions of this kind; but I make an exception just this once, so that I shan’t be accused of keeping silent because I don’t know what to say.

First, then, I maintain that the passage from Corinthians 8:2 should be understood as referring only to knowledge that isn’t conjoined with love, i.e. to the knowledge that atheists have. [Descartes defends this interpretation at some length, concluding:] Thus this passage that has been invoked •against me so openly •confirms my own opinion on the subject that I don’t think it can possibly be explained by anyone who disagrees with me ·on the matter that is in question here·. [He offers supporting evidence from I John 2:2 and 4:7.]

152

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

The same reasoning applies to the passages in Ecclesiastes. In this book Solomon is not adopting the role of an unbeliever but is speaking in his own voice as a sinner who has turned away from God and now repents. He says that back in the days when he used merely human wisdom without bringing in God, he couldn’t find anything wholly satisfying, anything that didn’t contain ‘vanity’. He warns us in various passages that we should turn to God,.... ·including one of the passages my critics bring against me·: ‘Then I understood that of all the works of God, a man can find no reason for the works that are performed under the sun’. This isn’t being said about any and every man, but about the man described in the preceding verse: ‘There is a man who doesn’t sleep, day or night.’ As though the prophet meant to warn us that those who stick to their studies too assiduously are not suited to the pursuit of truth. Those who know me won’t think that this applies to me! [A couple of years after this, Descartes wrote to the Princess Elizabeth: ‘The chief rule that I have always observed....is never to spend more than •a few hours a day in thoughts that occupy the imagination (including in that serious conversations and anything else that requires attention), and •a few hours a year in ones that occupy the intellect alone. I have given all the rest of my time to the relaxation of the senses and the repose of the mind.’] The phrase ‘works that are performed under the sun’ is important. It turns up frequently in Ecclesiastes, always referring to natural ·created· things considered apart from their relation to God, the point being that God is •above everything and hence is not •‘under the sun’. So the true sense of the quoted passage is that a man can’t achieve correct knowledge of natural things so long as he doesn’t know God—which is just what I too have asserted. Finally, the statements in 3:19 that •the death of a man ‘is as the death of a beast’ and that •‘a man has no pre-eminence above a beast’ are obviously meant to apply only to the body, for the passage mentions only things pertaining to the body. Just after that we find a separate comment about the soul: ‘Who knows whether the spirit of the sons of Adam goes upward and whether the spirit of the beasts goes downward?’ In other words: so long as man relies on human reasoning and doesn’t turn to God, who knows whether human souls are destined to enjoy bliss in heaven? Well, I have certainly tried to prove by •natural reason that the human soul •is not corporeal, but I agree that only •faith can enable us to know whether it •will go to heaven.

Freedom

Objection
(6) We have a problem concerning the indifference of ·our will or· our judgment, i.e. concerning liberty. [In this context, the ‘indifference’ of someone’s will is its being evenly balanced among the options, its not being driven to go one way rather than another.] According to you, this indifference is not a perfection in the will but an imperfection—one that goes away whenever the mind clearly perceives what it should believe or do or refrain from doing. But don’t you see that this view of yours destroys God’s freedom, removing from his will the indifference as to whether he shall create this world rather than another world or no world at all? It is an article of faith that God was from eternity indifferent as to whether he should create one world, or countless worlds, or none. But who doubts that God has always perceived utterly clearly what he ought to do or not do? Thus, a very clear perception of things doesn’t remove indifference of choice. And if indifference can’t be a proper part of our freedom it won’t be a part of God’s freedom either, because the essences of things are, like numbers,

•indivisible, ·so it can’t be that God has one part of the essence of freedom and we have another part·

153

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

and

•immutable, ·so it can’t be that the essence of freedom somehow changes when it moves from God to us·.

So indifference is involved in God’s freedom of choice just as much as it is in human freedom of choice. [The critics write as though they had first argued that indifference •isn’t part of human freedom, and then inferred that it •isn’t part of divine freedom either; whereas really they have moved in the opposite direction. This oddity doesn’t get in the way of the important things in Descartes’s reply.]

Reply
(6) How freedom of the will exists in God is not like how it exists in us. God’s will was indifferent from eternity with respect to everything that has happened or will ever happen. The denial of this is self-contradictory, because we can’t make up any ·coherent· story according to which •something is thought of in God’s intellect as good or true, or worthy of belief or action or omission, in advance of •his deciding to make it so. I don’t mean temporally ‘in advance’. What I am denying is that God’s idea of the good preceded his actions in the order of reasons, so that it impelled him to choose one thing rather than another. Thus, these are false:

•God willed the creation of the world in time because he saw that it would be better this way than if he had created it from eternity.

•God willed that the three angles of a triangle should be equal to two right angles because he recognized that they couldn’t be equal to anything else.

These are true:

•Because God willed the creation of the world in time, it is better this way than if he had created it from eternity.

•Because God willed that the three angles of a triangle should be equal to two right angles, they couldn’t be equal to anything else.

[In that striking passage, Descartes expresses two of his doctrines:

•It is impious to think that there is any objective standard of value, independent of God’s will, in terms of which God’s conduct can be evaluated.

•It is impious to think that there are any objective facts about what is and what isn’t possible, independent of God’s will, which circumscribe what God can do.

These are a natural pair, but still they are two.]

The merit of the saints can be said to be the cause of their obtaining eternal life, and that would be a problem for me if it meant that •their merit determines •God to will that they have eternal life. But that isn’t how things stand. Rather, •their merit ·directly· causes •their eternal life, this being a cause-effect link that God established from eternity. In short, God’s supreme indifference is the supreme indication of his omnipotence. [Descartes’s point is that if God were not supremely indifferent, that would mean that •he chooses to act as he does because he sees reasons for that choice; which would require that •there are standards of good/bad or right/wrong which are valid for God and are independent of his will; which would mean that •he is in some way limited, and thus not omnipotent.] In contrast with this, man finds that the nature of all goodness and truth has already been determined by God, and his [i.e. man’s] will can’t tend towards anything else; so it is obvious that the more clearly he sees what is good and true the more •willingly and thus •freely he will embrace it. The only times he is indifferent are when he doesn’t know which of the two alternatives is the better or truer, or at least when he doesn’t see this clearly enough to rule out any possibility of doubt. So human freedom relates to indifference very differently from how divine freedom relates to it. The thesis that the essences of things are indivisible isn’t relevant here. For one thing, no essence that can be attributed to God can be attributed in the same sense to any of his creatures. Also,

154

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

indifference isn’t part of the essence of human freedom: we are free when ignorance of what is right makes us indifferent, but we are especially free when a clear perception impels us to pursue some object.

Surfaces

Objection
(7) Concerning the surface in which, or by means of which, you say all our sensations occur [page 78]: we don’t understand how it can be that it isn’t a part of the bodies that are perceived by the senses, and isn’t a part of the air and its vapours; for you say it is no part of these things, not even the outermost layer. And we don’t grasp your assertion that there are no real accidents belonging to any body or substance—accidents that God •could make exist out of any subject, and that really •do exist in the sacrament of the Eucharist. [See note on page 78.] But our professors need not be upset by what you say, until they see whether you demonstrate it in the treatise on physics that you promise us; ·and they needn’t be anxious about this in the interim·, for they can hardly believe that your work on physics will provide us with such a clear account of the matter as to enable or require your view to be accepted in preference to the traditional one.

Reply
(7) I conceive of the surface by which I think our senses are affected in exactly the same way that all mathematicians and philosophers do (or ought to do), when they distinguish a •surface from a •body and suppose it to be wholly lacking in depth. That is one of the senses in which mathematicians use the term ‘surface’. In the other sense, they use ‘surface’ to refer to a •body whose length and breadth they are studying, not considering any depth it may have, though not denying that it has some degree of depth. The first sense—the one I am copying—takes a ‘surface’ to be ·not a body or part of a body but rather· a •mode of body—something that a body has in the way it has properties; and a surface in this sense has no depth. To avoid ambiguity, I stated that I was talking about the surface that is merely a mode and hence can’t be a part of a body—because a body is a substance, and a mode can’t be a part of a substance. But I didn’t deny that the surface is the boundary of a body; on the contrary it can quite properly be called the boundary of the contained body as much as of the containing one, in the sense in which bodies are said to be contiguous when their boundaries are together. For when two bodies are in mutual contact—·for example, when a ball is immersed in water·—they share a single boundary that isn’t a part of either of them; it is the same mode of each body, and it can remain even though the bodies are removed, provided only that other bodies of exactly the same size and shape take their places—·for example, replacing the water by other water·....

The ·two· arguments I have already used suffice to demolish the doctrine of the reality of accidents—i.e. to demolish the view that accidents or property-instances are ‘real’ in the sense of thing-like, and are able to move from one substance to another and to exist out of any substance. (a) All sense-perception occurs through contact, so only the surface of a body can be the object of sense-perception; but real accidents (if there were any) would have to be something different from the surface, which is nothing but a mode; so if there are any real accidents, they can’t be perceived by the senses. ·That doesn’t prove that there are no real accidents, but it undercuts the only reason for believing that there are·. The only reason why people have thought

155

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

that ·real· accidents exist is that they have believed that we perceive them by our senses. (b) The notion of real accident is completely self-contradictory: whatever is real can exist separately from any other subject; and anything that can exist separately in this way is a substance, not an accident. It might be said that real accidents can’t be separated from their subjects ‘naturally’, but only by the power of God. ·And this claim, it might be thought, blocks my argument (b): their being separable by God (the thought goes) is enough to make them ‘real’, while their not being separable naturally is enough to stop them from counting as ‘substances’·. But that move doesn’t achieve anything. To occur •‘naturally’ is simply to occur •through the ordinary power of God, which in no way differs from his extraordinary power—the effect on the real world is exactly the same. Hence if

•everything that can naturally exist without a subject is a substance,

then we should hold that

•anything that can exist without a substance through the (perhaps extraordinary) power of God is a substance.

....But what primarily led philosophers to believe in real accidents was their belief that sense-perception couldn’t be explained without them, and that’s why I promised to give a very detailed account of sense-perception in my writings on physics, taking each sense in turn. I didn’t expect any of my results to be taken on trust; but I thought that the explanation of vision that I had already given in my Optics would help the judicious reader to guess what I could accomplish with regard to the other senses.

Modality and God’s will

Objection
(8) Concerning one of your replies to Gassendi [page 130]: How can the truths of geometry or metaphysics, such as the ones you mention, be •unchangeable and eternal and yet not be •independent of God? What sort of causal dependence on God do they have? Could he have brought it about that there was never any such thing as the nature of a triangle? And how could he have made it untrue from eternity that twice four makes eight, or that a triangle has three angles? Either these truths depend solely on the intellect that is thinking of them, or on existing things, or else they are independent, since it seems that God could not have brought it about that any of these essences or truths were not as they were from all eternity. [This very condensed sentence may be worth unpacking. The point seems to be this: There are only three non-absurd stories we can entertain about the nature of modal truths such as those of logic and geometry: (a) they are somehow reflections of our own thinking, (b) they are very abstract truths about how things stand in the natural world, (c) they report on a free-standing self-sufficient objective realm of absolutely necessary modal truths. And on none of these accounts is it plausible to say that modal truths are made true by God. It is puzzling that the critics didn’t see both (a) and (b) as possible ways for modal truths to depend on God; yet the above does seem to be what they are saying, and it is certainly how Clerselier understood them in his French version.]

Reply
(8) Anyone who attends to the immeasurable greatness of God will find it utterly clear that there can’t be anything at all that doesn’t depend on him. This applies not just to all existing things, but also to all order, every law, and every reason for anything’s being true or good. If this were not so, then, as I pointed out a little earlier, God would not have

156

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

been completely indifferent with respect to the creation of what he did in fact create. If in advance of all God’s decrees there had been a reason for something’s being good, this would have determined God to choose the things that it was best to do; ·and this can’t be right, because it is grossly impious to suggest that anything could determine God, i.e. act on him or sway him or incline him or anything like that·. The real story runs in the other direction: precisely because God resolved to prefer certain things, those things are, as Genesis says, ‘very good’; they are good because God exercised his will to create them [the Latin could mean: ‘... exercised his will to make them good’]. What kind of causality (you ask) is involved in the dependence of this goodness on God, or in the dependence on him of other truths, both mathematical and metaphysical? There doesn’t have to be an answer to this; it wouldn’t be surprising if we didn’t have a label for this kind of causality; the various kinds of cause were listed ·and named· by thinkers who may not have attended to this type of causality. But in fact we do have a name for it—namely ‘efficient causality’, in the way in which a king may be called the efficient cause of a law, although the law is merely what they call a ‘moral entity’, not a thing that exists out there in the world. How could God could have brought it about from eternity that it was not true that twice four make eight? I admit that we have no understanding of how he could have done that. But there are two things that I do understand:

•There can’t be any kind of entity that doesn’t depend on God.

•Even with matters where we can’t grasp the possibility of things’ being other than the way they are, God could easily have brought it about that they were other than the way they are.

So it would be irrational for us to doubt things that we do understand correctly just because there is something that we don’t understand and that there is no visible reason why we should understand. So let us not suppose that eternal truths depend on the human intellect, or on other existing things; they depend on God alone, who, as the supreme legislator, has ordained them from eternity.

Senses versus intellect

Objection
(9) Our most worrying difficulty is your assertion that •we ought to mistrust the operations of the senses and that •the reliability of the intellect is much greater than that of the senses. How can the intellect enjoy any certainty that it didn’t first get from the senses when they are working properly? It can’t correct a mistake made by one of the senses unless it gets a lead from some other sense. Owing to refraction, a straight stick appears bent in water. What corrects the error?—the intellect? Not at all; it is the sense of touch. And similarly with other cases. Thus, if you appeal to all your senses when they are in good working order, and they all give the same report, that will give you the greatest certainty that man is naturally capable of. But you will often fall short of such certainty if you trust the operations of the mind; for the mind often goes astray in just those areas where it had previously thought doubt was impossible.

Reply
(9) To get a clear view of what kind of certainty attaches to the senses, we must distinguish three levels of sensory response. (a) There is

•the immediate stimulation of the bodily organs by external objects;

157

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

this can only be the motion of the particles of the organs, together with any change of shape and position resulting from this motion. (b) There are

•the immediate effects produced in the mind as a result of its being united with a bodily organ that is affected thus and so.

Examples are the perceptions of pain, pleasure, thirst, hunger, colours, sound, taste, smell, heat, cold and the like, which arise from the union—the intermingling, as it were—of the mind with the body, as I explained in the sixth Meditation. (c) Then there are

•the judgments about things outside us

that we have been accustomed to make from our earliest years—judgments that are triggered by the movements of these bodily organs. When I see a stick, what happens? A wrong answer: certain ‘intentional images’ fly off the stick towards the eye. The right answer: rays of light are reflected off the stick and set up certain movements in the optic nerve and, via the optic nerve, in the brain, as I have explained at some length in my Optics. This movement in the brain is the first level of sensory response; we have it and so do the brutes. It leads to the second level, which takes in the bare perception of the colour and light reflected from the stick; it occurs because the mind is so intimately conjoined with the body that it is affected by the movements that occur in the body. If we want a clean line between •the sensory faculty and the intellect, those two levels are all we should attribute to •the former. But now take a case where this happens:

I am affected ·at the second level· by a sensation of colour. This leads me to judge that a certain physical stick is coloured. Also, on the basis of the layout of the colour and its boundaries, together with its position in relation to the parts of my brain, I rationally calculate the size, shape and distance of the stick.

Such reasoning is commonly assigned to the senses (which is why I called it the third level of ‘sensory’ response), but clearly it depends solely on the intellect. I demonstrated in the Optics how •size, •distance and •shape can be perceived by reasoning alone, which works out any one of those features from the other two. ·What we have here is a difference not of process but only of circumstances·. •When we have some new kind of observation, and arrive at our first judgment about it, we think of this judgment as the work of the intellect. •When we have some sensory input of a familiar kind, and arrive at the old familiar judgment about it, we think of this judgment as coming from the senses. Yet the process of judgment-formation is exactly the same in the two cases, so why do we have a feeling that they differ? It is because in the latter case we work our way to the judgment at great speed because we have done this so often; or rather we remember our past judgments about similar objects ·and copy them in the present case, thus not having to ‘work our way’ to the judgment at all·. This shows that when we say

‘The •intellect is much more reliable than the •senses’,

we mean merely that

•the judgments we make as adults on the basis of various new observations are more reliable than •the judgments we unreflectively arrived at in our early childhood;

and this is undoubtedly true. The first and second levels of sensory response don’t come into this, because there can’t be anything false in them. So when people say that a stick in water ‘appears bent because of refraction’, they are ·not attributing falsehood to the second level of sensory response, but· saying in effect that the stick appears to us in a way that would lead a child—or would lead us if we weren’t careful—to judge that it was bent. My critics say that if we make that

158

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

wrong judgment it is corrected not by the intellect but by the sense of touch; and I think they are wrong about that. When we touch the stick we may judge that it is straight, and we may assign this judgment to the senses because it is of a kind that we have been accustomed to make since childhood. To correct the visual error we need not just •the sense of touch but also •some reasoning that tells us to believe the touch-based judgment rather than the sight-based one.... Thus even in my critics’ own example it is the intellect alone that corrects the error of the senses; and ·in reply to their final statement, I say that· they can’t possibly produce an example of error resulting from our trusting the operation of the mind more than the senses.

Thought-experiments

Objection
(10) After dealing with our questions, will you please give us help with this? You say that we can understand something entirely apart from some other thing in such a way as to make it certain that the one is so distinct from the other that they could exist apart—if only through the power of God. We need a reliable rule, and firm criteria, that will enable us to know vividly and clearly ·in a given case· that the distinction our intellect is making isn’t •produced purely by the intellect itself rather than •arising from the nature of the things themselves. Example of the difficulty: when we contemplate God’s •immensity while not thinking of his •justice, or contemplate God ·the •Father· while not thinking of the •Son or the •Holy Spirit, don’t we have a complete perception of God ·the Father· as existing, entirely apart from the other persons of the Trinity? If so, why can’t an unbeliever deny that the Son and the Holy Spirit belong to God on the same reasoning that leads you to deny that the mind or thought belongs to the body? If anyone infers ·from this simple thought-experiment· that •the Son and the Holy Spirit are essentially distinct from God the Father, or that they can be separated from him, this will be an unsound inference ·because its premise is true and its conclusion false·. Well, ·the threat is that· no-one will grant you the inference from •the separate conceivability of mind and body to the conclusion that •thought or the human mind is distinct from the body, despite your belief that the separate thinkability doesn’t come about simply through an abstraction of your mind. If you can give a satisfactory answer to these points, then, so far as we can see, nothing at all remains that can displease our theologians.

Reply
(10) These comments are put forward as doubts rather than as objections, and I’m not so confident of my powers that I’ll risk promising to give a satisfactory explanation of matters that I see still cause doubts in the minds of many learned and highly intelligent men. But I shan’t throw in my hand either: I’ll tell you frankly how I managed to free myself entirely from these same doubts. If this gives help to others, I’ll be delighted; if not—well, I didn’t make any promises! When the arguments set out in the Meditations first led me to conclude that the human mind •is really distinct from the body, •is better known than the body, and so on, I had to accept these results because all the reasoning was coherent—inferred in accordance with the rules of logic from quite evident principles as premises. And yet, I confess, I wasn’t entirely convinced. I was in the same plight as astronomers who have established by argument that the sun is many times larger than the earth, yet can’t help judging that it is smaller, when they actually look at it. But I pushed ahead, investigating physical things by the same

159

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

basic principles ·that had led me to where I was·. First I attended to my own ideas or notions of individual things, carefully distinguishing them from one another so that all my judgments should match them, ·i.e. match the physical things·. Here is what I found:

(a) The concept of body entails that every body has length, breadth and depth and is capable of various shapes and motions, and that is the whole content of that concept.
(b) These shapes and motions are ·not so-called ‘real accidents’; there is nothing thing-like about them; they are· merely modes, which no power can cause to exist apart from body.
(c) Colours, smells, tastes and so on are ·not qualities out there in the world, but are· merely certain sensations that exist in my thought, and differ from bodies as much as pain differs from the shape and motion of the weapon that causes it.
(d) All the qualities that we experience in bodies—heaviness and hardness, power to heat or to attract, and so on—depend on nothing but •whether and how the parts of the bodies are moving, •how they are organized, and •where they are.

This made a complete change in my beliefs regarding physical things; and that led me to look into the causes of my previous beliefs. I found that the principal cause was the following. From infancy I had formed a variety of opinions about physical things—all relating to the features of the things that were relevant to my own survival—and later on I kept these early opinions. But at the age at which I had formed them •my mind was more firmly attached to my sense-organs ·than it became later·, and •it employed the bodily organs less correctly than it now does. ·That double fact had a double upshot·: •my mind had no thoughts apart from my sense-organs, and •it perceived things only in a confused manner. Although it was aware of its own nature, and contained an idea of thought as well as an idea of extension, my mind never thought about anything without depicting it in the imagination. It therefore •took thought and extension to be one and the same thing, and •understood in corporeal terms all its notions of things related to the intellect. I had never freed myself from these early opinions, so I didn’t distinctly know anything, and supposed everything to be corporeal.

Yet many of my ideas or concepts of things that I supposed to be corporeal were really ideas of mental items rather than of bodies! My ideas about heaviness were examples of this, ·in three different ways·. (a) I thought of heaviness as being some sort of real quality inhering in solid bodies; and although I called it a ‘quality’ of the bodies in which it inhered, I added ‘real’, which showed that I was in fact thinking of it as a substance. [See note on ‘real accident’ on page 78.] In the same way clothing is in itself a substance, though in relation to the man who wears it it’s a quality. And—·coming to my present topic·—the mind is in fact a substance, but can be said to be a ‘quality’ of the body to which it is joined. (·My old way of thinking about heaviness involved

•thinking of a quality as though it were a substance;

whereas the way of talking about the mind that I have called attention to involves

•speaking of a substance as though it were a quality.

This comparison is admittedly a fairly abstract one.·) (b) Although I pictured heaviness as being scattered all through a heavy body, I still didn’t attribute to it the extension that constitutes the nature of a body. [To understand what Descartes says next, you need to know a background fact. Descartes accepted, as did many others, the no sharing thesis: extended things can’t ‘interpenetrate’, i.e. you can’t have two extended things each com-

160

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

pletely filling a single region of space (though of course you can have one occupying pores and tunnels in the other, like water in a sponge). He also accepted the no shrinkage or expansion thesis: you can’t have a single extended thing (or a single batch of extended stuff) completely occupying some region of space and then later completely occupying a smaller or larger region of space. In what he says next, as in various other places, Descartes writes as though these two theses were one, or at least that they necessarily stand or fall together.] The true extension of a body excludes any interpenetration of the parts, whereas I thought that there was the same amount of heaviness in a large piece of wood as in a smaller lump of gold—indeed I thought that the whole of the heaviness could be shrunk down to a mathematical point. Also, although the heaviness was scattered throughout the entire body, I saw that it could exercise all its force in any one part of the body: if the body is hung from a rope attached to one part of it, it would still pull the rope down with all its force, as though all the heaviness were in the part actually touching the rope instead of being scattered throughout all the parts. And that is exactly the way in which I now understand the mind to be coextensive with the body—the whole mind in the whole body, and the whole mind in any one of its parts. (c) But what makes it especially clear that my idea of heaviness was taken largely from my idea of the mind is my thinking of heaviness as carrying bodies towards the centre of the earth as though it—·heaviness itself·—knew where the centre was. For this surely couldn’t happen without knowledge, and there can’t be knowledge except in a mind. But despite all this I continued to ascribe to heaviness various attributes that can’t be understood to apply to a mind in this way—for example its being divisible, measurable and so on.

Later on, when I had thought all this through, and distinguished carefully the •idea of the mind from the •ideas of body and bodily motion, I found that all my earlier ideas of ‘real qualities’ or ‘substantial forms’ were constructed by me out of them—·i.e. out of the ideas of body and bodily motion·—and in this way I easily freed myself from all the doubts that my critics here put forward. First of all, I didn’t doubt that I had a clear idea of my mind, since I had a close inner awareness of it. And I didn’t doubt that this idea was quite different from my ideas of other things, and that there was nothing corporeal about it: in the course of looking for true ideas of all these other things, I had apparently come to have some general knowledge of all of them; and everything I found in them was completely different from my idea of the mind. As for the distinctness of mind from body: ·we have to distinguish two kinds of case·.

•(a) x appears to be distinct from y, even while we are thinking hard about both of them;

•(b) we can think of x without thinking of y; but when we think of both of them together, we can’t see how they could exist apart from one another.

·The examples presented by the critics are both cases of type (b)·. •We can think about God’s immeasurable greatness without thinking about his justice, but if we think about both at once ·we find that· it is flatly self-contradictory to suppose that God is immeasurably great and yet not just. •We can have true knowledge of the existence of God ·the Father· without knowing about the ·other· persons of the Trinity, because the latter can be perceived only by a mind that has been illuminated by faith; but when we do perceive them, ·we find it· unintelligible to suppose that they are ‘really distinct’ from one another in the sense of being different substances, though not to suppose that they ·are different persons who· stand in certain relationships to one another.

161

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

Appendix

There now follow a number of points suggested to me by other critics. [This, according to the Clerselier translation, is Mersenne addressing Descartes.] I put them in here to give you the opportunity to reply to them in conjunction with the preceding objections, since they involve the same line of thought. Some of your most learned and acute critics have ask you to clarify the following three points:

•How do I know for certain that I have a clear idea of my soul?

•How do I know for certain that this idea is wholly different from any other thing?

•How do I know for certain that this idea contains nothing of a corporeal nature?

And the following argument has been sent to me [still Mersenne] with the title: ‘From philosophers and geometers to Monsieur Descartes’.

However much we ponder on the question of whether the idea—i.e. our knowledge and perception—of the human mind contains anything corporeal, we don’t go so far as to assert that what we call ‘thought’ can’t be squared with the properties of a movable body. Our situation is this: we see that

•There are some bodies that don’t think,

and that

•Other bodies do think (human ones, and perhaps sub-human animals ones too).

Well, are we to infer that

•No bodies think

from those two premises? We are pretty sure that if we had originally devised this argument from ideas to establish the nature of the mind and the existence of God, you would have brought your method of analysis to bear on it, exposing us to lasting ridicule. ·Why, then, are you satisfied with this line of argument when it is you who puts it forward·? It seems that through your intense preoccupation with it, this analytic method has dulled your mind, so that you are no longer free to see that the individual properties or operations of the soul that you find in yourself depend on corporeal motions—·primarily on tiny physical events in the brain·.

If you don’t accept this, then you ·should help us to reject it also·. We can’t make our mind soar above every kind of body; you must think that some kind of strong fetters are holding our mind down; and we ask you to undo them! The crux of the trouble is this: We perceive very well that three and two make five, and that if you take equals from equals the remainders will be equal; we are convinced of these and many other matters, just as you are. Then why aren’t we similarly convinced—on the basis of your ideas, or our own—that a man’s soul is distinct from his body, and that God exists? You’ll say that you can’t instill this truth in us unless we are prepared to meditate along with you. Well, we have read what you have written seven times, and have exerted all our powers to raise our minds to the level of the angels, but we’re still not convinced. We don’t think you’ll accuse us of having minds that are possessed by a brutish stupor and are wholly unfitted for metaphysical subjects—not when we have pursued such subjects for thirty years! Surely you will prefer to accept that your arguments based on the ideas of the mind and of God aren’t weighty or strong enough to conquer the minds of learned men who have tried their hardest to detach themselves from corporeal stuff. We think, indeed, that you will readily admit this, if you re-read your Meditations in the spirit of analytical scrutiny that you would have adopted if an opponent had put them forward for you to examine.

162

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

Lastly, since we don’t know what can be done through the movements of bodies, and since you accept that without a divine revelation no-one can know everything that God that has imparted or could impart to any object, how could you possibly know that God hasn’t given certain bodies a power or property enabling them to doubt, think etc.?

These are our arguments, or our ‘preconceived opinions’ if you like. If you can cure them, Sir, we swear by the ever-living God that we will unite in giving you our fullest thanks for freeing us from the thorns that are choking the seed you have sown! May almighty God in his supreme goodness bring this about, for we can see that it is to his glory alone that you have devoted all your fine efforts.

Reply to the Appendix
I have not been so preoccupied with my method of analysis that I risked committing the blunder suggested by these critics. They have me starting from

•seeing that there are certain bodies that don’t think,

and then going on to assert that

•thought doesn’t belong to the nature of the body,

rather than noticing that

•some bodies, namely human ones, do think,

and inferring from this that thought is a mode of the body. The starting-point should have been; ‘clearly understanding that certain bodies can exist without thought’, ·but let that pass·. In fact I have never seen or perceived that human bodies think; all I have seen is that there are human beings who have both thought and a body. This comes from a thinking thing’s being combined with a corporeal thing, as I realized when I •examined a thinking thing on its own and discovered nothing in it pertaining to body, and •considered corporeal nature on its own and discovered no thought in it. Instead of discovering some such overlap or cross-connection, what I found was just the opposite: I didn’t find any mode of body (·any property that a body can have·) that isn’t just a special case of being extended; and I didn’t find any mode of mind (·any property that a mind can have·) that isn’t just a special case of thinking. Also, from the fact that we often see two things joined together we can’t rightly infer that they are one and the same; but from the fact that we sometimes observe one of them apart from the other we can rightly infer that they are distinct from one another. Nor should the power of God deter us from making this inference. For it is a conceptual contradiction to suppose that two things which we clearly perceive as two should become one and the same (that is, intrinsically one and the same, as opposed to being combined into a single complex thing); this is no less a contradiction than to suppose that things that are in no way distinct should be separated. Hence, if God has implanted the power of thought in certain bodies (as he in fact has done in the case of human bodies), then he can remove this power from them, and so it still remains really distinct from them.

It is true that I did, before freeing myself from the preconceived opinions acquired from the senses, perceive correctly that two and three make five, and that if equals are taken from equals the remainders are equal, and many things of this kind; and yet I did not think that the soul of man is distinct from his body. But I don’t find this surprising. For I can easily see why it happened that as an infant I never made any false judgments about propositions of this sort, which everyone accepts; the reason was that I had no occasion to employ these propositions, since children do not learn to count two and three until they are capable of judging whether they make five. But, by contrast, I had from my earliest years conceived of my mind and body as a unity of some sort (for I had a confused awareness that I was composed of mind and body). It happens in almost every case of imperfect

163

Objections and Replies René Descartes Sixth Objections)

knowledge that many things are apprehended together as a unity, though they will later have to be distinguished by a more careful examination.

What does greatly surprise me is that learned men who have pursued metaphysical studies ‘for thirty years’ and have read my Meditations ‘seven times’ think that if I re-read them in the spirit of analytical scrutiny that I would have adopted if the Meditations had been presented by an opponent, I wouldn’t believe that the arguments contained there had enough weight or strength to lead everyone to assent to them. I’m surprised that my critics should say this when they can’t point to any flaw in these arguments of mine. They imply that my kind of ‘analysis’ enables true demonstrations to be overthrown and false ones to be so disguised and tricked out that no-one can refute them. What a massive compliment! The truth is just the opposite: all I have sought is a method that will show the certainty of true arguments and show up the flaws in false ones. What strikes me is not so much that some learned men don’t yet accept my conclusions as that after carefully reading and re-reading my arguments they can’t point to any false assumptions or invalid inferences in what I have written. Why are they reluctant to accept the conclusions? Probably because they have such long-ingrained habits of making different judgments on these matters; they are like the astronomers I mentioned earlier, who find it hard to •picture the sun as being bigger than the earth although they can •demonstrate that it is, by most reliable arguments. And why haven’t they (or, as far as I know, anyone else) been able to fault my arguments? It must be because the arguments are completely true and certain. They don’t start from •obscure and unknown principles. Rather, they start from (first) •total doubt about everything, and then from (second) •principles that appear to be utterly evident and certain to a mind that has been set free from preconceived opinions; and they proceed to the conclusions step by step. So the arguments can’t contain any mistakes that wouldn’t easily be spotted by anyone of even moderate intelligence. So I think I am entitled to conclude that if these learned gentlemen still can’t accept my conclusions after several close readings, their non-acceptance doesn’t weaken my position, but in another way they strengthen it, through their failure after such a careful and repeated examination to note any errors or fallacies in my demonstrations.

164